<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi divorce - when world leaders go astray" author="Alexandra Topping" date="2009-05-03" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/03/silvio-berlusconi-divorce" hostname="theguardian.com" description="From Kennedy to Clinton, sex and power are a heady combination" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="62e25bff93f7d725">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The following correction was printed in the Guardian's Corrections and clarifications column, Wednesday 6 May 2009</hi>
    </p>
    <p>A story about marital disharmony in the Berlusconi household was accompanied by the article below on the sexual conduct of various national leaders, including the relationship between John Major and Edwina Currie. Major was not prime minister when this affair took place, and Edwina Currie was never, contrary to what we said, a cabinet minister.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">John F Kennedy</hi>, US president from 1961 till his assassination in 1963, was involved with a string of women during his marriage to Jacqueline Bouvier. Speculation of an affair with Marilyn Monroe was fuelled by her performance of "Happy Birthday, Mr President" at his birthday party in 1962.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">François Mitterrand</hi>, president of France from 1981 to 1995, was reported to have had numerous extramarital affairs. His long-term affair with Anne Pingeot, with whom he had a daughter, Mazarine, was kept secret among French journalists for 21 years.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Bill Clinton</hi> was forced to admit an "inappropriate relationship" with former intern Monica Lewinsky. Clinton said: "[I]t was wrong [...] I misled people, including even my wife. I deeply regret that."</p>
    <p>Former prime minister <hi rend="#b">John Major</hi> admitted a four-year affair with former cabinet minister Edwina Currie. He said: "It is the one event in my life of which I am most ashamed and I have long feared would be made public."</p>
    <p>South Africa's newly elected president,<hi rend="#b"> Jacob Zuma</hi>, has at least two wives, is thought to have married up to five times, and has fathered as many as 18 children. He once said: "There are plenty of politicians who have mistresses and children that they hide so as to pretend they're monogamous. I prefer to be open. I love my wives and I'm proud of my children."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>