<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi: I will veto Alitalia deal" author="John Hooper" date="2008-03-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2008/mar/22/theairlineindustry.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Berlusconi threatens to scupper Air France-KLM's purchase of Alitalia if returned to power next month" categories="Business" tags="Airline industry,Business,Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="6eed91e9b523dfed">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi threatened yesterday to scupper Air France-KLM's purchase of Alitalia from the outgoing Rome government, saying he would veto the deal if returned to power next month.</p>
    <p>The Franco-Dutch airline has said it would not try to buy Italy's stricken flag-carrier if the country's next administration opposed it. Berlusconi, who has a clear lead in the polls before the general election on April 13-14, told reporters: "The reply to Air France will be given by the next prime minister - and it will be a flat, round 'No'."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said he was "not against France, but against the conditions" stipulated by the buyer. However, in a clear appeal to nationalists, he said Italy's business people could "not be colonised".</p>
    <p>The deal was already at the centre of controversy in Italy, with trades unions railing at Air France-KLM's "take-it-or-leave-it" approach, and Italy's airport operator demanding compensation of €1.3bn (£1bn) if an agreement is reached.</p>
    <p>The finance minister in the outgoing, centre-left government, Tommaso Padoa-Schioppa, warned this week that, in the absence of a realistic counter-bid, the alternative to Air France's offer was bankruptcy. Last year, he failed to auction off Alitalia, which is losing almost €1m a day and has debts of more than €1.2bn.</p>
    <p>Air France-KLM plans to drop Milan's Malpensa airport as a hub, run down Alitalia's cargo operations and shed more than a sixth of the 9,900 jobs in the air and on the ground. A further 4,500 jobs would be at risk in the maintenance company AZ Servizi, which is partly owned by Alitalia. Maurizio Prato, Alitalia's chairman, has set a deadline of March 31 for agreement with the nine unions representing employees.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi first ploughed into the fray on Wednesday when he urged Italian companies to counter-bid and said his children would be ready to join a rescue operation. Yesterday, he again implied that Italy's top retail bank, Intesa Sanpaolo, which backed an earlier bid by the small Italian carrier Air One, would be prepared to fund the operation. But the bank said it would be impossible to make an offer without access to Alitalia's full accounts.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>