<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Letters: The Conservatives' new friends in Europe" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-10-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/oct/23/conservatives-new-friends-in-europe" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Letters: David Cameron and William Hague will continue to have to defend their new friends at Brussels as more of our allies understand the true nature of their new bedfellows" categories="Politics" tags="Conservatives,David Cameron,William Hague,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Angela Merkel" fingerprint="377fda37b107d0c9">
  <main>
    <p>David Cameron and William Hague will continue to have to defend their new friends at Brussels as more of our allies understand the true nature of their new bedfellows (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/oct/20/tories-eu-allies-us-pressure">Tories face US pressure</ref>, 21 October). In a little-noticed move on the eve of the Tory conference, Angela Merkel's <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian_Democratic_Union_(Germany)">CDU</ref> downgraded its relations with the Tories. Three joint policy groups – on the environment, security and economic competitiveness – have been cancelled, as has an annual meeting between the parties. Merkel understands that Cameron's decision to break from the European mainstream actually enabled the formation of their new group. Extremist parties like the Polish Law and Justice and Latvia's For Fatherland and Freedom wouldn't have the numbers to make a formal grouping, with the legitimacy and resources this brings. Despite condemning any criticism, deep down, Cameron and Hague must understand what murky waters they have blundered into.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Mike Katz</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Vice-chair, </hi>
      <hi rend="#i">Jewish Labour Movement</hi>
    </p>
    <p> Silvio Berlusconi's rightwing allies in the European parliament defeated – by a single vote – a Liberal Democrat resolution calling for freedom of the media in Italy and throughout the EU. But it is worth noting both the significance of that lost vote and the role that British MEPs played in it. The Italian prime minister controls private and public media in Italy to a degree that would have turned <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erich_Honecker">Erich Honecker</ref> green with envy. That's why Italian citizens are looking to the EU to uphold their right to freedom of expression. Instead, the European parliament has handed Berlusconi an apparent fig leaf of legitimacy and an undoubted political and media coup. It was deeply embarrassing to watch Tory MEPs rush to Berlusconi's defence. Perhaps they were afraid Rupert Murdoch would drop his newly given support? Cameron should feel as embarrassed about this as about his other distasteful European friendships. </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Lib Dem, London</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>