<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's press freedom in peril | Manuela Mesco" author="Manuela Mesco" date="2009-10-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/oct/10/italy-press-freedom-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Manuela Mesco: Silvio Berlusconi scoffs as huge crowds gather to protest about the state of the media, but the threat to democracy is clear" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Press freedom,Media,World news,Europe" fingerprint="765d0b14d3a5b391">
  <main>
    <p>After last week's <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8289166.stm">press freedom rally</ref> was hailed both as a "farce" and as a "necessary measure to take", it's hard to deny that Italy suffers from acase of contrasting perspectives.</p>
    <p>On 3 October Piazza del Popolo, in Rome, was packed with journalists, writers, intellectuals, lawyers, and ordinary citizens to peacefully demonstrate in favour of freedom of the press, against regulations to control journalists, and against government interferences within the media. According to the Italian police 60,000 people attended the event; the National Federation of the Press, which organised the rally, estimated a turnout of 300,000 people. Where's the truth?</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister, said during an interview with Sky TG24: "There's more freedom of information in Italy than in any other country". He added that the rally was a "farce". The international organisation Reporters Without Borders said Berlusconi was on the verge of being added to its list of the "<ref target="http://www.rsf.org/spip.php?page=article&amp;id_article=34640">predators of press freedom</ref>" over his "attacks and lawsuits against the press". So, again, where's the truth?</p>
    <p>The truth is that in Piazza del Popolo last Saturday, the attendance figure was certainly closer to 300,000 than 60,000.</p>
    <p>As for freedom of information, it's true that no dissident journalist has been arrested, no paper has been closed. In a democratic society the matter is definitely more subtle than that.</p>
    <p>There are a number of episodes occurred in the last few months that make clear that information is not delivered fairly in the country. Particularly, press freedom is endangered because Italian information is experiencing a systematic exclusion of certain stories from the main TV news bulletins so that the majority of Italians – who rely on them for information – don't get the full picture of what's happening in the country. They're not only deprived of a fair news service about political scandals, presidential gossip and trials, but also about other hot topics such as the recession.</p>
    <p>The government believes that bad news is to be restricted. Better not to show whatever might bring negative thoughts. Better, therefore, to accurately select which pieces of news need be reported. And editors and journalists are too often happy to meet this request.</p>
    <p>Italians are indeed informed but not fairly as independent, free journalism would do. The words used by the emeritus president of the Italian high court of justice, Valerio Onida, during last week's press freedom rally are explanatory: "Every badly informed citizen is not a free citizen". This is in brief the issue of press freedom in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>Augusto Minzolini, editor of the news bulletin Tg1, one of the main sources of information for the majority of Italians, in an editorial broadcast during in the evening news, said about the demonstration: "It is absurd to say that freedom of the press is endangered". To Minzolini, it's incomprehensible why people are rallying in favour of freedom of information.</p>
    <p>Thus, on the night of 3 October, this is the message that most of the Italian families received through the evening news, without the bare knowledge of what happened and what was said in Piazza del Popolo during the rally.</p>
    <p>The Italian controversy overcame even national boundaries. Last Thursday, the case for lack of press freedom in Italy was brought forward to the <ref target="http://www.upi.com/Top_News/2009/10/08/EU-wades-into-Italian-media-debate/UPI-52641255017806/">European parliament</ref>. It will be again on the agenda in the 21 October plenary session in Strasbourg, when a new resolution on pluralism and against media concentration in Europe is to be discussed.</p>
    <p>Mario Mauro, leader of PDL (Berlusconi's party) at the European parliament commented: "This is an attempt to make an unfair use of the European parliament aiming to destroy a democratically elected government".</p>
    <p>In a country where dissident newspapers are intimidated by excessively expansive libel actions, where TV schedules are suddenly changed to favour the prime minister's presence on air, and where journalists – appointed by Berlusconi's brother (who owns the paper Il Giornale) – threaten politicians and colleagues with alleged, often nonexistent scandals, the health of the media is indeed an issue. It's a situation that is compromising fair, balanced information but also journalistic ethics, which is possibly an even more serious matter.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>