<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi immunity ploy as wife demands share of empire in split" author="John Hooper" date="2009-11-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/12/berlusconi-italy-immunity-bill" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian PM launches counter-offensive against constitutional court on day Veronica Lario reportedly files for separation" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="92ac01859f13b6cb">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's supporters have unveiled a bill – drafted in large part by the Italian prime minister's own lawyer – with sweeping provisions to halt the trials in which he is a defendant.</p>
    <p>The bill was one of two that made up Silvio Berlusconi's response to the decision last month by Italy's constitutional court to overturn a law granting him immunity from prosecution. On Wednesday, one of his MPs tabled a proposal to restore the immunity which all Italian deputies and senators enjoyed until 1993.</p>
    <p>The association representing Italy's judges and prosecutors said it would also end "at least 100,000" other trials. The secretary of the national magistrates' association, Giuseppe Cascini, said that approving the measure would be like "saying to the victims of crime 'we were joking'".</p>
    <p>The prime minister's counter-offensive was unveiled as it was reported that his wife, Veronica Lario, had filed for a legal separation. The former actor announced her intention of splitting from her husband in May, claiming she could no longer remain with a man "who frequents minors" – an apparent reference to Berlusconi's still mysterious friendship with an 18-year-old would-be actress and model from Naples.</p>
    <p>Lario declined to comment on a report in Corriere della Sera that she had chosen a procedure that increased the chances of a messy split. Her lawyers would have to persuade the judge that her estranged husband had behaved irresponsibly towards his family, the paper quoted a divorce law expert as saying.</p>
    <p>It added that the legal team Lario had assembled suggested she was laying claim to a sizeable proportion of the prime minister's business empire. A multibillionaire, Berlusconi controls Italy's biggest private television network and its largest publishing house, and has extensive interests in film distribution, property and insurance.</p>
    <p>Under the terms of the immunity bill, charges would lapse two years after they were brought, provided the defendant did not have a criminal record and was accused of an offence carrying a sentence of less than 10 years.</p>
    <p>The new rules would not apply to various serious offences such as terrorism, and nor – at the insistence of the anti-immigrant Northern League, allied to Berlusconi's party – would they apply to illegal immigration.</p>
    <p>The effects on the Italian legal system, notorious for delay and inefficiency, would be dramatic. Among the trials at risk is one arising from one of the world's biggest corporate frauds, involving the Parmalat dairy group.</p>
    <p>The bill would also kill both the trials in which Berlusconi is a defendant. He is accused in one of bribing the British lawyer David Mills, and in the other of tax fraud. Mills, the estranged husband of Olympics minister Tessa Jowell, who is appealing against his conviction to Italy's highest appeals court, would also escape the threat of jail.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>