<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: the rise and fall" author="Tom Kington" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/timeline-silvio-berlusconi-italy-euro-elections" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Timeline: the political ups and downs of the media magnate's career as Italy's leader" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Euro,European Union,Economics,Elections past,Politics past,Politics" fingerprint="20a05e7f9284e77a">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">March</hi>
      <hi rend="#b">1994</hi>
    </p>
    <p>After the Clean Hands anti-corruption investigation decimates Italy's political parties, and only three months after he forms his Forza Italia party, media magnate Berlusconi wins parliamentary election.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">December 1994</hi>
    </p>
    <p>As investigators launch a bribery probe involving Berlusconi's Fininvest holding, his government coalition partner Umberto Bossi, head of the Northern League, pulls out of the government, forcing Berlusconi to resign.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">May 2001</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Berlusconi wins national elections after signing a "contract" with Italy on TV promising to lower taxes, create jobs and build infrastructure. He also promises to resolve the conflicts of interest which his business interests would pose.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">April 2006</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Loses national election to Romano Prodi after performing badly in a TV debate where he grows visibly irritated. Refuses to concede defeat at polls, alleging irregularities.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">December 2006</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Heart surgery to install a pacemaker at a clinic in the US, three weeks after collapsing while delivering a speech. Continues to boast he has the stamina of a younger man and will live to be 120.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">April 2008</hi>
    </p>
    <p>After Prodi's coalition of Catholics-to-former-Communists collapses after 18 months, Berlusconi wins a convincing victory over former Rome mayor and lefftist Walter Veltroni, and starts third term.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">May 2009</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Veronica Lario, Berlusconi's second wife, announces she wants divorce, after denouncing her husband for wanting to send young showgirls and Big Brother contestants to Brussels as MEPs.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">June 2009</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Prostitute Patrizia D'Addario claims she had spent the night at Berlusconi's Rome residence after joining 20 women for a party with champagne and jokes by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">February 2011</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Indicted by a Milan court on charges he paid an underage girl, Ruby Heartstealer, for sex, and used his position to try to cover up the subsequent disclosure.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">November 2011</hi>
    </p>
    <p>After the erosion of his parliamentary majority, Berlusconi informs Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, a veteran former Communist, that he will resign as prime minister – but says equivocally that it will be sometime in November, after he has passed economic reforms that have been demanded by the EU.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>