<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="He’s back! How Silvio Berlusconi staged a political resurrection" author="Stephanie Kirchgaessner" date="2018-01-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jan/28/silvio-berlusconi-march-election-matteo-renzi-five-star-movement" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Ahead of elections in March, even critics admit the disgraced former leader may understand Italy’s complexities best" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Politics,Matteo Renzi,Five Star Movement,The League" fingerprint="beaa522fb223c70d">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2017/apr/18/he-fought-the-mafia-and-won-now-this-mayor-is-taking-on-europe-over-migrants">Leoluca Orlando</ref>, the mayor of Palermo, has transformed his city from a mafia capital to a capital of culture. But these days, sitting in his palatial office in the heart of the Sicilian capital, just a dozen miles from where a high-profile anti-mafia judge was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/nov/17/toto-riina-sicilian-mafia-boss-of-bosses-dies-cosa-nostra-italy">killed in a car bomb</ref> 26 years ago – an act that set off the island’s campaign to dismantle the Cosa Nostra – Orlando is ill at ease.</p>
    <p>The recent return of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jan/23/italy-elections-as-left-splinters-berlusconi-waits-in-wings">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> as a major force in Italian politics is, he says, good news for the enemies he has been fighting for years. “I am not saying he is mafioso. I am not saying that,” Orlando says of the 81-year-old former prime minister. “But he is the man that the rich need, the man that the corrupt need, the man the mafiosi need.”</p>
    <p>Not far from city hall, a political debate is under way at trattoria Gigi Mangia, where the eponymous owner, a local legend, is sipping prosecco with Maurizio Miceli, a retired lawyer, and debating the sorry state of politics. Miceli supports Berlusconi, the man known as <hi rend="#i">Il Cavaliere</hi> (the knight) because – like millions of Italians – he sees the billionaire as the best of a bad set of options for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>It’s Berlusconi – not the centre-left led by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/dec/03/italy-referendum-defeat-would-complete-matteo-renzis-rapid-downfall">Matteo Renzi</ref>, nor the populist, upstart Five Star Movement – who really understands the country and its complexity, Miceli says.</p>
    <p>“When people have a pain in their bellies, when they are hungry, the issue of ethics becomes secondary,” he says. “When they hear their pensions will go up and that Berlusconi will bring a flat tax, they don’t care about the times he has been condemned in court.”</p>
    <p>Not that long ago Italy seemed to have turned its back on Berlusconi. In 2011, the media mogul was <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-15708729">forced to resign</ref> under a cloud as Italy was engulfed in an economic crisis that would see millions of Italians lose work, and a generation of young people lose hope. A year later, his conviction for tax fraud put him out of the running to hold public office. But there is no denying that Berlusconi has launched the comeback of his life, and is now the politician with the most momentum as Italy heads to national elections on 4 March.</p>
    <p>He leads a rightwing coalition composed of his party, Forza Italia, and two parties on the far right, the Northern League and Brothers of Italy. There are significant policy differences within the coalition but, with Berlusconi at the helm, the group appears far more united than the centre-left alternative, which has split and is running separately.</p>
    <p>Last November, in what was viewed as a possible preview of the March poll, Berlusconi’s coalition handily beat both the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/five-star-movement">Five Star Movement</ref> and Renzi’s Democratic party in elections in Sicily. It was a reminder of the island’s affection for Berlusconi: the biggest electoral win of his career was in 2001, when he took all 61 parliamentary seats there.</p>
    <p>How exactly did Berlusconi manage this comeback? How did a politician whose international reputation is one of corruption and sex parties with young women and prostitutes rehabilitate his reputation? The answer seems to be sheer will and a dire political situation that has created a vacuum in leadership. If nothing else, Berlusconi knows how to seize an opportunity.</p>
    <p>Giovanni Orsina, a political professor at Luiss University in Rome and author of <hi rend="#i">Berlusconism and Italy</hi>, which chronicles the former prime minister’s rise and fall, and rise and fall, attributes Berlusconi’s latest successful reinvention to the Forza leader’s ability to portray himself believably as the country’s most trustworthy and reliable politician. “We can say this is the most telling sign of the tragic state of Italian politics today,” Orsina says.</p>
    <p>In a recent television interview, Berlusconi described his primary rival, the Five Star Movement, as a bigger threat than communism ever was. He told <hi rend="#i">Corriere della Sera</hi>: “The challenge is between moderates like us … and rebellious, poverty-perpetuating vigilante movements like the followers of [M5S founder <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jan/24/beppe-grillo-steps-aside-from-italys-five-star-movement">Beppe] Grillo</ref>.” He has emphasised the party’s poor performance in government, especially in Rome, where <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/dec/29/rubbish-piles-up-in-rome-waste-five-star-movement">Virginia Raggi</ref>, the M5S mayor, has been seen as incompetent. Across Europe, a man who was once seen as a George W Bush-loving pariah and an embarrassment to the continent appears to be a palatable option.</p>
    <p>For all his foibles, Berlusconi is still a natural politician. “This man is tough. He is really tough. He would do anything not to die, literally and figuratively, and he is propelled by a view that the world cannot exist without him,” Orsina says.</p>
    <p>The former prime minister is also helped by uncommon resources in Italian politics: his wealth; his hold on vast swaths of Italian media, with control of a television network; and the comfort of knowing that 6%-8% of his voters support him on strictly personal grounds, irrespective of his political agenda. In a political landscape that is splintered, it’s a significant bloc.</p>
    <p>But even more important are the voters to whom Berlusconi has always managed to speak directly. Years before Hillary Clinton referred to half of Donald Trump’s supporters as a “basket of deplorables”, Orsina had a similarly negative catchphrase to describe the kinds of voters that flock to Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>“Everyone goes for the gazelles, and no one tries to win the warthogs, except for Berlusconi,” he says. “And this has been Berlusconi’s major source of strength. It is a bloc that doesn’t have political culture, or has it but it’s not political. They’re housewives, they’re unemployed, they are peripheral people.”</p>
    <p>While a good chunk of these voters have since migrated to the populist protest party M5S, others – who are less angry, more conservative, and are suspicious of the Five Star movement – have rallied around the man they already know.</p>
    <p>Some argue that Berlusconi never really left the scene. Even as he began <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/may/09/silvio-berlusconi-begins-community-service">community service </ref>in lieu of time in prison following his conviction on tax fraud, Italian media reports focused on the way Berlusconi charmed the Alzheimer’s patients at the centre where he worked, reportedly serenading the residents. He settled down with a new partner, 32-year-old Francesca Pasquale – distancing himself from his history of bunga-bunga parties – and talked up his vegetarian diet and animal rights. He cultivated the image of a man who had finally settled down and will not, this time around, be distracted by sex and partying.</p>
    <p>Outside Italy, Berlusconi is seen as the original Donald Trump. A flashy businessman with a taste for young (and in some cases underage) women, whose rampant sexism and casually racist remarks make him unfit for high office. But Italians, even those critical of him, take a softer, more complex view. While Berlusconi attacked the country’s judiciary, they say, he was also the subject of an unduly harsh campaign by prosecutors and judges. Italian democracy, they argue, was not really damaged under his watch. His critics were vocal; they were not silenced.</p>
    <p>Allegations of corruption are met with a retort that the left is corrupt, too. And, finally, while Berlusconi’s grip on the media represented the biggest threat to democratic values, it was the left that, even now, years later, has failed to force a change of rules to dismantle such conflicts.</p>
    <p>“The internal view was never as bad as how he was seen internationally. I am the first to have said or written that, in government, Berlusconi has failed, but he has not done major damage either,” Orsina says.</p>
    <p>Even as most outsiders point to Berlusconi’s record for sexism, and the fact that his media empire relentlessly propagated the objectification of women, Orsina and others say that although people think of him as surrounding himself with showgirls, there are serious female politicians in Forza Italia that he promoted.</p>
    <p>The story of Berlusconi’s return is about more than just the man himself. It is also the story of the extraordinary collapse of the political fortunes of Renzi, 43, the centre-left leader, former prime minister and former mayor of Florence, who was supposed to usher in a new political era, and leave Berlusconi in the dust. At the height of his tenure, in 2014, it seemed that the young, charismatic Renzi, with his ability to communicate a vision for a new era in Italian politics – with reform and an end to “politics as usual” – suggested Italy was ready to turn a page.</p>
    <p>But Renzi’s decision to hold an ill-advised referendum on electoral reform in 2016 – he lost badly and had to resign – and a handful of political and financial scandals involving his inner circle of advisers, who were known as the <hi rend="#i">giglio magico,</hi> the magic Florentine circle, took the shine off the “demolition man”.</p>
    <p>Voters nevertheless profess a level of agitation about Berlusconi’s return. “This model of democracy, it’s not the democracy of Socrates, of Plato, of Aristotle,” laments Vincenzo Barbera, a retired schoolteacher in Palermo who is unsure about who he will support. “It’s a Berlusconi model, just the same as the US’s Trump model.”</p>
    <p>Barbera and his wife, Anna Maria Maltesa, taking an evening stroll, see an Italy that is still not a meritocracy, one in which favours – either from organised crime or government – ultimately determine a young person’s fate. Although Italy was technically unified in 1870, it is still a divided country, they say.</p>
    <p>For all of their frustration, Barbera is uneasy about the Five Star Movement, and Renzi is simply dismissed as a public relations phenomenon who could not, ultimately, deliver on his promises.</p>
    <p>Sitting in her cosy top-floor flat in Rome, just steps away from central Piazza Navona, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/jul/25/arab-spring-label-future-west-democracy">Emma Bonino</ref>, the Italian feminist and former foreign minister who helped establish abortion and divorce rights in the 1970s, says Renzi’s fall is reminiscent of the politics of ancient Rome.</p>
    <p>“Almost everyone I knew fell in love with him, which is quite typical, and now they are the same people who despise him, which is what happens when you don’t have citizens but what in Italian we would call <hi rend="#i">plebei</hi> [commoners],” Bonino says.</p>
    <p>“They are like the ones who went to the Colosseum in ancient times. They went to the Circus Maximus where warriors were fighting against lions, and everyone was cheering and passionate, and 24 hours later they despised everyone,” she says.</p>
    <p>Bonino says Berlusconi filled the vacuum created by Renzi’s missteps. But what worries her more than Berlusconi are the questions about his coalition and the implications for Italy of the rise of his most important political partner, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/apr/26/donald-trump-gets-my-backing-says-italys-matteo-salvini">Matteo Salvini</ref>, the 44-year-old leader of the regionalist Northern League.</p>
    <p>Bonino points to a spate of recent articles that suggest Salvini could become interior minister if the centre-right wins in March. “For me, this is the real danger,” she says.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi may, indeed, be a moderating force on Salvini, who is openly xenophobic and racist. But the former prime minister has had serious health problems – he underwent major heart surgery in 2016. The unanswered question is who will follow in his footsteps.</p>
    <p>Most pundits do not forecast that Berlusconi’s coalition will win an outright majority on 4 March, though polls show they are edging toward 40%, with about 30% of voters still undecided.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">A</hi>nalysts predict that the election will lead to a hung parliament, and more instability. The Five Star Movement has traditionally spurned alliances, so even though it is the most popular single opposition, it could be kept out of government and remain a protest party.</p>
    <p>Some people predict that, as with Renzi’s administration, Berlusconi will have to combine forces with the centre-left for a grand coalition government that could – potentially – keep the current prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/dec/11/italy-paolo-gentiloni-to-succeed-matteo-renzi-as-prime-minister">Paolo Gentiloni</ref>, in place, as a leader upon whom most parties could agree.</p>
    <p>But with five weeks left to go it is too soon to count out the possibility of an outright win for one of Italy’s richest men.</p>
    <p>Back in 2001, with just weeks to go before Italy was to hold a national election, the then editor-in-chief of the <hi rend="#i">Economist</hi>, Bill Emmott, made a bold and damning pronouncement: Berlusconi was <ref target="http://www.economist.com/node/593654">unfit to lead any country</ref>, least of all one of the world’s richest democracies.</p>
    <p>It was not just the fact that Berlusconi controlled a vast business empire that raised untenable conflicts of interest (which he was uninterested in correcting), but that the man who was poised to become prime minister – again, after a stint in 1994 – was under investigation for a litany of serious misdemeanours, from money laundering to bribery to associations with organised crime.</p>
    <p>The foreign press has an exalted reputation in Italian culture, and Emmott’s admonition caused a stir. But it did not hurt Berlusconi at the polls. He won Sicily in a landslide.</p>
    <p>Today Emmott has changed his tune. In a recent article entitled <ref target="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/italy-election-berlusconi-comeback-by-bill-emmott-2018-01">The bunga-bunga party returns to Italy</ref>, Emmott describes how Berlusconi has cast himself as the elder statements, and thinks – just maybe – that he is right.</p>
    <p>Should Berlusconi’s centre-right coalition win an outright majority, Emmott writes, he will be the man to choose Italy’s next prime minister. If he falls short of that goal, he will nevertheless – surely – have a leading role in forming a grand coalition.</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi, in other words, is back. “Most remarkable of all,” Emmott wrote, “either scenario would be widely regarded as a stable and respectable outcome, compared with the most likely alternative: a minority government led by M5S.</p>
    <p>“Could Berlusconi end up being Italy’s political saviour? Don’t rule it out.”</p>
    <head rend="h2">Who’s in the running</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Democratic party</hi><lb/> Led by the former prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/matteo-renzi">Matteo Renzi</ref>, the centre-left Democratic party is trailing in the polls and is struggling to form alliances. The left has been splintered by fights between centrists and forces further to the left, who dismiss Renzi’s policies as being too business- and bank-friendly. The party is thought to be heading for a humiliating defeat on 4 March.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Five Star Movement</hi><lb/> The populist M5S has the overwhelming support of young voters but a poor track record in municipal governments. Co-founder Beppe Grillo recently stepped away, a move that could boost the party’s chances. The comedian turned politician was criticised for taking a swipe at Sadiq Khan, saying the Muslim mayor of London would “blow himself up in front of Westminster”.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Forza Italia</hi><lb/> It is still unclear whether Silvio Berlusconi would be allowed to serve as prime minister. He was banned from serving for six years following a conviction for tax fraud, but is challenging the legality of that law in European courts. As the head of Forza Italia – Let’s Go Italy, the party the four-times prime minister formed in 1993 – Berlusconi is nevertheless leading a coalition, alongside two parties on the far right – the Northern League and Brothers of Italy – which could plausibly win an absolute majority.</p>
    <p>Other potential prime ministers of the centre-right coalition include Luca Zaia, the Northern League president of Veneto, and Antonio Tajani, the president of the European parliament and a member of Berlusconi’s Forza Italia party.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>