<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi at Easter mass in quake city L'Aquila" author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-04-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/13/berlusconi-easter-mass-laquila-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="L'Aquila survivors celebrate holiest day on Roman Catholic calendar in makeshift chapels across central Italy" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Natural disasters and extreme weather,World news,Europe" fingerprint="7eaa136c36e1a057">
  <main>
    <p>Survivors of the Italian earthquake celebrated Easter Sunday mass yesterday in makeshift chapels across central <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>The prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who attended a mass for rescue workers and volunteers in the city of L'Aquila, declared the emergency phase over, but said it would still be months before most people displaced by the quake will know if they can go back to their homes.</p>
    <p>"Within two months we hope to certify which buildings can be inhabited and only then will we know how many citizens can return to their own homes," Berlusconi said.</p>
    <p>About 150, mostly elderly people celebrated the holiest day on the Roman Catholic calendar in L'Aquila's main tent city, where the population has declined to 1,300 from a peak of 1,700, as many with means find a more comfortable place to stay. L'Aquila's archbishop, Giuseppe Molinari, who said mass, acknowledged the anger over the huge losses suffered. "We're all a bit angry with God because we never expected a tragedy this big. But even anger toward God is a sign of faith."</p>
    <p>Another earthquake victim died in hospital yesterday, raising the death toll to 294.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said more than 55,000 people who were displaced by last Monday's 6.3-magnitude quake had been given temporary housing, nearly 22,000 in hotels and private homes, and another 33,306 in 106 tent cities. Agostino Miozzo, the head of the national civil protection agency, said that until people could return to their homes, "we need to make these tent cities liveable ... We need to make them less bad than they are now".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>