<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Two jobs for crisis-hit Berlusconi" author="Sophie Arie" date="2004-07-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jul/05/italy.eu" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, will be forced to double as finance minister at the EU summit in Brussels today following a weekend of political turmoil which heaped pressure on his government." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,European Union,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="5ab8019fd8a2cb15">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, will be forced to double as finance minister at the EU summit in Brussels today following a weekend of political turmoil which heaped pressure on his government.</p>
    <p>The media tycoon took up the economic reins after frantic meetings which culminated in the resignation of Giulio Tremonti, finance minister for the past three years.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's first act in the job will be to face a grilling in Brussels over Italy's runaway public spending. It was reported that he spent yesterday swotting up on the details of the national budget.</p>
    <p>The departure of Mr Tremonti - a loyal member of Mr Berlusconi's centre-right Forza Italia and a keystone of the current administration - was seen as a sign that the Italian leader is losing control of his government.</p>
    <p>The finance minister was asked to resign when Gianfranco Fini, leader of the second-largest party in the ruling coalition, National Alliance, threatened to withdraw support in a dispute over much-needed budget cuts.</p>
    <p>However, this has angered another coalition partner, the Northern League, which had backed Mr Tremonti's plans to reduce spending in the underdeveloped south. The League brought down Mr Berlusconi's last government in 1994 by withdrawing its support.</p>
    <p>Italian newspapers described the image-conscious prime minister as "a lame duck" at the mercy of his allies while his supporters said that a change of finance minister did not constitute a crisis.</p>
    <p>Piero Fassino, leader of the Democrats of the Left, called for Mr Berlusconi to resign, saying that his government was no longer the one Italians had elected in May 2001.</p>
    <p>Forza Italia took a beating in both European and local elections last month and the opposition has called for an early general election next year, a move Mr Berlusconi has already ruled out.</p>
    <p>By lasting for three years, he has already broken the record for the longest postwar government in Italy, but at a cost: Mr Tremonti is the third min ister to make a sudden exit.</p>
    <p>Analysts say that Mr Berlusconi has lost public support mainly because the economy has been at standstill for the past two years, leaving Italians disillusioned with their leader's failure to produce the promised economic miracle.</p>
    <p>Like 12 other EU member countries, Italy faces the threat of a fine for its growing budget deficit. Mr Berlusconi is expected to outline plans to cut Italy' budget by up to €7bn (£4.7bn) at today's meeting of the EU's finance ministers.</p>
    <p>It was reported yesterday that the EU competition commissioner, Mario Monti, was being pressured to become the new finance minister.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>