<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Politics Weekly podcast: Liberal Democrats hold Eastleigh after torrid week for Clegg" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-03-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/audio/2013/mar/01/politics-weekly-podcast-liberal-democrats" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Michael White, Jonathan Isaby and Prateek Buch join Tom Clark to discuss the Eastleigh byelection, which was won by the Liberal Democrats. Plus Lizzy Davies in Rome explains the baffling result in the Italian election" categories="Politics" tags="Eastleigh byelection,Liberal Democrats,Conservatives,UK Independence party (Ukip),David Cameron,Nick Clegg,Byelections,Liberal-Conservative coalition,Politics,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Mario Monti" fingerprint="bc370f5391fee1f3">
  <main>
    <p>The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/liberaldemocrats">Liberal Democrats</ref> held onto the Hampshire seat of Eastleigh in a battle with their coalition partners that left the Conservatives reeling in third place.</p>
    <p>The result came after an extremely difficult week for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/nickclegg">Nick Clegg</ref>, as he struggled to get his story straight over what he knew of sexual harassment allegations against his party's former chief executive Lord Rennard.</p>
    <p>Ukip took an unprecedented 28% of the vote to come second. Party leader Nigel Farage says that they are no longer simply a protest vote.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile Labour candidate John O'Farrell finished a distant fourth - a result that will fuel critics of Ed Miliband's party as one that cannot compete in the south of the country.</p>
    <p>Joining Tom Clark to discuss all of this: <hi rend="#b">Jonathan Isaby</hi> of the Taxpayers' Alliance; <hi rend="#b">Prateek Buch</hi> of the Social Liberal Forum; and the Guardian's <hi rend="#b">Michael White</hi>.</p>
    <p>Also this week: we look at the Italian election which has so far failed to produce a government. With the mainstream politicians rejected by voters and no leader claiming a ruling majority is the slumbering Euro-crisis about to return with a vengeance? We hear from our Rome correspondent Lizzy Davies.</p>
    <p>Leave your thoughts below - and follow us on <ref target="http://soundcloud.com/guardianpoliticsweekly">Soundcloud</ref>.</p>
    <graphic src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/3/1/1362138913173/Lib-Dem-MP-Mike-Thornton--005.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="Lib Dem MP Mike Thornton celebrates his Eastleigh byelection win with party leader Nick Clegg"/>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>