<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Greece given €8bn referendum warning by Merkel and Sarkozy" author="Jill Treanor; Katie Allen; Dominic Rushe" date="2011-11-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/nov/02/greece-warning-referendum-merkel-sarkozy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Germany and France offer Greece ultimatum to ensure a yes on austerity vote in make-or-break talks ahead of G20 summit" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,G20,World news,European banks,Business,Greece,Europe,France,Germany,Nicolas Sarkozy,Angela Merkel,Euro,European Union,Economics,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Financial crisis,US economy,China,Austerity" fingerprint="25b7001719a6c4ec">
  <main>
    <p>A showdown between the most powerful leaders in the eurozone and George Papandreou is under way amid increasing concern about the Greek prime minister's plan to hold a referendum and the impact it is having on financial markets.</p>
    <p>Ahead of a crunch two-day summit of the leaders of the G20 in Cannes, the German chancellor, Angela Merkel, and French president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref>, were holding make-or-break talks with Papandreou. Greece was warned it will not be handed €8bn (£6.9bn) of bailout money due this month unless there is a swift yes vote in the referendum.</p>
    <p>Officials at the Greek interior ministry have identified two potential dates in December for the vote – which cannot take place until ratified by parliament. That, in turn, requires Papandreou to survive Friday night's crucial vote of confidence in his fragile government in Athens.</p>
    <p>The European leaders met their international counterparts amid signs that a new recession is now stalking the eurozone – blamed in part on the sovereign debt crisis. A report showed factories in the 17-nation euro area suffered their sharpest decline in output in two years.</p>
    <p>Ben Bernanke, the Federal Reserve chairman, also admitted the eurozone crisis was hurting the US. After the Fed warned of "significant downside risks", Bernanke said it was "a bit frustrating" to watch the euro debacle from the sidelines and listed the crisis – alongside the nuclear accident in Japan and high oil prices – as part of a run of "bad luck" that has held back US recovery.</p>
    <p>Markets regained some poise as investors pinned their hopes on a deal being hammered out in Cannes to quell the anxiety caused by Papandreou's decision to call the referendum. Markets had fallen sharply on Tuesday after the prospect of a Greek referendum snuffed out any optimism about the rescue package eurozone leaders had announced last week to bolster banks by €106bn and add extra firepower to Europe's bailout fund.</p>
    <p>But uncertainty about the negotiations in Cannes and the referendum did force a crucial bond issue by the European Financial Stability Facility (ESFS), that was intended to help pay for Ireland's rescue package, to be abandoned for two weeks.</p>
    <p>China's deputy finance minister, Zhu Guangyao, speaking in Cannes, said Beijing could not invest any more in the ESFS, because there was not enough detail. He also expressed surprise at Papandreou's plan for a referendum. "Like our European friends we did not expect the Greek referendum." Europe is relying on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/china">China</ref> to come up with vast investments to help build up the bailout fund.</p>
    <p>Germany's stock market gained 2.3%, France's 1.4% while in London the FTSE 100 index rose 62.5 points, following two days of losses. The Dow Jones index was up 1.5% shortly before the close. On currency markets the euro had a choppy day although oil prices rose amid some signs of an improvement in the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/useconomy">US economy</ref>.</p>
    <p>Before meeting her Greek counterpart,Merkel made clear her frustration about the referendum. "We agreed a programme with Greece last week, and on behalf of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> and also from Germany, I can say that we want this programme to be implemented. But for this we need clarity, and that's what we will discuss during the talks this evening."</p>
    <p>The Italians, whose borrowing costs are regarded as being prohibitively high at over 6%, are under pressure to demonstrate their commitment to reform. Silvio Berlusconi's cabinet was meeting on Wednesday to ensure he did not turn up in Cannes without evidence of key reforms, like labour laws, that President Giorgio Napolitano has demanded to see. "We are writing the decree that will be introduced at the cabinet meeting with the most urgent of the measures contained in the letter sent by the government to Brussels," Italy's infrastructure minister, Altero Matteoli, said.</p>
    <p>Leaders were presented with evidence that the uncertainty about the euro is having a knock-on effect on the economy. A gloomy manufacturing report – known as Markit manufacturing purchasers' index – showed activity among eurozone manufacturers fell for the third month running and at its fastest pace for more than two years. "If there was any doubt that the eurozone was headed for recession, these data should confirm it," said Alan Clarke, eurozone economist at Scotia Capital.</p>
    <p>He said the economies of the eurozone were "screaming out [for] interest rate cuts from the European Central Bank. It is just a case of when, not if."</p>
    <p>The first test of the ECB's new boss, Italy's Mario Draghi, comes on Thursday with a discussion over whether to reverse interest rate rises imposed earlier this year when there were more concerns about inflation than recession in the eurozone.</p>
    <p>In a Reuters poll of 70 economists, 11 said the ECB would cut rates to 1.25% from 1.5% at this meeting. Two-thirds predicted a cut by December.</p>
    <p>James Nixon, at Société Générale, said: "The optimism stemming from last week's euro summit has now clearly dissipated and as a result, financial conditions are unlikely to improve in the fourth quarter. This increases the risk of a more protracted slowdown than we have hitherto envisaged."</p>
    <p>The eurozone crisis was only going to make matters worse, economists warned. "October's manufacturing surveys suggest Europe was slipping into recession even before the latest twist in the euro-zone crisis," said Andrew Kenningham, senior economist at Capital <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics">Economics</ref>. "As the eurozone crisis deepens, however, it is likely to drag world growth down further."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>