<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Ups and downs of Silvio Berlusconi's political career – timeline" author="Lizzy Davies" date="2013-11-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/27/silvio-berlusconi-political-career-timeline" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian former prime minister has been expelled from Senate 20 years after entering politics by founding Forza Italia party" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,The League" fingerprint="7e2cda2f9766c744">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">1993</head>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi, a law graduate and billionaire media tycoon, founds his own political party, Forza Italia – Go Italy – named after a chant used by AC Milan fans.</p>
    <head rend="h2">March 1994</head>
    <p>He wins first of three election victories and forms a coalition with the rightwing National Alliance and Northern League. The coalition crumbles after seven months after it emerges Berlusconi is being investigated for bribery.</p>
    <head rend="h2">April 1996</head>
    <p>Berlusconi loses first of two elections to Romano Prodi.</p>
    <head rend="h2">May 2001</head>
    <p>He returns to power as prime minister. His government goes on to be the longest-serving in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> since the second world war.</p>
    <head rend="h2">August 2004</head>
    <p>Berlusconi hosts Tony and Cherie Blair at his Sardinian hideaway.</p>
    <head rend="h2">April 2006</head>
    <p>He declares himself "the Jesus Christ of politics" on the campaign trail, but loses again to Prodi at the ballot box.</p>
    <head rend="h2">July 2006</head>
    <p>He is ordered to stand trial for alleged fraud, false accounting, embezzlement and tax fraud.</p>
    <head rend="h2">May 2008</head>
    <p>Berlusconi is elected prime minister for the third time. He faces 50 votes of confidence over the next three years.</p>
    <head rend="h2">October 2009</head>
    <p>Patrizia D'Addario gives a TV interview claiming Berlusconi slept with her knowing she was a prostitute. Months of lurid allegations of Berlusconi-hosted "bunga bunga" sex parties follow.</p>
    <head rend="h2">December 2009</head>
    <p>Berlusconi is hit in the face with an alabaster statuette of Milan cathedral during a political rally.</p>
    <head rend="h2">February 2011</head>
    <p>A judge orders Berlusconi to stand trial on charges of paying for sex with underage alleged prostitute Karima "Ruby" El Mahroug, a charge they both deny. He is also accused of abuse of office after it emerges he intervened in 2010 to have her released from a police station where she was being held for theft.</p>
    <head rend="h2">12 November 2011</head>
    <p>Four days after losing his parliamentary majority Berlusconi steps down as prime minister.</p>
    <head rend="h2">28 October 2012</head>
    <p>Berlusconi, angered by a court's jail sentence for tax evasion, a decision he believes is politically motivated, threatens a snap election to bring down the prime minister, Mario Monti, and throw the world of Italian politics into a panic.</p>
    <head rend="h2">7 January 2013</head>
    <p>Berlusconi renews his coalition with the far-right Northern League Alliance</p>
    <head rend="h2">24 February 2013</head>
    <p>Italy heads to the polls. Centre-left Enrico Letta forms a government which includes a close ally of Berlusconi's, Angelino Alfano.</p>
    <head rend="h2">24 June 2013</head>
    <p>Berlusconi is sentenced to seven years for abuse of office and paying a minor for sex.</p>
    <head rend="h2">27 November 2013</head>
    <p>Berluscono is expelled from the Italian Senate.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>