<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi to hold 'unscheduled meeting' with Putin" author="John Hooper" date="2010-12-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/02/us-embassy-cables-berlusconi-putin" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian PM reportedly adds lunch appointment with Russian counterpart in Sochi after publication of US embassy cables" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Vladimir Putin,Italy,The US embassy cables,Russia,World news,US foreign policy,US news,Obama administration,Europe" fingerprint="2f9d923f9da6d76b">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi was tonight flying to the Black Sea resort of Sochi where, according to a report from Moscow, he was to hold an unscheduled meeting with the Russian prime minister, Vladimir Putin.</p>
    <p>The change to the Italian prime minister's plans was signalled just hours after the publication of US diplomatic cables alleging that he and Putin had a secret business association in addition to their known personal and political links. It also came shortly after <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/russia">Russia</ref> was announced host country for the 2018 football World Cup.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi had been due to attend a two-day Italo-Russian summit that included a lunch with President Dmitri Medvedev tomorrow. But, according to the Ansa news agency quoting sources in Moscow, Putin will also fly to Sochi to attend the lunch.</p>
    <p>The release of the cables by WikiLeaks deepened the crisis surrounding Berlusconi's already embattled government, which faces a motion of no-confidence on 14 December. Five centrist groups in the Italian parliament today stepped up the pressure on the prime minister, calling on him to resign and announcing that, if he refused to do so, they would table a motion.</p>
    <p>One of the groups, Freedom and Future for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, was created by former ally Gianfranco Fini, who split from Berlusconi in July. That, on paper at least, left the government without a majority in the lower house.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi began today in Astana, the capital of Kazakhstan, where he lavished praise on its president. Italy's billionaire leader, who had been attending a conference of the Organisation for Co-operation and Security in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, said Nursultan Nazarbayev, who has been in power since 1990, was "rightly loved" by the population.</p>
    <p>Addressing him directly, Berlusconi said: "I have seen opinion polls carried out by an independent authority which have given you, Nursultan, 92% of the esteem and love of your people. It is a consensus that cannot but be based on deeds."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>