<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Paolo Sorrentino stops work on 'complicated' Berlusconi movie" author="Catherine Shoard" date="2016-11-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2016/nov/29/paolo-sorrentino-silvio-berlusconi-film-the-young-pope" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The director, who won an Oscar for The Great Beauty, has shelved plans for a biopic of the former Italian prime minister, and will instead work on a second series of The Young Pope" categories="Film" tags="Paolo Sorrentino,Film,Culture,The Young Pope,Television &amp; radio,Silvio Berlusconi,Biopics" fingerprint="4bbbc46d8591d372">
  <main>
    <p>Paolo Sorrentino, the Italian film-maker who has made a career of movies focusing on the loneliness of ageing playboys with enormous power, is no longer working on a biopic of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>The film, titled Loro, had been pencilled in to shoot next summer, but in a <ref target="http://news.cinecitta.com/default.aspx?pag=53&amp;nav=IT&amp;lng=it-it&amp;cnt=68508">new interview</ref>, Sorrentino said: “[I]t is a complicated story and it is not always possible to do the film that you want to do.”</p>
    <p>Loro had not been regarded as an especially controversial project, with reports saying it was “expected to be a depiction of Berlusconi’s world, but not a scathing sterile criticism”. The Hollywood Reporter speculates that funding may been hard to secure given Italy’s shaky finances and the stated lack of interest in the project by Medusa, which co-financed <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2015/may/20/youth-review-cannes-film-festival-2015-michael-caine">Youth</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2013/sep/05/le-grande-bellezza-great-beauty-review">The Great Beauty</ref>, and which is owned by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>Instead of the film, Sorrentino will work on a second season of big-budget series <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/the-young-pope">The Young Pope</ref>, which has been a huge success in Italy, although viewing figures in the UK have been less impressive. The series, which stars Jude Law and Diane Keaton, premieres in the US early next year.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>