<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi apology heals rift over Nazi jibe" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2003-07-03" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jul/03/italy.germany" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Chancellor Gerhard Schröder today said a diplomatic crisis with Italy was over, after Italian premier Silvio Berlusconi apologised for telling a German MEP that he should play a Nazi concentration camp guard in a film." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Germany,European Union,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="bcaa8867998ee50d">
  <main>
    <p>Chancellor Gerhard Schröder today said a diplomatic crisis with Italy was over, after Italian premier <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> apologised for telling a German MEP that he should play a Nazi concentration camp guard in a film.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi "expressed his regret about the choice of this expression and comparison," Mr Schröder told reporters in Berlin after speaking to Mr Berlusconi by telephone.</p>
    <p>"I told him that for me the matter was closed," Mr Schröder said.</p>
    <p>Earlier, Mr Schröder had demanded an apology for Mr Berlusconi's remarks to MEP Martin Schultz.</p>
    <p>The chancellor told the German parliament that Mr Berlusconi's comments, made during an address to the European parliament in Strasbourg yesterday, were "completely unacceptable".</p>
    <p>"I expect the Italian premier to formally apologise for this comparison," he said.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's jibe was directed at Mr Schultz, a Social Democratic MEP, during a speech to mark the start of Italy's six-month presidency of the EU.</p>
    <p>During a question and answer session following Mr Berlusconi's speech, which outlined Italy's priorities for the rotating presidency of the EU, Mr Schulz made a reference to the Italian leader's use of an immunity law to sidestep bribery charges.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi retorted: "Mr Schulz, I know there is a producer in Italy who is making a film on the Nazi concentration camps. I will suggest you for the role of commandant. You'd be perfect."</p>
    <p>Within hours, uproar in the European parliament had led to tit-for-tat diplomatic complaints in Berlin and Rome.</p>
    <p>Mr Schröder's office called in Italy's ambassador to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref>, Silvio Fagiolo, to hear a formal complaint about Mr Berlusconi's comment.</p>
    <p>In Rome, the Italian foreign ministry responded in kind by summoning the German ambassador, Klaus Neubert.</p>
    <p>Mr Neubert was told that Mr Schulz's comments "constituted a grave, unacceptable offence to the dignity" of Mr Berlusconi and all Italian and European institutions.</p>
    <p>The ministry also told the German ambassador that Mr Berlusconi's comments "certainly weren't intended to offend the German people or hurt their sensibility", and that the Italian premier "was sorry that his response was interpreted differently by some".</p>
    <p>However, members of Mr Schröder's Social Democratic party (SPD) were not mollified.</p>
    <p>"In relation to the countless people who fell victim to the dictatorship of the National Socialists, including many Social Democrats, there can be no irony," said Olaf Scholz, the secretary-general of the SPD.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>