<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: The Times attacks me because I taxed Rupert Murdoch's channels" author="Ben Dowell" date="2009-06-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2009/jun/04/silvio-berlusconi-the-times-rupert-murdoch" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Imposition of VAT on pay channels, including Sky Italia, led to 'breakdown in relations', says Italian prime minister. By Ben Dowell" categories="Media" tags="The Times,Rupert Murdoch,News Corporation,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3aaa803f9fb7c78c">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, accused the Times today of writing critical editorials about him because his government is in dispute with its owner, Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi blamed a series of articles in the Times on his government's <ref target="http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1880283,00.html">introduction of a 20% tax rate on pay TV firms last autumn, which affected Murdoch's Sky Italia business</ref>.</p>
    <p>In an interview on the Canale 5 TV channel, which he owns, Berlusconi said: "I don't mean to be nasty but unfortunately with the episode on VAT for Sky there was a breakdown in relations with the Sky group and with Murdoch's group, which has published a series of very critical articles attacking me."</p>
    <p>One recent Times article, written by Mary Beard and headlined <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/columnists/guest_contributors/article6418491.ece">"If the emperor has no clothes, history will expose him"</ref> dwelt on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/31/noemi-letizia-boyfriend-berlusconi-apology">Berlusconi's friendship with an aspiring teenage model, which has prompted his wife to demand a divorce</ref>.</p>
    <p>Beard compared Berlusconi with the decadent Roman emperor Tiberius, who she wrote was as "notorious for his sexual frolics as he was keen to keep them quiet. Remind you of anyone?"</p>
    <p>On Monday, the Times published an <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/leading_article/article6401859.ece">editorial entitled "The Clown's Mask Slips" </ref> that attacked Berlusconi for alleged womanising and inappropriate behaviour.</p>
    <p>"The most distasteful aspect of Silvio Berlusconi's behaviour is not that he is a chauvinist buffoon," the leader began. "Nor is it that he cavorts with women more than 50 years younger than himself, abusing his position to offer them jobs as models, personal assistants or even, absurdly, candidates for the European Parliament. What is most shocking is the utter contempt with which he treats the Italian public."</p>
    <p>Sky Italia currently commands about 90% of the Italian pay-TV market. Berlusconi's Mediaset, while having some pay subscribers, controls the terrestrial market with three channels, not subjected to VAT charges. As prime minister, Berlusconi also effectively controls the three channels operated by RAI, the state broadcaster.</p>
    <p>When Berlusconi doubled the VAT rate on pay-TV subscriptions from 10% to 20% last autumn, Sky Italia responded with a series of advertisements calling the decision unfair to consumers.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was also said to be furious at the broadcast on Murdoch's Sky Italia in April of the film <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/mediamonkeyblog/2009/apr/16/silvio-berlusconi-rupert-murdoch">Killing Silvio, which depicted an attempt to kidnap him</ref>. It was claimed that the film was intended to "instigate hatred against the prime minister".</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i"> To contact the MediaGuardian news desk email editor@mediatheguardian.com or phone 020 3353 3857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 3353 2000.</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>