<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="'Anti-everything' Tuscans boo out Berlusconi" author="Sophie Arie" date="2003-03-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/mar/04/italy.sophiearie" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi has been forced to abandon plans to add a 10th-century Tuscan castle to his private collection of villas after residents made it clear that he is not welcome." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="69cb522908c9ca0d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has been forced to abandon plans to add a 10th-century Tuscan castle to his private collection of villas after residents made it clear that he is not welcome.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister was abused by the people of the traditionally leftwing hilltop town of Montalcino, near Siena, on a recent visit, the environment under-secretary, Roberto Tortoli, said.</p>
    <p>"As far as I know, he has had second thoughts ... because of the type of welcome he received in the region," he told journalists in Florence.</p>
    <p>"This is not a normal country," he said. "Tuscany is like a black hole in western democracy - anti-government, anti-globalisation, anti-America, anti-everything."</p>
    <p>Last month it was reported that Mr Berlusconi, who owns villas in Sardinia and Portofino, was planning to buy Velona Castle as a "meeting place".</p>
    <p>Tuscany, known for its renaissance architecture, hill-top towns and some of Italy's best food and wine, is one of the country's wealthiest re gions and traditionally votes leftwing. It has been a focal point for recent protests against globalisation and war.</p>
    <p>Protesters have chained themselves to railway lines to stop trains carrying military equipment destined for the Gulf to a US base near Pisa, and a ski resort was attacked by environmental activists.</p>
    <p>On Sunday two suspected members of the the Red Brigades terror group were caught on a train near Arezzo. The police suspect that the pair, one of whom was killed, may have been planning to assassinate a government figure.</p>
    <p>The mayor of Montalcino, Massimo Ferrettive, confirmed that there had been an "incident" when Mr Berlusconi visited but blamed tourists.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>