<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi says he will not run for prime minister at next election" author="John Hooper" date="2012-10-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/oct/09/silvio-berlusconi-run-prime-minister" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian PM rules himself out of race next spring after four months of uncertainty" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Mario Monti,Europe,World news" fingerprint="7f9ad02d9162f53c">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has signalled that he will not, after all, run for prime minister at the next general election in Italy, due next spring. Instead, he floated the prospect of his successor, Mario Monti, leading the right in the hustings.</p>
    <p>Speaking about himself in the third person, the media tycoon told one of his own television channels: "Silvio Berlusconi has always said and continues to say that he is ready to stand aside to allow all moderates to unite in a single force that can face the left together." His comment brought to an end – albeit a somewhat fuzzy end – four months of uncharacteristic dithering.</p>
    <p>In June, he was widely assumed to have thrown his hat back into the ring after calling, at a rally of young conservatives, for the electorate to "give me 51% [of the votes]". Since then, however, his chances of a triumphant comeback have been severely undermined by his party's involvement in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/sep/25/lazio-governor-resigns-amid-scandal">a string of corruption scandals, notably in Lazio</ref>, the region around Rome, and elsewhere.</p>
    <p>Polls have repeatedly shown that not even Berlusconi's acknowledged campaigning skills could revive the fortunes of the Freedom People (PdL), the movement he founded on the basis of an alliance between his own followers and former neo-fascists. In a comment for the website of the daily La Stampa, the paper's political correspondent, Ugo Magri, said: "Judging by the most reliable estimates, if [Berlusconi] were to run he would risk a catastrophic fall [in votes]."</p>
    <p>In sharp contrast, support for Monti has grown since the early summer, despite harsh economic measures by his "technocratic" government aimed at pulling <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> out of the euro crisis. A poll this month indicated that he was far and away the most popular choice for prime minister, with 43% of Italians favouring a second mandate.</p>
    <p>Asked if Monti might replace him, Berlusconi told his interviewer: "I absolutely would not rule out it being <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref>. Ever since I've known him he has always been in the liberal camp, so it could easily be Mario Monti."</p>
    <p>The prime minister, who took office last November, has international credibility and the support of many in the financial and business communities. But it remains to be seen whether he would be ready to put himself at the head of a party so discredited by scandal.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>