<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's son in row over Mediaset sex content" author="John Hooper" date="2014-01-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jan/22/berlusconi-son-mediaset-sex-content" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Two programmes on Italian network told to make radical changes or shutdown by vice-president of organisation" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Television industry,Media,Europe,World news" fingerprint="f62112f90edf359">
  <main>
    <p>Like father, but apparently not like son. Pier <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the vice-president of Mediaset, his father's TV empire, has reportedly threatened to scrap two of the network's programmes unless they cut out – or at least tone down – the sex content.</p>
    <p>Earlier this week, the Italian parents' movement, known by its initials as Moige, launched a scathing attack on Mediaset's flagship Sunday afternoon programme, Domenica Live. Elisabetta Scala, Moige's media spokesperson, said it had written "one of the saddest and trashiest pages" in the history of Italian television.</p>
    <p>Scala said the programme, which went out at 2pm, was quite unsuited to a time of day when children were watching. It consisted almost entirely of reports with a sexual content. They included items on a musician under investigation for sexually abusing underage girls; army NCOs accused of sexually harassing young women soldiers; a clinic for sex addicts; a teacher claimed to have had sexual relations with his pupils, and a car park where young couples could go to have sex. In addition, the presenter interviewed a woman involved in multiple sexual relationships.</p>
    <p>The website of the daily Corriere della Sera said that, following an internal investigation, Pier Silvio Berlusconi had chaired a meeting at Mediaset's headquarters on Tuesday at which he made clear his annoyance with Domenica Live and another programme on a different Mediaset channel. The report said he had threatened to close down both programmes unless they made radical changes.</p>
    <p>Mediaset declined to comment.</p>
    <p>Pier Silvio Berlusconi's reported intervention is a far cry from the flesh-and-glitter variety shows with which Berlusconi's father broke into the closed world of Italian television in 1980s. His most notorious offering was Colpo Grosso, a so-called "Sexy Game al Casino", which involved a troupe of bare-breasted showgirls and contestants who shed their clothing as the game progressed.</p>
    <p>Interviewed on radio, Domenica Live's presenter Barbara D'Urso apologised for Sunday's programming, which she described as a "little slip". She said she had not seen all the items before going on air.</p>
    <p>Since 2009, Silvio Berlusconi's name has been repeatedly linked to sexual scandal. Last year, he was convicted of paying a 17-year-old girl for sex and then taking advantage of his position as Italy's then prime minister to cover up their relationship. Berlusconi, who is appealing against his conviction and denies wrongdoing, was sentenced to seven years in prison.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>