<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi kicks up a storm over plan to curb TV access" author="John Hooper" date="2003-12-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/dec/20/italy.television" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi's opponents, and even some of his followers, were yesterday left reeling by the latest move in his increasingly ruthless fight to preserve his media influence." categories="Media" tags="Media,Italy,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="5efa410db787c30f">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's opponents, and even some of his followers, were yesterday left reeling by the latest move in his increasingly ruthless fight to preserve his media influence.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister has announced that one of his top priorities in the new year will be to review the legislation that guarantees parties equal access to TV air time.</p>
    <p>It was introduced specifically to stop Mr Berlusconi from using his control of Italian commercial television to promote his party, Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>"The modification of the [law on equal access] is one of the issues... we need to discuss. It will be on [our] working agenda from January 7," he said.</p>
    <p>According to a report in yesterday's La Stampa newspaper, draft legislation has already been prepared.</p>
    <p>The paper said it also included the lifting of a ban on "negative advertising", that would allow parties and candidates to denigrate their election rivals.</p>
    <p>Though he has maintained his usual, sunny demeanour, Mr Berlusconi is widely reported to be extremely angry about the threat to his vast TV empire which materialised earlier this week when President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi refused to sign his government's communications bill.</p>
    <p>The proposed law would reverse a ruling by Italy's highest court ordering Rete4, one of the prime minister's three channels, to be transferred to satellite from January 1.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who has said he will close down Rete4 rather than see it shifted to satellite, announced a government decree to keep the channel on the air.</p>
    <p>It is expected the measure will be signed shortly before the deadline, but it remains to be seen whether President Ciampi will agree to countersign it.</p>
    <p>The prime minister's TV holding group, Mediaset, has said that job losses will run into thousands if Rete4 were to close.</p>
    <p>Without a decree, another provision of the constitutional court will come into effect, banning one of Italy's three publicly owned channels from taking advertisements.</p>
    <p>The director general of RAI, Italy's state broadcaster, has warned that that could lead to further redundancies.</p>
    <p>Although the threat to jobs has limited the opposition's argument, politicians have continued to criticise Mr Berlusconi's tactics, which threaten a bitter run-up to next June's European elections.</p>
    <p>Piero Fassino, the leader of the Democratic Left party, said he was convinced "Berlusconi is tremendously frightened of losing the elections and, for that reason, is doing everything he can to alter the rules in his favour".</p>
    <p>The latest initiative has also split the prime minister's followers. Equal access to air time is critically important for the smaller parties that make up Mr Berlusconi's parliamentary majority.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's initiative appeared at first to have the backing of the hard right National Alliance, the second-biggest party in his governing coalition. But yesterday one of the alliance's most prominent younger members balked at the idea.</p>
    <p>Gianni Alemanno, the agriculture minister, said: "We need to move with great caution to avoid giving more gifts to the left."</p>
    <p>About 95% of television output in Italy is directly or indirectly controlled by Mr Berlusconi. The three publicly owned channels are responsible to a parliament which his party and supporters dominate.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>