<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's gift to the mafia | Roberto Mancini" author="Roberto Mancini" date="2009-06-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/jun/29/berlusconi-mafia-wiretapping" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Roberto Mancini: A new wiretapping law makes prosecutors' jobs much harder – the grateful mafia will certainly express their thanks in votes" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Mafia,Silvio Berlusconi,Surveillance,World news,Organised crime,Europe" fingerprint="36eec32b7370d049">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piero_Ostellino">Piero Ostellino</ref> is the former editor and journalist of <ref target="http://www.corriere.it/">Il Corriere Della Sera</ref>, the most distinguished and conservative of all Italian newspapers. This is how he describes Italy today in the preface to his new book <ref target="http://www.lafeltrinelli.it/products/9788817028219/Lo_stato_canaglia/Piero_Ostellino.html?prkw=italia&amp;srch=9">Lo stato canaglia</ref> (The scoundrel state):</p>
    <quote>A country paralysed by a huge number of laws and regulations, suffocated by an invasive and slow-witted bureaucratic culture; run by a plethoric, costly, inefficient, and often corrupted, civil service; oppressed by punitive fiscal laws for those who pay their taxes and absent-minded towards those who don't; the prisoner of guild or nepotistic interests; from Rome southwards, in the hands of organised crime. A country in a relentless cultural, economic, political decline. This is Italy today.</quote>
    <p>I must be dreaming: here is a fierce protector of the establishment ruthlessly criticising it and using words that leave no room for hope. Ostellino, who is a moderate liberal rather than an opposition journalist, has written a book in which he tries, in vain, to find liberal ideas in his homeland, a country now run in a style reminiscent of Peròn on a series of soundbites.</p>
    <p>Ostellino's accurate analysis of our sick and weak country is given added force by the Berlusconi government's imminent new <ref target="http://www.eurotrib.com/story/2009/6/10/193417/055">law on wiretapping</ref>. Under the pretext of protecting privacy, the new law is a gift to the mafia. For a start, it will make it much more complicated for a public prosecutor to obtain permission to wiretap. They will be required to seek permission from three judges, instead of just one, to instigate a wiretap during a criminal investigation. But the real change is contained in this subtle nuance: whereas previously you could use wiretapping only in the "presence of a serious suspicion of a crime" now it will only be permissable when there is "serious circumstantial evidence of guilt".</p>
    <p>Let me give you an example to explain the difference.</p>
    <p>Often links between the various members of mafia families are pieced together and identified through collateral crimes. For example: if a few cars are set on fire, if some loan sharks are arrested, if a few shopkeepers are beaten up, if some building site vehicles (bulldozers, cranes) are set ablaze, the wiretapping could be extended to the victims' milieu.</p>
    <p>Since the terrified victims hardly ever talk or press charges against their persecutors, and pay these racketeers monthly protection money, it can take months of wiretapping before investigators manage to identify the foot soldiers who carry out these crimes. And how do you get at those at the top of the mafia family for whom they work? How can you prove the hierarchical link between the neighbourhood boss and the rank and file mafioso who sets fire to shops? Up to now, when you were in the "presence of serious suspicion of a crime", you could tackle the investigation by using of wiretapping.</p>
    <p>This will now no longer be possible: what circumstantial evidence can be produced to show a link between the person who carries out an order and the instigator? Logic has been turned upside down: in the past, wiretapping could help prove the guilt of the highest-ranking levels of the mafias (which are often formed by business consultants, lawyers, engineers, notaries). Now, in order to use wiretapping, you will first have to prove that they are guilty. It virtually guarantees that prosecutors will never be able to discover the identities of those at the highest levels of the mafias, only their "foot soldiers".</p>
    <p>The icing on the cake is that even if prosecutors persuade three judges that there is "serious circumstantial evidence of guilt", they will only be able to wiretap the suspect for 60 days. So, if a mafia boss orders a killer to carry out an execution and then leaves for a three-month holiday in the Bahamas, breaking off all contacts with Sicily, no responsibility for the crime will be linked to his phone number. On the 61st day, however, with a copy of the new law in hand, he might safely order a second murder. And so on.</p>
    <p>This new law is a gift to the mafia, the Camorra and the 'Ndrangheta, who will unite to thank their political benefactors by voting for them in the next election.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>