<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="John de Mol and Silvio Berlusconi buy Endemol" author="Chris Tryhorn" date="2007-05-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/may/14/independentproductioncompanies.citynews" hostname="theguardian.com" description="1.15pm update: Endemol is to be sold for €3.5bn to a consortium backed by John de Mol and Silvio Berlusconi. By Chris Tryhorn." categories="Media" tags="Independent production companies,Business,Media,Media business,Television industry,Silvio Berlusconi,Endemol" fingerprint="7801c8dc9b130399">
  <main>
    <p>Big Brother producer Endemol is to be sold for €3.5bn (£2.4bn) to a consortium including the group's co-founder John de Mol and former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>Spanish telecoms giant Telefonica said today it had agreed to sell its 75% stake in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/endemol">Endemol</ref> to the consortium for €2.63bn (£1.8bn).</p>
    <p>The buyers have also committed themselves to buying out the remaining 25% of Endemol's shares, which were floated on the Dutch stock exchange in November 2005.</p>
    <p>The owners of the publicly traded shares will be paid a price "at least equal" to what Telefonica is being paid for its 75% stake in Endemol.</p>
    <p>Overall, the deal values Endemol at €3.5bn (£2.4bn), representing a heavy discount on the €5.5bn paid by Telefonica in 2000, at the height of the dotcom-inspired boom in media companies.</p>
    <p>However, it marks a coup for Mr de Mol, who sold out at the height of the market and has now returned to Endemol heading the investment vehicle Cyrte.</p>
    <p>Cyrte is one of three partners in the winning bid team, alongside Goldman Sachs and Mediacinco Catrera, and a newly incorporated entity owned by Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset and its Spanish subsidiary Telecinco.</p>
    <p>The consortium's bid beat off rival offers fronted by Endemol's former chief operating officer, Tom Barnicoat; and the managing director of Endemol France, Stephane Courbit.</p>
    <p>Mr Barnicoat's bid was reportedly backed by Apax Partners and US group Thomas H Lee, while a French private equity player, PAI, supported Mr Courbit.</p>
    <p>Endemol, which was founded in 1994 by Mr de Mol and Joop van den Ende, was put up for sale by Telefonica in March.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 7278 2332.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>