<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi waters down controversial wiretaps bill" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2010-07-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/jul/20/silvio-berlusconi-waters-down-wiretaps-bill" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Sliding approval ratings and criticism from Italian prime minister's own allies led to concession" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Privacy,World news" fingerprint="7799099e56b17fed">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has watered down a draft bill limiting the use of wiretaps that was criticised even by his own allies.</p>
    <p>The bill initially aimed to ban the media from publishing phone tap transcripts until suspects were sent to trial; a step critics said would limit the ability of the press to report on investigations, given the lengthy delays common in the Italian justice system.</p>
    <p>A government amendment presented today bowed to pressure from newspapers, the opposition and members of the Italian prime minister's party, allowing the publication of transcripts when considered relevant by investigating magistrates.</p>
    <p>By rowing back on one of the most controversial elements of the bill, which Berlusconi says is needed to protect privacy, the government hopes to silence critics within the ruling coalition and win parliamentary approval by the end of the month.</p>
    <p>"Common sense prevailed," said Italo Bocchino, a member of Berlusconi's People of Freedom (PDL) party, who had voiced strong reservations about the original bill.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said the changes made the bill look different from what he had in mind. "The wiretaps law will change little from the current situation, and therefore will not allow Italians to speak freely on the phone," he said.</p>
    <p>Opponents of restrictions on the use of wiretaps by police and the publication of transcripts have said the measures would help criminals and muzzle the press when the government is engulfed in a widening corruption scandal.</p>
    <p>Under the new rules, magistrates can order wiretaps only if they have serious evidence that a crime has been committed. Time restrictions would apply and authorisation would be needed to tap the phones of parliamentarians.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's decision to change the draft and avoid a showdown in parliament appears to be a significant concession as opinion polls show coalition bickering and a string of government resignations are hurting his popularity.</p>
    <p>A poll in La Repubblica today showed Berlusconi's approval rating had fallen to 39% and was now 10 percentage points lower than a year ago. The daily paper is left-leaning but its IPR poll mirrors other recent surveys. The poll found moderate voters appeared to have lost confidence in Berlusconi and his government, citing the toxic climate within his party and the government's legal woes.</p>
    <p>Two ministers and a junior minister have resigned since May over judicial investigations, and more heads could roll.</p>
    <p>The most recent scandal, which cost economy undersecretary Nicola Cosentino his job last week, centres on an alleged secret conspiracy by PDL politicians and friendly magistrates to influence political appointments and judicial decisions.</p>
    <p>The centre-left opposition however had little to cheer about, according to the IPR survey. The popularity of the main opposition Democratic Party (PD), which is also riven by internal divisions, slipped 2 points to 32%.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>