<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roberto Mancini: Liberty is being lost in Silvio Berlusconi's Italy" author="Roberto Mancini" date="2009-02-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/feb/16/silvio-berlusconi-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Roberto Mancini: In Italy, liberty is being lost under an excess of trash TV, football and sequins for the masses" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Freedom of speech,Mafia,Media,Europe" fingerprint="f2d1d1a73b19f007">
  <main>
    <p>In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> the freedom of the press is threatened in three ways:</p>
    <p>1) By the open violence of the various <ref target="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/mafie">mafie</ref>: the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camorra">Camorra</ref> in Naples, the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/'Ndrangheta">'Ndrangheta </ref>in Calabria, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mafia">Cosa Nostra</ref> in Sicily and the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacra_Corona_Unita">Sacra Corona Unita</ref> in Puglia. About a dozen journalists work under police protection.<lb/> As well as the novelist <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto_Saviano">Roberto Saviano</ref>, author of the best selling <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2008/jan/12/crime.mafia">Gomorrah</ref>, there is also <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/3187615/Anti-mafia-journalists-home-burgled.html">Rosaria Capacchione</ref>, a reporter for the Naples daily newspaper <ref target="http://www.ilmattino.it/">Il Mattino</ref>. They both live with protective police escorts. She wrote the book, <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/29/world/europe/29italy.html?pagewanted=1">L'oro della camorra</ref>, an analysis of the international financial investments of Neapolitan criminals.</p>
    <p>However an even more relevant case is <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lirio_Abbate">Lirio Abbate's</ref>. The 38-year-old reporter from the office of the Ansa Press agency in Palermo (Sicily), is protected by the police 24 hours a day.<lb/> He – author of the enlightening book I Complici (The accomplices) - has <ref target="http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=26769">reported to Reporters Sans Frontières</ref> that journalists are more and more exposed to risks: "Mafia bosses have changed in the last ten to fifteen years. They are no longer farmers and peasants. Nowadays, they are doctors, politicians, university graduates. They are aware of how important information is and therefore they try to manipulate it. Violence is only the tip of the iceberg. Journalists may also yield to pressure, be corrupted or bought."</p>
    <p>2) By liberty-destroying laws, supported by an unfortunate coalition of centre-right and centre-left, aimed at obstructing the work of courageous judges and journalists. Both political parties have decided to turn a blind eye to the mafie, important collectors of votes, on condition they avoid openly carrying out sensational acts of slaughter.</p>
    <p>To this end, the Italian Council of Ministers (cabinet) has unanimously proposed a bill which limits the use of wiretapping when investigating crimes punishable by less than 10 years' imprisonment. In addition, the law would punish the unauthorised publication of wiretapping by the media with prison sentences and heavy fines.</p>
    <p>It's hard not to be deeply suspicious about this projected bill. While claiming to offer better protection of privacy, it actually actually removes certain crimes from becoming known to public opinion and from being investigated by magistrates.</p>
    <p>3) By the progressive increase in trash TV entertainment both on Berlusconi's private channels and on the public channels .<lb/> I am ashamed that in my country about 65% of the citizens form their impressions and opinions about the world exclusively from pictures on television. Only about 5 million Italians buy a newspaper every day. This is a situation more akin to a developing nation than an advanced democracy.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian.</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>