<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi rejects calls to resign over teenage girl" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2010-11-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/02/berlusconi-beautiful-girls-gay-ruby" hostname="theguardian.com" description="'It's better to like beautiful girls than be gay,' Italian PM tells critics" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy" fingerprint="feea123b1264c759">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi today dismissed <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/01/silvio-berlusconi-must-resign-fini">opposition calls to resign over reports he helped a 17-year-old bellydancer known as Ruby who attended parties at his villa at Arcore, near Milan</ref>.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister refused to apologise for his fondness for young women and denied doing anything improper, and said at a motorcyle show in Milan: "As always, I work without interruption and if occasionally I happen to look a beautiful girl in the face, it's better to like beautiful girls than to be gay.</p>
    <p>"You should be completely reassured about the government and about the fact that it's a government that still has a majority that intends to govern until the end of its term," he said.</p>
    <p>The Corriere della Sera reported a phone call Berlusconi made to a Milan police chief on Ruby's behalf when she was detained over a theft in May, raising questions of whether he improperly intervened.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi says he helped Ruby, whose real name is reported by Italian newspapers to be Karima El Mahroug, but denies exerting any improper pressure on police officers.</p>
    <p>"This recent storm in the newspapers is a paper storm," Berlusconi said. "You will see in the end that nothing else happened apart from an act of solidarity by the prime minister, which I would have been ashamed not to do."</p>
    <p>The teenager, now 18, told newspapers she received €7,000 ($9,760) from Berlusconi after attending two parties. She has denied having sex with him.</p>
    <p>Italian newspapers have begun speculating that the scandal could bring down Berlusconi's fragile centre-right coalition. In a front-page editorial, business daily Il Sole 24 Ore wrote: "One point is certain. The Berlusconi government is paralysed. Virtually dead, you could say, due to the loss of credibility by its leader."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's government is also under fire over strikes and protests in Naples which have left more than 2,000 tonnes of rubbish uncollected on southern city's streets. Berlusconi said the municipal authorities were to blame.</p>
    <p>"You absolutely cannot, as some newspapers have done, make the government responsible and blame it for something which is the responsibility of local authorities," he said.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's comments about homosexuality drew immediate condemnation from gay rights groups and were "unfortunate, archaic and idiotic," said actor Julianne Moore, at the Rome Film Festival to present The Kids Are All Right, about a lesbian couple raising their teenage children. "To hint or to say that there is something wrong with homosexuality … it's unfortunate and it's embarrassing when people continue to perpetrate these untruths," she said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>