<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi to do community service with Alzheimer's patients" author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" date="2014-04-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/30/silvio-berlusconi-community-service-alzheimers-dementia" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Ex-Italian PM will work at centre for disabled and elderly after tax fraud conviction, but will not take part in 'fun or relaxing activities'" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="b0f8c02d930f974d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi will begin his community service on 9 May working with Alzheimer's patients, the director of the centre where he will serve his tax fraud punishment has confirmed.</p>
    <p>Paolo Pigni, head of the Catholic-run Fondazione Sacra Famiglia, near Milan, said the former Italian prime minister would work in the part of the centre dedicated to caring for people with dementia and Alzheimer's disease.</p>
    <p>The media magnate – who has been ordered to work at the centre for disabled and elderly people one day a week for at least four hours – will help out with a morning programme including motor activities, reading, writing and games, Pigni said.</p>
    <p>"Berlusconi will not take part in fun or relaxing activities, nor will he spend time in an office," Pigni said, adding that the 77-year-old would find himself dealing with "situations of suffering which can enrich him".</p>
    <p>The director said that at Sacra Famiglia, "neither Silvio Berlusconi nor anyone else will be able to work on electoral campaigns".</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has appeared on television and radio over the past few days in a bid to draw media attention to his centre-right Forza Italia party's campaign for the European elections.</p>
    <p>The billionaire was convicted of fraud last year but was allowed to opt for community service instead of prison because of the leniency shown in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> for those over 70 years old who are convicted of crimes.</p>
    <p>Comments he made this week mocking community service as "ridiculous, not just for me but for the country" may result in a warning from the judicial system, according to Italian media reports, which said Berlusconi's continued outbursts could lead to him being put under house arrest.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>