<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Does Berlusconi sense the end is near? | George Turner" author="George Turner" date="2009-08-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/aug/16/berlusconi-media-tg3" hostname="theguardian.com" description="George Turner: When Berlusconi attacked a media outlet for simply reporting the news, he managed to unite the opposition – why did he do it?" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Media,World news,Europe" fingerprint="1da7824f9070960b">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has started the summer holidays by launching a blistering series of attacks on the Italian media. It began last Friday with this response to an innocuous question on Russian gas pipelines asked by a journalist from Italy's third public news programme, TG3, to which <ref target="http://archiviostorico.corriere.it/2009/agosto/08/Berlusconi_non_scheletri_nell_armadio_co_8_090808019.shtml">he responded</ref>: "You are part of a news organisation that yesterday published four headlines, all negative and all against the government. I believe that this is something that we no longer need to and cannot support: a publicly funded television station that attacks the government."</p>
    <p>The onslaught continued into this week with attacks on La Repubblica's "<ref target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2009/08/11/berlusconi-attacca-repubblica-fa-un-giornalismo-deviato.html">deviant journalism</ref>" after it published an interview with the president of the region of Puglia and prominent gay rights campaigner <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nichi_Vendola">Nichi Vendola</ref>.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's attack on TG3 was provoked by a series of news stories that challenged his image of Italy as a successful, prosperous country lead by a charismatic and popular leader. <ref target="http://www.tg3.rai.it/dl/tg3/articoli/ContentItem-d710a063-88f5-42c5-84eb-29691f337b44.html">The stories included</ref> reports on: figures showing a decline in industrial production of 20%; news of a <ref target="http://inaltreparole.net/en/resistance/operaiinnse120809.html">protest at the Milanese company Innse</ref> where four workers were conducting a sit-in at the top of a crane; the reaction of Italy's mayors to the introduction of a law allowing vigilante groups to patrol their cities; and congestion at airports and on roads at the beginning of the summer holiday season.</p>
    <p>This is not the first time that Berlusconi has attacked the press in Italy. But he has previously directed his anger against either newspapers that printed allegations of his <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/23/berlusconi-new-sex-tapes-revealed">relationships with young girls and prostitutes</ref> or leading leftwing opinion formers. The difference in this case is that Berlusconi was attacking TG3 for simply reporting the news.</p>
    <p>But the confusing part of the story is, why should Berlusconi attack these outlets, when he has near absolute control over the others? Why not let one channel and one newspaper carry on reporting the news, if only to give the impression of a free press?</p>
    <p>After all, Berlusconi's endurance during months of lurid revelations about his sex life, can only be a testament to his successful manipulation of the media in Italy. Although much ink has been spilled describing in sometimes sickening detail Berlusconi's relationship with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/24/silvio-berlusconi-scandal-magazine-interview">Patrizia D'Addario</ref>, most Italians prefer to get their news from the television. On TV, Berlusconi is king.</p>
    <p>Even with the persistence of TG3, Berlusconi has managed to exert effective control over the other two public TV networks, and owns three of the four remaining domestic private networks. Imagine the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/mps-expenses">MPs' expenses</ref> scandal being published only in the Telegraph, with only passing references to "rumours and politically motivated accusations about MP's expenses" on the TV and in other papers. This is what is happening in Italy today, the only difference is the nature of the scandal.</p>
    <p>The answer may be that Berlusconi knows that the end may finally be near. It has been reported that the prime minister has told his closest supporters that he believes there will be <ref target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2009/08/08/in-autunno-tenteranno-di-buttarmi-giu-il.html">an attempt to depose him</ref> in the autumn, and has already started preparing his "autumn campaign". Leaders on the left believe that the real extent of the effect of the global economic crisis will reveal itself in the autumn, with <ref target="http://www.antoniodipietro.com/2009/08/un_caldo_autunno.html">Antonio di Pietro</ref>, leader of Italia dei Valori, telling Libero this Tuesday: "If it's not the apocalypse, it will be something close to it."</p>
    <p>If Berlusconi's intention was to win the war of the airwaves before an autumn battle, his comments on TG3 may have dangerously overstepped the mark, as they have achieved what neither he or anyone else has previously, a united response from the opposition. <ref target="http://www.unita.it/news/politica/87164/e_il_pd_prepara_la_mobilitazione_in_difesa_della_libert_di_stampa">Dario Francescini</ref>, leader of the largest opposition party il Partito Democratico, has threatened that if Berlusconi does not back down, he will mobilise in September to protect freedom of information in Italy, a statement that was supported by all of the party's internal factions. All other opposition parties released strong statements condemning the prime minister's comments.</p>
    <p>A united left, brought together on a platform of civil liberties and constitutional reform, may be the powerful force that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> has continually failed to produce in the age of Berlusconi. For Italian politics this does indeed promise to be a "hot autumn", but for Italy's beleaguered prime minister, could this be his last?</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>