<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The week that Europe stumbled to the brink of disaster… and stopped" author="Heather Stewart; Katie Allen" date="2011-11-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/nov/13/eurozone-crisis-italy-greece-france-germany" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prime ministers fell, markets shook and there were rumours that the eurozone would split up. But it survived – for now" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Italy,Greece,Silvio Berlusconi,George Papandreou,Angela Merkel,France,Business,Germany,European banks,Europe,World news" fingerprint="658c81a1d1238621">
  <main>
    <p>When exhausted European leaders emerged from all-night negotiations in Brussels last month with a "comprehensive" plan to claw the euro back from the abyss, they could have had no inkling that, less than a fortnight later, it would have so comprehensively collapsed.</p>
    <p>Last week, no government in Europe dared feel safe, and contagion was the word on everyone's lips. Investors' attention swung from Italy to Greece and then even to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref>, and bets poured in over who would be next to succumb to the eurozone's spiralling debt crisis.</p>
    <p>It was also a week of political turmoil, as Greece appointed a former European central banker as its interim prime minister and Italy's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> was pushed towards the exit.</p>
    <p>If the week began with a sense of limbo, it rapidly spun into chaos. Italy's media mogul PM was insisting that he remained in charge for the time being, and promised a confidence vote with the words: "I want to look into the faces of those who are trying to betray me."</p>
    <p>He went on Facebook to deny rumours of his imminent resignation, crushing hopes that a new government would rapidly be drafted in to implement reforms. The country's borrowing costs rose rapidly, reaching the levels that had forced bailouts in Portugal, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/greece">Greece</ref> and Ireland. In Greece, talks dragged on over the creation of a new government.</p>
    <p>France did its best to stay out of the firing line with promises of another €7bn of tax rises and spending cuts, which prime minister François Fillon described as "sacrifices", but which would turn out to be an inadequate defence against the bond markets as the week evolved.</p>
    <p>Tuesday saw Italian bond yields pushed towards the danger level of 7%, as uncertainty continued to rattle investors. By the end of the day, Berlusconi finally pledged to resign; he had survived sexual and financial scandals, but not the debt crisis. After losing his parliamentary majority Berlusconi agreed to go and those markets still open on Wall Street and in Asia enjoyed what wags in the City called a "bunga-bunga bounce".</p>
    <p>It did not last. By Wednesday morning, the mood was again bleak: there appeared to be no sign of Berlusconi acting on his promise to go, and no clear candidate to take over.</p>
    <p>Italy's toxic combination of large debts and sickly growth has long been a worry for bond investors, but they have always brushed it aside on the assumption that other euro members would not allow it to fail. For many years, the markets lent to Italy as though it were rock-solid <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref>. The crisis of the past six months, and the questions it has raised about the shaky foundations of the single currency, mean that can no longer be taken for granted.</p>
    <p>The fumbled attempt to "leverage" the eurozone bailout fund, the EFSF, and to ask China to contribute, served to underline just how little of Europe's own money can be relied upon for any rescue. And Italy has always been seen as what Dhaval Joshi at BCA Research calls the "killer domino": too big to be allowed to fall, but also much too big for the eurozone alone to prop up.</p>
    <p>As Italian yields jumped beyond 7%, some City veterans said the atmosphere was reminiscent of another Black Wednesday – the day in 1992 when the markets forced the pound into a chaotic withdrawal from the European exchange rate mechanism, the forerunner to the euro. Everyone had the sinking feeling things were doomed to fail.</p>
    <p>Then, just when it appeared things could not get worse, news emerged from Athens that talks about who would be the prime minister in a caretaker government had collapsed.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, reports surfaced in Brussels that France and Germany had discussed creating a smaller, "core" eurozone, cutting Greece loose, and perhaps even Italy. Reuters published comments from a "senior EU official" saying "the truth is we need to establish exactly the list of those who don't want to be part of the club and those who simply cannot be part".</p>
    <p>Angela Merkel's earlier comment that it was time to move to a "new Europe" helped fuel the rumours. The story was swiftly denied, but many observers felt there might be a nugget of truth in it, underlining how febrile the mood had become. The very possibility of a country leaving the single currency was so taboo as to be unmentionable as recently as a month ago.</p>
    <p>Simon Derrick, currency strategist at BNY Mellon, said the eurozone was "faced with a stark choice: either it changes what it is, or who its members are".</p>
    <p>Thursday morning saw a critical test of market confidence as Italy held a bond auction. It was not as bad as it could have been: there were buyers for all of the €5bn worth of 12-month bonds. Still, the interest rate demanded by investors spoke volumes about the market's faith in Italy: at above 6%, it dwarfed the 3.57% rate seen at a similar sale in October.</p>
    <p>Thursday was also when the spotlight turned to France, as its bond yields spiked and fears intensified over its capacity to cope with the crisis. The eurozone's second-largest economy came under fire for not doing even more to cut government spending. A blunder at credit ratings agency Standard &amp; Poor's sent tensions soaring further as it mistakenly issued a notice stripping France of its coveted AAA rating.</p>
    <p>In Greece, Lucas Papademos, former ECB vice-president, was appointed as temporary prime minister. He warned that his new government will need to make serious decisions about rebuilding the economy.</p>
    <p>"The days ahead will not be easy but the problems can be solved and will be solved if there is unity, co-operation and consensus [and] if we all contribute to this difficult effort to correct the economy," he said.</p>
    <p>But Greece's burgeoning mass of anti-austerity demonstrators hit back at the undemocratic nature of his appointment. "The new government and the new prime minister are being called to impose a political policy that does not have democratic legitimisation," railed Alexis Tsipras, who heads the left-wing Syriza group.</p>
    <p>By Friday, a calmer mood returned. Equity markets surged, as the Italian senate passed a package of austerity measures, and former European commissioner – and economist – Mario Monti prepared to take the reins of a coalition government.</p>
    <p>In Greece Papademos was sworn in, anointed by the Archbishop of Athens. In the weeks ahead, the fragile new governments in Athens and Rome will face the full glare of scrutiny from Brussels and the world's financial markets – and from their own voters.</p>
    <p>"Ultimately, it's a question of the size of demonstrations on the streets," says Graham Turner of GFC Economics. He believes Italy could scrape through without needing a full-blown rescue package, but few commentators believe the euro's existential crisis is over.</p>
    <p>Michael Saunders, European economist at Citigroup, says: "When's it going to erupt again? There are so many potential triggers." He cites the capital-raising Europe's banks must go through to secure their finances under last month's euro deal, forthcoming Spanish elections, and the need for a Portuguese debt restructuring as three possible flashpoints in the coming weeks alone.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>