<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi quits sickbed to stem slide in the polls" author="Barbara McMahon" date="2006-03-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/mar/19/italy.barbaramcmahon" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian Prime Minister, Silvio Berlusconi, made a surprise appearance at a meeting of Italy's business leaders having previously announced that he could not attend because of a back problem." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="302e732c9b08cf5c">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian Prime Minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, trailing in the polls and with a general election due shortly, displayed his fighting spirit yesterday when he made a surprise appearance at a meeting of Italy's business leaders having previously announced that he could not attend because of a back problem.</p>
    <p>'I told the doctors, inject me with something, do what you have to but get me on my feet,' the 69-year-old billionaire told the astonished assembly.</p>
    <p>He then launched into a typically flamboyant performance, flattering his audience, launching a blistering attack on his centre-left rival, Romano Prodi, and lambasting the Italian newspapers who say he has lost the confidence of voters. He was greeted mainly with applause and cheers, but also with some boos.</p>
    <p>Italy's richest citizen, who is hoping for a second five-year term of office, had been under fire for announcing that he was not well enough to attend the meeting of the influential business group Confindustria. He sent Economy Minister Giulio Tremonti along in his place.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's office said before the meeting that a reoccurrence of a back problem, described as acute sciatica in the lumbar region, had flared up without warning. The Prime Minister underwent physical therapy on Thursday evening. He had called off a TV appearance and a cabinet meeting in Rome as well as the Confindustria grilling after being told he needed three days of complete rest.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's critics pounced on his absence, however, scoffing at the excuse and claiming that the billionaire media tycoon was simply running scared after Prodi, who promised to lower labour costs and invest in research, had received a warm response from the same group the day before.</p>
    <p>Italian newspapers added fuel to the fire by saying that Berlusconi felt it was not worth his time attending the meeting because he believed Confindustria was aligned to the centre-left and he would not be given a fair hearing.</p>
    <p>The criticisms obviously hit Berlusconi hard and he changed his mind, rising from his sick bed yesterday afternoon to make his surprise appearance. He appeared out of the blue at the conference in northern Italy and went full-out to persuade his audience that he remained the best man to lead the country.</p>
    <p>'I couldn't miss this appointment with those who, like me, are entrepreneurs, who are the engine of Italy,' he told his audience. 'After hearing what Prodi told you yesterday, I decided I couldn't leave it without a reply.' He continued: 'Don't believe these newspapers that talk of decline, a businessman has a duty to be optimistic. If an entrepreneur who hasn't lost his head supports the left, then he has many skeletons in the cupboard, he has things that need pardoning.'</p>
    <p>It was a positive end to a bad week of campaigning for the controversial media tycoon who was also criticised for his performance on the first live television debate of the election campaign.</p>
    <p>Prodi, the leader of the centre-left challenge and a former Prime Minister and former president of the European Commission, was judged to have been more dynamic of the two.</p>
    <p>Amid yesterday's drama, Confindustria issued a statement saying that it wanted to remain neutral in the election and urged all politicians to focus on the economy as the central issue to be addressed before voters go to the polls on 9 April and 10 April.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi and Prodi will have another televised face-off in 10 days' time, giving each man another chance to reach out to the Italian electorate. The latest polls show that Berlusconi is trailing by 4 per cent against the centre-left coalition, but that almost a quarter of Italy's electorate have not yet decided how to cast their ballot or whether they will vote in the election at all.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>