<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's performing arts go on strike in cuts protest" author="Tom Kington" date="2010-11-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/22/italys-performing-arts-go-on-strike" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Cinemas, theatres and opera houses close as singers, actors and others protest against 37% cut in government subsidies" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Culture,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Arts funding,Theatre,Stage,Opera,Music,Film industry,Business,Film,Circus" fingerprint="7c35348f45b1b553">
  <main>
    <p>Cinemas, theatres, concert halls, opera houses and circuses across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> shut today for a one-day strike in protest against swingeing arts spending cuts.</p>
    <p>Up to 250,000 actors, opera singers, technicians and ticket sellers were expected to take part in the strike as the Berlusconi government pushed through an austerity budget which will cut €146m (£125m), or 37%, from subsidies to the performing arts next year.</p>
    <p>Strikers met in Rome, Bari, Genoa and Milan, where Toni Servillo, the star of the mafia film Gomorrah addressed protesters alongside Stéphane Lissner, artistic director of La Scala opera house.</p>
    <p>In Rome, where set builders from the Cinecittà film studios erected a huge Roman statue at a protest meeting to highlight the firm's fate, 1,500 strikers demanded the cuts be rescinded while speakers called for tax breaks for the cinema industry be maintained.</p>
    <p>"Many talented youngsters are abandoning the cinema industry in order to survive," said the veteran director Ettore Scola. "This way we risk losing the next Bunuel."</p>
    <p>Protesters stressed that the arts was worth supporting in Italy. Italians spent €600m in 2008 to go to the theatre and live music events compared with €355m on attending football matches.</p>
    <p>The cuts, which will reduce art subsidies from €408m to €262m, are part of a broader decline in culture and archaeology funding which some blame for the collapse of the 2,000-year-old house of the gladiators in Pompeii this month.</p>
    <p>Italy's culture minister, Sandro Bondi, who is due to face a no confidence vote next Monday following the building's collapse, also came under fire last month when actors and directors blocked the red carpet at the Rome film festival in protest against the arts cuts, upstaging the actor Keira Knightley who later sided with the protesters.</p>
    <p>Bondi called that protest "unjustified", but he appeared to take a softer line in the run up to today's strike, saying: "I cannot but understand the reasons for the protest. He added that he would fight to stop tax breaks for the film industry being axed.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>