<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="David Mills and the Italian courts" author="James Sturcke" date="2010-02-25" url="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2010/feb/25/david-mills-timeline" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Timeline: how the events unfolded" categories="UK news" tags="David Mills,Silvio Berlusconi,Tessa Jowell,Law,UK news,World news" fingerprint="228e098dd589b5dd">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">1990s </head>
    <head rend="h2">Mid-1990s</head>
    <p>Mills's activities come under increasingly close scrutiny by Italian prosecutors investigating one of his clients, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. Mills had set up offshore companies and trusts for the Italian prime minister's business empire, which prosecutors try to show had been used to dodge tax and convey under-the-counter payments to politicians. Prosecutors initially treat Mills as a prosecution witness.</p>
    <head rend="h2">1997</head>
    <p>In unrelated developments, it emerges Mills was a non-executive director of Benetton's Formula One team at a time when controversy rages over the decision by his wife, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tessajowell">Tessa Jowell</ref>, then a health minister, not to ban F1 tobacco advertising.</p>
    <head rend="h2">1999</head>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-berlusconi-trial-letter">2004 letter to his accountant</ref>
    </p>
    <head rend="h2">2000</head>
    <p>Mills wants to invest in a fund. His bank lends him €650,000 secured upon the north London home he shares with Jowell. He pays off the bank loan using the $600,000 from the "B people". According to his 2004 letter, he does not inform the UK tax authorities of the $600,000 from the "B people".</p>
    <head rend="h2">2003 </head>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2003/may/04/uk.labour1">Mills lobbied a government minister for support</ref>
    </p>
    <head rend="h2">2006</head>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">26 February</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2006/feb/28/uk.italy">details of the "B people" loan emerge in the UK press</ref>
    </p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2 March</hi> - A <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/mar/02/broadcasting.politics">cabinet inquiry clears Jowell of breaching ministerial code</ref> as Mills did not tell her about the "B people" gift. By now, Mills has retracted the version of events he wrote in the 2004 letter to his accountant and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2006/mar/02/italy.politics4">claims the money came from a shipping magnate, Diagio Attanasio</ref>.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">4 March</hi> - <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2006/mar/05/italy.labour1">Mills and Jowell announce they are to separate</ref> after 27 years of marriage.</p>
    <head rend="h2">2009 </head>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/18/mills-berlusconi-bribe-case">convicted of bribery by an Italian court</ref>
    </p>
    <head rend="h2">2010</head>
    <p>Italian appeal court rules on the 2009 verdict.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>