<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi corruption trial begins in Naples" author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" date="2014-02-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/feb/11/silvio-berlusconi-corruption-trial-begins-naples" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former PM accused of giving €3m to senator from anti-corruption party in effort to undermine government in 2006" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="7f78c200fb27a60d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's latest trial, for allegedly bribing a senator to join his party's ranks, is getting under way in Naples.</p>
    <p>The former prime minister, who lost his parliamentary immunity when he was ejected from the senate last year over a tax fraud conviction, is not expected to attend the hearing.</p>
    <p>He is accused of giving €3m(£2.5m) in 2006 to Sergio De Gregorio, then a senator with the anti-corruption <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Values party, to join his People of Freedom party and help undermine the centre-left government in power at the time.</p>
    <p>A former Berlusconi aide, Valter Lavitola, is also on trial for being the alleged intermediary in the bribe. The trial is taking place in Naples as it was the seat occupied by De Gregorio, who is collaborating with investigators. The first two hearings in the trial, on Tuesday and Wednesday, are expected to be largely procedural.</p>
    <p>Among the issues on the table will be a request from the senate speaker, Pietro Grasso, to be considered a plaintiff in the trial – a move that has proved hugely controversial among Berlusconi's supporters.</p>
    <p>A new judge is due to be named as the current one has declared a conflict of interests – she is married to a prosecutor who worked in another trial in which Berlusconi was convicted for having sex with an underage 17-year-old prostitute and abuse of office. Berlusconi is expected to appeal against those convictions this year.</p>
    <p>The list of witnesses for the trial includes the former prime minister and former European commission president Romano Prodi, as well as two former senators expected to say they were offered bribe money by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>De Gregorio has told investigators he received €2m in cash and €1m for his political movement "Italians in the World". Berlusconi's lawyers Michele Cerabona and Niccolo Ghedini are expected to argue that corrupting De Gregorio would have been impossible since every senator can vote freely, whatever their party affiliation.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was forced out of parliament in November following a tax fraud conviction. While the 77-year-old does not have to go to prison because of his age, a court will decide in April whether he has to do a year of community service or house arrest for that crime, and he has lost his parliamentary immunity.</p>
    <p>The ban from parliament has not prevented Berlusconi from seeking to remain a powerful force, however. While some of his former proteges have switched to the new centre-right party in a ruling coalition with the prime minister, Enrico Letta, Berlusconi is rallying support for his refounded Forza Italia (Go Italy) party.</p>
    <p>He is unrepentant despite his frequent run-ins with the justice system, dismissing charges against him as politically motivated, and he still enjoys the support of six or seven million Italians, according to polls.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has vowed to run a robust campaign in the European elections in May, and on Saturday he declared that the euro was a "foreign currency" for Italians. In a phone call to supporters this weekend, he got confused about where he was calling and joked that it must be the fault of "some leftwing secretary".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>