<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="What happens if Berlusconi resigns?" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/italy-after-berlusconi-scenarios" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Four blueprints for the future in Italy if Silvio Berlusconi vacates the prime minister's office" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Eurozone crisis,Europe,Business,World news" fingerprint="fbd8caff79a5c77d">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">A broader majority</hi>
    </head>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi goes, but the right stays in power. His followers tell the president, Giorgio Napolitano, they can assemble a convincing majority in parliament in alliance with Umberto Bossi's Northern League, the junior partner in the current coalition, and one or more of the parties on the right of the opposition. The key to this would be a thumbs-up from the Union of the Centre (UDC), a party of conservative Christian Democrats. Most likely candidates for premier? Berlusconi's key ally, Bossi, favours Angelino Alfano, the head of Berlusconi's party; other candidates are his eternal Mr Fixit, Gianni Letta, and the senate speaker, Renato Schifani. All three are thoroughgoing Berlusconi loyalists, but it is unclear how much influence the TV mogul could exercise behind the scenes.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">A cabinet of technocrats</hi>
    </head>
    <p>This is the way out favoured by the markets and the Italian centre left: a government filled with specialists who could pass the unpalatable legislation needed to revive Italy's flagging economy without having to worry about re-election. It is the solution more commonly associated with the young democracies of the developing world, but it has had success in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. After Berlusconi fell in 1994 he was replaced the following year by Lamberto Dini, a former central banker, as head of a government of professors, generals and judges. Likely prime minister? Mario Monti, a former EU commissioner.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">The grand coalition</hi>
    </head>
    <p>Otherwise known as a government of national emergency or salvation. This too might be seen as a developing world solution. But with the interest rate on its sovereign bonds heading for the fateful 7% mark and the Milan bourse dipping south, Italy certainly has an emergency and needs salvation. Could its notoriously querulous politicians agree to govern together, though? It would probably need a politician – and a deft one – to run such an administration. Giuliano Amato, a widely respected Socialist who has twice been prime minister, might be just the man. His nickname is "Doctor Subtle".</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">Italy goes back to the polls</hi>
    </head>
    <p>This is what Berlusconi wants, as does Bossi. It would mean Berlusconi continues to lead the right. It would also help Bossi keep a grip on his increasingly rebellious troops: the election would have to be under existing rules, which enable party leaders to decide which of their followers get the best chance of being elected. But it would prolong the instability and appall the markets. Italian elections are marathons, at least 60 days.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>