<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi risks revolt with tax cut" author="John Hooper" date="2004-04-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/apr/01/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi faced a potentially lethal rebellion in his coalition last night as he tried to rally support for a plan to revive Italy's economy and his government's flagging popularity." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="77fd9839d40587ed">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi faced a potentially lethal rebellion in his coalition last night as he tried to rally support for a plan to revive Italy's economy and his government's flagging popularity.</p>
    <p>After a heated parliamentary session, Mr Berlusconi's government won a vote of confidence on an emergency decree allowing it to finalise a €6.6bn (£4.4bn) credit as part of efforts to trim Italy's widening budget deficit.</p>
    <p>The deputy prime minister, Gianfranco Fini, had earlier warned that he would pull his hard-right National Alliance out of government if its concerns were not met. The National Alliance is the biggest party in parliament after Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party.</p>
    <p>Italy's economy is stagnant despite the growth in other European countries in the past few months.</p>
    <p>Last week trade unions caused widespread disruption with a nationwide strike in protest at the government's handling of the economy.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi said on Tuesday night that he would not stand at the general election, due in 2006, if he had failed to cut the higher rate of income tax from 45% to 33% and bring in a uniform lower rate of 23%.</p>
    <p>As a first step, he intended to outline spending cuts of €6bn (£4bn) by the start of next month to fund tax reductions.</p>
    <p>Angry at not having been consulted in advance, Mr Fini said the tax cuts strategy touched on "the very reason for our remaining in government".</p>
    <p>He said Mr Berlusconi should start with tax cuts at the lower rate.</p>
    <p>"It is a question of social justice," he said. John Hooper, Rome</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b"> theguardian.com/italy</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>