<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi and the wall of files his lawyers hope will shield him" author="John Hooper" date="2011-05-31" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/31/silvio-berlusconi-italian-vice-trial" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister's vice trial told giant folders contain 16 reasons against process going ahead" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,Law,World news" fingerprint="eb31d3289ee8569f">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's lawyer half turned and waved a hand over the courtroom behind him. "It's all that stuff there," Niccolò Ghedini told the judge.</p>
    <p>He was gesturing at five giant folders – each more than a foot thick – and seven boxes. Ribbons for bundling documents trailed out of the folders like unlit fuses.</p>
    <p>The "stuff" covered a table the width of Milan's biggest courtroom;</p>
    <p>and, as Ghedini revealed at what was meant to have been the first substantive hearing of the vice charges against Italy's prime minister, it formed a wall his lawyers hope will shield him from conviction.</p>
    <p>In April, Berlusconi went on trial, charged with paying an underage prostitute and trying to cover up his alleged offence by abusing his position. He was arraigned without committal proceedings, and normally his trial would take a couple of months. After a first hearing devoted to technicalities, this was meant to be when it began in earnest.</p>
    <p>But anyone expecting a parade of demimondaines sashaying to and from the witness stand to be quizzed on salacious details was in for a disappointment. Instead, there was Ghedini telling the judges that, buried in the wall of paper, were the grounds for 16 separate legal arguments that the trial should not even be taking place.</p>
    <p>"This is all about stretching things out until 6 July," said Paolo Colonnello, co-author of a book on the case. "That's when the constitutional court has to decide on the admissibility of a petition by the Chamber of Deputies."</p>
    <p>Italy's lower house, dominated by Berlusconi's followers, wants the trial heard elsewhere.</p>
    <p>"If the appeal is admitted, then the judges will probably suspend the trial until the constitutional court reaches a decision. That could take up to a year," said Colonnello, whose book is entitled Sodom.</p>
    <p>Ghedini is a cadaverous man who rarely smiles, perhaps aware that the effect is often more upsetting than uplifting. But on Tuesday he positively radiated bonhomie.</p>
    <p>He shook hands with prosecution counsel before the hearing. And when he began speaking, and was immediately drowned out by a builder's drill, he joked that the same thing had happened the last time they were adversaries.</p>
    <p>It was not to be the only boring noise in court, however, as he and his fellow-counsel, Piero Longo, launched into speeches dense with the dates of laws, and the numbers and letters of their clauses and sub-clauses.</p>
    <p>Longo, in particular, speaks not only with inordinate circumlocution, but in a monotone that could usefully replace waterboarding as a means for extracting information from suspected terrorists.</p>
    <p>Ahead of him, above the judges, was an allegorical mural featuring three women in the kind of skimpy outfits said to have been "de rigueur" at "bunga bunga" parties. One held a book marked Lex (law).</p>
    <p>There were two other Latin words in the painting. Dux and Leader was displayed prominently in the middle. And, up in the top right-hand corner, barely discernible from the press benches, there was Veritas (truth).</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>