<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi's wife seeks £38m-a-year divorce deal" author="John Hooper" date="2009-11-26" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/26/silvio-berlusconi-wife-divorce-deal" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister's estranged spouse Veronica Lario reportedly demanding £3.2m a month" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Divorce,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3608822ebbba3769">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's wife, who is seeking a legal separation from her husband, has asked for maintenance of more than €3.5m (£3.2m) a month, it was reported today.</p>
    <p>Daily newspaper Corriere della Sera said Italy's billionaire prime minister made a counter offer of €200,000 on the understanding that it could be increased to €300,000 in special circumstances. The paper quoted sources close to the prime minister as saying he had already given her €60m to €70m.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's wife, who is known by her stage name of Veronica Lario, was not available for comment. A spokeswoman declined to confirm or deny the report. "The line is one of absolute silence, since this news does not come from us," she told the Guardian.</p>
    <p>The newspaper said the prime minister was ready to let his wife have the villa at Macherio, near Milan, where she lives with her three children by her marriage to Berlusconi. Lario, his second wife, is reportedly seeking a prominent role for their children in the prime minister's business empire, which includes media, publishing, film distribution, insurance and property interests.</p>
    <p>Lario let it be known in May that the marriage was over. She has since filed for a separation, using a procedure that looks certain to lead to a messy and lurid split. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/divorce">Divorce</ref> law experts said she would need to prove her husband was responsible for the breakdown of their marriage.</p>
    <p>For the last seven months, Berlusconi has been involved almost uninterruptedly in sexual scandal. On Tuesday, a call girl who claims to have spent the night with him at his Rome residence, published an <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">explicit account</ref> of her alleged love-making with the 73-year-old prime minister. Patrizia D'Addario is one of some 40 women whom a businessman from the southern city of Bari claims he accompanied to Berlusconi's home last winter.</p>
    <p>The news that Lario was splitting from her husband came days after it was learned that he had attended the 18th birthday party of an aspiring Neapolitan actress and model, Noemi Letizia, who said she had known the prime minister for several years. Berlusconi's wife was quoted as saying that she could no longer remain with a man who "frequented minors" – a claim to which the prime minister has angrily objected. Lario had earlier criticised a plan to put up a number of young women from the world of showbusiness as candidates for Berlusconi's party at the last European election.</p>
    <p>One of Berlusconi's lawyers, Ippolita Ghedini, said: "I find it unspeakable that these reports come out. This sort of news does not contribute towards a separation by mutual consent." Lario's lawyer, Maria Cristina Morelli, was quoted by Corriere as saying: "I do not make any statements to the press about my clients."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>