<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="We trust in Ancelotti, says Berlusconi" author="Paolo Menicucci; Guardian staff reporter" date="2008-03-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2008/mar/06/newsstory.championsleague1" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Milan president Silvio Berlusconi has promised that the defeat to Arsenal will not cost Carlo Ancelotti his job" categories="Football" tags="Football,Sport,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Carlo Ancelotti,Europe" fingerprint="3a5c77bd18a3a7f0">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has promised that Milan's defeat by Arsenal will not cost Carlo Ancelotti his job but that may change should they fail to qualify for next season's Champions League. "Ancelotti stays," Berlusconi said. "I am absolutely convinced also because of the special relationship we have with him. He has brought many victories to Milan and has the complete trust of the club."</p>
    <p>That could prove the president's dreaded vote of confidence. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> are 18 points behind the Serie A leaders Internazionale but even more worrying they are four points behind fourth-placed Fiorentina and in danger of missing out on the Champions League for the first time since the 2001-02 season. Paolo Maldini will retire in the summer and, with an ageing defence and midfield, Ancelotti would have to prove that he can still refresh and motivate the squad.</p>
    <p>The coach will also be aware that Jose Mourinho has been linked with the job, though Milan would probably turn to Marcello Lippi should they decide to end Ancelotti's spell after seven years. Lippi, the former Juventus coach, who turns 60 in April, is eager to end his 18-month sabbatical after leading <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to the World Cup and was reportedly close to joining the Rossoneri last season before Ancelotti saved his job by winning the Champions League.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>