<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="British values seem to revolve around the worship of celebrities" author="Alexander Chancellor" date="2009-08-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/aug/06/alexander-chancellor-britishness-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alexander Chancellor: Immigrants wanting to find out how to be true Brits should be shown Big Brother and I'm a Celebrity" categories="Opinion" tags="Politics,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="aa59d93f95a2965d">
  <main>
    <p>What are these "British values" that immigrants are to be taught as a condition of citizenship? A way to find out would be to attend one of the government's proposed "orientation days" if these, as I hope, will be open to old citizens as well as would-be new ones. Will the instructors emphasise freedom of speech or the limits on it? The right to protest or the duty not to provoke? Does "an active disregard for UK values", for which applicants for citizenship are to be penalised, mean repudiating multiculturalism or embracing it? Will they suggest the wearing of religious symbols, or their concealment for fear of giving offence?</p>
    <p>The answers to these questions are not obvious; for while tolerance of diversity has long been portrayed in our country as the greatest of civic virtues, there is now more emphasis than previously on protecting Britain's traditional Christian values, which suggests that some intolerance of other cultures is permissible (if not as much as in France, where there is the strong possibility of a law to stop women wearing Islamic veils in public).</p>
    <p>In Italy, where I am at the moment, the conflicting attitudes of the prime minister have provoked an agonised debate about values. On the one hand, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> presents himself as a champion of Christian morality; on the other, he is an alleged adulterer and apparently proud of it, boasting in public that he is "no saint". On the one hand, he promises a greater role for women in government; on the other, he gives one of his top cabinet positions to a former topless model and promotes the idea – both on his television channels and by his own behaviour – that sexiness and media celebrity are the highest goals to which women should aspire.</p>
    <p>Lately, there have been rumblings of discontent within the Roman Catholic church at the failure of its hierarchy to criticise Berlusconi for his habit of consorting with young models and escort girls. While even his daughter, Barbara Berlusconi, says this week, in an interview with the Italian version of Vanity Fair magazine, that politicians should "defend the values they express" and that "I don't believe a politician can allow a distinction between his public and private life", the Pope and his bishops seem to accept Berlusconi's line that his private life is private and nobody else's business.</p>
    <p>The church is wary of interfering in Italian politics, knowing the outrage that such interference tends to cause, but it interferes all the same when there are major ethical issues in play, such as abortion and euthanasia. The fact that Berlusconi always takes the church's side on such issues is seen by its critics as one of the reasons why it hesitates to criticise him for his own moral lapses. The church would probably still prefer a conservative government in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, even one run by an old libertine, to a government formed by the centre-left opposition, with former communists and anti-Catholics in its ranks.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, a number of parish priests have publicly attacked the bishops for failing to make a clear statement on the Berlusconi scandal. "The risk," wrote one, "is that young people take on board a role model according to which the best way to get ahead in this world is to sleep with the prime minister.</p>
    <p>"The church embraces sinners who repent," he went on, "but I do not get the impression that the prime minister has either admitted his errors or made amends. On the contrary, he boasts about it, he jokes about it." Another priest, accusing Berlusconi of having "lied to the entire country by denying any improper or immoral behaviour", reached the conclusion that "a prime minister who consorts with call girls and at the same time claims to follow Christian morality is simply not acceptable".</p>
    <p>Until the church's leadership also reaches this conclusion, it will be giving tacit support to a prime minister who, despite lip service to Catholic values, assiduously promotes the worship of celebrities and their easily- come-by riches. Even with the son of the manse (and his moral compass) at the helm, the British are no less victims of the same depressing culture. Immigrants wanting to be true Brits should be shown Big Brother and I'm a Celebrity rather than, as suggested, canvas for a political party. That heads of British banks should find it appropriate to justify their staffs' huge salaries and bonuses by comparing them to football managers and Hollywood stars says it all, really.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">The extraordinary propensity of people to</hi> believe whatever suits their prejudices is illustrated by an opinion poll last week which found that 28% of American Republicans believe that Barack Obama was not born in the United States and is therefore ineligible to be president. A further 30% of Republicans are "not sure", despite the fact that Obama's birth in Honolulu on 4 August 1961 was officially registered at the time, as his birth certificate shows, and was also reported in two Hawaiian newspapers. To deny Obama's American birth involves believing that records were fabricated at the time in the hope that this child would one day reside in the White House, which is not the easiest thing to accept. Nevertheless, only 42% of Republicans say they are actually convinced he was born in America. What, one wonders, would it take to convince the rest?</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>