<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Markets and Italian MPs applaud arrival of Mario Monti" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/11/markets-italy-applaud-mario-monti" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Economist given hero's welcome to senate but Berlusconi's party split on support for expected prime minister's administration" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe,Eurozone crisis,Business,Mario Monti" fingerprint="3f898ab5d8a3576c">
  <main>
    <p>The sober economist incongruously nicknamed "Super Mario" received a hero's welcome in the Italian parliamenton Friday as markets around the world toasted his expected appointment as Italy's prime minister.</p>
    <p>Seldom can grey-suited shoulders have borne heavier responsibilities than those implicitly taken on by the former EU commissioner, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref>, when he arrived in the upper house of parliament to take his seat as a life senator. Italian senators hope he can save his country from default, the euro from collapse – and the world economy from depression.</p>
    <p>Monti had been given his seat by President Giorgio Napolitano in a clear sign the head of state intended asking him to form a new government when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> leaves office.</p>
    <p>That could now happen as early as evening. After giving Monti a rousing ovation, the members of the senate passed a package of economic measures agreed with the EU last month.</p>
    <p>The measures are expected to be given final approval by the lower house, the Chamber of Deputies, on Saturday, clearing the way for Berlusconi's resignation and the appointment of a new government before the markets reopen on Monday. After losing his parliamentary majority this week, Berlusconi said he would remain in office until the package had been approved.</p>
    <p>The measures, aimed at reducing Italy's budget deficit and liberalising its economy, passed with 156 votes in favour, 12 against and one abstention. Italy's main opposition movement, the Democratic party, did not vote. Nor did the Christian Democrat Centre Union.</p>
    <p>Markets shrugged off the questions still surrounding the prospective Monti administration. The spread – the gap between the yields on Italian and German benchmark bonds, which is a measure of the extra risk of an Italian default – shrank to 4.6 percentage points. The interest rate on its 10-year BTP bonds fell below 6.5% — uncomfortably high, but well below the psychologically crucial 7% level that has triggered a bailout for other troubled euro zone states.</p>
    <p>The Milan bourse ended one of the worst weeks in its history with a 3.68% surge that took the FTSE MIB index to 15,778 points. It was the best performance among the leading European stock markets.</p>
    <p>But, as dealers left for the weekend, allies and followers of Berlusconi's government were coming and going from his home in Rome as talks continued on where they should stand in the abruptly changed political landscape. The Northern League, which has 59 of the 630 seats in the Chamber of Deputies, has said it will go into opposition, joining an anti-corruption movement, the Italy of Principles party which commands 22 votes.</p>
    <p>The prime minister's party, the Freedom People party (PdL) is deeply and acrimoniously split over whether to join, back or oppose the expected Monti government. Its formerly neo-fascist wing favours a hard line and a snap election instead of a government with no popular mandate. Berlusconi's personal following is divided.</p>
    <p>To prevent a split, it was thought likely the PdL, which can still muster around 249 votes in the lower house, would support, but not form part of the government. But since the unelected Monti could hardly form a cabinet made up of opposition politicians, that would probably mean a new government composed entirely of non-party "technocrats".</p>
    <p>The president of the European council, Herman Van Rompuy, who was due to meet Berlusconi in Rome on Fridaylast night, quipped that Italy "needs reforms, not elections". But an exclusively technocratic Monti government would clearly have a problem of democratic legitimacy and a shorter life expectancy than one in which all or most of Italy's political parties were represented. It could also be uncomfortably dependent on the continuing goodwill of the PdL.</p>
    <p>The tensions within Berlusconi's party burst into the open following an Italian news agency report about the foreign minister, Franco Frattini, who wants the PdL to join the next government. It quoted him as having described his adversaries within the party as "these fascists".</p>
    <p>Asked about the comment, a leading former neo-fascist, the defence minister, Ignazio La Russa, said "Frattini? Frattini who?"</p>
    <p>The commission of the chamber that has to give the thumbs up to the economic measures before they can be approved by the full house was also meeting and its deliberations were expected to go on well into the night. The package includes changes to the pension system and the labour market, a reform of the professions, a programme for the sale of state assets and local services, and reforms affecting the public sector.</p>
    <p>Monti's singular nickname comes from the eponymous Nintendo video game, first released in 1985. One of its hero's tasks is to pick up as many gold coins as possible while trying to deal with attacks from other characters in the game.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>