<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Eurozone crisis as it happened: EC admits recession will be deeper than feared" author="Graeme Wearden; Nick Fletcher; Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-02-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/feb/22/eurozone-crisis-italian-general-election" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy goes to the polls this weekend in a general election that could sooth the eurozone, or inflame it" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Mario Monti,Beppe Grillo" fingerprint="110c90f50134054c">
  <main>
    <p>Vote for me! Figurines representing the main candidates of the upcoming Italian general election as Christmas crib shepherds, at a shop at San Gregorio Armeno in Naples. Photograph: CIRO FUSCO/EPA Photograph: CIRO FUSCO/EPA</p>
    <p>Vote for me! Figurines representing the main candidates of the upcoming Italian general election as Christmas crib shepherds, at a shop at San Gregorio Armeno in Naples. Photograph: CIRO FUSCO/EPA Photograph: CIRO FUSCO/EPA</p>
    <p>The eurozone may be in a deeper than expected recession, there may be uncertainty over the Italian elections and the US spending cuts and tax rises, but stock markets have shrugged off these concerns, it seems. Investors have taken advantage of Thursday's steep falls to move back into equities in search of some bargains.</p>
    <p>The FTSE 100 has finished 44.16 points higher at 6335.70, up 0.7%</p>
    <p>Germany's Dax is 1.03% higher</p>
    <p>France's Cac has closed 2.25% better</p>
    <p>Italy's FTSE MIB is up 1.4%</p>
    <p>Spain's Ibex has added 2.05%</p>
    <p>The Athens market is up 0.7%</p>
    <p>And in the US, the Dow Jones Industrial Average is 0.58% higher.</p>
    <p>So with that, it's time to shut up shop for the weekend. We'll be back on Monday, with the Italian election on the agenda, in a week which also includes the deadline for the US to solve its spending cuts dilemma. Thanks for all the comments, have a good weekend and see you back here next week.</p>
    <p>Make English the language of the EU, says German president</p>
    <p>German president Joachim Gauck has called for English to be made the language of the EU and appealed for the UK to remain in the EU. Kate Connolly in Berlin writes:</p>
    <p>[Gauck] earned applause for his remarks made in Berlin on Friday in a speech on Europe's future at a time of rising Germans scepticism towards the EU.</p>
    <p>"Dear English, Scots, Welsh, Northern Irish and new British citizens, we want to continue having you on board," he said. "We need your experience as the oldest parliamentary democracy, we need your traditions, your sober-mindedness and your courage."</p>
    <p>Street newspaper to be launched in Athens next week</p>
    <p>A street newspaper to be sold by homeless and unemployed people will be launched in Greece next week.</p>
    <p>The paper, called Shedia (‘Raft’) will be sold in Athens and becomes the 122nd street paper to join the Glasgow-based International Network of Street Papers (INSP).</p>
    <p>According to a press release, Shedia has recruited over 70 vendors ahead of the launch next Wednesday and will sign up more once it hits the streets.</p>
    <p>Vendors buy the magazine for €1.50 and sell it for €3, keeping the proceeds. Chris Alefantis, founder of Shedia said:</p>
    <p>Following years of preparations, the country's only street paper is about to be launched. Fighting poverty and social exclusion is at the forefront of our campaign, particularly considering the desperate economic hardship that Greece and its people are currently faced with.</p>
    <p>On the last day of the current five day strike by Iberia airline staff in Spain, there have been protests at airports in Madrid and Barcelona.</p>
    <p>According to AP, several thousand protesters gathered inside the largest terminal of Madrid's international airport, blowing whistles and air horns in a noisy demonstration against the airline's 3,800 planned job cuts. In all the unions plan 15 days of strikes.</p>
    <p>Protestors at Barajas Airport in Madrid. Photograph: Getty Images/Pablo Blazquez Dominguez Photograph: Pablo Blazquez Dominguez/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Iberia staff shout slogans during the protest at Barajas Airport in Madrid. Photograph: Getty Images/ Pablo Blazquez Dominguez Photograph: Pablo Blazquez Dominguez/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Iberia's workers dressed as prisoners protest at Terminal 1 of Barcelona's airport. Photograph: Reuters/Albert Gea ( Photograph: Albert Gea/REUTERS</p>
    <p>Business confidence in Belgium rose to a 10 month high in February, but was still in negative territory.</p>
    <p>The index came in at -11 compared to -13.2 in January and expectations of around -12. The improvement came as manufacturers said they were increasingly positive about the outlook. The news follows the German Ifo index, which showed its biggest monthly rise since July 2010.</p>
    <p>On the Belgian figures, Philippe Ledent at ING said:</p>
    <p>After a very disappointing result in January, Belgian business confidence rebounded in February. In the manufacturing sector, which constitutes the biggest part of the index, confidence increased by 2.8 points, after a drop by the same amplitude last month. A healthier assessment of inventories and better confidence in future demand are driving this slight recovery. Confidence also increased in the service sector, for the second month in a row.</p>
    <p>Even if the short term outlook remains quite subdued, today’s business confidence confirms that the Belgian economy is probably turning the corner. To be sure, full year growth is likely to remain limited in 2013, to the tune of 0.2%. But compared to last year (-0.2%), this has to be considered as good news.</p>
    <p>Italian bond auctions to provide early election reaction</p>
    <p>One of the first indications as to how the markets view the Italian election outcome will come early next week as the country issues more bonds. Reuters reports:</p>
    <p>Italy may have to pay a big premium to sell bonds next week if the market gets rattled by an indecisive election result that puts in doubt reforms needed to spur growth and cut the country's debt.</p>
    <p>A sale of inflation-protected bonds on Monday will be the first test of investor demand as Italians go to the polls to choose a new government that will have to deal with the country's mammoth €2trn of public debt.</p>
    <p>This will be followed up by an auction of an estimated €7bn of conventional bonds on Wednesday, expected to include a new 10-year benchmark paper. The Italian Treasury [is] the sole scheduled issuer in the euro zone primary market next week.</p>
    <p>Markets are widely expecting the centre-left party of Pier Luigi Bersani to win the February 24-25 vote and rule in coalition with technocrat centrist Mario Monti, with a comeback by former Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi - reviled by markets - largely dismissed.</p>
    <p>This has kept Italian bond yields steady in recent weeks after an initial sell-off in early February, with benchmark 10-year debt yields within the 4.10%-4.75% range that has prevailed so far this year.</p>
    <p>People cycle by electoral billboards in Rome on the day of campaigning. Photograph: AFP/Getty Images/Filippo Monteforte Photograph: Filippo Monteforte/AFP/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Am scooting now, so Nick Fletcher will guide the blog into port. Have good weekends all (I'll be in the office on Sunday, so expect I'll be tweeting the latest Italian developments then too). GW</p>
    <p>Italy's outgoing premier, Mario Monti, has held his final pre-election rally in Florence today:</p>
    <p>Mario Monti is greeted by a group of children as he arrives for his closing political rally in Florence, Italy, Friday, Feb. 22, 2013. Photograph: Matteo Bovo/AP Photograph: Matteo Bovo/AP</p>
    <p>Italy's new government, after elections this weekend, must cut bureaucracy and taxes and reform an ineffective legal system if the shrinking economy is to be jolted back to life, businesses and foreign investors say.</p>
    <p>Italians vote on Sunday and Monday for a successor to Mario Monti's technocrat government whose austerity policies saved Italy from a Greek-style debt crisis but did nothing to pull it out of deep recession. Italy's economy has contracted for six consecutive quarters, shrinking 2.2 percent last year, and companies say it is time to pull down the barriers that have hampered Italian businesses and put foreign investors off Italy for years.</p>
    <p>"I would like a government that truly thinks about growth and that could bring Italy out of the quicksand," said Massimo Scaccabarozzi, CEO of pharmaceutical company Janssen-Cilag SpA, a unit of Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
    <p>"It's no secret that we are bottom of the list when it comes to ease of business."</p>
    <p>It also points out Italy ranks 73rd out of 183 countries as a place to do business, according to the World Bank index.</p>
    <p>"The new government must simplify procedures, make the system more transparent and figure out how to cut labour costs," said Fabio Gianisi, a Milan lawyer who advises Chinese and Russian investors with an interest in Italy.</p>
    <p>A trader at the Frankfurt Stock Exchange. Photograph: Thomas Lohnes/Getty Images Photograph: Thomas Lohnes/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Europe's stock markets have not been hit by this morning's predictions of a deeper eurozone recession (10.09am onwards), or the latest talk of a hung Italian parliament (see 11.52am).</p>
    <p>FTSE 100: up 49 points at 6340, + 0.78%</p>
    <p>German DAX: up 85 points at 7668, + 1.13%</p>
    <p>French CAC: up 72 points at 3697, +2%</p>
    <p>Italian FTSE MIB: up 292 points at 16302, +1.8%</p>
    <p>Spanish IBEX: up 137 points at 8151, + 1.7%</p>
    <p>And in the bond market, Spanish and Italian sovereign debt has strengthened slightly. The yields on their 10-year bonds are down 4 basis points, or 0.04%, at 5.16% (Spain) and 4.43% (Italy).</p>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani gesturing during a rally in Naples yesterday. Photograph: Marco Cantile/AP Photograph: Marco Cantile/AP</p>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani, whose centre-left Democratic Party is most likely to win Italy's general election, is pledging to push European leaders to rethink their approach to the crisis:</p>
    <p>In Italy Pier Luigi Bersani tells me 'I Intend to convince Europe that austerity alone is not enough'. Sounds familiar? Francois Hollande!</p>
    <p>Re-Define: Time for a Grand Bargain for the eurozone</p>
    <p>Sony Kapoor, head of the Re-Define thinktank, says today's warning of a deeper eurozone recession is the fault of European leaders for pursued "economically illiterate, socially destructive, self-defeating polices" since the financial crisis began:</p>
    <p>Instead of a more relaxed fiscal and monetary policy supporting the structural reforms that were necessary, as we have been suggesting for a long time now, the EU has followed a deeply flawed policy of fiscal contraction. This is the result of the application of a ‘small economy mentality’ that prevails in the German economic debate to what is the largest economic area in the world. The current economic policy betrays a level of macroeconomic illiteracy that is shocking for an otherwise well-educated policy-making elite.</p>
    <p>Instead of on focussing on a 5-10 year strategy and a financially, politically and socially sustainable adjustment path for rebalancing, EU leaders have taken a very short-termist view of policy. At the same time that they rant against the short-termism of financial markets, their own policies have been even more myopic. What may be rational for a small country in the short-run, which is the policy lens they have used, will be self-defeating and irrational for the EU-wide economy over a longer horizon.</p>
    <p>Re-Define argues that Europe's leaders are failing their own test, of reducing fiscal deficits and stabilizing debt to GDP ratios, even if we ignore the ripping of the region's social fabric.</p>
    <p>Yesterday, around 40,000 protesters marched through the streets of Brussels, Belgium in an anti-austerity demonstration. Photograph: Andrew De Bruyne/Demotix/Corbis Photograph: Andrew De Bruyne/ Andrew De Bruyne/Demotix/Corbis</p>
    <p>Instead of the current policies Re-Define proposes a "grand political bargain", which addresses the imbalances across the eurozone and creates a fairer balances between fiscal consolidation and growth:</p>
    <p>What we need at this point is a grand political bargain, and that is one that only Mrs Merkel can offer. We will require a period of five to ten years of adjustment in the European economies which needs to happen both in deficit countries as well as surplus ones not suffering from the immediate crisis. During the course of this adjustment, financial support needs to be made available at reasonable cost to the economies to provide political and economic space for structural reforms and medium-term fiscal adjustment.</p>
    <p>Without such a grand political bargain, which gives certainty, predictability and which puts us onto an economically, financially socially and politically sustainable path we are in deep-deep trouble. But such a bargain is not likely, at least not before the German elections. Let us see what happens after, but we are not holding our breath.</p>
    <p>John Hooper: Beppe Grillo's popularity is scaring Bersani, and bad for Monti</p>
    <p>Back to Italy, and there are reports that Beppe Grillo's radical Five Star movement is polling in second place, ahead of the Berlusconi-Northern League alliance.</p>
    <p>Our Southern Europe editor, John Hooper, provides this punchy analysis of the general election campaign:</p>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani this morning switched his attack to Beppe Grillo, and got personal. One of Grillo’s vulnerabilities as a paladin of the people is the considerable wealth he has amassed – a product of his successful career as a comedian.</p>
    <p>“I’m the son of a mechanic, not abillionaire”, said Bersani.</p>
    <p>His remark added substance to a report in Corriere della Sera this morning that Bersani’s aides are now thoroughly alarmed by Grillo’s progress in the final stages of the campaign.</p>
    <p>Without quite saying so (because Italian publications are banned from carrying poll results in the last two weeks before the vote), Corriere indicated clearly that surveys conducted for the Democratic party showed Grillo’s Five Star Movement (M5S) overtaking Silvio Berlusconi’s Freedom People (PdL) movement to regain the second placeit held for a while early last summer.</p>
    <p>Now, if you look here, you will see the rather more heavily disguised results of a poll carried out by a firm that has consistently favoured Berlusconi. It does not show Grillo in second place, but it does show him on 19%, which is a huge leap – of about six per cent – since the polling ban came into effect.</p>
    <p>That is bad enough for Bersani's PD. But just as worryingly, there is mounting evidence from the same un-publishable polls that the alliance flung together by the outgoing prime minister, Mario Monti, is fading rapidly. That makes psephological sense.</p>
    <p>If Monti and his pals were to take only 10% of the vote, say, we might well get either a hung parliament or a centre-left that could only pass legislation with more help than Monti can offer. Even if the radical left-wing alliance headed by a state prosecutor, Antonio Ingroia, can muster enough votes for a seat or two, that is going to mean going cap in hand to Grillo.</p>
    <p>The European Central Bank has just spooked the markets by reporting that fewer banks than expected have taken the chance to repay ultra-cheap loans handed to them just over a year ago.</p>
    <p>The ECB reported that 356 banks will hand back a total of €61.1bn of Long Term Refinancing Operation (LTRO) funding, sharply lower than the €130bn analysts had expected.</p>
    <p>Marco Buti, the EC's director general for Economic and Financial Affairs, warns in today's Winter Forecasts that Europe's unemployment crisis is deepening.</p>
    <p>Buti wrote:</p>
    <p>Employment is forecast to shrink further for some quarters, and unemployment remains unacceptably high in the EU as whole and even more so in the Member States facing the largest adjustment needs.</p>
    <p>This has grave social consequences and will, if unemployment becomes structurally entrenched, also weigh on growth perspectives going forward.</p>
    <p>The most recent data shows that the Eurozone unemployment rate is 11.7%.</p>
    <p>Breaking news: the European Commission has slashed its growth forecasts for the eurozone, and now believes the single currency region will not return to growth this year.</p>
    <p>In its Winter Forecasts, the EC predicted that eurozone GDP would shrink by 0.3% during 2013, not manage the 0.1% growth pencilled in previously.</p>
    <p>The EC warned that Europe's unemployment crisis was a desperately serious problem.</p>
    <p>It warned that Italy would shrink by 1% in 2013, not the 0.5% contraction it had expected. And for Cyprus, it now sees a 3.5% plunge in GDP, down from a 1.7% drop before.</p>
    <p>Germany is expected to grow by just 0.5% this year, not 0.8%. While France will manage a measly 0.1% growth, not 0.4%.</p>
    <p>German business confidence has jumped this month, as Europe's biggest economy shrugged off the suffering elsewhere in the eurozone.</p>
    <p>The monthly IFO survey (which measures morale at 7,000 German firms), has risen to 107.4 for February, up from 104.3 in January.</p>
    <p>That's the biggest month-on-month rise since the summer of 2010.</p>
    <p>Economists see it as another sign Germany has returned to growth after shrinking by 0.6% in the last three months of 2012. Extra information on that GDP decline was also released this morning - it showed that falling demand for exports knocked 0.8% off GDP, while domestic demand contributed 0.2% of growth.</p>
    <p>Five-Star Movement leader Beppe Grillo held a rally in Viterbo, north of Rome, last night -- and his supporters packed the place:</p>
    <p>Photograph: MAX ROSSI/Reuters Photograph: MAX ROSSI/Reuters</p>
    <p>Photograph: MAX ROSSI/Reuters Photograph: MAX ROSSI/Reuters</p>
    <p>Grillo is the wildcard in the Italian election. He's playing the game his own way -- avoiding the usual round of TV interviews in favour of web campaigning and barn-storming rallies.</p>
    <p>Grillo's message is that the old politics is dead and must be chopped out, by a new wave of MPs untainted by sleaze and corruption. Alongside a euro referendum, he wants to give people more control over political decisions (allowing them to vote on whether a new road or hospital is built).</p>
    <p>He also argues that Europe's malaise is so great that radical measures - including rewriting all major Eu treaties – are needed.</p>
    <p>The comedian from Genoa is the figurehead leading a team of politically-untested candidates – and Italians have heard big promises so many times. Feeling terribly let down by the mainstream, many potential voters, undecided, seemed caught in the glare.</p>
    <p>In his way, Grillo is a visionary, but he says Five Star won’t join any coalition government and he won’t serve in parliament. Instead, he promises to oppose and obstruct, and says his goal is to have enough legislators in parliament to topple the next government. If Grillo can suck enough votes away from other parties on Feb. 24-25, then he could make the formation of a stable government impossible from the outset, forcing new elections.</p>
    <p>This would be a replay of the damage wrought by the upstart Syriza party in the first of Greece’s repeat elections last year. Think of the lost time and the instability that resulted, and then multiply that mayhem by eight to reflect the size of Italy’s economy.</p>
    <p>The markets may not like it, but it's called democracy.</p>
    <p>European stock markets are clawing back some of Thursday's big losses, suggesting they're not as nervous about Silvio Berlusconi romping to triumph this weekend.</p>
    <p>FTSE 100: up 45 points at 6337, + 0.7%</p>
    <p>German DAX: up 42 points at 7630, +0.6%</p>
    <p>French CAC: up 38 points at 3662. +1%</p>
    <p>Italian FTSE MIB: up 211 points at 16221, +1.3%</p>
    <p>Spanish IBEX: up 109 points at 8123, + 1.35%</p>
    <p>Yesterday's selloff was triggered by the latest minutes from the US Federal Reserve, which showed concern over its quantitative easing programme.</p>
    <p>Traders have now had more time to digest this, and concluded that there's no risk of the Fed tightening policy soon.</p>
    <p>As Chris Weston of IG explains:</p>
    <p>We know there are hawks within the Fed’s ranks, many of them non-voters and what the minutes (as opposed to the actual FOMC statement) gives is a chance for non-voters to express their view....</p>
    <p>while at the margin the minutes were hawkish there were still some clear dovish underlying themes that will see the Fed firmly in the market till the end of the year.</p>
    <p>A quick run-through the details of the Italian election:</p>
    <p>There are four groups fighting for votes in Italy.</p>
    <p>1) The centre-left coalition led by the Democratic Party, and its leader Pier Luigi Bersani.</p>
    <p>2) The alliance between People of Freedom, Silvio Berlusconi's party, and The Northern League</p>
    <p>3) Mario Monti's centrist coalition -- comprising MPs running under the Civic Choice with Monti for Italy banner, along with Christian Democrats Future, and Freedom for Italy./</p>
    <p>4) The Five Star Movement -- comedian Beppe Grillo's group. He is winning popular support on a platform demanding fundamental changes on public water, transportation, development, internet availability, and the environment.</p>
    <p>The far-left FARE party is also fielding candidates.</p>
    <p>The political set-up</p>
    <p>The parties are fighting for seats in the Chamber of Deputies (the lower house of parliament), and in the Senate (or upper house).</p>
    <p>There are 630 MPs in the Chamber of Deputies, where Bersani is expected to win the most votes. The convoluted Italian political system ensures he'll then get a majority of seats.</p>
    <p>The Senate consists of 315 elected member. Here, the winning party in each region is guaranteed 55% of available seats, with the other parties sharing the remaining 45% of the seats based on voting share.</p>
    <p>Given the Senate's political power, the key question is whether Bersani wins an outright majority (158 seats), or can hit that total through an alliance with Mario Monti. This depends on the results of the four swing states - Lombardy, Campania, Sicily and Veneto.</p>
    <p>Election fever is mounting as the Italian general election campaign enters its final couple of days. Voters head to the polls on Sunday, for a poll that has major implications for the whole eurozone.</p>
    <p>If a clear winner emerges (most likely the centre-left group led by Pier Luigi Bersani), then Italy is likely to continue on the path of financial reforms and austerity set by Mario Monti – who could even join Bersani in a coalition.</p>
    <p>But there's a strong chance that the election will result in a divided parliament, leaving Italy's next leader struggling to govern effectively.</p>
    <p>With a ban on new opinion polls, speculation over the result is rife. Investors dread the prospect of a resurgent Silvio Berlusconi holding the balance of power, while analysts aren't convinced that even a Bersani-Monti coalition could hold power for long.</p>
    <p>As Eoin Ryan of IHS Global Insight puts it:</p>
    <p>A surge in support for anti-austerity parties is raising chances of an indecisive election result and post-vote political instability.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's breezy promise to eliminate Italy's much-loathed new property tax has lured some floating voters back to his People of Freedom party.</p>
    <p>There is also significant support for Beppe Grillo, the (professional) comedian whose radical manifesto includes a referendum on Italy's eurozone membership. In the complex world of Italian electoral mathematics, a strong performance by Grillo's Five-Star Movement could scupper Bersani's hopes of winning enough seats to govern.</p>
    <p>One thing is clear - it's going to be fascinating to watch....</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>