<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Peter Bradshaw's Cannes round-up" author="Peter Bradshaw" date="2010-05-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2010/may/16/peter-bradshaw-cannes-round-up" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Mike Leigh shone, Woody Allen hit cruise control and there was a lot of nonsense about teens: Peter Bradshaw picks his highlights so far" categories="Film" tags="Cannes film festival,Mike Leigh,Woody Allen,Silvio Berlusconi,Film,Culture,Cannes 2010" fingerprint="f6259b5ab042a054">
  <main>
    <p>As Cannes passed its first weekend, the first big auteur made his appearance: British director <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/mikeleigh">Mike Leigh</ref>, with his new film <hi rend="#b">Another Year</hi>, a characteristically muted, bittersweet tale, starring Jim Broadbent, Ruth Sheen and Lesley Manville. It is composed in the distinctively stylised Leigh idiom, which, after you have taken time to acclimatise, discloses a hugely involving and subtle story; I was utterly immersed by the final credits.</p>
    <p>Sheen plays Gerri, a psychotherapist; her husband, Tom (Broadbent), is an engineer. Both are nearing retirement and gently content with their careers, their marriage and the way their lives have turned out. But despite, or perhaps because of the gentle glow of happiness they radiate, their home is a magnet for unhappy souls. Chief among these is their desperately messed-up divorcee friend Mary (Manville), who keeps insinuating herself into their lives, yet is too chaotic and absurd to be a parasite. Gradually, the awful truth dawns on the audience about the way Mary imagines the future of their relationship.</p>
    <p>For those who have not acquired the Leigh taste – and it took me a while – Another Year may be unpersuasive. But this is a rich and deeply compassionate film, one of the best of Leigh's late period.</p>
    <p>From the sublime to the ridiculous: Hideo Nakata's <hi rend="#b">Chatroom</hi>, scripted by Enda Walsh from his play, centres on a nightmare in cyberspace. Five London teens meet in an online chatroom, only to discover too late that one is intent on destroying the most vulnerable member. Nakata and Walsh are having an off day with this awful, fatuous nonsense, convulsed with dated, tabloidy fear of the internet, whose supposed dangers are imagined with naive and tacky prurience. It is hugely condescending to teenagers, whose attitude to the web is a lot more savvy than the grownups who made this film. Aaron Johnson, a bright newcomer (Nowhere Boy, Kick-Ass), is woefully undirected in the lead role.</p>
    <p>Woody Allen's new London-set movie <hi rend="#b">You Will Meet a Tall Dark Stranger</hi> is a shruggingly pessimistic ensemble comedy, which screened out of competition. Naomi Watts is a would-be gallery owner married to a struggling writer (Josh Brolin), who gets involved in a bizarre imbroglio; Gemma Jones and Anthony Hopkins play Watts's troubled parents. It tootles along amiably, but, as ever, Allen is coasting.</p>
    <p>The most sensational and urgent film at Cannes is Sabina Guzzanti's <hi rend="#b">Draquila: Italy Trembles</hi>, a magnificently full-blooded attack on the grotesque and scandalous misrule of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. As a satirist and activist, Guzzanti is almost the only person in the Italian media with the courage to attack Berlusconi directly. Her film is a sizzling polemic, indebted to Michael Moore and directed at the way Berlusconi exploited the L'Aquila earthquake to pursue a taxpayer-funded construction programme that lined his cronies' pockets; he also created more legal opportunities for suspending civil liberties. The beautiful and historic town of L'Aquila still lies abandoned and derelict, while Italy, particularly its younger generation, fumes at Berlusconi's chilling arrogance.</p>
    <p>First-time director Katell Quillévéré's beguiling <hi rend="#b">Love Like Poison</hi> is the best film I have seen showing in the Directors' Fortnight. It is sexually frank, yet has a wonderful innocence and charm. Clara Augarde is Anna, a pious 14-year-old preparing for her confirmation, and plagued with uncertainties after falling in love; she develops the rather 19th-century habit of fainting in public. What a treat this is: why wasn't it screened in the main competition?</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>