<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy and Germany clash over aid arrests" author="John Hooper; Guardian staff reporter" date="2004-07-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/news/2004/jul/14/immigrationasylumandrefugees.internationalnews" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi's government was again at loggerheads with Germany last night after officials arrested three German aid workers who rescued a group of shipwrecked Africans and landed them on Sicily." categories="UK news" tags="Immigration and asylum,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="fe0420bbe6b645fe">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's government was again at loggerheads with Germany last night after officials arrested three German aid workers who rescued a group of shipwrecked Africans and landed them on Sicily.</p>
    <p>As Italian ministers protested that they had been "duped" into accepting the immigrants, a German cabinet minister demanded the aid workers be released. They include Elias Bierdel, the head of the Cap Anamur aid group.</p>
    <p>"It is unacceptable that Elias Bierdel should be punished because he wanted to help people who chanced on great hardship," said Heidemarie Wieczorek-Zeul, the development minister.</p>
    <p>In Rome the justice minister, Roberto Castelli, said the landing of the 37 Africans had set a "devastating precedent". Italian officials were told they were Sudanese fleeing the war-stricken Darfur region, but police who questioned the men after they disembarked said most appeared to be from Ghana and Nigeria.</p>
    <p>The latest stand-off between Rome and Berlin comes almost a year after the governments clashed over Mr Berlusconi's jibe that one of Gerhard Schröder's party colleagues reminded him of a Nazi concentration camp guard.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's rightwing government was reluctant to accept the Cap Anamur ship and its unexpected passengers. The aid group, which had been delivering supplies to Africa, said it came across the men adrift in a rubber dinghy.</p>
    <p>The ship was blocked from landing for almost three weeks, but after reports that men were ready to throw themselves into the sea the vessel was allowed to into Porto Empedocle on Monday.</p>
    <p>It was then impounded and Mr Bierdel, the ship's skipper and his first mate were taken into custody. A hearing to decide whether the three should stay behind bars is due tomorrow.</p>
    <p>The Africans, who were taken to a holding centre, are expected to apply for asylum in Italy.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>