<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi says he will stay on as Italy's PM even if convicted in court" author="Richard Rogers" date="2009-11-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/01/italy-berlusconi-immunity-scandal-prosecution" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The law granting him immunity from prosecution has been lifted but Berlusconi insists forthcoming trials will not oust him" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="393b120db0c1f71d">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, has insisted he will stay in office even if he is convicted in one of the trials in which he is a defendant. </hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">After a summer of sex scandals and legal wrangling, Berlusconi faces two trials, following a decision by the country's top court to lift his immunity from prosecution and allow proceedings against him to resume. </hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">In one case, due to start on 16 November, he is accused of tax fraud and false accounting in the management of his media companies. In a separate trial, whose next hearing is due on 27 November, Berlusconi is charged with paying a $600,000 (£363,121) bribe to British lawyer David Mills to withhold incriminating details of his business dealings. </hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">"I still have faith in the existence of serious magistrates who hand down serious verdicts, based on facts," said Berlusconi, according to excerpts of a forthcoming book that were released yesterday. "If there were a conviction in trials like these, we would be facing such a big subversion of the truth that I would feel even more duty bound to stay in my post to defend democracy and the rule of law."</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Berlusconi has been in defiant mood since Italy's constitutional court ruled last month that his protection from prosecution while he holds office violated the constitution. The ruling overturned a law that critics had denounced as tailor-made to protect him from his legal woes. Since then, he has repeatedly attacked the judicial system as overrun by "communist" magistrates out to destroy him. </hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>