<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="G20 leaders press Italy to accept IMF checks on cuts programme" author="Patrick Wintour; Larry Elliott" date="2011-11-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/04/g20-italy-imf-checks-cuts" hostname="theguardian.com" description="European leaders urged to sign up to more specific austerity measures or else US and others will not put extra funds into IMF" categories="World news" tags="G20,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Eurozone crisis,International Monetary Fund (IMF),European banks,Euro,Economics,Global economy,Business,Economic policy,George Osborne,Politics,UK news,Austerity" fingerprint="bff5430459a9378b">
  <main>
    <p>Barack Obama is leading a group of world leaders who are effectively ordering <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> to accept surveillance of Italy's austerity measures by the International Monetary Fund.</p>
    <p>The move comes as doubts grow that the Italian prime minister has the capacity to oversee a major debt reduction programme or even to stay in power next week.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi had been expected to come to the G20 summit in Cannes with a specific austerity package in line with a lengthy letter he sent to EU leaders at an <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/26/eu-summit-eurozone-crisis-leaders">emergency summit</ref> on 27 October.</p>
    <p>But divisions within his cabinet meant he arrived empty-handed, frustrating other EU leaders concerned that the euro edifice could collapse.</p>
    <p>When asked, the chancellor, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/georgeosborne">George Osborne</ref>, did not deny that Britain was making contingency plans for the break-up of the eurozone.</p>
    <p>EU leaders fear monetary meltdown is set to spread from Greece to Italy – a far larger economy, and one to which the whole European banking system is severely exposed.</p>
    <p>Italian debt yields – the rate at which the bond market is willing to buy Italian debt – <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/03/g20-greece-eurozone-crisis-mood?newsfeed=true">rose to alarmingly high levels</ref> on Thursday before falling back slightly on the news that Greece had withdrawn a planned referendum on its austerity package. It is far from certain that the Greek government will survive a vote of confidence on Friday.</p>
    <p>There are signs that some members of Berlusconi's People of Freedom party in the lower house will defect, making it likely that the PM will be unable to survive a confidence vote next week.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is examining proposals such as raising the pension age, dismissal for redundant public sector workers who do not accept a move to a new job within two years, and the speeding up of assets sales to €5bn (£4.3bn) a year for three years.</p>
    <p>He assured world leaders that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> would be able to pay its debt and had always done so historically. The country faces new tests in further auctions of its debt this month – it has to raise €30.5bn in November and €22.5bn in December.</p>
    <p>The European Central Bank has been buying Italian bonds since the start of August. The move initially pushed yields below 5%, but they are now above 6.5% – levels that make it difficult to pay back debt.</p>
    <p>Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, who would have the responsibility for constructing an interim government if Berlusconi's collapses, has held discussions with party leaders to evaluate the situation.</p>
    <p>The concern about Italy is one of the factors driving the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g20">G20</ref> summit leaders towards the expansion of an IMF fund on which troubled countries can draw. It is likely the $950bn (£592bn) fund will receive an injection of $300bn, but negotiations about the different contributions by economies including China and Russia are continuing.</p>
    <p>Throughout the morning, pressure was applied to European leaders, notably Italy, to sign up to a more specific austerity package or else the US and other countries would not put extra funds into the IMF.</p>
    <p>The Italians were resisting the idea of surveillance, which would allow the IMF to ensure Italian commitments to an austerity package are implemented to a clear timetable without any slippage.</p>
    <p>Osborne continued to insist that Britain was willing to contribute to the fund along with other countries, but said this should not be seen as a direct bailout of the eurozone. One option under discussion is to use some of that money to beef up the European financial stability facility, the eurozone's bailout fund.</p>
    <p>The IMF would essentially print and distribute a certain amount of <ref target="http://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/sdr.htm">special drawing rights</ref>, an international reserve asset created by the IMF in 1969 to supplement its member countries' official reserves. They are valued based on a basket of major currencies: US dollars, yen, sterling and euros.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>