<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi says democracy at stake in Senate vote on expulsion" author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-11-25" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/25/silvio-berlusconi-senate-vote-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="In letter to Democratic and Five Star senators, former PM claims new evidence proves he did not commit tax fraud" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="b72ed098daa9565c">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi begged his fellow senators on Monday not to kick him out of parliament, claiming new evidence proved he did not commit the tax fraud that has threatened his political future.</p>
    <p>In a last-ditch effort to stave off a Senate vote that could keep him out of public office for years, the former prime minister claimed that affidavits from 12 witnesses and 15,000 pages of documentation from Hong Kong proved he was innocent.</p>
    <p>The claim is legally contentious: Berlusconi's conviction for tax fraud has been upheld by Italy's highest court, and such rulings are final. But he was still trying to convince the court of public opinion 48 hours before the scheduled vote.</p>
    <p>In a letter to senators from the centre-left Democratic party and the populist Five Star Movement, Berlusconi set aside his typically combative tone and painted himself as a concerned elder statesman, saying he understood their indignation and "authentic love for Italy" but that freedom itself was at stake.</p>
    <p>"I ask you to truly reflect in the intimacy of your conscience … before taking a decision that concerns not just myself but our democracy," he said.</p>
    <p>The 77-year-old has said his removal from parliament would amount to a government coup, even though he has no role in the government.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was convicted last year over the purchase of rights to broadcast US films on his Mediaset channels through a series of offshore companies that involved the false declaration of payments to avoid taxes. His defence argued that he was busy in politics at the time and no longer involved in managing the day-to-day activities of the business.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi read aloud the text of an affidavit by a one-time manager of a US company who insisted the billionaire had nothing to do with the film deals.</p>
    <p>Italy's high court upheld the conviction and four-year prison sentence on 1 August. A law passed last year bans anyone sentenced to more than two years in prison from holding or running for public office for six years.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's lawyers have argued the law cannot be applied retroactively to crimes allegedly committed before it was passed, but the Senate vote to expel him appears poised to go ahead unless his allies can pull off a last-minute delay.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>