<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian government forged from team of rivals" author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-04-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/apr/27/italian-government-team-rivals-recession" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Berlusconi-era conservatives return in power-sharing deal with liberal opponents to jointly save country from recession" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Eurozone crisis,European Union,European monetary union,European banks,Financial sector,Euro,Business" fingerprint="fd8e7e193505e269">
  <main>
    <p>A coalition of Silvio Berlusconi's forces and center-left rivals forged a new Italian government on Saturday, an unusual alliance that broke a two-month deadlock following inconclusive elections in the recession-mired country.</p>
    <p>The daunting achievement was pulled off by Enrico Letta, the center-left PM-designate who will be sworn in as premier along with the new cabinet on Sunday at the presidential Quirinal Palace.</p>
    <p>Letta, 46, is a moderate with a reputation as a political bridge-builder. He is also the nephew of former premier Berlusconi's longtime adviser, Gianni Letta, a relationship seen as smoothing over often nasty interaction between the two main coalition partners.</p>
    <p>Serving as deputy premier and interior minister will be Berlusconi's top political aide, Angelino Alfano. He is a former justice minister who was the architect of legislation that critics say was tailor-made to help media mogul Berlusconi in his many judicial woes.</p>
    <p>The creation of the coalition capped the latest political comeback for Berlusconi, who was forced to resign in 2011 as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> slid deeper into the eurozone's sovereign debt crisis.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, a fervent anti-communist, views Italy's left as a personal nemesis, and Letta's Democratic Party has some of its roots in what was the west's largest communist party.</p>
    <p>The new premier, Letta, expressed "sober satisfaction over the team we put together and its willingness" to form a coalition.</p>
    <p>President Giorgio Napolitano, who tasked Letta with creating a government out of bitter rivals, called upon the coalition partners to work "in a spirit of absolute, indispensable cohesion" as they work for sorely needed political and economic reforms.</p>
    <p>"I hope there is maximum cohesion," said Napolitano, sounding almost breathless as he expressed confidence the rivals could work together for the good of the country.</p>
    <p>Napolitano continued: "It was and is the only possible government," adding there was no room for "delay, in our country's and Europe's interests."</p>
    <p>Napolitano, 87, reluctantly agreed to be re-elected by Parliament earlier this month for another seven-year term because of the political instability.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>