<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's Mediaset eyes Endemol" author="Julia Day" date="2006-06-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/jun/19/independentproductioncompanies.citynews" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's broadcaster Mediaset said it was interested in buying Big Brother production company Endemol. By Julia Day." categories="Media" tags="Independent production companies,Media business,Media,Business,Television industry,Silvio Berlusconi,Endemol" fingerprint="7c40cb345b33a2d8">
  <main>
    <p>Former Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's broadcaster Mediaset said it was interested in buying Big Brother production company Endemol.</p>
    <p>Dutch company Endemol's Spanish owner Telefonica has said it is considering offloading the production house, which also makes Channel 4's quiz hit Deal or No Deal.</p>
    <p>The Mediaset Chairman, Fedele Confalonieri, said: "There is a general interest for Endemol as there is for everything."</p>
    <p>He added that there was nothing more concrete at the moment.</p>
    <p>Reuters reported last week that Dutch media mogul John de Mol may team up with Mediaset to buy Endemol, the company he founded.</p>
    <p>And Dutch newspaper Het Financieele Dagblad has reported that Mediaset and De Mol's investment company Talpa were willing to offer 14 euros per share for Endemol, pushing up its shares more than 8%.</p>
    <p>Executives at Mediaset, controlled by Berlusconi's family, have long said they want to buy more content but Endemol was too big for the Italian network to acquire on its own, fuelling reports it could form a consortium to buy the company.</p>
    <p>Mediaset has not ruled out buying Endemol as part of a larger group that could involve private equity firms, investment banks and other media groups.</p>
    <p>Last week, Endemol nominated a Telefonica executive, Elias Rodriguez-Vina Cancio, as its new chief executive to succeed Joaquim Agut, who resigned last week.</p>
    <p>Analysts had expected the Endemol chief operating officer, Tom Barnicoat, to replace Mr Agut, whose departure was interpreted as presaging a sale of the business.</p>
    <p>Telefonica bought Endemol for $5.5bn (£3.8bn) at the height of the dotcom boom and floated a 22% stake in the company last year.</p>
    <p>Today Endemol's shares were down 2.3% at 13.45 euros.</p>
    <p>As well as private equity firms, other media companies are also understood to be interested including Time Warner, Sony and News Corp.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>