<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Politicians' embarrassing moments - in pictures" author="John Crace" date="2013-09-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/gallery/2013/sep/05/politicians-embarrassing-moments-in-pictures" hostname="theguardian.com" description="We round up some politicians' most mortifying moments to be caught on camera. John Crace imagines what they were thinking" categories="Politics" tags="Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Al Gore,Angela Merkel,John Kerry,François Hollande,Geert Wilders,Barack Obama,John McCain,George Bush;Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Al Gore,Angela Merkel,John Kerry,François Hollande,Geert Wilders,Barack Obama,John McCain,George Bush" fingerprint="1b46d8d5811c51d7">
  <main><head rend="h1">Politicians' embarrassing moments - in pictures</head><p> A picture of Francois Hollande looking less than statesmanlike caused a stir today, after picture agencies were accused of </p><ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/say-fromage-agency-denies-censorship-after-withdrawing-gormless-picture-of-francois-hollande-8799276.html">pulling the gormless image in a bout of self-censorship</ref>. Anyone would think Hollande was the first politician to be caught on camera looking daft. In fact, whether it's Geert Wilders seemingly picking his nose with a ballpoint pen or George Bush being upstaged by a turkey, there are plenty of other mortifying examples to enjoy. John Crace imagines what they were thinking<list rend="ul"><item><head rend="h2">Francoise Hollande, today.</head>'I didn't realise being America's new best friend meant I'd have to look like Mickey Mouse'<p>Photograph: Guardian</p></item><item><head rend="h2">Al Gore, at the opening of a centre for homeless children in 2003:</head>'I tell you, the whole fucking polar ice cap is melting like<hi rend="#i">now</hi>and we're all going to die'<p>Photograph: Stephen Chernin/Getty Images</p></item><item><head rend="h2">David Miliband outside Labour conference in 2008:</head>'You run and hide, Ed, while I count to 10. Then I'm going to come and shoot you' Photograph: Jeremy Selwyn/Rex Features</item><item><head rend="h2">George Bush and a turkey in 2001:</head>'It takes one to know one'<p>Photograph: Kevin Lamarque/Reuters</p></item><item><head rend="h2">Dutch politician Geert Wilders in 2009:</head>'Me and Le Pen turn our noses up at foreigners'<p>Photograph: Marcel Antonisse/AFP/Getty Images</p></item><item><head rend="h2">Angela Merkel reacts at a meeting in 2012:</head>'I<hi rend="#i">told</hi>you there was no more money'<p>Photograph: Frabrizio Bensch/Reuters</p></item><item><head rend="h2">John Kerry struggles to catch a football in 2003:</head>'The Syrian crisis needs a safe pair of hands'<p>Photograph: Jim Bourg/Reuters</p></item><item><head rend="h2">Silvio Berlusconi gurning in 2013:</head>'I think I've overdone the Botox'<p>Photograph: Alessandra Benedetti/Corbis</p></item><item><head rend="h2">John McCain in 2008:</head>'I've just found Tony Blair's Iraq dossier'<p>Photograph: Emmanuel Dunand/AFP/Getty Images</p></item></list></main>
  <comments/>
</doc>