<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi sparks outrage by likening pressures of legal woes to Holocaust" author="Tom Kington" date="2013-11-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/06/berlusconi-legal-investigations-holocaust-nazi-germany-hitler" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian former prime minister says he and his children 'feel like Jewish families must have felt in Germany during Hitler's regime'" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="762aca6f9003cf8c">
  <main>
    <p>The former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has caused outrage after likening the pressure he and his family face from legal investigations to the persecution of Jewish people in Nazi Germany.</p>
    <p>"My children say they feel like Jewish families must have felt in Germany during Hitler's regime," he said in an interview. "We truly have everyone against us."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is facing a year of social work following his conviction for tax fraud and is appealing against a sentence for paying an underage prostitute while fighting to keep his party from splitting amid internal disputes.</p>
    <p>But the gaffe-prone politician, who delights in whipping up controversy with politically incorrect remarks, had gone too far with his Holocaust parallel, said Renzo Gattegna, the president of the Italian Union of Jewish Communities.</p>
    <p>"Under Nazism, the Jews of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> were caught in a black vortex of violence, persecution and death," he said. "Any parallel with the affairs of the Berlusconi family is therefore not only inappropriate and incomprehensible but also offensive to the memory of those who were deprived of all rights and, after atrocious and unspeakable suffering, deprived of their lives."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is no stranger to making light of the Holocaust. In 2010, he wooed a youth rally with a joke about Hitler promising his supporters he would make a comeback, "but on one condition ... next time I'm going to be evil".</p>
    <p>The same year he was attacked by the Vatican's daily newspaper after he cracked a joke based on the assumption that Jewish people are parsimonious.</p>
    <p>In 2003, Berlusconi caused uproar in the European parliament when he compared a hostile German MEP to a Nazi concentration camp guard. Earlier this year, the three-time Italian prime minister was described as a "disgrace" after choosing a Holocaust memorial event to praise the Italian fascist dictator Benito Mussolini.</p>
    <p>Reacting to his latest comments, Danilo Leva, a member of the centre-left Democratic party, said: "Berlusconi has completely lost grip of the scale of things. He has been regaling us for 20 years with the myth of his persecution and today, instead of asking forgiveness from Italians for his tax fraud conviction, he risks this shocking parallel with a tragedy like the Holocaust."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>