<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The laughable cavaliere" author="Sophie Arie" date="2004-05-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/may/20/worlddispatch.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The public may not like Silvio Berlusconi's election posters, but Italy's satirists love them, writes Sophie Arie." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="daf6022cd330c64d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has long been accused of monopolising Italian television. But these days, his familiar, bronzed face is all over the country's streets, not just its screens.</p>
    <p>The prime minister's image is plastered on thousands of billboards in the run-up to the European elections, on June 12 and 13.</p>
    <p>Grannies at bus-stops, businessmen behind the wheel and canoodling couples in parks are looking up to find the benignly smiling, soft-focus Silvio gazing down at them.</p>
    <p>A quick drive through Rome suggests there are three or four smiling, surgically rejuvenated Silvios for every sombre-faced Romano Prodi, leader of the opposition Olive Tree Alliance. Giancarlo Fini, the National Alliance leader, and leaders of smaller parties only occasionally interrupt the roadside pattern.</p>
    <p>Each Forza Italia poster shows the prime minister in a fatherly pose, immaculately groomed with gentle crow's-feet.</p>
    <p>Alongside the reassuring face is a series of big numbers: immigrati clandestini (illegal immigrants) down 40%; 1,558,000 pensions raised; 21,573 fewer road accidents; 7,646bn lire (£2.7bn) for schools; L93,000bn spent on major new public projects.</p>
    <p>The figures are mind-boggling - all the more so since the largest ones are given in old lire, not euros, ensuring longer strings of zeros and appealing to Italian nostalgia for the lost currency.</p>
    <p>If numbers count, you might guess Berlusconi's party is about to sweep the floor at the European elections.</p>
    <p>But according to a recent poll by Coesis research, the posters have been one of the more remarkable communications flops of the media tycoon's political career.</p>
    <p>Although 80% of the 406 voters polled had seen the Big Brother-style posters and the big figures, only 6% were convinced by them. 57% of former Forza Italia voters were so put off by them they were considering voting for someone else.</p>
    <p>However, the poster campaign has proved a great and unexpected success in one respect: it has inspired satirists.</p>
    <p>Hundreds of mock posters have emerged on the internet, with the same smiling face but new slogans, such as: "Italy's credibility reduced to 0%;" "2,190 lies, at least two a day for three years;" and "A 30% increase on my shares in Mediaset [Berlusconi's private television network]."</p>
    <p>A backfiring election poster campaign was the last thing Mr Berlusconi needed.</p>
    <p>The media tycoon may have shown record staying power, leading the most durable postwar Italian government, but he is also facing the stickiest situation in his political career.</p>
    <p>The weekly magazine L'Espresso recently celebrated Silvio's milestone in Italian political history by listing 1,000 lies it says the prime minister has told in the last three years.</p>
    <p>With the Italian economy struggling, the conflict of interest debate still raging and 20 Italians killed so far in Iraq and at least four held hostage, Italians may deliver a vote of no confidence in the Berlusconi government at the European elections.</p>
    <p>According to a recent poll for La Repubblica newspaper, the number of disappointed Italians has doubled in the past two years. 68% now feel Berlusconi's government has broken its election promises, most importantly failing to bring about a promised financial miracle in Italy.</p>
    <p>While Forza Italia has adopted a more serious and less personality-based campaign than in the 2001 elections, when a biographical booklet on Mr Berlusconi was delivered to the doors of millions of Italians, the personality of the leader is still the party's strongest card.</p>
    <p>Perhaps in case Forza Italia voters are wavering, the official party website has posted a list of 10 reasons why Mr Berlusconi is still the man to vote for.</p>
    <p>They include: "He is rich but he is not a snob;" 'He knows how to laugh at himself;" and "Thanks to him, Italy matters more in Europe and the world."</p>
    <p>But perhaps the most important asset of the businessman-leader to the sceptical Italian public is: "He is not a professional politician."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>