<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi must choose: media or politics?" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2006-09-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2006/sep/11/berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi, the former Italian prime minister, this week faces the most difficult decision of his career. In order to continue as the leader of his country's official parliamentary opposition, Berlusconi may have to renounce his multi-billion pound media empire. On Wednesday the new Italian government will put forward legislation - a so-called &quot;conflict of interests&quot; law - that aims to ensure that so much power is never again concentrated in one man's hands. Berlusconi owns three of Italy's seven national television channels, two newspapers, the largest publisher, the largest advertising agency and numerous internet ventures. (Via Sunday Telegraph)" categories="Media" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="5ffa0a2c9767c249">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2006/09/10/witaly10.xml"> Silvio Berlusconi, the former Italian prime minister,</ref> this week faces the most difficult decision of his career. In order to continue as the leader of his country's official parliamentary opposition, </p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Berlusconi</hi>may have to renounce his multi-billion pound media empire. On Wednesday the new Italian government will put forward legislation - a so-called "conflict of interests" law - that aims to ensure that so much power is never again concentrated in one man's hands.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Berlusconi</hi>owns three of Italy's seven national television channels, two newspapers, the largest publisher, the largest advertising agency and numerous internet ventures. (Via</p>
    <p><ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/">Sunday Telegraph</ref>)</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>