<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: A conflict too far | Editorial" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2010-12-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-italy-conflict-too-far" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Editorial: In Italy growth is stagnant and the man at the helm has lurched from one personal crisis to another" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="e7a95835d035d777">
  <main>
    <p>What chance would you give any leader of surviving a vote of no confidence after being accused of the following: profiting from energy deals with Russia; paying off the Cosa Nostra for protecting his family; buying the votes of deputies in parliament; intervening with police to secure the release of the 17-year-old belly dancer who claimed she had been the guest of parties which ended in an erotic game known as bunga bunga? And all in the last two months?</p>
    <p>If the leader is called <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the chance of survival is quite high. The latest crisis was brought about by Gianfranco Fini, a former neo-fascist, who was kicked out of Mr Berlusconi's party in July and took 30 deputies with him. At the weekend Mr Fini claimed what the left had long alleged: that Mr Berlusconi's only motive for staying in power was to avoid prosecution in court. However Mr Fini, consumed with rage, had not thought through what happens if the motion of no confidence succeeds today in the lower house of parliament.</p>
    <p>Italy's political opposition is notoriously fractious. Wherever you are in the spectrum another party stands immediately to the left or the right, splitting your vote. A natural ally for Mr Fini, who is softening his brand image as an autocratic conservative, would be Pier Ferdinando Casini's Christian Democrat Union of the Centre (UDC). The two parties even voted together against the government. But Mr Fini and Mr Casini have two different projects. One wants to shake up the right, the other aims to be the bellwether centrist swapping partners to stay in power. So no joy there.</p>
    <p>The centre left is split three ways. The Democratic party, a combination of ex-communists and former progressive Christian Democrats, is run by Pier Luigi Bersani, who lacks both charisma and regular access to the main television channels. Mr Bersani is hemmed in to the right by the UDC, and the vehemently anti-Berlusconi Italy of Principles party, and to the left by a charismatic, gay leftist, Nichi Vendola. So when the press in Italy accuse Mr Fini of propelling the country into a "crisis in the dark, it has a point. So, too, did <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-italy-senate-appeal">Mr Berlusconi yesterday</ref> when he told deputies that bringing down the government would lead to months of political paralysis that could send the country spiralling into the euro debt crisis.</p>
    <p>In truth, Italy has not had a government since the spring of 2009 when the sex scandals around the prime minister first broke. It has had ministers, but growth is stagnant and the man at the helm has lurched from one personal crisis to another. The conflicts of interest in having Mr Berlusconi as leader are just too great. Italy needs fresh elections and a new leader, and Mr Berlusconi finally needs to face charges in court.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>