<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The showman returns" author="Anna Masera" date="2008-04-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/16/theshowmanreturns" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Anna Masera: There's little comfort for supporters of the radical left in the Italian elections, where they were trounced by Silvio Berlusconi" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe,The League" fingerprint="b7c1185baa323f35">
  <main>
    <p>We are a nation full of surprises. Against all the odds, Italy chose the centre-right People of Freedom party, (Popolo delle Libertà, or PDL) led by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, in a big way. We gave it a strong lead not just in the house of representatives, but in the senate too, so it doesn't need any allies to form a government for the next five years. The Democratic party (PD) leader Walter Veltroni bowed to the superiority of his opponent and wished him good luck: there's a lot of work ahead to reform the country.</p>
    <p>But two other big surprises emerged from these elections: the polarising effect of the PD, which wiped out the radical left (the Communist and Green parties, together under the <ref target="http://www.sinistrarcobaleno.it/">Sinistra Arcobaleno</ref> umbrella, and the Socialist party). And the strong result for the federalist, anti-tax Northern League, inside the PDL (between 8% and 9%, practically double their result in 2006): this was a clear mandate from electors fed up with an ancient, centralised, bureaucratic economic system that is paralysing the country.</p>
    <p>Yesterday, <ref target="http://www.corriere.it/english/">Corriere della Sera</ref> columnist Gian Antonio Stella (best known for his book La Casta, which highlights the privileges of the Italian political caste), underlined the extinction of the Green party, whose leader, Alfonso Pecoraro Scanio, was forced to admit that he had had no hope for the party to begin with. And a short sarcastic editorial note by Jena in <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/redazione/default.asp">La Stampa</ref> summarised the wiped-out left's feelings: "One must admit that Veltroni achieved an absolutely extraordinary result: he destroyed the left." As usual, leftists debate who is most at fault; but most analysts agree that if the Socialist leader Enrico Boselli has succeeded in effecting the first extinction of his party from parliament since the foundation of the republic, it can't be only Veltroni's fault.</p>
    <p>The fact is, the radical left's loss is the Northern League's gain: the popular working-class vote shifted towards the party that seems to better represent their feelings, anger and desire for change. It's the result of the sociological changes that have taken place in post-industrial Italy: the new working class sees the League as the "say no" party which stands up against wastes of public money, over-taxation, malpractice, abuse of power and injustice. Columnist Lucia Annunziata <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/_web/cmstp/tmplRubriche/editoriali/gEditoriali.asp?ID_blog=25&amp;ID_articolo=4399&amp;ID_sezione=&amp;sezione=">blames</ref> the Romano Prodi centre-left government for fostering this "say no" movement, by accepting it instead of defeating it promptly during the no-<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treno_Alta_Velocit%C3%A0">Tav</ref> protests (against the high speed train), or the no-incinerators action (incinerators were supposed to resolve Naples' <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2007/may/27/italy.waste">garbage</ref> crisis), all the way back to the no-nukes movement.</p>
    <p>A small consolation for the centre-left comes from the personal success of ex-<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani_Pulite">mani pulite</ref> (clean hands) magistrate Antonio Di Pietro's Italia dei Valori party, which got 4.3% of the votes in both houses of parliament rallying against corruption. A result that Berlusconi, his victim in many trials, resents: "How can an Italian possibly vote for him?" he confided yesterday to his aficionados. One thing is even more certain after these elections: the road against corruption in Italy is an uphill one.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>