<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="G8 summit: Barracks for Barack Obama, with basketball court thrown in" author="John Hooper" date="2009-07-03" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/03/g8-summit-italy-berlusconi-obama" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi oversees final preparations at heavily-guarded site near earthquake zone of L'Aquila" categories="World news" tags="G8,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Barack Obama,Natural disasters and extreme weather,World news,Europe,Earthquakes" fingerprint="bea9501d872f0255">
  <main>
    <p>"Excuse me, but what are you doing?"</p>
    <p>Italians phrase things so delicately. Even this one, who was cradling a sub-machine gun with a pistol strapped to his thigh, Rambo-style.</p>
    <p>It was proof the Guardian had penetrated what, until next Friday, when the world's leaders end their latest G8 summit, will be the most sensitive, heavily guarded location on earth – Barack Obama's basketball court.</p>
    <p>It was created, outside the president's temporary residence ("Building P1"), as a gesture of goodwill by his host, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. There again, it might be thought Italy's prime minister owed him a gesture or two.</p>
    <p>After once describing the US president as "tanned", he then decided Obama and others, who had been looking forward to convening by the balmy waters of Sardinia, should meet at a barracks in an earthquake zone.</p>
    <p>Today there was yet another after-shock of the disaster that, in April, left almost 300 dead. The tremor, magnitude 3.6, sent workers fleeing into the streets from the regional government headquarters and other recently reoccupied buildings in L'Aquila.</p>
    <p>The mighty of the earth will arrive by way of a flying club hastily turned into an airport. Officials say the new Aeroporto dei Parchi, whose control tower is made of pre-fabricated units, can handle planes with up to 40 passengers.</p>
    <p>But that is on a rare stretch of even land in a valley ringed by mountains, and the first planes to touch down on Thursday were making spine-tingling turns to line up with the runway. Once the presidents and prime ministers are over that little adventure, they will be driven to the barracks through an area still visibly shattered by the earthquake.</p>
    <p>The natural route is through the village of Coppito, many of whose inhabitants are living in an encampment beside the main street. One of the first sights for the illustrious guests could be of a house that has lost an entire wall, revealing the contents within.</p>
    <p>Though some activity has returned, the area round L'Aquila looks like a war zone: lorries ferrying humanitarian aid, helicopters clattering overhead, buildings that seem to have been shelled, and roadside stalls run by shopkeepers unable yet to return to their usual premises.</p>
    <p>The barracks, three miles (5km) from the centre of L'Aquila, must have been an awkward choice for Italy's flamboyant leader. It houses a training school for the Guardia di Finanza (motto: "Nec recisa recedit" — "Never, even broken, does it retreat").</p>
    <p>This a branch of the armed forces which comes under the finance ministry and whose duties include checking on tax fraud — an offence for which Berlusconi, who denies the charge, is currently on trial. Not for the first time.</p>
    <p>Stretching out from under the sprawling parade ground is a network of bunkers. It reportedly includes vaults taken by the Italian central bank to hold part of the country's reserves.</p>
    <p>The site has another link to the global financial meltdown that will be top of the G8's agenda: La Repubblica reported yesterday that, in 2004, it was privatised by the last Berlusconi government to a consortium in part comprising the now-defunct Lehman Brothers and the nationalised Royal Bank of Scotland.</p>
    <p>Visting the site on Thursday, Berlusconi said he would have "everything ready with days to spare". Since his officials were not offering a tour, The Guardian decided to see for itself.</p>
    <p>Beyond a line of crash barriers was a site that looked as if it might just be ready at about 11.59 on the night before Wednesday's opening session. There were workmen hefting plasterboard walls, laying turf outside the delegates' accommodation and shifting mounds of garbage behind the main conference hall, which was a sea of plastic sheeting and loose cables. Nor was Obama's basketball court – alongside a nondescript building that previously served as married quarters – exactly match-ready.</p>
    <p>The visit was cut short by the revenue guard and a burly, bearded sergeant who made us delete our pictures before having us removed. The photo below? That's a trade secret. Nec recisa recedit. As we say of the Guardian.</p>
    <graphic src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2009/7/3/1246661070002/A-makeshift-basketball-co-001.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="A makeshift basketball court that has been set up for Barack Obama"/>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>