<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi in court as divorce battle begins" author="Tom Kington" date="2010-01-31" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/jan/31/silvio-berlusconi-veronica-lario-divorce" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister shows up with four lawyers for first court hearing with wife Veronica Lario" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3f7a52299ad56333">
  <main>
    <p>After a hard week fighting mafia clans and the "hostile" magistrates he claims are trying to overthrow him, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> might have been forgiven for thinking he could relax at the weekend. But yesterday he experienced a face to face encounter with perhaps his toughest opponent to date – his wife.</p>
    <p>At a court hearing in Milan, the Italian prime minister met Veronica Lario for the first time since she announced nine months ago she was leaving him over his friendship with an 18-year-old model. In what could be the start of a gruelling divorce battle, Berlusconi was taking no chances, showing up with four lawyers for five hours of talks across the table from Lario's lone lawyer, Cristina Morelli, reported Corriere della Sera.</p>
    <p>Throwing in the towel on 19 years of marriage to Berlusconi last May, Lario criticised his mysterious relationship with 18-year-old Noemi Letizia and his alleged attempt to send TV showgirls to the European parliament, calling him "unwell".</p>
    <p>Revelations followed of young women attending parties thrown by Berlusconi, culminating in claims by a prostitute, Patrizia D'Addario, that she had sex with Berlusconi, 73, in November 2008. Berlusconi has denied paying for sex.</p>
    <p>Although the meeting in Milan was fixed to find a quick settlement, that appears unlikely after Lario, 53, demanded maintenance payments of €3.6m (£3.1m) a month against an offer from the Berlusconi camp of no more than €300,000.</p>
    <p>Lario is also claiming shares of Berlusconi's fortune for their three children equal to those due to Berlusconi's son and daughter from his first marriage, said Corriere della Sera.</p>
    <p>In an opening salvo yesterday before a second hearing in March, Berlusconi's team presented a "detailed" dossier on Lario's own alleged infidelities, added Corriere, possibly related to claims made in the pro-Berlusconi newspaper Libero last year that she was involved in a relationship with her bodyguard.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>