<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian PM loses opera plot" author="Philip Willan" date="2003-08-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/aug/23/italy.germany" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi baffles his fellow Italians by unexpectedly cancelling a dinner date and trip to the opera with Germany's chancellor, Gerhard Schröder." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Germany,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="adef882f9084de0f">
  <main>
    <p>It is polite when inviting a colleague for a fun night out to turn up yourself for the grand event. And when your invitation is to a "kiss-and-make-up" soiree following an unfortunate gaffe that alienated your friend's entire country, you would be wise to be on your best behaviour.</p>
    <p>But last night <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> baffled his fellow Italians by unexpectedly cancelling a dinner date and trip to the opera with Germany's chancellor, Gerhard Schröder.</p>
    <p>The prime minister was to have taken Mr Schröder for an evening meal with the mayor of Verona and then to a performance of Bizet's Carmen in the city's Roman arena, also in the company of Romano Prodi, president of the European commission. It would have sealed a reconciliation between the German and Italian leaders after the latter's offensive remark to the European parliament at the start of his EU presidency in July.</p>
    <p>Mr Schröder cancelled an Italian holiday when Mr Berlusconi likened the German MEP Martin Schulz to a Nazi concentration camp guard - a gaffe aggravated by an Italian tourism minister then describing German visitors as drunk and arrogant hypernationalists.</p>
    <p>Last night Mr Berlusconi said he had cancelled to avoid the possibility of disruption by leftwing protesters, saying he feared they would ruin the evening for everyone. "This is an act of affection for Verona and for the Arena, which at all costs must not be exploited for thoughtless political aims," he explained. Mr Schröder and Mr Prodi said they regretted the decision but understood its motives.</p>
    <p>Opposition MPs were less understanding. "In politics you receive whistles as well as applause. Only dictators insist they get nothing but applause," said a Left Democrat MP, Luciano Violante. A Green MP, Alfonso Pecoraro, Scanio thought Mr Berlusconi feared the applause would have been all for Mr Schröder and Mr Prodi, a former Left prime minister of Italy; Berlusconi's "prima donna syndrome" meant he wanted the stage to himself.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>