<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi vows to keep Italian firms out of the hands of foreign owners" author="John Hooper" date="2008-10-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2008/oct/16/berlusconi-italy-business" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prime minister claims oil-producing countries are seeking Italian acquisitions at bargain prices" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Business,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7e8003bf9443331d">
  <main>
    <p>Fresh from saving Alitalia being taken over by the French and Dutch, Silvio Berlusconi, is acting to ensure no other <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italian</ref> company falls into foreign hands at the bargain prices available on the Milan borsa.</p>
    <p>On Wednesday night, the Italian prime minister declared in Brussels that Consob, the country's stock market regulator, and the treasury were working to change the rules.</p>
    <p>He said he had information on an influx of cash from sovereign funds, particularly those belonging to oil-producing countries.</p>
    <p>The finance minister in Berlusconi's right-wing government, Giulio Tremonti, said amendments would be inserted into two decrees approved by the government and intended mainly to bolster Italy's banks.</p>
    <p>According to reports today, the new measures would lower the 2% threshold at which equity holdings in a company have to be made public and suspend a rule that requires companies to get "poison pill" and other defences approved in advance by a meeting of shareholders. Tremonti said the measures would be "within the European framework".</p>
    <p>The government's initiative won it rare plaudits from trade unionists in a society where inward investment is almost universally regarded as a menace</p>
    <p>Berlusconi made defence of the "italianita", or Italian-ness, of the economy a centrepiece of his successful campaign to be re-elected prime minister this year.</p>
    <p>Renata Polverini, the general secretary of the UGL trades unions federation, said: "The government does well to prepare legislative initiatives to enhance the rules and protect our firms."</p>
    <p>The earliest warning was sounded on Tuesday by Consob president Lamberto Cardia. In evidence to the senate's finance committee, he said the collapse in share prices had created "new worries" about hostile takeover bids.</p>
    <p>However, he also said most of the selling on the Milan borsa had been by foreigners or their agents.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, by contrast, said he "had information from oil-producing countries, which have ample funds and are making huge acquisitions on our markets".</p>
    <p>He said: "First, I got information from journalistic sources in Arab countries. Then, I got confirmation from the oil-producing countries' governments themselves.</p>
    <p>"Many Italian companies have a share price that does not correspond at all to their value, so there are excellent opportunities for those who may wish to make hostile bids."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi last week encouraged Italian investors to snap up the stock of solid firms such as Eni and Enel.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>