<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Bomb found near Berlusconi villa after Blair visit" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2004-08-18" url="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2004/aug/18/italy.politics" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian police said today that they had defused a bomb near the Sardinian holiday villa of the country's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, only hours after a visit by his British counterpart Tony Blair." categories="UK news" tags="UK news,Italy,Politics,September 11 2001,UK security and counter-terrorism,US news,Foreign policy,World news,Counter-terrorism policy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="ff44518d9821db57">
  <main>
    <p>Italian police said today that they had defused a bomb near the Sardinian holiday villa of the country's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, only hours after a visit by his British counterpart Tony Blair.</p>
    <p>Officers spent hours scouring the area for a possible second bomb after a local leftwing group reportedly telephoned a warning to a local newspaper, claiming to have planted two devices. Police eventually concluded the second device did not exist.</p>
    <p>Mr Blair and his wife, Cherie, had left Sardinia a few hours earlier after staying overnight as Mr Berlusconi's guests. Security measures on the island had been stepped up for the visit.</p>
    <p>The caller, who contacted Sardinian newspaper L'Unione Sarda, claimed to represent the Proletarian Nuclei for Communism (NPC).</p>
    <p>The Italian daily newspaper Corriere della Sera described the NPC as an "anarcho-separatist" group. The organisation has carried out 20 attacks in the last four years, including small-scale bombings of government party headquarters in Sardinia.</p>
    <p>Corriere della Sera said the group had given the location of one bomb - a large bin near the centre of tourist town Porto Rotondo, less than a mile from Mr Berlusconi's Villa Certosa.</p>
    <p>Police said they found the bomb ten minutes after the warning had been given at 10.45pm yesterday. The paper reported that the device had been set to explode at 2am.</p>
    <p>"The other one: we're not telling you - go and find it. It's for Berlusconi," the caller said, according to the Corriere della Sera. Police told Reuters they had checked all other bins in the area but found nothing. The prime minister has been heavily criticised in the UK for accepting hospitality from the controversial Mr Berlusconi as part of his holiday.</p>
    <p>His visit followed a stay at Sir Cliff Richard's Barbados villa. Mr and Mrs Blair were returning to Prince Guicciardini Strozzi's Tuscany villa to complete their summer break.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>