<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy begins search for new president with Berlusconi still pulling the strings" author="Stephanie Kirchgaessner; Guardian staff reporter" date="2015-01-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jan/29/italy-search-new-president-berlusconi-renzi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Election will have major consequences for Italian politics and prime minister Matteo Renzi’s long-term ambitions" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Matteo Renzi,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" fingerprint="fedeab379aa587e5">
  <main>
    <p>The shadowy process of selecting a new Italian president began on Thursday, testing the political prowess of the country’s centre-left prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/matteo-renzi">Matteo Renzi</ref>, less than a week after elections in Greece rattled the European establishment.</p>
    <p>The election is also expected to measure the political relevance of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the disgraced former prime minister and media mogul who remains at the helm of the centre-right opposition party Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>The first round of voting on Thursday did not yield a winner because no single candidate reached the required two thirds majority for victory and many lawmakers in the Democratic Party (PD) voted blank, as they were encouraged by Renzi. The decisive fourth round of votes is expected to occur on Saturday when the winner will only need a simple majority, although the process could drag on for longer.</p>
    <p>The role of the Italian head of state is not just a figurehead: he – a woman has never been elected – is supposed to be an independent arbiter who can dissolve governments, call new elections, and help form new administrations.</p>
    <p>Giorgio Napolitano, the former communist whose resignation this month after nine years prompted the election, greatly expanded the traditional role of president, serving as a power-broker in Italian politics at the height of the eurozone crisis.</p>
    <p>Napolitano, 89, reluctantly accepted an unprecedented second term in 2013 when another replacement could not be agreed.</p>
    <p>Renzi has been trying to generate support for his choice for president, a Sicilian judge named Sergio Mattarella, among the 1,009 lawmakers and other elected officials who will begin voting in a secret ballot election on Thursday. But he is operating in a political minefield.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has been an unlikely but necessary ally for Renzi, because the prime minister was expected to face defections from some on the left flank of his own party. They have been emboldened by the election in Greece of leftist Alexis Tsipras and believe Renzi to be too centrist.</p>
    <p>But even left-leaning critics of Renzi appeared content with the choice of Mattarella on Thursday, raising questions about whether the prime minister would have to rely on Berlusconi, 78, who reportedly scoffed at the namein a meeting with Renzi this week.</p>
    <p>Mattarella and Berlusconi have history. In 1990, the former resigned as a minister in a Christian Democratic government – the party is now defunct – in protest against the passage of a law that greatly consolidated Berlusconi’s television empire. Mattarella’s brother was murdered by the mafia in 1980 while he was serving as governor of Sicily.</p>
    <p>Renzi’s first-round pick is not a well-known figure internationally, compared with other former and current politicians who have been floated as candidates and could still be elected in subsequent rounds of voting.</p>
    <p>The presidential election will have significant consequences for Italian politics and Renzi’s long-term ambitions.</p>
    <p>Renzi and Berlusconi established a pact shortly before Renzi came to power after an intra-party coup in the PD last year. The two men agreed to compromise on a series of election and constitutional reforms that are seen internationally as necessary to revive the country’s economy and gridlocked politics.</p>
    <p>Analysts say that a prolonged fight over the presidential race would complicate that pact and raise the possibility of early elections being called.</p>
    <p>“Renzi and Berlusconi’s ideal candidate would be a weak figure, politically dependent on their alignment,” said Wolfango Piccoli, managing director at Teneo Intelligence. “On the other hand, Renzi’s detractors desire a strongly independent president capable of standing up to the prime minister.”</p>
    <p>The first rounds of voting will require a candidate to win a two-thirds majority of the votes to be elected. In the fourth round, which is expected on Saturday, the winning candidate will only require only a simple majority.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>