<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roy Greenslade: Axel Springer wants Google to help charge for content" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2009-12-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2009/dec/07/charging-for-content-germany" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Germany's leading newspaper publisher, Axel Springer, has explained how it will charge for content. Christoph Keese, an architect of the company's online strategy (and its chief PR) told the New York Times: &quot;A highly industrialised world cannot survive on rumours. It needs quality journalism, and that costs money.&quot;" categories="Media" tags="Charging for content,Germany,Google,Silvio Berlusconi,Newspapers,US press and publishing,Digital media,Media,Paywalls,Europe,Axel Springer" fingerprint="7bfbb14235878feb">
  <main>
    <p>Germany's leading newspaper publisher, <hi rend="#b">Axel Springer</hi>, has explained how it will charge for content. <hi rend="#b">Christoph Keese</hi>, an architect of the company's online strategy (and its PR chief), <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/07/business/media/07iht-springer07.html">told the New York Times:</ref> "A highly industrialised world cannot survive on rumours. It needs quality journalism, and that costs money."</p>
    <p>There may be some dispute about whether Springer's flagship, <hi rend="#b">Bild</hi>, Europe's best-selling daily, exemplifies quality journalism, but that's another matter.</p>
    <p>Here is Keese's plan. Instead of building separate paywalls around individual newspaper sites, he wants publishers and internet companies to work together to create a "one-click marketplace solution" for online content.</p>
    <p>In his ideal system, search engines would continue to display links to newspaper articles, videos and other content from a variety of providers. But some of the items - what Keese calls "non-commodity journalism" - would include a price tag.</p>
    <p>An example? Pictures of Italy's prime minister <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi> cavorting with models at his villa in Sardinia — published by the Spanish daily <hi rend="#b">El País</hi>. Surely people would pay €5 for that, he said.</p>
    <p>A single click would allow the user to pay for and view the pictures. But Keese also envisages readers buying flat-rate packages to provide access to content from a variety of media outlets. And Springer is happy to work with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/google">Google</ref> on bringing the concept to fruition.</p>
    <p>Keese clearly sees Springer's initiative as a great deal more positive than the plans advanced by US newspaper publishers, believing it will preserve print media, ending his interview with a pro-German flourish.</p>
    <p>"The Americans don't give a damn if the newspapers go down," he said. "This is very different in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref>. This is Gutenberg's country. We invented this."</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Source:</hi>
      <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/07/business/media/07iht-springer07.html">New York Times</ref>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>