<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Calm words not enough to save eurozone" author="Nils Pratley" date="2011-08-03" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/aug/03/barroso-and-berlusconi-try-to-quell-european-debt-crisis" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Nils Pratley: Berlusconi and Barroso put on a soothing double act, but it may take more than that to quell contagion" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,European banks,Business,Euro,Currencies,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Market turmoil" fingerprint="ddd15b499a34ced">
  <main>
    <p>You can't blame Silvio Berlusconi and José Manuel Barroso, president of the European commission, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/aug/03/italy-debts-economic-reform">for trying to quell the sense of panic </ref>in bond markets. When Italian and Spanish 10-year bond yields are above 6%, and bank shares are plunging, there's definitely a crisis. But merely telling investors that they've got their numbers wrong is not a tactic that will succeed.</p>
    <p>Take Barroso's comment that developments in the sovereign bond markets of Italy and Spain are "clearly unwarranted on the basis of economic and budgetary fundamentals". We'll be the judge of that, investors are likely to respond, because the latest indicators suggest the global recovery is slowing at an alarming rate.</p>
    <p>Jamie Dannhauser, of Lombard Street Research, calculates that this week's PMI, or purchasing managers' data, suggests output has been falling in both Italy and Spain since May. In Spain's case, he says, the composite PMI index last month was at its lowest point since September 2009, when the economy was in deep recession. Deficit reduction measures are clearly affecting output, and growth in the eurozone as a whole is slowing.</p>
    <p>Others report stresses on the banks' funding lines, thereby hampering lenders' ability to finance recovery. Huw van Steenis, of Morgan Stanley, is not speculating wildly when he says "the risk of a credit crunch in southern Europe is growing". Most bankers would agree, at least in private.</p>
    <p>The eurozone leaders' intended response is to get the European financial stability facility up to speed and into action in the bond markets; Barroso is writing a letter urging governments to hurry up with their approvals. Conceivably, the European Central Bank could be ordered to act before then. But if German chancellor Angela Merkel shares the sense of urgency, she is yet to show it.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>