<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi declares 'we've won the bet' in his attempt to salvage Alitalia" author="John Hooper" date="2008-08-31" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2008/sep/01/theairlineindustry.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Government's plan envisages smaller company and up to 5,000 jobs losses" categories="Business" tags="Airline industry,Italy,Business,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="77b689bf1232cb61">
  <main>
    <p>Representatives of Silvio Berlusconi's government will today meet trade union leaders in a bid to secure their backing for the take-off of a new Italian flag-carrier airline, salvaged from the wreckage of Alitalia. The government's plan envisages a much smaller company and up to 5,000 job losses.</p>
    <p>On Friday, Corrado Passera, the chief executive of the stricken airline's sale adviser, Intesa Sanpaola, said a deal with its traditionally militant unions was crucial to the re-launch plan, which is sponsored by Berlusconi's government. The prime minister made defence of Alitalia's "Italian-ness" a central plank of his successful campaign for election in April.</p>
    <p>The effect of his undertaking was to harden union resistance to an earlier scheme promoted by the previous, centre-left government. The unions' stance drove away the key player in that operation, Air France-KLM.</p>
    <p>Last week, after details of the new plan were officially released, Berlusconi declared victory. "We have won the bet", he said. "The only alternative was [corporate] failure."</p>
    <p>But financiers and industrialists central to the strategy, known as Project Phoenix, were more cautious. Passera said: "The next four to five weeks will be crucial to understanding if we can go ahead or not." Roberto Colaninno, president of the Piaggio scooter company, who is expected to chair the revamped Alitalia, added that finding a foreign partner was "indispensable".</p>
    <p>He told the daily La Repubblica that negotiations were being held with Air France-KLM and Lufthansa, and that they were "going at the same speed".</p>
    <p>Project Phoenix is likely to face scrutiny on competition grounds from the European commission. And it could also prompt legal action from the Italian airline's international rivals, many of whom will see it as an exercise in state aid.</p>
    <p>Walter Veltroni, the unofficial leader of the centre-left opposition, damned the scheme as a "messy, confused, dangerous solution that does not, in fact, meet the interests of the country". He said <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> would be left not with a flag carrier but a "bunting carrier".</p>
    <p>The proposed airline - made up of the profitable rump of Alitalia and its main domestic rival, AirOne - would have 36% fewer aircraft, 40% fewer employees and 28% fewer destinations, most of them concentrated in Italy and the rest of Europe. Crucially, however, it would have a government-enforced monopoly of the most profitable route in Italy, the one linking Milan's Linate airport with Fiumicino outside Rome.</p>
    <p>Colaninno heads a consortium of 16 investors, all Italian, who have expressed a readiness to sink €1bn (£806m) into the new airline. The €1.2bn debts of the "bad company" would be dumped on the taxpayer, along with the even greater costs of winding it up.</p>
    <p>The government has promised that share- and bond-holders will, if necessary, be compensated out of a fund created to reimburse the victims of financial swindles. The redundant workers are to be offered up to seven years of welfare support.</p>
    <p>Colannino called Project Phoenix a "market operation". He indignantly rejected opposition claims that members of the consortium had been arm-twisted into saving the prime minister's face.</p>
    <p>However the shadow finance minister, Pierluigi Bersani, said some had gone in "with a pistol to the temple". Passera called the remark "unfortunate".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>