<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi shrugs off fears of new terror threat" author="Sophie Arie" date="2004-08-18" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/aug/19/italy.politics" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi brushed off fears yesterday of a fresh terrorist threat in Italy, insisting he would finish his holiday in Sardinia despite a bomb scare in the seaside town where Tony Blair ended a flying visit yesterday." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Politics,Foreign policy,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="178c304f0a21ff32">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi brushed off fears yesterday of a fresh terrorist threat in Italy, insisting he would finish his holiday in Sardinia despite a bomb scare in the seaside town where Tony Blair ended a flying visit yesterday.</p>
    <p>Police found a home-made device - a plastic tube filled with dynamite wired to a fuse and a timer - hidden between two bins by a main street in the seaside resort of Porto Rotondo.</p>
    <p>The device was defused soon after midnight on Tuesday night, at a spot roughly a mile from Mr Berlusconi's Villa Certosa estate where the Blairs had stayed the night before. It had been set to explode at 4.30am, local police said, roughly eight hours after Mr Blair had left the island.</p>
    <p>The explosives had been hid den in a bag and left in a stone shed to conceal the bins in the wealthy resort.</p>
    <p>A leftwing "anarcho-separatist" group reportedly said it had planted the mini-bomb as part of a campaign against the Italian prime minister and specifically against the war in Iraq.</p>
    <p>The tip-off came from an anonymous caller, claiming to be from an extremist group called the Proletarian Cells for Communism, who contacted the island's Unione Sarda newspaper on Tuesday.</p>
    <p>"We are not joking. We had promised a summer of flames and this is the response to that piece of shit Berlusconi. War on war," said the caller. The group has carried out a low-level terror campaign targeting conservative politicians, businesses and union officials in Sardinia for several years.</p>
    <p>On Wednesday, as several police helicopters circled low over the seaside town, Mr Berlusconi's office played down the importance of the bomb, saying the prime minister would not be changing his holiday plans or returning early to Rome.</p>
    <p>Police were unable to say when the device had been planted or how it had gone unnoticed by sniffer dogs which had searched street bins and manholes before and throughout the Blairs' 24-hour visit. The town had been on particularly high alert after a spate of threats Italy has received in recent weeks from an Islamic fundamentalist group purporting to be the European wing of al-Qaida.</p>
    <p>The device did not appear designed to cause major damage or injury. Investigators told journalists it would probably have injured passers-by and broken windows.</p>
    <p>Aides had indicated on Tuesday morning that the two leaders might make an appearance at the seafront at Porto Rotondo, to eat an ice cream. But if such a walkabout had been planned, it was abandoned and the Blairs were flown out of Mr Berlusconi's Villa Certosa estate in a police-escorted helicopter to the nearby airport at Olbia.</p>
    <p>The night before, the two leaders and Cherie Blair had taken a stroll among crowds in the nearby resort towns of Porto Quatu and Porto Cervo. The public appearance was a surprising diversion in what had been billed as a "strictly private" visit.</p>
    <p>Local newspapers say the Proletarian Cells for Communism have staged more than 20 mini-bomb attacks in the past four years.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>