<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roy Greenslade: Murdoch-Berlusconi feud takes another turn" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2009-09-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2009/sep/17/rupert-murdoch-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The feud between Rupert Murdoch and Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, took another turn yesterday" categories="Media" tags="Rupert Murdoch,Silvio Berlusconi,News Corporation,Media" fingerprint="3b8cc90fb1fa498c">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/16/business/media/16paytv.html">The feud </ref>between <hi rend="#b">Rupert Murdoch</hi> and Italy's prime minister, <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>, took another turn yesterday.</p>
    <p>Murdoch's <hi rend="#b">News Corporation</hi> announced that its Italian satellite pay-television division, <hi rend="#b">Sky Italia</hi>, had filed a lawsuit against two of Berlusconi's media companies for anti-competitive practices.</p>
    <p>It is suing<hi rend="#b"> RTI</hi>, the company that operates the TV channels of Berlusconi's <hi rend="#b">Mediaset</hi> media empire, and <hi rend="#b">Publitalia</hi>, Mediaset's advertising division, for refusing to accept advertising from Sky Italia.</p>
    <p>News Corp said it was taking the legal action "for violation of antitrust rules under article 82 of the European Treaty and for unfair competition".</p>
    <p>In June, Berlusconi accused Murdoch of mounting a personal attack through <hi rend="#b">The Times</hi> because the paper carried reports <lb/> and comment about relationship between Berlusconi and an 18-year-old model.</p>
    <p>At the time it was suggested that Berlusconi's greatest concern was not the content of the articles but Murdoch's business ambitions in Italy. Both men are competing for control of the country's pay-TV market.</p>
    <p>The feud can be traced back to December when Murdoch complained about a decision by Berlusconi's government to double the VAT levied on Sky Italia to 20%.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#i">Sources:</hi><ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/a76f9e3e-a301-11de-ba74-00144feabdc0.html?ftcamp=rss">Financial Times</ref>/<ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/16/business/media/16paytv.html">New York Times</ref></p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>