<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi leaves hospital after 24 days medical supervision" author="Lorenzo Tondo" date="2021-05-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/may/01/silvio-berlusconi-leaves-hospital-after-24-days-medical-supervision" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy’s former prime minister, who left hospital on Friday, was allegedly admitted due to long-term effects of Covid" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,Coronavirus" fingerprint="6f92c20d1007ce91">
  <main>
    <p>Italy’s former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> left hospital on Friday after spending 24 days under medical supervision due to alleged long-term effects of Covid-19.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who is 84, was seriously ill with Covid-19 last year, an experience described by the media billionaire as the “worst of his life”.</p>
    <p>Last September, Berlusconi, who led three Italian governments between 1994 and 2011, was admitted to hospital with the early stages of double pneumonia after testing positive for coronavirus.</p>
    <p>After a few days, he became critically ill as doctors said he had “the worst viral load”.</p>
    <p>“[The virus] is very bad,” Berlusconi said at the time. “I’m giving it my all, I hope to make it and to get back on track.”</p>
    <p>Last year, Berlusconi <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/sep/02/silvio-berlusconi-tests-positive-for-covid-19-after-sardinia-visit">was tested for Covid-19</ref> after a stay at his villa on Sardinia’s Costa Smeralda. Several coronavirus clusters that emerged there in August were <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/sep/06/how-sardinia-went-from-safe-haven-to-covid-19-hotspot">traced to nightclubs</ref>, including Billionaire, owned by the former Formula One team boss Flavio Briatore. On 12 August, Briatore shared a video of the two together at Berlusconi’s villa. Briatore was also admitted to San Raffaele hospital for a few days in late August after contracting the virus.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was eventually discharged from hospital 10 days after overcoming what he considered “perhaps the most dangerous challenge of my life”.</p>
    <p>Doctors said most Italians in his condition did not survive the virus.</p>
    <p>After his discharge from hospital, Berlusconi, who had heart surgery in 2016 and uses a pacemaker, urged Italians to adhere to mask mandates, social distancing norms and frequent handwashing.</p>
    <p>However, early in April, after a series of scheduled medical check-ups, doctors decided to admit him to hospital again in order to conduct more tests due to alleged long-term effects of Covid.</p>
    <p>His hospitalisation was first announced by his lawyer during a hearing in Milan linked to the long-running “bunga bunga” sex scandal and investigation into Berlusconi’s alleged relationship with an underage girl, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/15/karima-el-mahroug-runaway-silvio-berlusconi">Karima El-Mahroug</ref>, dubbed “Ruby the heartstealer”.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors are investigating alleged payments to witnesses by Berlusconi to buy their silence over his so-called “bunga bunga” parties.</p>
    <p>According to media reports, Berlusconi is now back home in his villa in Arcore, north of Milan.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>