<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Letters: Italy gets the full Monti government of technocrats" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2011-11-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/20/italy-full-monti-technocrats" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Letters: Berlusconi only resigned because he had lost his majority in one of the two houses of parliament (the Camera)" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Germany,Europe,Italy" fingerprint="7fb842a7b5b5071d">
  <main>
    <p>Alexander Chancellor's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/17/berlusconi-provisional-support-for-successor">comments on Berlusconi</ref> (G2, 18 November) are confused and confusing. First, Berlusconi has not served three terms in office. His first "term" lasted only about eight months (May 1994-January 1995), and his third term (which started in May 2008 and has just ended) has also been (thankfully) abbreviated. Second, Chancellor writes that the Berlusconi government was brought down by "the verdict of the markets" and not by the loss of a vote of confidence in parliament. It's true that technically it wasn't a confidence vote, but Berlusconi only resigned because he had lost his majority in one of the two houses of parliament (the Camera). He would never have agreed to go otherwise.</p>
    <p>Lastly, the article argues that "it is hard to fault Berlusconi's claim that the new government has no democratic mandate". Berlusconi may have said that, but he has also voted in parliament (with the rest of his party) in favour of the Monti government. Chancellor himself admits that the survival of the Monti administration "depends on the backing of an elected parliament". Exactly. What's not democratic about that?<hi rend="#b">Franco Bianchini</hi><hi rend="#i">Leicester </hi></p>
    <p> So Italy will now be governed by an unelected elite. The PM is a former European commissioner, the minister of development and infrastructure a prominent banker. The labour minister is an academic and consultant to the World Bank. The minister of defence is an admiral. While it is great to see Berlusconi's government fall, shouldn't this have been through the democratic process? Do we now refer to a coup d'etat as "the introduction of a technocratic government"?<hi rend="#b">Paul Foley</hi><hi rend="#i">Stockport</hi></p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>