<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian president says Berlusconi's conviction must be respected" author="Lizzy Davies" date="2013-08-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/14/silvio-berlusconi-conviction-respected" hostname="theguardian.com" description="President warned it will be 'fatal' for Italy's coalition government to be plunged into crisis over the issue" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="bf84501ddbadc76f">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian president, Giorgio Napolitano, said on Tuesday night that Silvio Berlusconi's landmark conviction for tax fraud must be respected, warning that it would be "fatal" for Enrico Letta's coalition government to be plunged into crisis over the issue.</p>
    <p>Following the former prime minister's first definitive conviction on 1 August, the 88-year-old head of state has come under pressure from members of the centre-right Freedom People (PdL) party to allow their leader to continue in politics.</p>
    <p>But, breaking his silence over the issue that has exacerbated the divides in the three-month-old coalition government and called into question its very future, Napolitano presented Berlusconi with no easy way out.</p>
    <p>"Any definitive sentence, and the consequent obligation of applying it, cannot but be taken into account," he said in a statement.</p>
    <p>He said he had not received a formal request for a presidential pardon or act of clemency, and therefore could not respond to it.</p>
    <p>While his four-year jail sentence was reduced under a 2006 amnesty, Italy's longest-serving postwar prime minister still faces the prospect of serving a year under house arrest or in community service. At 76, he is deemed too old for prison.</p>
    <p>He will also be the subject of a potentially explosive vote in the upper house of parliament over whether to strip him of his senate seat and bar him from running for office for six years.</p>
    <p>The situation has enraged his loyalists, who are reportedly planning a series of barnstorming events over the coming long weekend to highlight the return of Forza Italia, Berlusconi's first political party.</p>
    <p>Napolitano, while saying he understood some of their anger, condemned any threats of retaliation against the government as unacceptable.</p>
    <p>He said his and the great majority of Italians' fundamental concern was ensuring the stability of a government capable of leading the eurozone's third-largest economy out of its longest recession since the second world war.</p>
    <p>"A crisis in a government formed with great effort little more than 100 days would … be fatal," he said, referring to the prolonged uncertainty that led to the creation of the awkward coalition. "The relapse of the country into instability and uncertainty would prevent us from seizing and consolidating the chance for an economic recovery which is at last taking shape."</p>
    <p>Amid the stern warnings, there were some crumbs of comfort for Berlusconi. Napolitano did not explicitly rule out a pardon or form of clemency, saying that such moves were in general only possible in certain circumstances and following a formal request.</p>
    <p>He also singled out the reform of the judiciary − Berlusconi's theme of the moment − as one of the key areas the government needed to tackle.</p>
    <p>The intervention seems unlikely to dampen reported plans to inject a little summertime glow into the Forza Italia rebirth. In recent days, posters advertising the return have appeared in towns and cities throughout Italy, and newspapers close to Berlusconi have reported that there are plans for several aeroplanes to fly past beaches trailing banners declaring "Forza Silvio!"</p>
    <p>Contacted on Monday, a spokeswoman for the PdL said the plan was "a possibility" but that the details remained "top secret". She added: "Berlusconi will never step back. He is a great man. The great men of history, like Napoleon, do not step back when there are attempts to eliminate them."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>