<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Eurozone hit by record unemployment as Italian politicians spar - as it happened" author="Graeme Wearden" date="2013-03-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/mar/01/eurozone-crisis-italy-grand-coalition-unemployment" hostname="theguardian.com" description="German politician suggests Italy could leave the eurozone, as Pier Luigi Bersani says he hopes to lead a 'government of change'" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,Italy,Greece,World news,Unemployment,Silvio Berlusconi,Beppe Grillo" fingerprint="3794893510a0c76f">
  <main>
    <p>After a dramatic week, Italy remains far from agreement over its next government, while the latest economic news from the eurozone and the UK has alarmed investors.</p>
    <p>Here's a round-up of today's main developments:</p>
    <p>One of the co-founders of the Five Star Movement has told The Guardian that the party, which holds the balance of power in the Italian Senate after this week's election, will not join a coalition (see 3.08pm). Gianroberto Casaleggio suggested, though, that the group could support a minority government on policies it agreed with.</p>
    <p>Fellow co-founder Beppe Grillo was more acerbic, accusing the centre-left of acting like "vulgar predators", preying on M5S's senators. He also repeated his attacks on its leader, Pier Luigi Bersani, saying he was 'out of history' (see 11.50am)</p>
    <p>For his part Bersani ruled out a deal with Silvio Berlusconi, saying a grand coalition with the centre-right was not an option. (see 8.47am).</p>
    <p>Italy's president has urged Germany to help Europe through more expansionary economic policies (see 1.42pm).</p>
    <p>Eurozone unemployment has hit a new record high of 11.9% (see 10.06am onwards)....</p>
    <p>...while the region's manufacturing sector is still shrinking, dragged down by Italy and France (see 9.32am).</p>
    <p>This pushed the euro to its lowest level of 2013 (see 12.29pm)</p>
    <p>The pound fell through the $1.50 mark against the US dollar for the first time since July 2010, after much weaker-than-expected manufacturing data. Analysts reckon sterling could slide to $1.40 (see 2.42pm).</p>
    <p>Hope you have good weekends, all. Thanks for reading and commenting, as ever. Goodnight!</p>
    <p>We have some fresh analysis of the political situation in Italy tonight, from @AlbertoNardelli.</p>
    <p>He sees three likely options:</p>
    <p>1) A Bersani minority government receives sufficient support from a majority of senators.</p>
    <p>It is fundamental to understand though that a Bersani, or any government, would need to win a confidence vote - a majority is required even to install a minority government. M5S has reiterated that it will not give any government a confidence vote, and PD rules out an alliance with the centre-right. An abstention is akin to a no-vote, and President Napolitano is unlikely to give Bersani, or anyone else, a mandate to form a government unless after consulting with parliamentary groups he believes there is a majority.</p>
    <p>2) There aren’t the numbers to form an alliance or a minority government.</p>
    <p>In this case, Napolitano would likely resign early and a Monti/technocratic government continue in the interim. The reason for this is that a president at the end of their term cannot dissolve parliament and call elections. Parliament would then need to elect a new president. The newly elected president would at that point consult with parliamentary groups, and if s/he too cannot see a feasible majority would need to dissolve parliament and call an election.</p>
    <p>The strategy of the PD seems to evolve around these two options: a minority government or an election in the short-term with Bersani once again at the helm. In taking this road, I believe Bersani is flirting with fire. The PD leader is underestimating the level of support the M5S could hit in an election held in the short-term (and the implications of this) and the reasons why the PD fell short at the polls. A majority may well emerge from a new election (especially if held under a changed voting system), but it is far from certain that it would be to PD’s liking.</p>
    <p>3) the newly elected president, in addition to exploring majorities within the current parties would likely also explore the possibilities of a caretaker government led by someone else.</p>
    <p>This option would buy time, which in practical terms means elections in a year or so, with different party leaders. A caretaker government though, like a minority government, would require a confidence vote.</p>
    <p>Alberto goes on to explain some of the key factors - including why Five Star Movement might favour a new election soon.</p>
    <p>In it, Ian explains that Beppe Grillo isn't the only man winning support from Europeans who despair about the traditional political classes - from Alexis Tsipras in Greece to Nigel Farage in the UK*, via Geert Wilders in Holland, the backlash against the status quo is gathering pace.</p>
    <p>Here's a taste:</p>
    <p>Where voters have not "kicked out the bums", the big EU rulers have acted instead, with Berlin, Paris, Brussels, and the European Central Bank in Frankfurt conspiring to bring down elected prime ministers Silvio Berlusconi in Italy and George Papandreou in Greece.</p>
    <p>The message to the Italians from the German government this week was "you may have kicked out our politicians, but you must not kick out their policies".</p>
    <p>Two academics from Rome's Luiss Guido Carli university, Roberto D'Alimonte, professor of political science, and Giuseppe Ragusa, econometrics professor, met with my colleague Phillip Inman today.</p>
    <p>They suggested a few interesting scenarios for Italy - including president Giorgio Napolitano replacing Mario Monti as technocratic prime minister, or Monti himself staying on despite being given the order of the boot by Italians. More here.</p>
    <p>Gianroberto Casaleggio (left) alongside Beppe Grillo at Movimento 5 Stelle's final political rally last month. Photograph: Giorgio Cosulich/Getty Images Photograph: Giorgio Cosulich/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Gianroberto Casaleggio, joint founder of the Italian Five Star Movement, has given an exclusive interview to the Guardian in which he states there is no chance of the group joining the country's next government.</p>
    <p>But... speaking to John Hooper, our Southern Europe editor, Casaleggio also suggests that the party could provide limited support for a minority government, on policies which M5S agreed with.</p>
    <p>If a government is put together, formed by other parties, the Five Star Movement will vote for everything that forms an integral part of its programme.</p>
    <p>Significantly, Casaleggio also says the party will remain on the sidelines as president Napolitano tries to build a coalition over the coming days. That, John says, is a new, tougher line from M5S.</p>
    <p>Definitely worth a read, as Casaleggio opens up about the party's long-term ambitions, and about how digital democracy will fundamentally reshape politics around the globe.</p>
    <p>What is happening in Italy is just the beginning of a much more radical change. It's a change that is going to touch all democracies.</p>
    <p>The pound just slipped below the $1.50 mark for the first time since early July 2010, a fall of 1.5 cents against the US dollar today.</p>
    <p>Sterling has been suffering since this morning's weak manufacturing data was released, fueling fears of a triple-dip recession.</p>
    <p>Kit Juckes of Societe Generale reckons the pound could soon be as low as $1.40.</p>
    <p>Since, as I've argued plenty of times before, a weaker pound won't really help UK exports (of planes, lawyers and investment bankers) as much as they hurt consumes' real incomes, the UK's de facto weak pound policy won't work well, so will continue for a long time.</p>
    <p>Italian president Giorgio Napolitano laying a wreath for the Victims of War and Tyranny, at the Neue Wache memorial in Berlin. Photograph: Reynaldo C. Paganelli/Demotix/Corbis Photograph: Reynaldo C. Paganelli/ Reynaldo C. Paganelli/Demotix/Corbis</p>
    <p>Italy's president has challenged the German government to do more to help the eurozone out of its economic crisis, on the final day of his trip to Germany.</p>
    <p>President Giorgio Napolitano told an audience in Berlin that Germany had shown leadership in the crisis. However, he then appeared to chide its government for not stimulating its domestic economy more vigorously to help its neighbours:</p>
    <p>Napolitano said:</p>
    <p>I don't want to simplify the problem, but it would be reasonable to expect an expansive impulse from Germany to contribute to a real, not just proclaimed, recovery in growth and employment in Europe.</p>
    <p>(quote via Reuters).</p>
    <p>Today's manufacturing data showed that Germany's factories are enjoying rising output, while most other countries are still suffering the impact of the euro recession.</p>
    <p>The Italian president also dampened speculation that the election could be rerun soon, telling reporters that "I'm not interested in a new vote", and that his successor (Napolitano's term ends in May) is unlikely to want more instability either.</p>
    <p>Napolitano's trip had already been marred by the diplomatic spat after the SPD's candidate for the chancellorship, Peer Steinbrück, over his comment that two clowns had won the election.</p>
    <p>Italy has missed its deficit reduction target for 2012 - but the good news is that it didn't exceed the 3% target limit set by the European Commission.</p>
    <p>Italy's deficit came in at 3.0%, rather higher than Mario Monti's most recent forecast of 2.6%. But it still low enough for the country to extract itself from the EC's 'excessive deficit' procedure.</p>
    <p>This pushed the total national debt to a new record high of 127% of GDP.</p>
    <p>The euro has fallen to its lowest level of 2013, following the latest record unemployment levels and weak manufacturing data.</p>
    <p>The euro just dropped through the $1.30 mark for the first time since last December, to a low of $1.2987.</p>
    <p>Traders are blaming fresh fears over the health of Europe's economy, with eurozone jobless rate now at 11.9% (see 10.06am) and factory output falling sharply in Italy and France (see 9.32am)</p>
    <p>The ongoing uncertainty over Italy, following Beppe Grillo's latest attack on the centre-left (see 11.50am), isn't helping the euro either.</p>
    <p>Economist Megan Greene suggests that the solution to the deadlock in Italy could be for Bersani to step down and be replaced by Matteo Renzi, who was defeated for the leadership of the centre-left late last year.</p>
    <p>What abotu a Renzi-led one? MT @yannikouts: Beppe Grillo says he is not available to back a Bersani-led government. /via @cvecchiofx</p>
    <p>Renzi, mayor of Florence, had pledged to be loyal to Bersani - but Beppe Grillo's repeated personal attacks on the Democratic Party leader are adding to the pressure for a change.</p>
    <p>Back to Italy, and Beppe Grillo has just tried to sink Pier Luigi Bersani's efforts to become the prime minister of a minority government.</p>
    <p>In a new blog post (see it here), Grillo accused Bersani and his Democratic Party of acting like "vulgar predators" by trying to persuade some his Five Star Movement's new senators to work with him.</p>
    <p>Grillo pointed out that everyone who stood as a M5S candidate had agreed not to "associate with other parties or coalitions or groups except for voting on shared points".</p>
    <p>Grillo declared that:</p>
    <p>M5S, its elected officials, its activists, its voters are not for sale.</p>
    <p>and added that Bersani does not realise he is "out of history".</p>
    <p>This looks like a blow to Bersani's hopes of persuading president Napolitano that he can build a consensus with M5S (see 8.47am).</p>
    <p>Inflation in the eurozone has fallen below the 2% mark, giving the European Central Bank some leeway to cut interest rates.</p>
    <p>The consumer prices index dropped to 1.8% in February, from 2.0% in January. The ECB's goal is to have the cost of living rising by a little below 2% per year - so there's now more leeway for a rate cut...</p>
    <p>Britain's manufacturing sector has also suffered a grim February, with Markit reporting the first contraction since last November.</p>
    <p>The UK manufacturing PMI skittered down to 47.9, from 50.5 in January. Economists had expected a rise to 51, and the pound had swiftly shed one cent against the US dollar, to $1.505.</p>
    <p>Markit warned that the manufacturing sector will be 'a drag on economic growth' this quarter, unless we see a big recovery in March. The triple-dip recession remains a risk.</p>
    <p>The slump in Italian and French manufacturing output reported this morning could show the region will continue to suffer recession this quarter.</p>
    <p>The eurozone manufacturing PMI for February, which measures activity across the region, crept up to 47.9 vs 47.8 in January. That means it still shrank, despite Germany hitting growth again.</p>
    <p>Howard Archer of IHS Global Insight commented:</p>
    <p>While Eurozone economic activity appears to have bottomed out around last October, it looks highly possible that the single currency area will still suffer a fourth successive quarter of contraction in the first quarter of 2013.</p>
    <p>When we say 'record high' - the Italian jobless data goes back to 1992, so this is the worst unemployment situation in at least 21 years. Certainly since the euro was created.</p>
    <p>And another blow for Italy: its jobless rate has jumped to a new record high.</p>
    <p>Unemployment across Italy is now running at 11.7% of the population, up from 11.3% in January. The youth unemployment rate also rose to a new record high, with 38.7% of young people out of work.</p>
    <p>Rising unemployment was a big factor in the Italian election, particularly among parties arguing against Mario Monti's economic reforms. This will surely bolster their argument.</p>
    <p>Economic data just released shows that the Italian economy is in a bad way - manufacturing activity has fallen for the 19th month in a row, and by more than expected.</p>
    <p>The monthly PMI survey came in at a mere 45.8 for February, down 47.8 in January -- which means the country's manufacturing sector is shrinking at a faster pace [any number below 50 means contraction].</p>
    <p>Other European economies are also reporting PMI data - and it shows that Germany continues to outperform weaker members of the eurozone.</p>
    <p>German manufacturing PMI rose to 50.3, from 49.8 in January - meaning it returned to growth.</p>
    <p>But France manufacturing sector is still shrinking, but at a slower pace (with a PMI of 43.9, up from 42.9 in January).</p>
    <p>Italy remains in a state of political flux this morning. Pier Luigi Bersani, the centre-left leader whose hopes of winning this week's general election were dashed, has this morning ruled out a Grand Coalition with the centre-right.</p>
    <p>In an interview with the La Repubblica newspaper, Bersani insisted that he can become Italy's next leader without getting into bed with Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>He declared:</p>
    <p>I want to spell it out clearly: the idea of a grand coalition does not exist and will never exist.</p>
    <p>Instead, Bersani hopes to persuade Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, that he could govern without a majority in the Senate (having narrowly won control of the lower house). He has drawn up a seven or eight-point plan to present to Napolitano next Wednesday.</p>
    <p>Asked if his goal was to be prime minister in a minority government, Bersani said:</p>
    <p>Call it what you want: a minority government, a government of purpose, I do not care.</p>
    <p>I call it a government of change, which I assume the responsibility of guiding.</p>
    <p>With Beppe Grillo ( refusing to back Bersani in a vote of confidence, a deal with Berlusconi was the only way the centre-left could get a majority in the Senate.</p>
    <p>Some political analysts have questioned whether Napolitano would agree to a minority government, given the implicit instability. We'll find out next week....</p>
    <p>In the meantime, the rest of Europe watches the events in Italy with interest. And one German politician has raised the possibility of the country abandoning the euro.</p>
    <p>Klaus-Peter Willsch, a member of Angela Merkel's CDU party, has even declared that Italy should leave the eurozone, rather than hold fresh elections, if a majority of the population will not support the measures needed to support the eurozone.</p>
    <p>A monetary union will survive only if it benefits all of its members.</p>
    <p>It's a little early to be discussing Italy's exit from the single currency, I'd suggest - but Willsch's comments do show how much concern Italy has created.</p>
    <p>As usual we'll be tracking the action through the day....</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>