<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi vows to resign as Italy's prime minister" author="John Hooper; Larry Elliott; Patrick Wintour" date="2011-11-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-to-resign-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Media tycoon's reign as Italy's longest-serving prime minister nears end after he loses majority in lower house of parliament" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Business,Eurozone crisis" fingerprint="7f8ec93d98a3cf74">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has pledged to resign as Italy's prime minister in a long-delayed move that doomed his third government and appeared to foreshadow the end of the media tycoon's eventful and frequently scandalous 17-year career in politics.</p>
    <p>But opposition leaders were swift to warn that Berlusconi could be plotting to re-emerge. "[He] has not disappeared. He has resigned," said Pierluigi Bersani, leader of Italy's biggest opposition group, the Democratic party (PD). Antonio Di Pietro, of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Principles party, claimed Berlusconi was "taking another month to try to buy a few [parliamentarians]".</p>
    <p>The PD called for the head of state, President Giorgio Napolitano, to use his constitutional powers to set up a transitional government. But Berlusconi told one of his three television channels: "It is absolutely unthinkable in a democracy for the parties that lost the election to assume governmental responsibilities."</p>
    <p>His control of parliament had become a crucial element in the eurozone's raging debt crisis as investors in Italy's debt fretted over the country's ability to implement the austerity measures needed to cut its deficit.</p>
    <p>A statement from the president's office said Berlusconi had signalled "his awareness of the implications of the vote in the chamber [of deputies]". It said he would surrender his government mandate following the approval of the austerity measures.</p>
    <p>These are due to go to the upper house, the senate, on Wednesday. Political sources said the package could take between 10 and 15 days to clear the legislature.</p>
    <p>Earlier, Umberto Bossi, leader of the Northern League, the junior partner in Berlusconi's rightwing coalition, had signalled its time was up. He told reporters outside parliament: "We asked the prime minister to step aside."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi returned to office in 2008, but his third term as premier has been rocked by sexual and financial scandals.</p>
    <p>Earlier this year, he suffered the ignominy of being put on trial, accused of paying an underage prostitute and taking advantage of his position to cover up the alleged offence. But despite falling popularity ratings and a rebellion by members of his party, he succeeded in clinging to power through a succession of cliff-hanging confidence votes in parliament.</p>
    <p>Financial markets in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> were closed when Berlusconi said he intended to quit, but on Wall Street shares rose after the announcement. Earlier, the interest rate on 10-year Italian bonds had edged closer to the danger level of 7% as uncertainty about Berlusconi's political future rattled investors.</p>
    <p>Analysts said the situation in Italy was rapidly approaching the critical levels seen in Greece, Ireland and Portugal just before they were forced to seek help from the European Union and the International Monetary Fund. They said yields on Italy's debt were at their highest since the creation of the euro, despite intervention in the markets to buy the bonds of the single currency's third biggest economy.</p>
    <p>The leading UK employers' organisation, the CBI, warned that Europe's sovereign debt crisis was having a marked impact on Britain's growth prospects. The CBI called on the government to use this month's autumn statement to remove obstacles to growth, as the country's growth forecast for 2011 was cut from 1.3% to 0.9%, and that for 2012 was reduced from 2.2% to 1.2%.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, the former Labour chancellor Alistair Darling said the situation facing Europe was far worse than the banking crisis of 2008, and if it was not sorted out by Christmas the eurozone would break up. "I despair of the way in which EU leaders are constantly behind events," he told the Guardian. "I do not think enough people realise how serious this crisis is, and how hard it is going to hit us."</p>
    <p>In Tuesday's vote to approve last year's public accounts, Berlusconi's rightwing coalition won the support of only 308 of the 630 members of the chamber.</p>
    <p>Looking uncharacteristically glum, the prime minister walked from the floor of the house on his way to a crisis meeting with senior members of his own party and the Northern League. After it ended, he headed for the Quirinale palace, the residence of the head of state.</p>
    <p>He and Bossi will be hoping to persuade the president to call new elections in which Berlusconi could again play a role. And Bossi suggested that, if the country did not go back to the polls, Berlusconi's protege, Angelino Alfano, could take over as prime minister in a new rightwing administration.</p>
    <p>Though the markets reacted with delight on Monday when it began to look like the government would fall, attention has since shifted to the prospect of a protracted election campaign, or lengthy negotiations to form a new coalition.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>