<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's regret at Nazi jibe defuses diplomatic stand-off" author="Ian Black; Sophie Arie" date="2003-07-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jul/04/pressandpublishing.media1" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's billionaire prime minister Silvio Berlusconi last night expressed regret for his Nazi jibe against a German MEP. By Sophie Arie in Rome and Ian Black in Brussels." categories="World news" tags="World news,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,Italy,Germany,European Union,Television industry,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="9fae8a2ebd8efe0c">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's billionaire prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> last night expressed regret for his Nazi jibe against a German MEP, in a bid to end a serious diplomatic stand-off between the two countries just as Italy takes over the European Union presidency.</p>
    <p>The German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, who had demanded a full and formal apology, told a news conference in Berlin: "He expressed regret for the choice of this expression and comparison. I explained to him that as far as I am concerned this ends the affair."</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's comments in the European parliament in Strasbourg on Wednesday were "inappropriate and completely unacceptable", Mr Schröder added.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's office in Rome issued a statement confirming that the prime minister had expressed regret for the misunderstanding over his comments, but also insisting the Italian prime minister had been offended.</p>
    <p>"During a telephone conversation with the German chancellor, the prime minister told him about the serious affront that he faced in the European parliament yesterday," the Italian statement said.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's jibe followed criticism on Wednesday from a German MEP, Martin Schulz, over the Italian prime minister's use of an immunity law to sidestep bribery charges. The Italian leader riposted: "Mr Schulz, I know there is a producer in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> who is making a film on Nazi concentration camps. I will suggest you for the role of commandant. You'd be perfect."</p>
    <p>"I should have bitten my tongue," Mr Berlusconi was reported saying by Italian news agency Adnkronos.</p>
    <p>"It is clear to everyone that a good bit of provocation was organised to damage me," the prime minister said. "Unfortunately I fell for it."</p>
    <p>Enrico Boselli, the leader of the Social Democrats of Italy party, said: "We hope, at least, that this episode will serve as a lesson [for Mr Berlusconi] and that next time, provocation or not, he will count to ten before answering."</p>
    <p>"Mr Berlusconi has caused a major crisis unlike any other in EU history," said Enrique Baron, president of the socialist group in the 626-member European parliament.</p>
    <p>Mr Schröder said he told Mr Berlusconi it was in Europe's interest that the Italian presidency of the EU, which began on Tuesday, "should now be a success" - especially because European leaders faced "a very important decision" on a European constitution at the end of the year.</p>
    <p>Hans-Gert Pöttering, chairman of the European People's party, the dominant group in parliament, had also asked Mr Schulz to apologise for his "offending remarks."</p>
    <p>Romano Prodi, the Italian president of the European commission, meeting the prime minister in Rome today, declined to comment but he was said to be mortified by the incident.</p>
    <p>In Italy, state television's evening news programme TG1 dubbed over the prime minister's voice as he delivered his offending "joke". "TG1 shuts its ears and hides European gaffe," said the left-leaning daily Repubblica. The chiefs of the three state television channels, which are all indirectly controlled by Mr Berlusconi, were called for questioning next week by a parliamentary broadcasting commission.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>