<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi promises reforms to tackle Italy's debt crisis" author="John Hooper" date="2011-10-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/27/berlusconi-reforms-italy-debt-crisis" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister plans public asset sales and pension reforms – but fails to convince coalition partners and opposition" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Eurozone crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,European banks,Business,Europe,World news" fingerprint="c78d80bd99a08e4f">
  <main>
    <p>The keenly awaited letter from Silvio Berlusconi's government, intended to convince the markets of Italy's ability to weather the eurozone debt crisis, has been hailed by the European Central Bank's president designate, Mario Draghi, as a blueprint for courageous reforms.</p>
    <p>Italian opposition leaders, however, described it as a catalogue of pious intentions.</p>
    <p>The letter included previously unreported plans for a programme of public asset sales to bring in €15bn (£13bn) over three years, and a change to employment laws that would make it easier for bosses to reduce their workforce in a downturn. As widely forecast, the letter contained a watered-down pension reform.</p>
    <p>Several of the promised initiatives were accompanied by target dates. With Berlusconi's government hanging by a thread though, it was far from certain the government would be able to steer the proposed changes through parliament.</p>
    <p>The text of the letter was released as Italy's prime minister met the head of European commission, José Manuel Barroso, and the European council president, Herman Van Rompuy, before the debt crisis summit. With Italy moving to centre-stage in the crisis, tensions were running high and spilled over into a near-fight in the Italian parliament when two members had to be separated by attendants.</p>
    <p>Pier Ferdinando Casini, the leader of the Union of Christian Democrats, which once formed part of Berlusconi's governing alliance, called the government's letter a "book of dreams". He said he agreed with many of the measures it outlined, but added: "Given the state of the governing majority and the credibility of the government, they remain [just] good intentions."</p>
    <p>Per Luigi Bersani, the leader of Italy's main opposition group, the Democratic party, dismissed the letter as containing nothing serious. Susanna Camusso, head of Italy's biggest trade union federation, the CGIL, said she would suggest other labour organisations join a "united mobilisation" against the proposed employment law reform.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi had hoped to convince the Northern League, the junior partner in his rightwing coalition, of the need for a radical change in the pension system. The most the party leader Umberto Bossi would accept, however, was a slight modification to existing plans to raise the normal retirement age by 2026.</p>
    <p>The letter committed the government to raising the retirement age from 65 to 67. According to some accounts, denied by the Northern League, Bossi's consent was made on the condition that the prime minister stood down in January 2012 to force a snap election.</p>
    <p>It had been widely speculated in Italy that Berlusconi might step aside in the new year. La Repubblica, however, reported that the 75-year-old prime minister would again stand as the candidate of the right as part of "secret pact".</p>
    <p>Such a move would dash the hopes of many in the markets who had been assuming Berlusconi would be replaced by a technocrat who would introduce painful but necessary reforms without worrying about the political cost.</p>
    <p>Bossi refused to endorse a plan to abolish Italy's time-in-work pension entitlements, which allow for retirement before the standard pensionable age – the sticking point behind the brawl in parliament.</p>
    <p>In a television discussion on Tuesday night, the speaker Gianfranco Fini reminded viewers that Bossi's wife retired at 39. The scuffle came after a supporter of the speaker defended his remarks.</p>
    <p>The letter released on Wednesday included plans for liberalising the economy to stimulate growth – a key requirement if Italy is to fulfil its plans for reducing its government deficit and trimming its public debts.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>