<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Five-star Movement makes stunning debut in Italian elections" author="John Hooper" date="2010-03-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/mar/30/italian-elections-five-star-movement" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Party founded by comedian and blogger Beppe Grillo wins 3.5% of vote in five regions where it stood" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Beppe Grillo,Five Star Movement" fingerprint="505b1871922bd5cf">
  <main>
    <p>A new party founded by the political comedian and blogger <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/beppe-grillo">Beppe Grillo</ref> has made a stunning debut in Italy's regional elections.</p>
    <p>Without public funding and largely ignored by the media, the Five-star Movement won half a million votes with a campaign that mixed environmentalism, denunciation of corruption, and contempt for mainstream political leaders including the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. In the five regions where it stood the party's candidates took 3.5% of the vote.</p>
    <p>Grillo's campaign relied on his <ref target="http://www.beppegrillo.it/">blog</ref>, some slickly-produced <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XgMPdGK-Gw">YouTube videos</ref>, and plenty of old-fashioned tub-thumping in city squares. His party appeared to have succeeded in winning over many young Italians alienated by Berlusconi and the main opposition group, the Democratic Party (PD).</p>
    <p>One visitor to his website from Lazio, the region around Rome, summed up the Movement's appeal with a posting that said: "If you had run [here], I would certainly not have abstained."</p>
    <p>Grillo responded with a message saying: "Thanks, kids. This is just the beginning of a journey."</p>
    <p>Three of the five regions in which his party ran were in the north of the country – the area where the PD had the most disappointing results. But the Five-star Movement's best showing was in Emilia-Romagna, traditionally a stronghold of the left, where it picked up 7% of the votes and two seats in the 50-member regional assembly.</p>
    <p>It took another two seats in Piedmont where the PD's leader, Pierluigi Bersani, accused Grillo of letting in the right. But Grillo said: "If the centre-left loses, it's nothing to do with us."</p>
    <p>The 61-year-old accountant turned comedian has been likened to Michael Moore. He has a similarly raucous style but, unlike the American film-maker, has often seemed ready to vault the barrier that separates satire and commentary from politics itself. He founded the Five-star Movement last October after being prevented from running in primary elections for the leadership of the PD.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>