<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's wake up call to voters angers left" author="John Hooper" date="2004-06-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jun/12/italy.elections2004" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian left is crying foul after the office of the prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, sent 56m text messages to mobile telephones urging their owners to turn out to vote in tomorrow's European and local elections." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Elections 2004,Politics,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="e696813e9c23966f">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian left is crying foul after the office of the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, sent 56m text messages to mobile telephones urging their owners to turn out to vote in tomorrow's European and local elections.</p>
    <p>The ballot has assumed a much greater importance in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> than in most other EU nations, and a high turnout traditionally favours parties of the right-wing ruling coalition, including that of Mr Berlusconi, Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>But last night some opposition politicians were comforting themselves with speculation about a possible boomerang effect.</p>
    <p>Many of the messages arrived in the night, activating the alarms of hundreds of thousands of mobiles and waking their owners. More than 90% of Italians own a mobile phone.</p>
    <p>The left claimed that the mass texting was a breach of Italy's electoral rules and a violation of its privacy laws.</p>
    <p>"Clearly, the ownership of three television channels and political control of the RAI [Italy's public broadcasting network] are no longer enough for [Mr Berlusconi]," joked one centre-left MP, Roberto Giachetti.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, speaking from the US where he is attending the G8 summit, said: "We noted not all Italians were aware of the hours within which they could exercise their right to vote.</p>
    <p>"This initiative was needed to inform the Italian people and make life easier for them."</p>
    <p>Italian law authorises the government to carry out mass texting "in cases of disaster or natural calamities" and "for reasons of public order or public health and hygiene".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's supporters argued that a decree authorising the move, signed by the interior minister, Giuseppe Pisanu, on Thursday, complied with the law because the messages would ensure a steadier flow of voters and thus avert any threat to public order.</p>
    <p>Opposition representatives scoffed at this explanation. Fabrizio Morri of the centre-left said it would cost the taxpayer more that €5m (almost £3.5m) - a figure that was, in turn, derided by government supporters.</p>
    <p>A consumers' organisation in the northern city of Bologna, a traditional bastion of the left, said that it had begun legal proceedings against the mobile operator Telecom Italia Mobile for having released its subscribers' numbers to the government.</p>
    <p>Sunday's vote is seen as a crucial test for Mr Berlusconi's most dangerous rival, Romano Prodi, the EU commission president who defeated him in 1996. Mr Prodi is not running, but has openly backed a broad alliance of the left.</p>
    <p>Political scientists agree the right-wing vote in Italy is less loyal than support for the left, partly because the right-wing parties have shallow roots.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's party was created just 10 years ago. His potential supporters also include more second-home owners and, on average, four million Italians leave their normal homes, and their constituencies, at the weekend.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>