<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi outraged by Economist" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2003-08-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/aug/02/pressandpublishing.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, threatened last night to sue the Economist magazine over articles in its latest edition which accuse him of abuse of power to thwart justice and further his own business interests." categories="Media" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,The Economist,Europe" fingerprint="3ece4bad9386d348">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, threatened last night to sue the Economist magazine over articles in its latest edition which accuse him of abuse of power to thwart justice and further his own business interests.</p>
    <p>Lawyers from Mr Berlusconi's Fininvest holding company were poring over a dossier published by the weekly, which accused the Italian leader of using his political power to avoid justice and enact laws favourable to his own media empire.</p>
    <p>Fininvest said it was the target of a "hostile campaign" aimed at discrediting the Italian government and staining the reputation of "one of the most experienced and brilliant businessmen of the past quarter of a century".</p>
    <p>A statement went on: "It's obvious there will be a judicial issue over this despicable self-styled journalistic investigation."</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is already suing the Economist over an article published two years ago that asserted he was unfit to govern <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister has since appeared in court to defend himself from allegations of bribing judges in the 80s. But the case was suspended after Italy's parliament, where Mr Berlusconi's allies have a solid majority, passed a law in June giving the prime minister immunity during his time in office.</p>
    <p>The Economist sent Mr Berlusconi an "open letter" urging him to reply to detailed questions and documentary evidence concerning the judge-bribing case against him.</p>
    <p>It said Mr Berlusconi was "an outrage against the Italian people and their judicial system" and was Europe's "most extreme case of the abuse by a capitalist of the democracy within which he lives and operates".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>