<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's old guard" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2006-04-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/news/blog/2006/apr/12/post120" hostname="theguardian.com" description="As Silvio Berlusconi, 69, and Romano Prodi, a mere 66, squabble over victory in the general election, MPs have begun calling on President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi to stay on and sort out the mess - at the age of 85." categories="News" tags="World news,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="4b12c0ddf6a8aaaf">
  <main>
    <p><lb/> President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi casting <lb/> his vote in the Italian elections. <lb/> Photograph: Enrico Oliverio/APIn modern British politics, youth is all. Hence <ref target="http://politics.theguardian.com/person/0,,-6188,00.html">David Cameron's</ref> repeated assertions of his thirtysomething vitality. In Italy, it seems, they do things differently, <hi rend="#i">writes Peter Walker</hi>.</p>
    <p>As Silvio Berlusconi, 69, and Romano Prodi, a mere 66, squabble over victory in the general election, MPs have begun calling on President <ref target="http://www.quirinale.it/">Carlo Azeglio Ciampi</ref> to stay on for another seven-year term and sort out the mess - at the age of 85.</p>
    <p>Mr Ciampi, a former head of the <ref target="http://www.bancaditalia.it/rootcollection;internal&amp;action=_setlanguage.action?LANGUAGE=en">Italian central bank</ref>, is due to step down from the largely ceremonial presidency next month, and is reportedly happy to leave the tricky business of inviting one side or another to form a government to his successor.</p>
    <p>But his preparations for a well-earned retirement are under threat. Politicians from left and right say that Mr Ciampi, age notwithstanding, is the ideal candidate to broker a deal between the warring parties. "It would be a very sensible move," according to <ref target="http://ansa.it/main/notizie/awnplus/english/news/2006-04-11_11110438.html">Alfonso Pecoraro Scanio</ref>, head of Italy's Green party, which is a member of Mr Prodi's centre-left coalition.</p>
    <p>Sensible perhaps for Italian politics - Mr Ciampi is a hugely respected figure who followed his 14 years at the helm of the central bank with a short spell as interim prime minister, with other posts including three years as treasury minister, some of that while Mr Prodi was prime minister.</p>
    <p>Mr Ciampi's cross-party appeal meant that in May 1999, MPs took just one vote to make him president. The previous presidential election in 1992 took 10 days and 16 ballots.</p>
    <p>But is a man who will turn 92 before he has completed a second full term up to it? More to the point, at this stage of life, wouldn't he rather be doing something else? Thus far Mr Ciampi appears less than keen. On a visit to Germany last month, he referred pointedly, and perhaps with relief, to his "final state visit".</p>
    <p>Very old politicians are not unknown, but they tend to be life-long devotees of the pursuit. The best-known example is Strom Thurmond, who spent 49 years in the US Senate (despite a somewhat distasteful early career as an avowed segregationist) before bowing out in 2003, shortly after his 100th birthday.</p>
    <p>The US Senate is still home to <ref target="http://byrd.senate.gov/">Robert C Byrd</ref>, a 53-year veteran of the chamber who turned 88 last November. Curiously enough, he also has a dubious past, spending some time in his 20s as a member of the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
    <p>Mr Ciampi has fewer political skeletons in his closet. After finishing his literature degree, he spent two years in the Italian military, but then escaped to join the anti-fascist resistance.</p>
    <p>Britain has its own share of veterans, led in the current House of Commons by <ref target="http://politics.theguardian.com/person/0,,-2893,00.html">Piara Khabra</ref>, Labour's 81-year-old member for Ealing South. Then of course there was Sir Edward Heath, who finally bowed out of parliament in 2001, just before his 85th birthday. By that stage of his career Sir Edward was almost as much of an impartial figure as Mr Ciampi - in this case because he seemed to dislike everyone more or less equally.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>