<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: a timeline" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2011-11-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/13/silvio-berlusconi-timeline" hostname="theguardian.com" description="From selling vacuum cleaners and singing on cruise liners to election victories, the rise and fall of the Italian politician" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="2e2cc24b96b7c755">
  <main>
    <p><hi rend="#b"> 29 September 1936</hi><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is born in Milan. The young man begins his career by selling vacuum cleaners and builds a reputation as a singer in nightclubs and on cruise liners.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1961</hi> Graduates with a law degree from the University of Milan and sets up Edilnord, a construction company, establishing himself as a residential housing developer around his native Milan.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1965 </hi>Marries Carla Elvira Dall'Oglio. The couple have two children, but divorce in 1985.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1971</hi> Launches local cable-television company Telemilano, which grows into Italy's biggest media empire, Mediaset. Through his holding company Fininvest, Berlusconi also owns football club AC Milan, Italy's largest publishing house, Mondadori, and newspaper <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi>, among other holdings.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1990 </hi>Marries Veronica Lario 10 years after seeing her for the first time, performing topless in a play. They have three children.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1993</hi> Founds his own political party, Forza Italia - Go Italy - named after a chant used by AC Milan fans.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">March 1994</hi> Wins first of three election victories and forms a coalition with the rightwing National Alliance and Northern League. The coalition crumbles after seven months.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">April 1996 </hi>Loses first of two elections to Romano Prodi.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">May 2001 </hi>Returns to power. His government goes on to be the longest-serving in Italy since the second world war.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">August 2004 </hi> Hosts Tony and Cherie Blair at his Sardinian hideaway.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">April 2006 </hi>Declares himself "the Jesus Christ of politics" on the campaign trail, but loses again to Prodi.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">July 2006 </hi>Ordered to stand trial for alleged fraud, false accounting, embezzlement and tax fraud. A Milan court refuses to indict the prime minister in 2011, but his eldest son, Pier Silvio Berlusconi the Mediaset chairman, Fedele Confalonieri, and nine other defendants will appear in court.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">May 2008</hi> Elected prime minister for the third time. Faces 50 votes of confidence over the next three years.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">May 2009</hi> Lario confirms she will file for divorce. She is reported to have said she could not be with a man who "consorted with minors" after Berlusconi attends Noemi Letizia's 18th birthday party.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">October 2009 </hi>Patrizia D'Addario gives a TV interview claiming Berlusconi slept with her knowing she was a prostitute. Months of lurid allegations of Berlusconi-hosted "bunga-bunga" sex parties follow.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">December 2009</hi> Is hit in the face with an alabaster statuette of Milan cathedral during a political rally.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">February 2011</hi> Judge orders Berlusconi to stand trial on charges of paying for sex with underage alleged prostitute Karima "Ruby" El Mahroug, a charge they both deny. He is also accused of abuse of office after it emerges he intervened in 2010 to have Ruby released from a police station where she was being held for theft.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">12 November 2011</hi> Four days after losing his parliamentary majority and saying he will resign as prime minister, Berlusconi steps down. He faces three ongoing trials.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>