<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi keeps his promise to the earthquake victims of L'Aquila" author="John Hooper" date="2009-11-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/27/italy-earthquake-berlusconi-promise-tents" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Last tent to be struck tomorrow but natural disaster is still shattering lives in rubble-strewn city" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Natural disasters and extreme weather,World news,Europe,Earthquakes" fingerprint="da00950fb6f145fd">
  <main>
    <p>When <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> returns to L'Aquila tomorrow for the removal of the last of the tents put up to house the victims of the earthquake that struck the city on 6 April, he can expect a hero's welcome.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister may be under pressure over his private life and his attacks on the judges trying him for corruption. But, though his administration is strapped for cash, he has fulfilled a promise to provide decent housing for the highest-priority cases before the winter.</p>
    <p>In a society where cynicism about the state is ingrained, and where the victims of natural disasters have often been ignored, if not exploited, that is a novelty. It helps explain why, despite scandal and controversy, almost 50% of voters continue to back him.</p>
    <p>Nearly eight months after the disaster, though, much remains to be done and questions remain about what, if any, future Berlusconi's government has in mind for one of Italy's loveliest cities.</p>
    <p>More than a third of the 60,000 people made homeless are still living in hotels. Another 10,000-12,000 are funding their own accommodation. And while the earthquake has ceased to destroy buildings, it continues to shatter lives.</p>
    <p>Francesca Luzi, a call centre worker, said she was "the complete earthquake victim … I've lost my job and my house."</p>
    <p>The US multinational that ran the call centre closed it down. And, a few days ago, Luzi and her husband learned their block of flats in the centre of L'Aquila could not be saved. Yet she considers herself lucky. They and their two children recently moved in to one of the 5,000-odd timber-built flats the government has built in little settlements dotted across the countryside. "Not bad, eh?" said Luzi, waving a hand over the parquet flooring, new washing machine, dishwasher and refrigerator in the kitchen-diner of the two-bedroom flat. The largesse of a government led by a media tycoon even runs to free flatscreen TVs.</p>
    <p>Through the double-glazed windows, the snow-capped Apennines were disappearing into the winter gloom. Earthmovers crawled across an expanse of churned mud soon to be a lawn and a playground.</p>
    <p>"So what is all this telling us?" asked Luzi, suddenly serious. "Maybe that we're going to be here for another 10 years."</p>
    <p>"What is lacking is an overall plan for the relaunching of the city," said Eugenio Carlomagno, the principal of L'Aquila's fine arts academy and a member of the city centre residents' committee.</p>
    <p>On the outskirts, buildings are being repaired: some offices and factories are working again, and some shops have reopened. But much of the centre remains closed. Until 6 April L'Aquila was Italy's Bath, its stately 18th century architecture a reminder that the city was largely rebuilt after the last great earthquake in 1703. Today the prime demand of the residents' committee is for the removal of rubble from the streets.</p>
    <p>Officials have begun securing and restoring 1,200 buildings with preservation orders. That leaves several thousand others, many damaged beyond repair.</p>
    <p>"[The authorities] need to be clear about who can go back and who can't," said Carlomagno. "This is politically the most sensitive aspect, but it needs to be tackled so we can move forward."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>