<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Football quiz: Sepp Blatter or Silvio Berlusconi?" author="Tom Bryant" date="2014-11-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/quiz/2014/nov/16/football-quiz-sepp-blatter-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Can you tell the difference between quotes from the head of Fifa and the Italian politician?" categories="Global" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Sepp Blatter,Football,Sport" fingerprint="cb545b86378e586e">
  <main>
    <p>This article is more than 10 years oldFootball quiz: Sepp Blatter or Silvio Berlusconi?This article is more than 10 years oldWho said it – the head of Fifa or the Italian politician? Said &amp; Done: Fifa's 'robust' process1."We have a responsibility to act according to the good governance principles of transparency and zero tolerance towards any wrongdoings."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal2."There is no one on the world stage who can compete with me."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal3."I would say [gay people] should refrain from any sexual activities."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal4."[The pope] asked me to give hope to the poor … We cannot do everything, but we will do what we can."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal5.“We have seen what the British said … There’s a great deal of discrimination and racism, and this hurts me. It really makes me sad.”Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal6."It's better to like beautiful girls than to be gay." Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal7."People criticised us for years … [But now] I am very happy that we have one full [female] member and co-opted another two. We call them ladies."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal8."I don't need to go into office for the power. I have houses all over the world, stupendous boats... beautiful airplanes, a beautiful wife, a beautiful family... I am making a sacrifice." Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal9."Let's get women to play in different and more feminine garb than the men, in tighter shorts for example." Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal10."My grandmother always said a clock rings ding and dong, not ding-ding-ding. You have to listen to ding and to dong, and for now I only hear ding."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal11."In my opinion, and not only mine, I am the best leader we can find today."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal12."Women are lining up to marry me. Legend has it, I know how to do it." Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal13."Those who have more should share with those who have less. For this is [our] principle."Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal14."Crisis, what is a crisis … we are not in a crisis we are only in some difficulties and these will be solved inside our family.”Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiReveal15."There are not many names the media haven't thrown at me in the last few years. I would be lying to you if I said it did not hurt. You ask yourself: 'What have I done?'"Sepp BlatterSilvio BerlusconiRevealExplore more on these topicsSilvio BerlusconiSepp BlatterquizzesShareReuse this content</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>