<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian judge backs 'buffoon' attack on Berlusconi" author="John Hooper" date="2006-06-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jun/09/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's highest appeals court has ruled that calling the former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi a &quot;buffoon&quot; can be actively useful for society." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3b4a8208d3e7c35f">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's highest appeals court has ruled that calling the former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> a "buffoon" can be actively useful for society.</p>
    <p>Overruling the conviction of a freelance journalist who hurled insults at the then premier as he left a court three years ago, the court of cassation acknowledged that the man had levelled "strong criticism". But Judge Alfonso Amato argued in a written judgment that it was "socially useful in terms of the interest of society as a whole in the expression of opinions".</p>
    <p>The judge added that a courthouse was the "ideal" place in which to "stimulate reflection on the subject of legality and respect for the law".</p>
    <p>In May 2003 Pietro Ricca, 31, confronted Mr Berlusconi as the then premier was leaving a trial in Milan in which he was accused of bribing judges to obtain a favourable takeover decision. He was later acquitted. "Buffoon!" shouted Mr Ricca. "Get yourself convicted." He compared Mr Berlusconi to Romania's late dictator, Nicolae Ceausescu, and was then arrested.</p>
    <p>Last month the court revoked a €500 (£340) fine imposed on Mr Ricca on charges of impugning Mr Berlusconi's honour, and ordered a magistrate to try him again - a ruling likely to mean the case is "timed out" by a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>Judge Amato's explanation of the ruling, released this week, angered conservative politicians yesterday. Fabrizio Cicchitto, of the ex-premier's Forza Italia party, said: "It is evident that there are no limits to the partisanship [of Italy's judges]." Mr Berlusconi has long complained of being hounded by left-leaning magistrates.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>