<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi slaps veto on paparazzi party shots" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-05-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/31/silvio-berlusconi-paparazzi-veto-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian PM blocks publication of photos from New Year's Eve event at Sardinia villa attended by Noemi Letizia" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Privacy &amp; the media,Media,World news,Privacy,Europe" fingerprint="8ed05b0f9876e715">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has blocked the publication of hundreds of photographs of a party attended by Noemi Letizia at his Sardinia villa last New Year's Eve.</p>
    <p>Letizia is the aspiring model whose hosting of the 72-year-old Italian premier at her 18th birthday party last month led his wife to seek divorce because he "frequents minors".</p>
    <p>Rome prosecutors yesterday ordered the seizure of the pictures after Berlusconi's lawyers alleged a violation of privacy. The photographer had allegedly offered them to newspapers for more than a million pounds.</p>
    <p>"These photos are of a private event, and therefore fall foul of the law," said Niccolò Ghedini, Berlusconi's lawyer.</p>
    <p>Letizia's presence at his party was acknowledged only after it was revealed by her former boyfriend, who claimed that 30 to 40 young girls attended.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi denied the photographs were damaging, claiming they "consist of people photographed during absolutely private moments which are completely legal".</p>
    <p>Antonello Zappadu, who took the shots with a long lens outside the villa, told the Italian daily La Stampa: "I can only say that among the guests there were many young girls."</p>
    <p>Renault Formula One manager Flavio Briatore, who has attended parties at the villa, said Berlusconi had lived apart from his wife for years and was free to invite young women. "The prime minister is single, and behaves as if he were single," he told Corriere della Sera yesterday.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>