<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Prosecutors seek confirmation of Silvio Berlusconi's seven-year sentence" author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" date="2014-07-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/11/prosecutors-confirmation-silvio-berlusconi-seven-year-sentence-appeal-court" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The former prime minister's original lawyers are not present for the appeal as they are being investigated for bribing witnesses" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="e72ad20d1267e669">
  <main>
    <p>Italian prosecutors asked an appeals court on Friday to confirm a seven-year prison sentence against the country's former prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, for having sex with an underage prostitute and abuse of power in office.</p>
    <p>Piero de Petris, presecutor, said the sentence handed down last year had been "severe" but "irrefutable", as the court prepares to issue a ruling in the case on 18 July.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was not present in the courtroom as the billionaire tycoon is doing community service in an old people's home near Milan for a separate conviction for tax fraud, which also led to his expulsion from parliament.</p>
    <p>Neither were his main lawyers present at the hearing as they are themselves being investigated for allegedly bribing witnesses during the original trial.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was sentenced in June 2013 in what has become known as the "Rubygate" case, which focused on raunchy parties hosted by Berlusconi at his sprawling villa.</p>
    <p>The ageing playboy was found guilty of having sex for money with a 17-year-old exotic dancer, Karima El-Mahroug, better known by her stage name: Ruby the Heart Stealer.</p>
    <p>He was also convicted of putting pressure on police to have her released from custody after she was detained for petty theft, apparently concerned she would reveal their liaison.</p>
    <p>Many of the witnesses in the original trial were young women who attended the Berlusconi parties and described them as "elegant dinner parties", prompting prosecutors to look into the possibility of witness tampering.</p>
    <p>Others have described the events as little more than orgies, featuring an array of strippers dressed as nuns and politicians, and ending up in Berlusconi's bedroom.</p>
    <p>A ruling against Berlusconi could be appealed again at the supreme court. If Berlusconi loses that final appeal, he would face either house arrest or community service.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>