<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's borrowing costs keep on rising despite Berlusconi's promise to quit" author="Graeme Wearden" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/nov/09/italy-borrowing-costs-record-high" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Yield on Italian 10-year bonds reaches record 7.5% despite prime minister's promise to resign" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Bonds,Business,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,European banks,European Central Bank,Financial crisis" fingerprint="7c6002f1918af51">
  <main>
    <p>Italian borrowing costs soared to new record levels as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-to-resign-italy">the promised resignation of Silvio Berlusconi</ref> failed to reassure the financial markets that Italy could avoid insolvency.</p>
    <p>The yield, or effective interest rate, on 10-year Italian bonds reached a record 7.5% on Wednesday. Such high borrowing costs threaten to make Italy the latest victim of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/blog/2011/nov/09/greece-prime-minister-italy-berlusconi-resigns">the European economic crisis</ref>.</p>
    <p>Relief at Berlusconi's decision to step aside evaporated quickly, with most European stock markets falling sharply.</p>
    <p>Italian president Giorgio Napolitano admitted that his country needed a "immediate and sustained commitment to the management of our public debt". Analysts warned that the political crisis within <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> risks dragging the country into bankruptcy, as efforts to strengthen its economy are undermined.</p>
    <p>"Alarm bells are ringing that Italy is perilously close to slipping into insolvency," said Raj Badiani of IHS Global Insight.</p>
    <p>Stuart Gulliver, chief executive of HSBC, agreed that the situation looked perilous. "There is a feeling in Asia that this crisis could go terribly wrong," <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/nils-pratley-on-finance/2011/nov/09/endgame-italy-bond-yields-surge">he told journalists</ref> this morning.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi agreed to step aside on Tuesday night after failing to secure an absolute majority in the lower house of parliament in Rome. With his majority gone, he acknowledged, he could no longer win support for new economic measures to address Italy's debt problems. The country owes almost €2tn (£1.7tn), around 2.7 times as much as Greece, Ireland and Portugal combined. Those three countries were all forced to accept a bailout, tied to tough austerity measures, after their bond yields broke above 7%.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said on Wednesday morning that early elections may need to held next year. Investors, though, want a "cabinet of technocrats" created to drive through unpopular economic changes. This political uncertainty has eroded demand for Italian debt.</p>
    <p>"The markets are coming to terms that the removal of Berlusconi as Italy's prime minister provides little by way of solution," said Jane Foley, senior currency strategist at Rabobank. "Perhaps a bigger problem facing Italy is the lack of a strong and credible opposition. The markets are hoping for a technocrat interim government charged with the difficult task of implementing structural reform."</p>
    <p>Italian yields stabilised after the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> aggressively bought up the country's debt in the financial markets. However, the ECB may not be able to stem the crisis without permission – currently denied by Germany – for a huge expansion in its bond-buying programme, perhaps through quantitative easing (the creation of new money).</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>