<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Indulging Berlusconi | John Hooper" author="John Hooper" date="2009-08-26" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2009/aug/26/silvio-burlusconi-indulgence-perdonanza" hostname="theguardian.com" description="John Hooper: The Italian PM is planning to have his sins absolved at L'Aquila's Perdonanza festival. But will it save him?" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Catholicism,Religion,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="7e9ece15df23d7eb">
  <main>
    <p>Is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> about to cash in on one of Roman Catholicism's more questionable practices? Italy's prime minister, beset by sex scandal, is to take part in the 715th <ref target="http://www.whatsonwhen.com/sisp/index.htm?fx=event&amp;event_id=29660">Perdonanza</ref>, to be held on Friday in the earthquake-hit city of L'Aquila.</p>
    <p>The Perdonanza is an annual festival and procession to celebrate the plenary indulgence <ref target="http://www.abruzzoheritage.com/magazine/2002_05/f.htm">granted in perpetuity by Pope Celestine V</ref> to all those who enter the Basilica of Santa Maria di Collemaggio on 28 or 29 August each year. Celestine had a particular attachment to L'Aquila and Abruzzo, the wild and rugged region that surrounds it, having spent much of his life there as a hermit.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is expected in L'Aquila on Friday for a progress report on the government's efforts to rebuild the city and the surrounding district following <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/10/italy-earthquake-mass-funeral">April's disaster</ref>.</p>
    <p>A plenary indulgence is the doctrinal reverse of a life sentence. Every sin you ever committed is wiped out at a stroke, and so long as you don't err again you go streaking up to the pearly gates and straight into heaven without having to spend even the odd, mildly vexing hour in purgatory.</p>
    <p>It is just the sort of arrangement that could be expected to appeal to a man-in-a-hurry such as Berlusconi. And the papal bull with which Celestine made his unrepeatable offer of eternal bliss does not except mysterious <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/aug/04/berlusconi-barbara-vanity-italy">entanglements with teenagers</ref> or <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/22/silvio-berlusconi-sex-tape">nights spent with escorts</ref>.</p>
    <p>But there are doubts as to whether Italy's eternally controversial prime minister will be willing – or able – to take advantage of the opportunity. Just by joining the procession he would be announcing to the world that he regards himself as a sinner badly in need of a break. And Berlusconi, even more than the rest of us, has difficulty in admitting he is in the wrong. When his wife announced she was <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/6074339/Silvio-Berlusconis-wife-Veronica-says-she-wants-a-divorce-because-shes-tired-of-his-lies.html">divorcing him</ref> because of his alleged frequenting of "minors", he declared that it was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/04/silvio-berlusconi-divorce">she who should ask for his forgiveness</ref>, and not the other way round.</p>
    <p>Even more problematic is Berlusconi's own status with respect to the Catholic church. He is divorced and thus unable to take communion. And, according to those who should know in the L'Aquila diocese, one of the conditions stipulated by Celestine was that recipients of the indulgence need to have received the Eucharist before taking part in the Perdonanza.</p>
    <p>This may be just as well. Berlusconi has good reason not to be associated too closely or publicly with the <ref target="http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03479b.htm">hermit pontiff</ref>, who reigned for five troubled months in 1294. He is best known to Catholics as <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_resignation">one of the few popes to resign</ref>.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>