<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi gets in shape for election" author="John Hooper" date="2005-05-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/may/20/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="With less than a year to go before the next election, the legislators of Italy's ruling party yesterday gathered to hear what their leader, Silvio Berlusconi, had to tell them of new policies and stratagems. They did not have to wait long." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="16a8d21fb492fb55">
  <main>
    <p>With less than a year to go before the next election, the legislators of Italy's ruling party yesterday gathered to hear what their leader, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, had to tell them of new policies and stratagems. They did not have to wait long.</p>
    <p>"From today," the prime minister announced, "I am on a diet." His revelation, which was reported by local media to have drawn applause from the assembled deputies, was the latest in a string of cosmetico-political initiatives from the leader of what is probably the world's most appearance-conscious nation. In two years Italy's prime minister has also had a facelift and a hair transplant.</p>
    <p>"This is the sign he is ready to launch his fight for re-election," said Laura Della Pascua, political correspondent of the Rome daily Il Tempo and author of a recent book on politics and food, Il Potere a Tavola.</p>
    <p>Yesterday's announcement came amid growing debate among supporters and allies over whether the 68-year-old Mr Berlusconi is the right man to lead Italy's conservatives into the next election. By the end of the next legislature he will be 74.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi told yesterday's meeting he had accepted a bet from the leader of his party in the lower house of parliament. "I want to lose five kilos in a month," he said. It will not be easy.</p>
    <p>"Italian politics are conducted almost exclusively at table," said Ms Della Pascua. "Berlusconi has always preferred to negotiate agreements over a meal, and that also applies to the discussion of issues within his party."</p>
    <p>Most of the recent changes to Italy's political landscape have been crafted over a portion of pasta and a glass of wine. Newspapers sometimes publish maps showing which politicians lunch at which Roman restaurants, and sometimes even floorplans to show who sits where.</p>
    <p>Not that Mr Berlusconi needs to repair to a local trattoria. As Italy's richest citizen he has his own chef, Michele Persechini.</p>
    <p>Dining with the prime minister is the abiding dream of some of his followers.</p>
    <p>Ms Della Pascua's book describes how every year three MPs from his Forza Italia party hire a villa on Sardinia near that of the prime minister specifically to get invited to dinner by him. It costs them €8,000 (£5,500) a month each.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>