<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi cleared of corruption" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2004-12-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/dec/10/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="A court in Milan today cleared the Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, of corruption charges, but dropped a key corruption charge against him because time had run out. The court fully acquitted the 68-year-old billionaire of a second charge of graft." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="5ffec028d56fd79c">
  <main>
    <p>A court in Milan today cleared the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, of corruption charges, but dropped a key corruption charge against him because time had run out. The court fully acquitted the 68-year-old billionaire of a second charge of graft.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who owns a media empire in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, was the first serving Italian prime minister to stand trial on criminal charges. The case related to the sale of a state food conglomerate, SME, in the 80s - a decade before Mr Berlusconi entered politics.</p>
    <p>In 1985, judges blocked the sale of SME to the Buitoni group, led by Carlo De Benedetti, a top Italian industrialist, ruling in favour of a group of business magnates including Mr Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>The prosecution alleged that Mr Berlusconi had given money to one of his close associates, Cesare Previti, to bribe judges in Rome in an unsuccessful bid to buy the conglomerate.</p>
    <p>On a second count, Mr Berlusconi was accused of keeping another Rome judge, Renato Squillante, on his payroll in case criminal charges stemming from his business empire were brought against him.</p>
    <p>The prime minister maintained his innocence throughout, and said the lengthy legal battle amounted to a witch hunt by leftwing prosecutors.</p>
    <p>He has faced several criminal cases related to his business empire since entering politics a decade ago. In previous trials, he has been acquitted, or his convictions have been reversed on appeal or annulled because of the statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>The SME trial began in March 2000, but was halted after the passage of a government-backed law that made Mr Berlusconi and four other top office holders immune from prosecution.</p>
    <p>The trial resumed in April after the constitutional court ruled that the legislation violated the principle that all citizens were equal before the law.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>