<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi party protests at attempt to close loophole that could spare him jail" author="John Hooper" date="2013-07-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/10/silvio-berlusconi-party-loophole-appeal-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Supreme court moves to hear Berlusconi's final appeal before conviction expires under law his government passed in 2005" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="be39189711319361">
  <main>
    <p>The parliamentary leaders of Silvio Berlusconi's party have demanded the suspension of parliament in protest at a decision by the supreme court aimed at preventing him from evading a four-year jail sentence on a technicality.</p>
    <p>The heads of the media tycoon's Freedom People (PdL) movement in both chambers said they wanted the legislature to cease all activity for three days. The centre-left Democratic Party (PD), which is joined to the PdL in Italy's left-right coalition, immediately rejected the demand, opening a rift within Enrico Letta's already fragile government.</p>
    <p>In a further threat to its survival, Berlusconi's representatives announced they were boycotting a meeting on Wednesday of the three parties that make up the coalition.</p>
    <p>The media tycoon has already been convicted in two lower courts of a €7.5m (£6.5m) tax fraud orchestrated by his Mediaset TV company. The judges added to the prison sentence, which Berlusconi is unlikely to have to serve, a ban on his holding office for five years, which would be an even harsher blow.</p>
    <p>If his case had followed its normal course through the supreme court, his final appeal would have been heard in about six months' time. But – as the result of a law passed by Berlusconi's government in 2005 – one of the counts on which he was charged would have been "timed out" in the meantime by a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>The judges would probably have had to send the case back to a lower court for a recalculation of the sentence. In Italy, that could easily take 12 months, during which period the other count would have been timed out.</p>
    <p>The supreme court decided that Berlusconi's appeal should be heard on 30 July before a tribunal that deals with urgent matters during the summer legal holidays.</p>
    <p>The billionaire politician's followers expressed outrage at the decision. Maurizio Lupi, the transport minister, said: "Millions of Italians wait years for justice, but for Silvio Berlusconi the [supreme court] gets convened in record time."</p>
    <p>But the Corriere della Sera, the paper that first spotted the loophole through which the leader of the Italian right might once again wriggle, pointed to a 1969 law that instructs judges to speed up cases that are at risk of lapsing during the summer break because of a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>Roberto Maroni, the leader of the Northern League, which was in coalition with the PdL until 2011, said a suspension of parliament would be an "affront to democracy".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>