<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Across Europe, the left's fightback has begun | John Palmer" author="John Palmer" date="2011-09-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/sep/27/europe-left-fightback" hostname="theguardian.com" description="John Palmer: Far from being in retreat, the political pendulum is swinging back to the left – with a more integrated EU at the heart of its agenda" categories="Opinion" tags="European Union,Euro,Euro,Germany,Europe,France,Nicolas Sarkozy,Angela Merkel,Denmark,Labour,Italy,Currencies,Economics,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Business,Politics" fingerprint="9557e855d001a825">
  <main>
    <p>Speaking at the Labour party conference in Liverpool on Sunday, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2011/sep/26/labour-iraq-libya-douglas-alexander">Douglas Alexander</ref> drove home a frequently made point that throughout Europe – not just in the UK – the right is rampant and the left is more or less everywhere in retreat. "For a decade around 1997, the centre left was defeating the right. Now the centre right is beating the left," he declared.</p>
    <p>During the past five years this has indeed been the dominant political trend in the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref>. It explains why the right, which has come to dominate the EU council of ministers and the European commission, has been able to sweep aside opposition to the European governments' economic austerity orthodoxy. However, the shadow foreign secretary may be missing evidence that this trend is now reversing.</p>
    <p>Last week we had the success of the coalition of Social Democrats, the Socialist People's party and the Red-Green Alliance in the <ref target="http://www.cphpost.dk/component/content/52161.html?task=view">Danish general election</ref>. This week we have learned about the unexpected victory of the alliance of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/sep/26/french-socialists-senate-sarkozy">French Socialists and Greens in taking control of the French Senate</ref> – following a series of dramatic election victories for the left in the French regions earlier this year.</p>
    <p>But the most significant evidence that the political tide is turning against the right is surely the near implosion of the current German coalition government of Christian Democrats and (notionally) liberal Free Democrats, led by Angela Merkel. A series of devastating losses of important regional elections in Germany have seen power pass to the <ref target="http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/09/18/us-germany-states-factbox-idUSTRE78H1S520110918">Social Democrats and the Green party</ref> – sometimes with support from the leftwing Die Linke party.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, in Italy, the ramshackle conservative coalition headed by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> totters ever closer to collapse. In Italy it is true that the parties of the left have a lot of ground to make up. And in the dwindling number of EU member states where the centre left still holds on to power, such as Spain and Cyprus, it seems almost certain the popular reaction to massive public spending cuts and soaring unemployment will see their defeat in the fairly near future.</p>
    <p>However if, as now seems likely, President <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref> and the French right lose the French presidential election next spring, and this is then followed by a Social Democrat/Green victory in the German general election in early 2013, the centre of power at the heart of the European Union will have moved as well. What is not widely understood in Britain is that the French and German socialists and their green allies now share very similar ideas about the future governance of the eurozone and the wider European Union.</p>
    <p>The German conservative parties have resisted every proposal to move to a full scale economic union where the collective credit of the eurozone could be deployed to support countries under the financial cosh. But the German social democrat/Green opposition backs the ideas of euro bonds and <ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/eus-ultimatum-to-germany-act-now-to-save-the-euro-2354988.html">urges a different economic strategy, which would prioritise sustainable growth at EU level</ref>.</p>
    <p>Significantly, when the rightwing Free Democrats played with euroscepticism in a desperate effort to reclaim lost votes, their support collapsed in the recent Berlin region elections. Even more encouraging has been the evidence from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/denmark">Denmark</ref>, Sweden and elsewhere that support for far right racist parties is starting to ebb – in part in disgusted reaction to the Norwegian massacres this summer.</p>
    <p>It is one thing to say that the political pendulum may be swinging back from the right in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, it is another to say that the centre left will be equal to the task of forging a new direction for EU economic and social strategy. Indeed, a future failure by the centre left to halt the drift to a new recession or possibly a full scale depression could generate a disastrous political backlash.</p>
    <p>The French and German opposition parties insist that they want to see both an economically and politically more integrated EU and a deliberate distancing from the neoliberalism ideology that has dominated European politics for the past decade. Indeed their conviction that closer European integration is essential is being reinforced by the current confusion and division among centre right EU governments over how to handle the financial crisis.</p>
    <p>The British <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/labour">Labour</ref> party has maintained a studied silence on most of these issues – bizarrely leaving George Osborne and the eurosceptics to pressure eurozone governments to move faster to a full economic union. It will be more difficult for Labour to maintain such indifference as the debate among their own comrades in Europe about moving further down the road to economic and political union gathers pace.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>