<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi ultimatum to Italy" author="John Hooper" date="2004-11-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/nov/20/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi last night threatened to bring down his own government unless he could fulfil an election pledge to reduce income tax." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="5eb88b5fe730c729">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi last night threatened to bring down his own government unless he could fulfil an election pledge to reduce income tax.</p>
    <p>The prime minister is convinced tax cuts will deliver election victory in 2006, when his government will have been the first in Italy's postwar history to serve a full term.</p>
    <p>Others in his rightwing coalition fear tax cuts could unbalance the public finances and breach eurozone rules.</p>
    <p>Last week they appeared to have persuaded Mr Berlusconi to agree to put off the cuts. Asked yesterday if the delay threatened his government, he replied: "For Forza Italia that would certainly be a reason for new elections." He added his party would contest elections only alongside those allies who backed him.</p>
    <p>The billionaire took his gamble after failing to wrest concessions from his deputy, Gianfranco Fini, in exchange for making him foreign minister, even though his party, the National Alliance, remained solidly opposed to early cuts.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi risks a collision with Brussels and eurozone states committed to keeping budget deficits to 3% of GDP; the European commission has expressed concern at Italy's runaway spending.</p>
    <p>The alliance backs the finance minister, Domenico Siniscalco, whose budget for next year aims to reduce the deficit rather than taxes. When Mr Berlusconi signalled his displeasure this week, Mr Siniscalco was put in the humiliating position of having to say his proposals were still under discussion.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>