<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Angelino Alfano: the perfect choice for Berlusconi as Italy's new PM" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/angelino-alfano-berlusconi-italy-pm" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Berlusconi's anointed successor is young, clever, and unswervingly loyal to his interests" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" fingerprint="dfd0c00acce297fd">
  <main>
    <p>If <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> decided to take a leaf out of the book of his old friend Vladimir Putin and name as his successor a Dmitry Medvedev <hi rend="#i">alla italiana</hi>, he could scarcely find a better candidate than Angelino Alfano.</p>
    <p>Aged 41, Alfano is young by the gerontocratic standards of Italian politics. He is clever. And he has been unswervingly loyal to the cause, and interests, of Italy's outgoing prime minister.</p>
    <p>Currently secretary of Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People, he was previously minister of justice. In that role, he oversaw the introduction of a controversial law, overturned by the constitutional court in 2009, that granted immunity from prosecution to the four highest officers of state, including the prime minister. Earlier this year, he sponsored another measure to guillotine legal proceedings which opposition politicians said was intended to stop Berlusconi's trial for allegedly bribing his British legal adviser, David Mills.</p>
    <p>Born at Agrigento in Sicily, Alfano studied law at the Catholic Sacro Cuore university in Milan. He practised as a lawyer before entering parliament at the age of 31 when Berlusconi returned to power in 2001.</p>
    <p>Four years later, he was made regional co-ordinator for Sicily of Berlusconi's earlier party, Forza Italia. Alfano's name has twice been linked with the mafia, but in very different contexts.</p>
    <p>In 2002, the daily La Repubblica drew attention to an amateur video showing he had attended the wedding six years earlier of the daughter of an alleged Mafia "godfather". Alfano said he had been invited by the groom and did not know the bride's family.</p>
    <p>Last month, a petty criminal told prosecutors that he had become aware in jail of a Cosa Nostra plot to "get rid" of Alfano because of his role in enforcing the tough regime imposed on mafia prisoners.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>