<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Former Italian MP flees Italy before court rules on his mafia conviction" author="Lizzy Davies" date="2014-04-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/11/italian-mp-court-mafia-marcello-dellutri-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Marcello Dell'Utri, said to have acted as a mediator between the Cosa Nostra and Silvio Berlusconi, has been declared a fugitive" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Mafia,World news" fingerprint="fa2af70bbdcd5305">
  <main>
    <p>A former Italian MP who allegedly acted as a mediator between the Cosa Nostra and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> before the ex-prime minister entered politics is believed to have fled Italy as the supreme court prepares to hear his final appeal against a conviction for mafia association.</p>
    <p>Marcello Dell'Utri, a long-time Berlusconi ally who helped create the former premier's Forza Italia (FI) party in the 1990s, has been declared a fugitive after authorities said they had been unable to serve him with an arrest warrant issued earlier this week.</p>
    <p>The 72-year-old, who was sentenced last year to seven years in jail by an appeals court in Palermo, was being sought "nationally and internationally", Sicilian anti-mafia investigators said in a statement.</p>
    <p>Italy's top appeal court is due to hear his case on Tuesday.</p>
    <p>Due to a telephone conversation intercepted by police, investigators had reason to believe Dell'Utri could have gone to Lebanon or the west African nation of Guinea-Bissau, La Stampa newspaper reported.</p>
    <p>The Dominican Republic was reported to be another possibility, given that the former politician – in parliament as a deputy, MEP and senator, from 1996 until 2008 – is known to have gone there previously.</p>
    <p>In its reasoning last year, the appeals court said Dell'Utri had carried out "mediation" between figures in the Cosa Nostra and Berlusconi in the 1970s, and that this "pact of protection" lasted until 1992, two years before the billionaire media tycoon was first elected prime minister.</p>
    <p>Dell'Utri has always denied links with the mafia and any ties between it and Berlusconi. The former premier also denies any links.</p>
    <p>The old friends are both coming to crunch moments in long-running legal battles. The 77-year-old FI leader is due soon to find out how he will serve his commuted one-year sentence for tax fraud.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>