<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi to spend another night in hospital after attack" author="Haroon Siddique" date="2009-12-15" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/15/silvio-berlusconi-hospital-attack" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister unlikely to return to work for 10 days after being hit in the face with plastic souvenir during rally" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="1e1cd32c834b6257">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, is to be kept in hospital for another night as he recovers from the attack in which he was struck by a model of Milan's cathedral, his personal doctor said today.</p>
    <p>A statement released by the San Raffaele hospital said the 73-year-old, who suffered a broken nose and two broken teeth in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-punched-face">Sunday's attack</ref>, was in pain but his condition was not worrying. His doctor, Alberto Zangrillo, said he was unlikely to return to work for 10 days.</p>
    <p>Italy's interior minister, Roberto Maroni, said the "actions" of Massimo Tartaglia, 42, who threw the souvenir at Berlusconi during a political rally outside Milan's gothic cathedral, were premeditated, saying the attacker had been "developing a rage against the prime minister for some time".</p>
    <p>Maroni said Tartaglia had been in the square from 11am on Sunday morning and, as well as the plastic model cathedral, obtained from a stall nearby, was carrying pepper spray and a resin crucifix.</p>
    <p>In a letter to the Italian leader, Tartaglia expressed his "heartfelt regret for a superficial, cowardly and rash act in which he did not recognise himself", the attacker's lawyers said. They added that their client, who has a history of mental health problems, acted alone and did not have a political agenda.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was shaking hands and signing autographs when he was struck. He was taken to hospital with his face bloodied.</p>
    <p>There was condemnation of the attack from across the political spectrum but the Italian media has suggested the incident reflected the prime minister's polarising effect on the public.</p>
    <p>Italy's best-selling daily newspaper, Corriere della Sera, said it was indicative of the "civil war" going on in Italian politics.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's popularity has fallen after a year in which he has been embroiled in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">sex scandals detailing his alleged use of prostitutes</ref>. He has also experienced legal troubles with the constitutional court <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/07/silvio-berlusconi-immunity-law-uncontitutional">throwing out a law that granted him immunity</ref>. That could open him up to a series of trials for fraud, tax evasion and bribery. But despite his troubles his approval rating remains just over 50%.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>