<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi warns of 'madness' of no-confidence vote" author="John Hooper" date="2010-12-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-italy-senate-appeal" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prime minister tells senate his opponents risk plunging Italy into eurozone debt crisis if they bring down government" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Euro,European Union,World news" fingerprint="7fb511a79901cf35">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi today warned Italian legislators they would send the country spiralling into the the eurozone debt crisis if they brought down his government.</p>
    <p>The move would be "political madness", he told members of the senate ahead of two votes tomorrow to decide the fate of his 29-month-old government.</p>
    <p>His rightwing administration is expected to win a vote of confidence in the upper house but is considerably more vulnerable to a motion of no confidence in the lower house, the chamber of deputies.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi and his allies have been without a guaranteed majority in the lower house since July when <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/jul/30/silvio-berlusconi-italy-gianfranco-fini?intcmp=239">followers of his former deputy, Gianfranco Fini, stormed out of the governing majority to set up a parliamentary group of their own</ref>.</p>
    <p>Key passages of the prime minister's speech to the senate were clearly aimed at wooing back some of the more equivocal rebels in the lower house.</p>
    <p>At the weekend, six of Fini's followers signed an appeal for peace talks with Berlusconi. But Fini promptly stamped on their initiative, announcing that his group would join the opposition after Tuesday's ballots, regardless of the outcome.</p>
    <p>"The votes of the centre-right's electorate cannot be taken and added to those of the opposition," Berlusconi told the senate. "Free parliaments are called to represent and interpret the popular will, not replace it."</p>
    <p>In an encouraging development for the prime minister, one of Fini's followers said she would not be attending a meeting tonight to agree on how the rebels should vote. Most calculations pointed to a government victory but suggested the margin in the chamber of deputies could be as little as one vote.</p>
    <p>As Berlusconi's main remaining ally, Umberto Bossi of the Northern League, observed: "With an edge of just one vote, you cannot govern."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi made it plain that, if he survived, he would try to broaden and consolidate his majority by bringing into government the conservative Christian Democrat Union of the Centre (UDC), which he cited by name. He also said he was willing to consider electoral reform, but only if it guaranteed the survival of a bipartisan system.</p>
    <p>That, however, could scotch any deal with the UDC: its aim is to form a new, "third force" in Italian politics that can hold the balance of power and play the right off against the left.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>