<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi denies quit claims and stakes future on economic reform vote" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/07/italy-debt-berlusconi-denies-resignation" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy PM's defiance over government's handling of Italian debt crisis sparks wild fluctuations in stock and bond markets" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Eurozone crisis,European banks,Business,European Union,Silvio Berlusconi,Bonds" fingerprint="6faa50b590a31779">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's imperilled Italian government faces a fresh test of its strength after Rome's corridors of power were engulfed by speculation of the prime minister's impending resignation, sending financial markets on a rollercoaster ride.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi appeared determined to stake his government's future on yet another confidence vote. "I want to look into the faces of those who are trying to betray me," he told the Libero newspaper. Where and when the vote would be held remained unclear, however.</p>
    <p>The prime minister declared he was prepared to survive or perish in a ballot on sweeping economic reforms, but wild fluctuations in the bond and stock markets showed investors had little faith in his ability to see them through.</p>
    <p>Italy has been dragged into the centre of the eurozone crisis as investors have fretted over its vast public debts – amounting to some 120% of GDP – and the Berlusconi government's ability to put the country in a position to start repaying them.</p>
    <p>The Milan bourse's FTSE Mib index soared almost 500 points – more than three percentage points – on a claim by two journalists close to the PM's party that he had decided to resign.</p>
    <p>In the bond markets, the 'spread' – the difference between Italian and German benchmark interest rates – contracted sharply before Berlusconi denied the claims on his Facebook page.</p>
    <p>Several opposition politicians called for an investigation by Italy's stock market regulator to rule out any suspicion the bourse had been manipulated. Both journalists concerned denied the insinuation.</p>
    <p>Franco Bechis, deputy editor of Libero, said Berlusconi had changed his mind after speaking to his family at a lunch in Milan. After meeting the PM at his home near Milan, Gianfranco Rotondi, a minister without portfolio, said: "If we have the majority we will carry on, otherwise there will be elections."</p>
    <p>Tuesday's vote is being held to approve the public accounts for 2010. The rejection last month of a routine, technical ballot plunged Berlusconi's government into a crisis from which it has yet to recover. Though the PM's Freedom People party scraped through a confidence vote on 14 October, several deputies have since abandoned the governing majority. On Sunday night, the interior minister, Roberto Maroni, said on the latest arithmetic the government may no longer have an outright majority in Italy's lower house, where its position is weakest.</p>
    <p>The party's latest deserter was an unexpected one for the PM. Gabriella Carlucci, a former TV showgirl, declared she was leaving to join the Union of the Centre, a party of conservative Christian Democrats. By some reckonings, 15 or more others have lost faith in Berlusconi and his administration, which has repeatedly been wrongfooted by the euro zone crisis.</p>
    <p>The public accounts vote is not expected to be a confidence vote and so, even if the government were to lose, it would not fall. But a second rejection could spark panic on international financial markets because it would block the passage of key measures the government has agreed with the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> and the European Central Bank.</p>
    <p>Speculation suggested the opposition could abstain, which would allow the accounts to be approved while testing the extent of the government's support. Anything less than an absolute majority would be highly embarrassing for Berlusconi and intensify pressure for him to go.</p>
    <p>However, a defiant Berlusconi was quoted by Libero saying: "I shall call a confidence vote on the letter sent to the EU and ECB. I want to look into the faces of those who are trying to betray me."</p>
    <p>If the government did lose a confidence vote, President Giorgio Napolitano would have the power to appoint a cross-party government or a cabinet of non-politicians, if he could muster sufficient support.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is free to call a make-or-break division on any government declaration, and could therefore peg his political survival to a reading of the pledges of economic reform he has made to European institutions. That would give him the chance to pre-empt a threatened no-confidence vote tabled by the opposition.</p>
    <p>But the economic reform plans are in any case due to be voted on in the Senate next week, and subsequently in the Chamber. There was speculation that Berlusconi might turn either or both of these forthcoming ballots into a vote of confidence, defying the opposition to vote down Italy's undertakings to Brussels and, implicitly, to Frankfurt. And the possibility of the opposition having to throw out the reforms measures in order to throw out Berlusconi really is likely to worry the markets – a scenario the foreign minister, Franco Frattini, said he hoped that would not happen. If, however, the government were to fall sooner, the economic reform package would anyhow be endangered.</p>
    <head rend="h2">What happens next?</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">8 November</hi> Vote in the chamber of deputies, the lower house of the Italian parliament, on the public accounts for 2010. Not a confidence vote. At least not yet. But vital if the government is to continue functioning.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">15 November</hi> Expected date of a ballot in the upper house, the senate, on a 50-clause amendment to the Italian government's austerity package. The bill must go to the chamber for approval. Either or both of these divisions could be turned into a confidence vote by Berlusconi's government. But it could fall victim to either:</p>
    <p>A vote of confidence on a declaration by the prime minister, which the government would have to win in order to survive.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>