<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Do let's stop sneering at Italy, like some global Lady Muck | Marina Hyde" author="Marina Hyde" date="2009-07-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/10/italy-g8-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Marina Hyde: The ability to run a G8 summit like clockwork is no sign of civilisation, but the boast of an irrelevant, tedious middle manager" categories="Opinion" tags="G8,Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Politics,Europe" fingerprint="c31599e4a14cb99d">
  <main>
    <p>At last, an answer to the annual question: "What is the point of the <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/country_profiles/3777557.stm">G8</ref>?" Every year, this gathering of very important nations – with China and India sweetly given the role of tea boys – arrives at a few vague agreements, which they then renege on 10 minutes later in the comfort of their own homelands. Consequently, there are some who have suggested the wildly expensive jolly tends toward the purposeless – but how very foolish those people now look. This year the G8 has shown what it is for. It is not a gathering of the leaders of the industrialised nations. It is an organisational challenge devised by snooty diplomats to expose Silvio Berlusconi as an Eye-talian, with all the overemotional, chaotic sleazebaggery that classification apparently implies.</p>
    <p>As of this week, you are formally advised to retire the cliche: "Couldn't organise a piss-up in a brewery". The on-trend expression is now: "Couldn't organise an international summit in an earthquake-stricken city".</p>
    <p>To the casual observer, the Italian PM has managed to recreate the same mealy-mouthed lack of direction in <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L'Aquila">L'Aquila</ref> that one would expect of the G8 every year, but it seems that some US diplomats think they've had to do all the grunt work. The Italians are in high dudgeon – even though they are lovers, not fighters – and it is clear that certain forces wish to designate the country part of a new axis of feeble. Which other feeble-doers you include in that bracket is up to you, though do try to stick to southern Europeans. And Johnny Turk should probably make the cut.</p>
    <p>What must be done, "going forward"? I would move for sanctions by the liberati, so that all the people who care about this sort of thing nobly forgo decamping to Tuscany for August. If they're not fit to host a summit, are they really fit to host your holiday? It's such a paradox. The Italian peasants who make one's vacation so picturesque, as opposed to places populated by oikishly tracksuited Brits and Yanks, are the very people whose existence permits one to sniff "third-world country" when it comes to the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref>.</p>
    <p>By now, if you are simpatico, you may be on the point of detecting a certain sarcasm. Like a certain nation's mythical tanks, this column only has a reverse gear – because it is obviously very silly for the British to be playing Lady Muck. Were Berlusconi minded to adopt some of our own lingo, he might hoot: "Hark at her! She's no better than she should be …"</p>
    <p>Without getting too heavily mired in moral relativism, we could all benefit from a little self-awareness. After all, it was only recently that London hosted the G20, and what an absolute triumph that turned out to be. Ask someone to name the first thing that comes into their head when they hear the words "<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/jul/07/g20-protests-police-tactics">G20</ref> in London" and they won't embark on an awestruck hymn to the IMF's increased overdraft facility. They will think of a man being struck from behind by an unprovoked police officer, and dying within the hour.</p>
    <p>Similarly, one has to ask if this is really the season for the British to be taking the moral high ground on ruling-class corruption, or indeed bemoaning the fact that the person who really runs the country owns so much of the media – Silvio in their case, Rupert in ours. As for our comical national debt, has the time come to ask whether Britain should even be at the G8? We only think we matter because of our ridiculous nuclear weapons, and that seat on the UN security council we've done such a bang-up job with in recent years.</p>
    <p>Bafflingly, there are those Brits who still believe their image abroad is that of the mannerly, stiff-upper-lipped gentleman spy, and perhaps in certain pockets of America we have managed to preserve this illusion. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, where we fly cheaply to disport ourselves at stag parties and football matches and on all-you-can-drink holidays, it is fair to say the David Niven ideal was buried some aeons ago.</p>
    <p>Indeed, speaking of odious British tourists, what was the only thing more embarrassing than that 2004 photo of Berlusconi at his Sardinian villa wearing a bandana to hide his recent hair transplant? Correct. It was Tony and Cherie Blair, grinning manically next to him on yet another freebie holiday.</p>
    <p>So do let's stop sneering at Italy's summit-hosting abilities, as though making sure the increasingly pointless G8 runs like clockwork were a litmus test of civilisation, instead of something that marks you out as a tedious middle manager. Rather than a nation of shopkeepers, let us accept that we are a nation of summit-hosters, mainly because summits allow us to swank about as though it were 60 years ago, and wheel out the Queen as a prop.</p>
    <p>Come to think of it, a neat solution suggests itself. With the pound as weak as it is, we're a useful cheap destination. To guarantee our place at the table in perpetuity, let us lobby for all summits, always, to be held in Britain, in an extension of the World Cup rule that says that the host nation qualifies automatically, however rubbish they are.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>