<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The view from a broad: Is it any wonder Italian women want Berlusconi out?" author="Laura Barton" date="2011-02-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/14/unsurprised-at-berlusconi-protests" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy ranks 74th in global gender gap report. Plus, football's attitude to women has changed – but not enough" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Women,Football" fingerprint="6657882a92334847">
  <main>
    <p>✤ Apologies if our arrival today lacks the splendour of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/music/gallery/2011/feb/14/grammy-awards-2011">full Gaga egg-hatching spectacle</ref>; madam's Grammy performance rather stole our thunder. Anyway, some splendid news: on Sunday, hundreds of thousands of Italian women assembled in protest against the general slimy toading of their prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, and in the hope of becoming "a country that respects women". Italy, lest we forget, ranked 33 places below Kazakhstan in <ref target="http://www.weforum.org/issues/global-gender-gap">the World Economic Forum's latest global gender gap report</ref>, coming in a lacklustre 74th out of 134 countries surveyed. Is anyone really surprised they're angry?</p>
    <p>✤ These are dubious times in the relationship between women and football. We have only just stopped reeling after Richard Keys and Andy Gray and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2011/jan/26/richard-keys-resigns-sky-sports">Do Me A Favour-gate</ref>, and now we learn that Manchester United overlord Sir Alex Ferguson rejected a job application by a physiotherapist, because she happened to be a woman. "Most of the players felt that football was very much a male sport and did not like the thought of females being involved with the treatment of sports injuries within the training complex," <ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1356474/Sir-Alex-Ferguson-sexism-football-row-Woman-physio-My-lads-wont-like-that.html">Ferguson wrote to the applicant</ref>. Granted this was 17 years ago, and United have hoped to quell any furore by declaring that "times have changed" in football.</p>
    <p>✤Certainly we now have female physios in football clubs, as well as female linesmen and, at West Ham, a female vice-chairman in the form of Karren Brady, but it's a sorry fact that when we think of women and football we don't think of Brady, or linesman Sian Massey, or <ref target="http://marta10.com/en/">Marta Vieira da Silva</ref>, five-times winner of the Fifa Women's World Player of the Year award, or even <ref target="http://www.thefa.com/England/womens-seniors">the England women's football squad</ref>, who will play in the World Cup this summer. Rather, we think of the wives and girlfriends of the players, accessories to their men, sex scandals, high court injunctions, the roastings in hotel rooms. Times have changed, perhaps, but they've not changed enough.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>