<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Terry Daley: Anti-Berlusconi outrage is understandable" author="Terry Daley" date="2008-07-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/jul/12/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Terry Daley: But anti-Berlusconi campaigners need to ensure anger doesn't get the better of them" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3ea8006b986bf70d">
  <main>
    <p>Only in Italy could an actress take the stage at a demonstration organised for Italians to show their anger at the Silvio Berlusconi-led government and declare, "<ref target="http://www.ansa.it/site/notizie/awnplus/english/news/2008-07-09_109238606.html">In twenty years' time I want to see the Pope in hell being tormented by gay devils</ref>."</p>
    <p><ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabina_Guzzanti">Sabina Guzzanti</ref>, who is also a well known satirist and blogger, was speaking at "No Cav Day" (the Italian Prime Minister is a cavaliere, the Italian equivalent of a knight), an event organised in the most part by <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Di_Pietro">Antonio Di Pietro</ref> and his IDV (Italia dei Valori or Values of Italy) in Rome's Piazza Navona. Guzzanti's comments caused uproar among the writers, politicians, and TV personalities who had spoken before her. It certainly didn't help that she also launched into personal abuse of Mara Carfagna, minister of equal opportunities and former television showgirl, with Guzzanti claiming that Carfagna was only in her current position because she was "sucking Berlusconi's dick." Other speakers rushed to the stage to distance themselves from her vitriol, causing panic and not a little bit of embarrassment, as well as threatening the credibility of over three hours of powerful protest.</p>
    <p>Up until that point the event had been going swimmingly, with leading figures on the left (and those who just hate the current political elite) giving impassioned speeches about Italy's current political situation and the crimes that they regard Berlusconi as committing against the state. Di Pietro himself <ref target="http://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,23992454-38200,00.html">was not shy about apportioning the blame</ref>. "This is the real democracy here, not what is happening in government," he said. "What is happening here is a crime of political extortion ... all of Berlusconi's first actions were about protecting himself. He is killing the political process for his own ends."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is attempting to pass a law that will stop wire tapping on anyone who isn't in a recognised organised crime syndicate (thereby stopping pesky trials against himself), and which will render him and a few other people in powerful political positions <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/28/italy1">immune from prosecution</ref> as well as make journalists who report on the evidence liable for prosecution and imprisonment. But that pales into insignificance when compared to the racial profiling of the country's beleaguered <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/27/race.italy">Roma population</ref>, who have already been fingerprinted in Milan and Naples as part of a programme that has a horrible historical precedent. Not only that, but the act of profiling a minority in this way is deeply unconstitutional. After Benito Mussolini's Fascists were defeated, Italy's constitution was changed to stipulate that "all citizens... are equal before the law, without distinctions of sex, race, language, political opinions, personal and social conditions." It seems that Berlusconi wants to change that.</p>
    <p>Certainly the comparisons with the fascist era came thick and fast yesterday and on Monday, when a few thousand Romans opposed to the persecution of the Roma lined up in Piazza Esquilino in the city to have their <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/29/italy">fingerprints taken in solidarity</ref>. It was no coincidence that many members of the Jewish community, who can hear echoes of what the government is trying to do in their own past, showed up to offer their fingerprints. For those who forget that both Jews and Gypsies were victims of the Holocaust, it was a powerful reminder. "Democracy is like a plant," said <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moni_Ovadia">Moni Ovadia</ref>, a Jewish musician who was born in Bulgaria but who settled in Milan with his family in his early childhood. "If you don't take care of it then it suffers. If we're not careful we will end up in the Republic of Salo; a fascist and racist regime will take place here."</p>
    <p>The electoral reforms brought in by Berlusconi in 2005 mean that over 1.5million Italians who voted for left wing parties have no political representation, and the brazenness of the government's disregard for human rights and the judicial process is angering many. Di Pietro garnered rapturous applause yesterday when he said "when there is a democratic emergency, we all have to take a stand", but it remains to be seen if a country where conspiracy theories are rife, distrust of authority is near total and corruption in high places is expected – even tolerated – can be roused to change.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>