<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Playing fast and loose with TV in Italy" author="John Hooper" date="2004-03-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2004/mar/09/media.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Questions are being raised over Italy's newest television channel, Sportitalia, which is backed by two of Silvio Berlusconi's closest associates, reports John Hooper." categories="Business" tags="Business,Media,Italy,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2ca89da6b3accfdc">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's newest television channel, Sportitalia - backed by two of Silvio Berlusconi's closest associates - went on air with a minimum of publicity on February 6. It still has no listing in the telephone directory; the only way to make contact with it is through a toll-free number on its website.</p>
    <p>Though most Italians have yet to hear of Sportitalia, it nevertheless has the technical means to be a leading player on the media scene. According to a company statement before the launch, its terrestrial frequencies enable it to reach 81% of the population, making it only the ninth free-to-air channel with a nationwide reach.</p>
    <p>Of the remaining eight, one is a shopping channel, three are operated by the publicly owned RAI and three belong to Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset empire. In theory, therefore, there is a gap in the market for a terrestrial sports channel.</p>
    <p>But with Rupert Murdoch's new, satellite-based Sky Italia pouring cash into the rights to key sports events including the main Serie A football fixtures, Sportitalia would seem to have its work cut out finding a substantial audience. Its prime offering one recent weekend was the Indoor Motorcycling Trial World Championship from Pesaro.</p>
    <p>The channel is 51% owned by the Tunisian-French media entrepreneur, Tarak Ben Ammar, who until last July was a board member of Mediaset. The remaining 49% is held by the French group, Eurosport, whose managing director, Angelo Codignoni, created Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia - or "Come on Italy!" - party.</p>
    <p>On February 19, the centre-left's media spokesman, Paolo Gentiloni, demanded clarification of the way in which Sportitalia had acquired its licence. In a written parliamentary question, he set out a chain of deals whereby the company had acquired frequencies originally allotted to the defunct pay TV channel Telepiu.</p>
    <p>On Christmas eve, the communications ministry had issued a statement that "took note of the change ... from restricted to unrestricted access", Mr Gentiloni said.</p>
    <p>Since the 1998 law governing broadcasting licences specifically ruled out changing the type of licence once it had been granted, Sportitalia's concession was "blatantly illicit", he added.</p>
    <p>Mr Codignoni told the Guardian: "It is not up to Sportitalia to answer a question put by a member of parliament. That is for the ministry to do.</p>
    <p>"But from the point of view of Sportitalia, everything has been done respecting the procedures and rules. We have done nothing without authorisation."</p>
    <p>The new channel arrives at a time when Mr Berlusconi and Mediaset are under severe pressure.</p>
    <p>Italy has laws designed to scotch precisely the kind of media concentration its prime minister has so skilfully achieved. Under the terms of a judgment by Italy's highest court, Mediaset was meant to have transferred its third channel, Rete 4, to satellite at the end of last year. A bill sponsored by the government which shielded Rete 4 from blackout, was approved by parliament shortly before the deadline, only to be thrown back by the head of state, President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi. Mr Berlusconi and his supporters have since rammed a stop-gap measure through the legislature allowing Rete 4 to continue broadcasting.</p>
    <p>But it has already been the subject of sniping from the government's own supporters in parliament.</p>
    <p>Opposition politicians suspect Sportitalia could form part of a "fallback strategy" in the event of the battle going against Mr Berlusconi in parliament.</p>
    <p>"This could be a way out - to sell Rete 4 to an old and good friend who all of a sudden has a free-to-air licence with which to put it back on the air," said one MP.</p>
    <p>The son of a Tunisian father and French mother, Tarrak Ben Ammar has TV and film production interests in several countries, including Italy.</p>
    <p>In 1995, he structured the $1bn deal in which Mr Berlusconi sold off 25% of his empire to outsiders including the German magnate Leo Kirch and Mr Ben Ammar's lifelong friend Saudi prince Alwaleed bin Talal. Part of the rationale behind the deal was to counter criticism of a conflict of interest between Mr Berlusconi's roles as politician and media tycoon.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>