<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Peter Preston: EU fiddling fails to let freedom reign on television" author="Peter Preston" date="2009-08-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/organgrinder/2009/aug/02/media-news-peter-preston" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Peter Preston: How can you organise a proper network of functioning, co-operating free states if one of them is governed by a media tycoon" categories="Media" tags="Press freedom,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Newspapers,Television industry,BBC,John Humphrys,Radio industry,The Times,Ofcom,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,European Union,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="ea51515bb29698d1">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The following correction was printed in the Observer's For the record column, Sunday 9 August 2009</hi>
    </p>
    <p>In the article below we described John Nolan as "boss" of ITN. He is, in fact, a member of its press office. Apologies.</p>
    <p>Sit at the back of the room and scratch your head. The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> (at least in legend) is an embryo superstate seeking to micro-manage our lives. Yet here I am in Croatia, the next country primed to join, listening to journalists from all over the Balkans talking about press freedom, or rather, press repression. "Things were better in Tudjman's time," says one Zagreb investigative reporter bitterly. "Then he owned the judiciary so he didn't mind what you said: now the judges are independent so the politicians have to stop you saying anything interesting in the first place".</p>
    <p>Tales of woe flood in. Television presenters suddenly out of a job because they turned over the wrong stones; specialist correspondents shelved for digging too deep; newsroom culls that consign independent minds to redundancy first; and, of course, violence, intimidation, threats, even murder.</p>
    <p>It's a brutal business being a journalist in the Balkans these days, but somehow <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> stands coyly to one side. Democracy matters hugely, in theory: the tests for entry are essentially tests of democratic credentials. But once inside - take Slovenia, Bulgaria, Romania - some very odd things happen. And, as Croatia knows from the case of the editor Ivo Pukanic only 10 months ago, you can also get shot on the doorstep.</p>
    <p>Freedom House, the American NGO that monitors the workings of democracy around the world, has just issued its latest European rankings. Bulgaria and Romania are not classed as "free", just "partly free" (76 and 94 in liberty's pecking order respectively). Croatia has slid back to 81 and the elephant on top of the Partly Free League is the biggest affront of the lot: Berlusconi's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, at number 65.</p>
    <p>How can you organise a proper network of functioning, co-operating free states if one of them is governed by a media tycoon who can run his sticky fingers over six out of Italy's seven terrestrial TV channels? Answer: without great difficulty, because nobody outside Italy is tough enough to make waves. What Silvio wants, Silvio can get away with (unless too many of them tumble out of his bed). And if Silvio can raise two fingers to freedom's campaigners, what message does that send to other countries in the EU waiting line? Serbia at 83, Bosnia-Herzegovina at 97, Turkey at a lamentable 101?</p>
    <p>Brussels knows something is badly wrong. The spokesman for its media commissioner frankly acknowledges the difficulty in a survey for the latest issue of E!Sharp magazine. We're not a superstate, says Martin Selmayr: "We do not have a competence on media legislation or to second-guess the fundamental rights situation in a member state." That's a job for the quite separate European Convention on Human Rights, policed much more frailly via the Council of Europe.</p>
    <p>Various studies on "media pluralism" inch forward in commission HQ offices, as promised in 2004 when the new team took over, but there's no sign of a big debate, let alone a sea change, coming. Brussels can and does look into the competition ramifications of satellite TV and newspaper distribution, but falls flatly silent where the real freedoms of a free press are concerned.</p>
    <p>Britain can't smile too superciliously. We're 27th on the Freedom House list, far adrift from Iceland and Finland at 1 and 2. Estonia, Lithuania and the Czech Republic show us a clean pair of heels. Endless surveillance and snooping, plus the pall of the libel courts, is dead weight.</p>
    <p>But at least, you say, Brown is better than Berlusconi. If that's consolation then we have it, but look at the continent we belong to, and wonder how long it can go on snoring behind a newspaper whenever its TV services leave truth on some distant corner of the studio floor.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Auntie's political heavyweights face a summer offensive from stand-ins</head>
    <p>Jeremy Paxman is 60 next May, David Dimbleby turns 71 in October, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/john-humphrys">John Humphrys</ref> celebrates his 66th birthday this month. No, I'm not raking over the plight of women broadcasters consigned to oblivion one wrinkle at a time, but the BBC's political heavyweights are growing older together.</p>
    <p>Should they call it a day in some kind of collective grand exit, perhaps after the next election? There's scant sign of that happening, and if you want to know why then absolutely the best answer comes from Humphrys in an interview for a new book, Conversations on Truth: "I don't have to do it any longer to earn money because I've earned enough now. But I've just signed up to another two-year contract when I thought initially I wasn't going to because I thought 'Oh shit, I'm going to be lying there at eight in the morning listening to an interview and going 'Aargh!".'</p>
    <p>In short, they'll have to drag him (and the other two) out of the studio - and that won't happen until there's somebody equally good poised to take over. Evan Davis as embryo head honcho for Today, Nick Robinson standing in as summer relief on Newsnight? It seems to be happening in little ways this damp holiday season.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Putting the boot in over BBC's web footage</head>
    <p>Four national paper websites - Telegraph, Guardian, Indie and Daily Mail - will henceforth be able to use some <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/bbc">BBC</ref> video footage for political, education and business coverage. "We regard this initiative as a core part of the corporation working more effectively as a public service partner," says deputy director general Mark Byford.</p>
    <p>But here comes a sourer view from John Nolan, the boss of ITN. This initiative threatens to undermine "the demand for content from independent news providers, potentially undercutting a very important revenue stream ... so the BBC's latest move risks pulling the rug from under us". Even more exciting in a rather abrasive way.</p>
    <p>Enter a BBC spokesman: "We are simply allowing newspapers to embed branded content we have already published on BBC Online. We are not making bespoke content available or providing raw news footage or 'white-labelled' news content that papers can brand as their own or editorialise."</p>
    <p>Not exciting at all, and even less pulsating when Mr Murdoch's papers and Ms Bailey of Trinity Mirror turn sniffy - unless you want a lecture on Auntie's difficulty of being all things to all friends and foes alike, and getting damned little credit wherever she goes.</p>
    <head rend="h2">No T***s please, we're the Times</head>
    <p>We call it the silly season because it generates pretty silly stories. But does that include silly newspaper behaviour?</p>
    <p>Take the David Cameron row over twits and twats as quipped on air, then see an almost full Times' page 4 with the "Chief revise editor" talking sonorously about vulgar slang, his teenage sexual naivety and (nudge, nudge) Virgin Radio. "What I can tell him [Cameron] is that on the Times we try to steer clear of spelling out obscenities, as they offend our readers."</p>
    <p>So a t*** is t*** for old Printing House Squares. And a leaden portentousness rules in a Wapping safe for twerps.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Ofcome finally realises there are some local difficulties</head>
    <p>There are gentle signs that the demise of newspapers may be somewhat delayed. Trinity Mirror found a little advertising sunshine in the English regions last week and saw its share price take a bound at last. In America, some of the worst-hit shares - Gannett and McClatchy - rebounded after three-monthly results proclaiming profit, not loss as expected.</p>
    <p>But how, meanwhile, is the basic scenery changing? Here's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/ofcom">Ofcom</ref>, beginning a consultation period to see if the rules limiting newspaper groups from owning local radio stations (and maybe community TV stations) in the same area should be relaxed. Why not make it two out of three? Ofcom asks. There's the advertising march of the internet. There's BBC local radio. Nobody should be fearing monopolies in a world like this.</p>
    <p>Logic, of course, goes further. Logic wants three out of three if the rather bright Conservative plans to compete with the BBC via up to 81 local television outlets are to get a fair hearing. At least, though, the regulators do seem to have noticed there's still a crisis. Soon they may also do something about it.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>