<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian lower house backs law to delay Berlusconi prosecutions" author="Philip Pullella; Guardian staff reporter" date="2010-02-03" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/03/italian-mps-berlusconi-trial-delay" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Planned law upholds 'legitimate impediment' principle, meaning ministers can postpone trials for being 'too busy'" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="3fbad034b4a2cfdb">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's lower house approved a law that could effectively block trials against the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, for up to 18 months, a move the opposition says is his latest attempt to avoid prosecution.</p>
    <p>The lower house approved the measure voting 316 in favour and 239 against. It now moves to the upper house Senate.</p>
    <p>Known as the "legitimate impediment law", it allows the prime minister or members of his cabinet to ask that trial hearings be postponed on grounds that they will be too busy with government work to attend.</p>
    <p>The hearings can be postponed three times for periods of up to six months each, meaning that the two trials Berlusconi is currently facing can be suspended for as long as 18 months.</p>
    <p>The law, which will remain in effect for 18 months after it is approved by the Senate, effectively strips a judge of the power to reject a request for postponement.</p>
    <p>One centre-left opposition leader, former anti-graft magistrate Antonio Di Pietro, called it "the murder of legality".</p>
    <p>"It's one thing to say you are legitimately impeded [from attending a trial] because you've broken your leg and are in hospital and another to say 'I'm a minister and my job impedes me from going to court'," Di Pietro said.</p>
    <p>But Fabrizio Cicchitto, leader of Berlusconi's party in the lower house, said that without the law, Berlusconi would have to spend several days a week in court.</p>
    <p>The Democratic Party, the largest in the opposition, as well as Di Pietro's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Values party, voted against the measure. The small centrist Union of Christian Democrats (UDC) abstained.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>