<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Senate backs new Berlusconi government" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2005-04-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/28/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The new government formed by the Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, today won a vote of confidence in the Italian senate, one day after winning approval in the lower house of parliament." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7fa6c0bd9682c77f">
  <main>
    <p>The new government formed by the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, today won a vote of confidence in the Italian senate, one day after winning approval in the lower house of parliament.</p>
    <p>The senate voted 170-117 to approve the new government, formed after Mr Berlusconi briefly resigned to reshuffle his cabinet last week in a bid to end infighting among members of his centre right coalition. The reshuffle followed an embarrassing defeat at regional elections.</p>
    <p>In a 30-minute address to the senate prior to the vote, Mr Berlusconi promised economic changes including tax cuts for businesses and a new push to lift Italy's poorer south, as well as help for families whose buying power, he says, has decreased since the introduction of the euro.</p>
    <p>With elections just a year away, Mr Berlusconi has come under attack from opposition parties over his handling of the economy. Criticism has focused on Italy's faltering economic growth and its fiscal deficit. The government forecast 2.1% growth for this year, but the figure is expected to be lowered soon.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi spoke extensively about the economy in his speech to the senate. He put much of the blame for Italy's economic woes on global trends and called on the European central bank to revise its monetary policy.</p>
    <p>"The solution does not depend on a national government. It concerns the European central bank," he said. He took the bank to task for focusing on inflation and not doing enough to keep the value of the euro down, thus damaging European exports.</p>
    <p>He said the bank's policy was "destructive for the competitiveness of all companies in Europe".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi failed to mention the shooting of Italian intelligence agent Nicola Calipari in Iraq last month, even though reports that the US intends to exonerate its soldiers over the killing has aroused public anger.</p>
    <p>Mr Calipari, who has become a hero in Italy, was shot at a US checkpoint on Baghdad's airport road just after he had helped free kidnapped journalist Giuliana Sgrena.</p>
    <p>There have been calls for the 3,000 Italian troops in Iraq to be brought home. The prime minister supported the US-led war in Iraq in defiance of fierce domestic opposition.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi put his government's prestige on the line with assurances to the nation that full light would be shed on the shooting. Any public finding seen to absolve the US soldiers would be likely to undermine his credibility.</p>
    <p>Both sides said this week they were still working on the final report of a US-Italian investigation into the shooting. Italian and US officials attached to the coalition forces in Baghdad were trying to negotiate a document that could resolve the impasse, US officials said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>