<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian politicians go into conclave for crucial presidential election" author="Lizzy Davies" date="2013-04-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/apr/17/italy-politicians-conclave-presidential-election" hostname="theguardian.com" description="As Giorgio Napolitano quits the Quirinale, the presidency has become a bargaining chip in the wider battle for a government" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Mario Monti,Beppe Grillo,Italian elections 2013" fingerprint="3f908a0fd5a4f77d">
  <main>
    <p>Italian cinemas are this month showing a film about a bald librarian from the mountains called Peppino who, due to a voting glitch that terrifies everyone – including himself – is elected to the highest office in the land. As it charts his journey from provincial joker to maverick statesman, Benvenuto Presidente! has given viewers some much needed laughs at a time when real-life politics is every bit as strange as fiction, but certainly not as funny.</p>
    <p>On Thursday, seven weeks after elections that resulted in little more than unbreakable gridlock, more than 1,000 politicians are due to gather in the lower house of parliament to start the process of electing a new president to replace Giorgio Napolitano, the widely respected former communist who, at the age of 87, has come to the end of his seven-year term.</p>
    <p>The choice of a new head of state is always important, but this time, as the clock ticks and there is still no new government, it is crucial. It will be up to Napolitano's successor to see whether bickering politicians can be cajoled into forming a government or whether a return to the polls is the only way forward. Even for those with rather more political experience than Peppino, the challenge is daunting.</p>
    <p>"This election is extremely important because the president of the republic is in office for seven long years without interruption," said Gianfranco Pasquino, a leftwing political scientist and former senator. "He has the power first to appoint the prime minister and second to dissolve parliament, so he is a very powerful man, especially because the [political] parties are very weak and there is no majority for any party or any single coalition."</p>
    <p>Although a largely symbolic office, the Italian presidency has been likened to a concertina that can expand and contract according to need. In the past year and a half that need has been greater than ever. When Silvio Berlusconi's government collapsed in November 2011 it was Napolitano who drafted in Mario Monti and invited the economist to form a technocratic government.</p>
    <p>In the long and anguished aftermath of February's election, "King George", as he has been dubbed by the media, has once again played a central role. But, due to constitutional restrictions on the powers of a president in his final six months in office, he has not been able to dissolve parliament and call new elections. So all eyes will be on his successor – but quite who that will be remains unclear.</p>
    <p>What is always an obscure process cloaked in intrigue has become even more so this year as the presidency becomes a bargaining chip in the battle for a government. Any candidate will need broad support; in the first three rounds a two-thirds majority is needed, while thereafter the requirement falls to a simple majority.</p>
    <p>It had been hoped that, if a president were elected with the backing of both Pier Luigi Bersani's centre-left and Silvio Berlusconi's centre-right, the path to some form of new government might potentially run more smoothly. But , as Bersani threw his support behind Franco Marini, a prominent Catholic in the Democratic party (PD) and former speaker of the senate, the supposed "consensus" candidate immediately appeared to expose the deep faultlines within his own party.</p>
    <p>While backed by Berlusconi's bloc and Monti's centrists, Marini's candidacy was vehemently opposed by Bersani's chief leadership rival, Matteo Renzi, who had already slated Marini earlier in the week and who declared last night that his presidency would do a "disservice" to the country.</p>
    <p>There was speculation that elements of the centre-left unhappy with Marini could back the candidate of Beppe Grillo's anti-establishment Five Star Movement, Stefano Rodotà, a leftwing professor of law. The M5S had originally backed investigative journalist, Milena Gabanelli, but she politely but firmly declined.</p>
    <p>Francesco Clementi, a constitutional expert and professor of law at the University of Perugia, said the election – which is carried out by secret ballot – would be a gauge of the various divisions in the PD. "This will be a very interesting, very strange election in which we will be able to check the influences within the party," he said. Among the other names suggested as potential candidates have been Giuliano Amato, a respected former prime minister, Massimo D'Alema, who in 1998 became the first former Communist to become prime minister of a Nato country, and Sergio Mattarella, a former deputy prime minister under D'Alema who is now a judge in Italy's constitutional court. Former prime minister Romano Prodi, championed by many on the centre-left, was dismissed outright by Berlusconi, who lost two elections to him.All predictions are made with caution. Observers compare the presidential election to the papal conclave and say that, just as he who is dubbed the greatest <hi rend="#i">papabile</hi> usually exits a cardinal, so frontrunners for the Quirinale palace tend not to emerge as president-elect. The process can also be as lengthy as a conclave: while two presidents have been chosen with lightening speed on the first ballot, it ran to 16 rounds in 1992 and 23 in 1971.</p>
    <p>Many Italians are watching the election with scepticism. Near the Quirinale, Tonino Giardini, a consultant, said on Tuesday that none of the potential candidates inspired much faith. "We don't have anyone on Napolitano's level," he said. "I'm looking, but I can't see anyone."</p>
    <p>Over coffee in a nearby bar, Paolo Ganino, a 27-year-old journalism student based in London, bemoaned the paralysis. "We need a government. I came back from England to vote to have a government, and I still don't have it. I have the government that was appointed by the president and not voted by anyone that is still in charge," he laughed, bitterly. Will the new president, whoever he or she is, be able to change much? Ganino, a PD voter, was not hopeful, suspecting that fresh elections would be on the cards before the year's end. "It's a very difficult situation. I'm really into politics," he said. "But I do not see a way out."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>