<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="A scene worthy of Caravaggio as Silvio Berlusconi finally falls from grace" author="Ed Vulliamy" date="2013-10-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/06/silvio-berlusconi-fall-from-grace" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The pointing figure of his accusers was straight out of a baroque masterpiece as Italy's political playmaker slumped in defeat" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="adae4a8b14307f83">
  <main>
    <p><hi rend="#i">Ecce Homo</hi> (Behold the Man): the citation from Pontius Pilate that accompanies hundreds of paintings across Italy featuring a finger pointing at Christ. In <ref target="http://www.google.co.uk/imgres?imgurl=http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/27/Michelangelo_Caravaggio_040.jpg&amp;imgrefurl=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contarelli_Chapel&amp;h=218&amp;w=231&amp;sz=1&amp;tbnid=IYEmFD3j9sHNtM:&amp;tbnh=160&amp;tbnw=169&amp;zoom=1&amp;usg=__FtBPmr39utB6HxznE_rZDX6QgjQ=&amp;docid=0XdMsoJAacl3TM&amp;itg=1&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=TOVOUqXoJ6mL0AW27ID4Cw&amp;ved=0CJQBEPwdMAo">Caravaggio's masterpiece </ref>in the French church of St Louis a few hundred metres from the Senate in Rome, it is Christ who does the pointing, at Saint Matthew.</p>
    <p>In the Senate last week, it was a former party ally pointing at the leader who delivered himself, not without messianic delusions, to the mercy of the state – <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, in a scene worthy of a baroque painting. In this picture, Berlusconi is seen surrounded by his People of Freedom (PdL) party after he was forced to withdraw the threat to bring down the government of Enrico Letta following a revolt by ex-party allies, signalling the humiliating collapse of his authority and the end of his political power.</p>
    <p>Could this be the end? And was it really 20 years ago that <hi rend="#i">Il Cavaliere</hi> stepped into the political ring? I covered Berlusconi's first successful election, in 1994, after four tumultuous years as Rome correspondent, during which an entire political class had come under investigation and much of it under arrest – even the pillar of Italy's opaque establishment, the prime minister and Christian Democrat leader, Giulio Andreotti.</p>
    <p>With their usual yearning for apocalypse, papers and pundits foresaw a collapse of power-as-we-knew-it, the creation of a vacuum into which a new democracy would be born.</p>
    <p>The shamed <hi rend="#i">partitocrazia</hi> – party-ocracy, as the Italians called it – had existed thanks to an alliance in government between, simply put, the new economic powerhouse around Milan, under the sway of Bettino Craxi's Socialist party, and what could be called "permanent Italy" in the south, where the interests of church, mafia and other traditions cemented into the formidable Christian Democrat party.</p>
    <p>The contenders to fill the vacuum were the new Left Democrat party, which had shed its communist hammer-and-sickle in 1991 to form a Blairite prototype. Then, suddenly, enter the construction magnate who had turned himself into a media mogul, largely thanks to Craxi's corruption: Berlusconi. Few believed that a purveyor of topless quiz shows and <hi rend="#i">TV spazzatura</hi> – rubbish TV, denounced by Pope John Paul II as a curse – could become the figurehead of conservative Catholic Italy.</p>
    <p>Most of Berlusconi's advisers at the apex of his Fininvest commercial empire counselled against a move into politics – but for a dark genius called Marcello Dell'Utri, who backed the idea. Dell'Utri was a Sicilian Berlusconi had befriended on the football field in student days; he has spent much of the past two decades fighting off judicial investigations into alleged mafia connections.</p>
    <p>Dell'Utri managed the 1994 campaign – a dazzling phantasmagoria of dancing girls under the lights, while he saw to the shadows.</p>
    <p>Italy had fought bloodily for decades to keep the communists in opposition and its occult power machine would resist even the sanitised, pink version of the old party, even if it meant embracing a soft-porn merchant and probable criminal to do so.</p>
    <p>In that fateful election of 1994 Italy, eyes wide open, inaugurated the era of <hi rend="#i">Il Cavaliere</hi>, in order to change almost nothing more than the showcase. Last week that era drew to a close, with the humiliation of its central figure plain to see as he slumped, defeated and isolated.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>