<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Aid: Give and take | Editorial" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-07-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/07/aid-g8-summit-editorial" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Editorial: Taking sufficient action to protect the world's poorest countries against the next crisis requires real political bravery" categories="Opinion" tags="G8,Global development,Douglas Alexander,Labour,Global recession,Italy,Politics,Society,Business,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7b0dc29f3e45265b">
  <main>
    <p>This is not a good time to be making a case for giving aid. The worst global downturn since the second world war has prompted individuals and states to pull in their horns, hitting donations to charity and allowing rich countries to backslide on their promises of aid to the developing world. Some governments needed no excuse; <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, hosting this week's G8 summit of industrialised nations, has a terrible record on aid. In an era of fiscal-stimulus packages and bank bailouts, it is every nation for itself - which all too often means that the developing world is left with nothing at all. Last year, the plight of the world's poor was highlighted by runaway food and fuel prices - this year they are out of sight and out of mind. The arguments for aid have also run into fierce opposition from the likes of Bill Easterly and Dambisa Moyo, two economists who argue that much government help is wasted and that it is anyway a poor substitute for market forces.</p>
    <p>So when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/douglasalexander">Douglas Alexander</ref> yesterday unveiled plans for spending more on developing countries he was either risking attack from the all-aid-is-wasted-aid lobby, or at best courting indifference from an electorate and media with other things on their minds (the Jackson funeral, anyone?). In this economic climate, it would have been just as easy for the development secretary to keep his head down and hope no one raised any tricky questions about why taxpayers' money is going towards classrooms in Dhaka rather than Deptford. That he did not give in to that temptation is to be commended. Mr Alexander did better than that, arguing that aid spending should be kept up not only because the rich have a moral duty to the poor, but also because it is in Britain's economic self-interest. Aid can both help to stabilise poor countries and turn them into viable markets for British goods and services. What is remarkable about such arguments is that they now seem almost platitudinous, whereas in 1997 they were contentious. The true measure of success in politics is to render a policy uncontroversial - and that is what Labour has done with development. It promoted aid after years of Tory cuts and compromise; now David Cameron will ring-fence development spending. True Blues in Eastbourne may dissent, but across the frontbenches there is consensus on the quantity of aid.</p>
    <p>There is, however, fierce disagreement on how the money is to be spent. Among other proposals to be unveiled within the next few days, the Tories want to give out vouchers so that slum dwellers in Nigeria can send their kids to private schools. That is not a stupid policy - but, given the other problems facing the world's poorest, it is irrelevant, influenced more by Thatcher worship than by the needs of those on the ground. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/labour">Labour</ref> thinking too, there has been a shift. Yesterday's aid white paper put more emphasis on job creation than the previous priorities of health or education. Mr Alexander will also concentrate the £9bn aid budget on war-torn countries; this is a policy influenced by economist Paul Collier (whose fingerprints are all over this document) but one that could, without clear benchmarks, turn development into the dustpan department, the arm of Whitehall that goes into countries either wrecked by the Ministry of Defence or abandoned by the Foreign Office.</p>
    <p>Much of what the government said yesterday on aid is commendable; it is what it did not say that is worrying. The past two years have been a crisis of globalisation, in which poor countries have been hit by a tsunami that originated in rich nations, and were not adequately protected by the IMF or the World Bank. Yet Mr Alexander said little about reform of the Washington institutions, or rethinking the rules of globalisation. Speaking up for the world's poor is certainly courageous, but taking sufficient action to protect them against the next crisis requires real political bravery.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>