<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi denies sex allegations with statement of 'stable' relationship" author="Tom Kington" date="2011-01-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/17/silvio-berlusconi-allegations-dating-relationship" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian PM counters claims he paid a teenager for sex, saying he has been dating one woman since the failure of his marriage" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="6ff04a3d51458629">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has said claims he paid a teenage dancer for sex and threw erotic parties for prostitutes cannot be true because he is enjoying a "stable, affectionate relationship" with one woman.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who has previously described himself as single since his wife left him in 2009, is under investigation on suspicion of paying Moroccan dancer Karima el-Mahroug for sex at his mansion near Milan when she was 17, an offence in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>In a video message aired by one of his TV channels last night, Berlusconi said he had been quietly dating a woman, whom he did not name, since his marriage broke down.</p>
    <p>"This person has obviously been with me rather often, including – and I underline this – on those evenings and certainly would not have allowed, at dinner or after dinner, those absurd goings-on that certain newspapers have hypothesised," he said.</p>
    <p>Witnesses have reportedly told investigators that topless women dressed as nurses and police officers performed stripteases for Berlusconi in the "bunga bunga" room at his mansion during parties held in 2010 and vied with each other to be asked to stay the night.</p>
    <p>Police on Friday raided the apartments of around 14 alleged habitués of the parties, finding sex toys and thousands of euros in cash.</p>
    <p>Speaking from a studio at the mansion, its shelves lined with photos of his family, Berlusconi likened the operation to a mafia roundup, claiming that the only crime committed by the women was "to give me friendship and affection" during the "elegant" and "tranquil" soirees that gave him the chance to communicate with young people.</p>
    <p>Tackling reports he doled out large sums of cash to his female guests, Berlusconi said he was proud to help those in need "with their homes, medical care and schooling for their children, but there was never any connection between money and sexual performances".</p>
    <p>Mahroug, a teenage runaway who was reportedly invited to Berlusconi's parties after meeting Italian celebrity agent Lele Mora, has said she was given 7,000 euros by Berlusconi but did not sleep with him.</p>
    <p>She has described Berlusconi as a "person who suffers from solitude, who is not very happy".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>