<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Union-busting" author="John Hooper" date="2008-05-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/may/23/unionbusting" hostname="theguardian.com" description="John Hooper: Italy's new government is ignoring European law. Does Berlusconi really want to be part of the EU?" categories="Opinion" tags="European Union,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="fea8c1977131375d">
  <main>
    <p>Does Berlusconi's Italy want to be part of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>?</p>
    <p>Not much, to judge by the outcome of his government's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/may/22/italy1">first cabinet meeting</ref> this week in Naples. It approved a vast number of legislative initiatives. The cabinet gave the thumbs-up to measures on everything from drunk driving to variable mortgage rates, and from rubbish removal to marriages of convenience.</p>
    <p>But what is striking is that no less than four of the most important provisions seem to be at odds with certainly the spirit, and very probably the letter of European laws and treaties.</p>
    <p>One of the last acts of the previous, centre-left government was to nod through, at Berlusconi's request, a huge, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2008/apr/23/theairlineindustry.italy">€300m (£240m) cash injection</ref> for Italy's stricken national flag carrier, Alitalia. This was to buy time for the incoming prime minister to put together a consortium of Italian investors who could keep it from falling into the hands of foreign buyers (or, as some people might put it, Italy's EU partners, the French and Dutch in the form of Air France-KLM). To allay the entirely reasonable suspicions that this was a subsidy, the government protested to Brussels that it was a loan, at market rates, to be repayable by December 31.</p>
    <p>Yet almost hidden among the welter of measures approved in Naples is one that converts this supposed debt into an asset, openly described as having been injected into the balance sheet to cover Alitalia's losses. So, it was a subsidy all along.</p>
    <p>Then there are the various measures being introduced to deal with troublesome outsiders. It would be wrong to make light of this.</p>
    <p>Italy has seen a rise in crime in recent years and the statistics show that a disproportionate number of arrests are of foreigners (though that could be, in part, a function of the greater "identifiability" of non-Italians).</p>
    <p>Nobody is arguing that Italians should tolerate those who enter their country to rob, rape and sell drugs. Few would quibble with measures like one that introduces stiff penalties for parents who make their children beg. But the fact is that several aspects of the so-called "security package" appear to be at variance with the laws of the community of which Italians claim to be such enthusiastic supporters. The cabinet must have been told that. Berlusconi's foreign minister, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franco_Frattini">Franco Frattini</ref>, was <ref target="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_barroso/frattini/welcome/default_en.htm">the EU's justice commissioner</ref> until a few weeks ago.</p>
    <p><ref target="http://ec.europa.eu/justice_home/fsj/citizenship/movement/fsj_citizenship_movement_en.htm">The 2004 directive on freedom of movement</ref>, for example, allows countries to kick out EU nationals only in the most exceptional circumstances. One of the formulations used is when they pose "a genuine, present and serious threat affecting one of the fundamental interests of society".</p>
    <p>Yet the package endorsed by the Italian government this week provides for the deporting of EU nationals who get given jail sentences of as little as two years. That provision comes into effect immediately, as does another ordering judges to hand down stiffer sentences to illegal immigrants. As of today, if you are convicted of an offence in Italy, and you are there without authorisation, then your jail sentence, fine or whatever will be increased by one third. It is hard to see that as anything but a violation of article 13 of <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Rome">the EC Treaty</ref> (the amended Treaty of Rome), which deals with non-discrimination and equality before the law.</p>
    <p>Then there are the limitations Italy has just imposed on the right to apply for asylum. UNHCR noted with concern that, under the new rules, asylum seekers whose applications have been turned down at the first hearing can be expelled without further ado, which is "clearly at odds with one of the fundamental principles of law and article 14 of the <ref target="http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/en/Treaties/Html/005.htm">European convention for the protection of human rights</ref>".</p>
    <p>Asked about possible objections by Brussels and other EU nations to the latest measures, Berlusconi's interior minister, Roberto Maroni, had this to say: "We don't intend to yield one millimetre to these underserved pressures."</p>
    <p>In other words, "They can go to hell".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>