<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi resignation doubts drive up interest rate on Italy's debt" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/berlusconi-resignation-interest-rate" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Fears that resignation announcement will lead to period of instability in Italy send shock waves through financial markets" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,Eurozone crisis,European banks,Business,World news" fingerprint="e7a8912d9ca3d779">
  <main>
    <p/>
    <p>Fear that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> might cling on to power, or that his resignation could trigger acute instability, sent shock waves through markets and drove the interest rate on Italy's public debt to a level from which no eurozone state has so far returned without a bailout.</p>
    <p>The prospect of a default by Italy that could spark a European or even global depression sent stocks plunging, despite a concerted effort by President Giorgio Napolitano to prop up investor confidence. Prime minister Berlusconi's own Mediaset TV group was a very heavy loser, its shares plunging more than 11%.</p>
    <p>In a move giving the clearest possible indication of his own solution to the crisis, the president named as a life senator the man who is widely tipped as a prime minister for a government of national salvation. Honouring Mario Monti, a former EU competition commissioner, allows him to be answerable in parliament for a cross-party grand coalition or a non-party technocratic government.</p>
    <p>A consensus that action is urgently needed also got parliamentary leaders of the main parties to agree to speed through the economic reforms and fiscal adjustments agreed with the EU. They ruled that the upper house, the Senate, would sit on Saturday, and that the lower house, the Chamber of Deputies, would if necessary sit on Sunday to approve the measures. This allows <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to deliver on its promises to Brussels before Monday's re-opening of the markets.</p>
    <p>The head of Italy's employers' federation, Emma Marcegaglia, had for months been decrying Berlusconi's failure to take care of the economy and warning that Italy stood at the edge of an abyss. She declared: "The country is now <hi rend="#i">in</hi> the abyss."</p>
    <p>And, she said: "Efforts will be in vain if we do not manage to restore the credibility we've lost in the eyes of the international institutions. We must do so immediately, within hours."</p>
    <p>Her comment was "dangerous alarmism", responded one prominent Berlusconi MP, Giuseppe Marinello. But with the Milan bourse, hammered by weeks of growing anxiety, dropping another 5%, and the yield on government bonds leaping beyond 7%, panic overspilled from the markets into the streets of Rome's historic centre, where Italy's big political decisions are taken. From the Quirinal palace, Napolitano issued an uncompromising statement, pronouncing that Berlusconi would be leaving office soon, and his departure would not be the prelude to a lengthy period of political instability.</p>
    <p>"There's no uncertainty about the prime minister's decision to resign," the statement said.</p>
    <p>On Tuesday evening, after losing his majority in the chamber of deputies, Berlusconi told Napolitano he would step down. But, he said, he would only go once the economic package had been approved.</p>
    <p>The fall of his government would otherwise have frozen the passage through parliament of the economic measures, together with two austerity packages introduced earlier this year under pressure from the ECB and Italy's eurozone partners.</p>
    <p>But fears over Berlusconi's true intentions – that maybe this was merely another machination – were ramped up when he gave a barrage of interviews to radio and TV, insisting his party would only agree to an election as a solution to the crisis. Fear turned to panic when his defence minister, Ignazio La Russa, said the favoured date was in February.</p>
    <p>Napolitano has the power to appoint a replacement government, provided he can get sufficient backing from party leaders. But he cannot start consulting them until Berlusconi leaves office.</p>
    <p>The premier said that either a new government would be formed "to take every necessary decision", or an election would be held "within the shortest time". But that could not be before January. Even some of Berlusconi's supporters doubt the wisdom of waiting so long against a background of threatened apocalypse in the economy. A former minister, Claudio Scajola, said it was "undesirable".</p>
    <p>Berlusconi also used the interviews to point to his likely successor: Angelino Alfano, the secretary of Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People, and a former justice minister.</p>
    <p>He told one of his TV channels the choice would depend on party members, but Alfano was in "pole position" to be the right's candidate at the elections he wanted to see. His appointment would signal a "generational change".</p>
    <p>In another interview, with the daily La Stampa, the prime minister said: "Now is Alfano's moment. He'll be our candidate for prime minister. He's very clever, better than one might think; and his leadership has been accepted by all."</p>
    <p>He insisted that he would not himself stand again. "On the contrary," he mused, "I feel liberated."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>