<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi unaware dancer he paid for sex was underage, court rules" author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" date="2014-10-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/oct/16/silvio-berlusconi-dancer-sex-underage" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Appeal court says evidence does not support claims that former Italian leader knew ‘Ruby the Heart Stealer’ was only 17" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="ff60521cfac1d25d">
  <main>
    <p>Italy’s former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> did have sex with an exotic dancer nicknamed Ruby the Heart Stealer, but did not know she was underage at the time, an appeal court has said.</p>
    <p>The billionaire was found guilty in 2013 of paying Moroccan-born Ruby – whose real name is Karima El-Mahroug – for sex when she was 17 years old.</p>
    <p>But in a surprise move in July, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/18/silvio-berlusconi-cleared-underage-sex-charges-rubygate-bungabunga-abuse-office-coverup">a Milan appeals court overturned Berlusconi’s suspended seven-year prison sentence</ref> and lifelong ban from holding public office on the basis that his actions “did not constitute a crime”.</p>
    <p>In the summary of its decision, published within the three-month legal limit, the court said there was “certain proof … of prostitution at Arcore on the evenings when Karima El-Mahroug was present”, referring to parties held at Berlusconi’s luxury villa near Milan.</p>
    <p>But it found that the accusation that Berlusconi knew El-Mahroug was underage was “not adequately supported by evidence”.</p>
    <p>It also overturned his conviction for pressuring the police while he was still prime minister to release El-Mahroug from custody when she was arrested for theft.</p>
    <p>He said he only made the call because he thought she was then-Egyptian president Hosni Mubarak’s niece, and the court found there was no threat made.</p>
    <p>The case could still go for review before the supreme court.</p>
    <p>The three-time premier – who has ambitions to return to the political scene – has been plagued by a host of other legal woes. He is currently on trial for allegedly bribing a senator with €3m (£2.3m) in 2006 to join his party and destabilise a centre-left government.</p>
    <p>In another case, prosecutors have requested that he face trial on suspicion of paying off a pimp to provide false testimony in an investigation into sex workers who attended parties at his residences in Milan and Rome.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is also being investigated for allegedly paying off witnesses – young women who attended his parties – to provide false testimony at El-Mahroug’s trial. The charges in that case have not yet been formally levied.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>