<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi escapes eurozone budget rebuke after pledge to lower Italy's deficit" author="Mark Milner" date="2004-07-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2004/jul/06/italy.europeanunion" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi was yesterday spared the humiliation of a reprimand over his country's budget backsliding on his first day as finance minister - but only after promising a €7.5bn (£5bn) improvement in Italy's public finances." categories="Business" tags="Business,Italy,European Union,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="4cc881ff82a2cc64">
  <main>
    <p>Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> was yesterday spared the humiliation of a reprimand over his country's budget backsliding on his first day as finance minister - but only after promising a €7.5bn (£5bn) improvement in Italy's public finances.</p>
    <p>European Union finance ministers decided not to issue an "early warning" notice regarding Italy's budget deficit after Mr Berlusconi, who took on the finance portfolio at the weekend, detailed a series of spending cutbacks.</p>
    <p>In his attempt to shore up the public finances, Mr Berlusconi is planning to cut tax breaks for the financial services sector by more than €1bn as well as pruning subsidies to industry, the regions and state-owned operations, including the rail and postal services.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister has given himself 10 days to win domestic political backing for his programme, which is designed to keep Italy's public sector deficit within 3% of gross domestic product - the limit set out in the eurozone's stability and growth pact.</p>
    <p>Explaining the decision to spare Mr Berlusconi's blushes, French finance minister Nicolas Sarkozy said: "The euro group has taken into account [Italy's] efforts and tries to help countries which makes efforts rather than complicating their task."</p>
    <p>France will break the pact's limits for the third year in succession in 2004. Italy's budget sums have been made worse by a near-stagnant economy that has depressed tax revenues but increased spending.</p>
    <p>In April the EC recommended finance ministers issue an early warning to Italy as growth projections had been too optimistic and the budget deficit was likely to hit 3.2%.</p>
    <p>Public sector debt put at 106% of GDP is also a concern. As the departed finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, who was ousted by some of Mr Berlusconi's coalition partners, noted wryly: "It is difficult to manage the world's third biggest debt pile without being its third biggest economy."</p>
    <p>Yesterday's measures may win Mr Berlusconi a breathing space, but he is expected to need further deficit measures next year. Fellow finance ministers appeared confident yesterday that he will be able to achieve them.</p>
    <p>"Berlusconi is ambitious to cut the deficit below 3% next year; we trust him," said Austrian finance minister Karl-Heinz Grasser said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>