<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Eurozone crisis: Nick Clegg rallies opposition to treaty change" author="Patrick Wintour" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2011/nov/09/eurozone-crisis-nick-clegg-rallies" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Deputy prime minster believes he has persuaded Germany not to impose greater financial measures on struggling euro nations" categories="Politics" tags="Nick Clegg,Politics,Eurozone crisis,European banks,European Central Bank,Business,Germany,Europe,World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,David Cameron,Liberal-Conservative coalition,Financial crisis,UK news" fingerprint="86cdc865b96b8ced">
  <main>
    <p>The deputy prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/nickclegg">Nick Clegg</ref>, believes he has won widespread backing in Europe to persuade the Germans not to push for EU treaty changes as a way of imposing greater financial discipline on crisis ridden euro-member countries.</p>
    <p>British ministers also still hope that market confidence in the Italian economy can be restored if the prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, stands by his promise to resign and a tough growth package is quickly implemented that includes structural reform over the labour market and pensions. David Cameron and Clegg are trying to persuade EU leaders that a big conference on treaty change would be a fatal distraction now. But ministers admit they have far less leverage in persuading the Germans to contemplate a more interventionist role for the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> (ECB), and that Germany remains resolute in refusing this.</p>
    <p>Figures such as Clegg have been privately urging the Germans to allow the ECB to take a more interventionist role for three months, even if they sympathise with the roots of German reluctance. One minister said: "Some of this debate in Europe about the role of central banks is becoming increasingly effete in the face of the gravity of the crisis. But at the end of the day, the argument bumps up against a very profound cultural, ideological and theological abhorrence in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref> to allow the ECB to intervene … everyone has got one alibi or another, but in the end it comes back to the same thing, which is a granite refusal to intervene. Anyone who is outside the eurozone has come up against the same reaction, and all you can do is marvel at the rigidity of the response."</p>
    <p>In a speech to the European Parliament setting out his approach to reform, Clegg, a former aide to the then EU trade commissioner Lord Brittan, urged <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> not to become embroiled in a kneejerk round of introspective renegotiations over EU treaties. There have been suggestions that treaty changes to shore up the euro are required by March, but neither Cameron nor Clegg wants this to happen, partly because it would open divisions within the coalition.</p>
    <p>Clegg said it would be "a huge political distraction" from the urgent task of making Europe more competitive and warned that, unless the EU did become more competitive, it would suffer perpetual decline even if it solved the debt crisis sweeping Europe.</p>
    <p>He said he supported German plans for greater financial surveillance, but it would be better if this could be achieved without time-consuming treaty changes. "To sit around tables for months on end, agonising over this article or that one, becoming engulfed in endless institutional introspection, would be a huge political distraction from the economic task at hand."</p>
    <p>He said the sovereign debt crisis was "not caused by inadequate treaties but, in large part, by the decision in 2005 to relax the conditions on eurozone membership. It was not the rules that were at fault, but governments who failed to implement them."</p>
    <p>Insisting that the crisis has been as humbling for the UK as for the eurozone, he said the EU's chief task must be to restore growth, adding: "It is the best weapon against Europe's high deficits and debt stocks.</p>
    <p>"Unless this continent becomes more competitive, it will find itself in perpetual decline. And even if we are successful now in pulling Europe's economy back from the edge of a precipice – unless we deal with these underlying weaknesses – in five, 10, 15 years time we will find ourselves in crisis again.</p>
    <p>"Too many European economies suffer from low productivity or inflexible workforces or red tape that strangles business."</p>
    <p>He also warned against the euro members forming a club within a club, saying: "To retreat from each other now would be to leave ourselves isolated in extremely tempestuous times."</p>
    <p>He said safeguards might be needed if the eurozone restructured so that decisions affecting the 27 EU member countries must always be taken by the 27.</p>
    <p>Despite his pro-European credentials, Clegg set out more detailed proposals than before to persuade the European Commission to relax some of its over-centralised oversight of UK domestic law. He called for reform of the common fisheries policy, and closure of several small EU budgets such as youth policy, tourism and culture.</p>
    <p>He also urged the EU to review its approach to employment law: "Is it really essential or desirable for the healthy functioning of a thriving Europe to have EU legislation insisting people work a 48-hour week, regardless of whether they want – or need – to work longer?" He said such working time restrictions should be imposed by nations.</p>
    <p>None of these changes Clegg believes requires excising any part of the existing EU treaty.He set out plans to extend online trade across EU borders, dismantle professional qualification red tape, and enforce open trade more quickly. And he argued against plans for a financial transaction tax. He said a Robin Hood tax "would have a massively disproportionate impact on the City of London, responsible for more than half of the revenues that would be taxed. And, according to the commission's own analysis, it would also reduce EU GDP as a whole".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>