<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi leaves hospital four days after attack" author="Staff; Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-12-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/17/silvio-berlusconi-leaves-hospital-attack" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister vows to go on 'with more strength and determination than before' after being hit with model of Milan cathedral" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="6e8192ef11470617">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi left hospital today after spending <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/dec/16/berlusconi-attack-hospital">four nights under medical supervision</ref> after he was attacked with a souvenir model of Milan cathedral.</p>
    <p>The 73-year-old prime minister waved but looked grim as he was driven away from San Raffaele hospital, in Milan, his face covered in bandages.</p>
    <p>In a statement, Berlusconi said he would go on "with more strength and determination than before".</p>
    <p>"I will remember two things about these days – the hatred of a few and the love of many, many Italians," he said.</p>
    <p>Initial news reports said the prime minister's motorcade was heading for Arcore, his villa on the outskirts of Milan, but journalists there reported that, hours after leaving hospital, he had not arrived.</p>
    <p>A Swiss media report quoted the mayor of Gravesano, in southern Switzerland, as saying that Berlusconi was expected to check into a clinic in the town <ref target="http://www.lifeinitaly.com/node/15243">amid reports</ref> that he was to have cosmetic surgery on injuries caused by the attack.</p>
    <p>On Wednesday night , his doctors put off a decision on discharging him from hospital for the third time since he was admitted after the attack on Sunday.</p>
    <p>His personal physician, Alberto Zangrillo, said the prime minister was in considerable pain and was unable to eat normally.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi lost half a litre of blood after being <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/video/2009/dec/14/berlusconi">hit with an angular souvenir replica of Milan cathedral</ref>.</p>
    <p>He suffered a broken nose, two chipped teeth and cuts inside and around his mouth – unpleasant injuries, but not necessarily ones warranting a four-day stay in hospital.</p>
    <p>On Tuesday, Zangrillo said the blow to the prime minister's head had inflamed a long-standing neck complaint.</p>
    <p>A judge approved the jailing of Berlusconi's assailant, Massimo Tartaglia, who is being held in medical care at San Vittore prison, in Milan.</p>
    <p>The cabinet will tomorrow discuss proposals to black out venomously anti-Berlusconi websites and tighten security at public gatherings.</p>
    <p>As Italy's interior minister, Roberto Maroni, expressed concern over copycat attacks, a man was arrested trying to reach Berlusconi's hosiptal bedroom.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>