<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi: Italy earthquake victims should view experience as camping weekend" author="John Hooper" date="2009-04-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/08/italy-earthquake-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister causes controversy with quip made during interview following country's worst earthquake in three decades" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Natural disasters and extreme weather,World news,Europe,Earthquakes" fingerprint="75ac1009f647d719">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, today sparked controversy when he said the 17,000 people made homeless by Monday's earthquake should think of themselves as being on a "camping weekend".</p>
    <p>Berlusconi made the remark during an interview with a German television channel as he visited one of the emergency camps set up to cater for people who have lost their homes in the disaster.</p>
    <p>The quake, which devastated the city of L'Aquila and surrounding towns and villages, has now claimed 260 lives.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi told the reporter for the N-TV channel that the homeless quake victims "lacked nothing".</p>
    <p>"They have medicaments. They have hot food. They have shelter for the night," he said.</p>
    <p>"Of course, their current lodgings are a bit temporary. But they should see it like a weekend of camping."</p>
    <p>His remarks – which seem to have been intended to reassure the public – scarcely correspond to the experiences of the homeless.</p>
    <p>Between Monday and Tuesday, they had to endure a night of driving rain and hail during which temperatures fell to 4C (39F).</p>
    <p>Yesterday, Berlusconi told a press conference in L'Aquila that 14,500 tents had been made ready and another 2,000 were available on standby.</p>
    <p>However, tents were still lacking for 200 people by the time night fell.</p>
    <p>Twenty "tent cities" have been set up to take the homeless, while other people driven out of their houses by the earthquake have been lodged in hotels and elsewhere.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's comments came as rescuers continued searching for survivors after a powerful aftershock brought two apartment blocks crashing down in L'Aquila today, causing panic among rescue workers and survivors.</p>
    <p>The aftershocks caused chunks of masonry to fall from damaged buildings, including parts of the basilica in L'Aquila. The tremor – measured by the US Geological Survey at magnitude 5.6 – was felt as far away as Rome.</p>
    <p>A 76-year-old Roman man was reported to have died of a heart attack following the tremor, according to Reuters.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said 260 people including 16 children, had died, while nine bodies remained to be identified. He said about 100 of the injured were in serious condition.</p>
    <p>The Ansa news agency reported today that four students trapped in the rubble of a dormitory of the University of L'Aquila had died.</p>
    <p>The first funeral of a victim was due to take place in the town of Loreto Aprutino today, led by the archbishop of Pescara.</p>
    <p>Pope Benedict XVI said he would visit the shocked and injured people of the area as soon as possible.</p>
    <p>The pontiff praised the relief operations as an example of how solidarity could help overcome "even the most painful trials".</p>
    <p>The Vatican said he would visit the stricken area after Easter Sunday.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has said he will appeal for special European Union funding to deal with the consequences of the disaster, which came as his debt-laden government was struggling to respond to the global economic crisis.</p>
    <p>He suggested that some of the cash earmarked for infrastructure projects designed to revive the economy could be spent in the L'Aquila area.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>