<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi seeks to woo anti-immigrant party" author="John Hooper" date="2008-04-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/16/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="New PM moves to appease Northern League with pledges of lower taxes, more police and camps for jobless foreigners" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="6fbcc3adb026c789">
  <main>
    <p>Italians yesterday got their first taste of life under their new government as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> moved to appease the newly powerful Northern League with pledges of lower taxes, more police and camps for jobless foreigners.</p>
    <p>"One of the things to do is to close the frontiers and set up more camps to identify foreign citizens who don't have jobs and are forced into a life of crime," he said in a TV interview. He added that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> also needed "more local police constituting an army of good in the squares and streets, to come between Italian people and the army of evil".</p>
    <p>His comments were seemingly at odds not only with Italy's open borders under the Schengen accords but also with the temperate tone he had adopted on election night.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi appeared to be reacting to the success of the anti-immigrant Northern League. Umberto Bossi's populist movement fought its campaign on a law-and-order platform, and almost doubled its share of the vote. It will be the third biggest force in the new legislature, with its representatives in a position to deprive Berlusconi of his majority in both chambers.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's first diplomatic engagement will be with Russia's president, Vladimir Putin. The Ansa news agency reported that they would hold talks in Sardinia, where the billionaire media tycoon has a villa.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said that he had emerged from his triumph in the general election "oozing energy from every pore". His Freedom Folk and its allies won outright majorities in both houses of parliament in a vote that swept many of Italy's smaller parties out of the legislature.</p>
    <p>The leader of the right said his first cabinet meeting would abolish local authority property tax and scrap taxation of overtime and productivity bonuses. He said it would also introduce a reward of €1,000 (£800) for every newborn child.</p>
    <p>His other priorities would be to tackle the refuse crisis in Naples and to ensure that the failing national airline, Alitalia, remained "at the service of tourism and the Italian economy".</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said he planned to spend "three days a week" in Naples, though what he will do there is unclear since the piles of rubbish which accumulated earlier this year have been cleared already under a scheme introduced by the outgoing government.</p>
    <p>The incoming prime minister promised a streamlined cabinet. He has indicated he will give the finance portfolio to Giulio Tremonti, who had the post in the previous Berlusconi administration, and said his foreign minister would be the EU's justice commissioner, Franco Frattini.</p>
    <p>He has also vowed to hand ministerial portfolios to at least four women. Asked if he wanted a Spanish-style cabinet with more women than men, he said José Luis Rodriguez Zapatero had formed a team that was "too pink" and added that it would not be possible "because in Italy there is a prevalence of men".</p>
    <p>In neighbouring Albania, the prime minister, Sali Berisha, convened a press conference to hail Berlusconi's triumph. He called it "a great event for the centre-right in Italy, Albania and the whole of Europe". One of the planks in the electoral platform of Berlusconi's Freedom Folk was a plan to fund the construction of nuclear power stations in Albania and elsewhere in the Balkans to provide electricity by undersea cable to Italy.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>