<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi ‘fired up’ for Italian presidency bid – but faces obstacles" author="Lorenzo Tondo" date="2021-12-09" url="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/dec/09/berlusconi-fired-up-for-italian-presidency-bid-but-faces-obstacles" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Controversial former prime minister’s divisive personality could make it hard to muster broad support" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3ea8d87ab206574d">
  <main>
    <p>Undeterred by health woes, sex scandals and advanced age, the former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is doggedly pursuing a promise he once made to his mother: that one day he would become president.</p>
    <p>Parliament will choose a new head of state early next year and the 85-year-old is putting himself forward for a race that could transform the Italian political landscape.</p>
    <p>Candidates do not usually declare themselves in advance of the election. However, Berlusconi’s name has been put forward repeatedly in the media, and he has not tried to dampen speculation that he wants the job.</p>
    <p>“I’ve met him twice in the last two weeks and he was totally fired up,” said a lawmaker from Berlusconi’s Forza Italia party, who asked not to be named. Berlusconi, who was seriously ill with Covid-19 last year, is ploughing ahead with his unofficial campaigning, presenting himself as an experienced elder statesman of European politics.</p>
    <p>The billionaire media mogul remains a highly controversial figure, however. He was temporarily barred from public office after a conviction for tax fraud in 2013, and is still on trial for allegedly bribing witnesses in an underage prostitution case tied to his infamous “bunga bunga” sex parties of more than a decade ago.</p>
    <p>Analysts believe that such a divisive personality will find it hard to muster the broad support needed to become president, a role whose holder serves as the problem-solver in Italian politics and is regularly called upon – as the incumbent, Sergio Mattarella, has been – to resolve government deadlocks.</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta, leader of the centre-left Democratic party (PD), has already ruled out backing Berlusconi. He said the election of the president “has to be based on a large majority … otherwise the government will immediately fall apart.”</p>
    <p>The parties of the far right, such as the Brothers of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, led by Giorgia Meloni, and the League, led by Matteo Salvini, also do not seem convinced.</p>
    <p>In January, Salvini said that “Berlusconi would be a great president of the republic”, but last week seemed more detached. “All candidates over 50 are eligible, there is no one more or less eligible according to Italian law,” he said.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, Italy’s longest-serving postwar prime minister – who in October said: “I think Silvio Berlusconi can be useful to the country” – last month sent an anthology of his speeches and policy priorities to almost all the nearly 1,000 parliamentarians who will elect the president, committing himself to a list of liberal values in an effort to broaden his appeal.</p>
    <p>In an abrupt U-turn, he also praised the flagship citizens’ income welfare scheme of his arch political enemy, the Five Star Movement, which he has previously likened to the Communist party.</p>
    <p>The leader of the Union of Christian Democrats (UDC), Lorenzo Cesa, said: “If Berlusconi is a candidate for the presidency of the republic, we have a duty to support him.”</p>
    <p>A winning candidate needs to secure two-thirds of votes, but if no one reaches that target in the first three rounds, the bar is lowered to 50% of votes plus one. With the maths looking difficult, some analysts believe Berlusconi is simply hoping to gain leverage to put himself in a position to act as a kingmaker.</p>
    <p>Lorenzo De Sio, head of the Italian Centre for Electoral Studies at Rome’s LUISS university, said: “He has no bargaining power if he himself is not considered plausible.”</p>
    <p>In the meantime, the Italian national newspaper il Fatto Quotidiano has launched a petition to convince members of parliament not to vote for him.</p>
    <p>“The president of the republic must be the guarantor of the constitution,” it said. “Silvio Berlusconi is the guarantor of corruption and prostitution.”</p>
    <p>The newspaper then listed a long series of legal proceedings and verdicts against Berlusconi and finally added: “For these reasons, we ask all parliamentarians not to vote him for the presidency of the republic. In fact, they shouldn’t even talk about it, and, if possible, not even think about it.”</p>
    <p>Over 160,000 people have already signed the petition.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>