<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's president refuses to sign pro-Berlusconi media bill" author="John Hooper" date="2003-12-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/dec/16/silvioberlusconi.pressandpublishing" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's head of state last night dealt Silvio Berlusconi's conservative government a humiliating blow by refusing to sign into law a bill the prime minister's critics have said will boost his already vast influence over the country's media, writes John Hooper." categories="Media" tags="Media business,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Television industry,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="befc89bc3ea1dfe9">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's head of state last night dealt Silvio Berlusconi's conservative government a deeply humiliating blow by refusing to sign into law a bill the prime minister's critics said would boost his already vast influence over the country's media.</p>
    <p>Apparently heeding the arguments of the centre-left opposition and international media watchdogs, President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi sent the bill back to parliament for further debate.</p>
    <p>His decision appeared to ensure that Mr Berlusconi would be forced to transfer one of his three free-to-air television channels to satellite - a move that would put an end, at least in the short-term, to his group's dominance of Italy's airwaves.</p>
    <p>The timing of Mr Ciampi's decision effectively guaranteed redoubled humiliation for the prime minister, who today is due to go before the European parliament, the scene of an earlier controversial clash over his conflicting interests.</p>
    <p>Last July, exasperated by the taunting of a German MEP who questioned his overlapping roles in politics and the media, Mr Berlusconi compared the MEP to a Nazi concentration camp guard. The uproar that followed ensured a calamitous start to Italy's six-month EU presidency.</p>
    <p>Last night's decision by Mr Ciampi was the first time he had refused to sign a bill into law for anything other than budgetary reasons.</p>
    <p>In a five-page letter sent to the speakers of both houses of parliament, the president said the communications bill would effectively overturn a ruling by the constitutional court stripping the prime minister of one of his terrestrial channels.</p>
    <p>As head of the government, Mr Berlusconi is also in a position to influence indirectly what is put out on the other three main channels, run by Italy's state broadcasting corporation, RAI.</p>
    <p>The proposed law would also have changed the rules in a way likely to increase the amount of advertising revenue that could be earned by any one media group. Mr Ciampi's letter said this was "not in line" with decisions made by the courts and could lead to "the creation of a dominant position".</p>
    <p>After meeting the president, Mr Berlusconi said that if the bill were returned to parliament it would not be a serious setback."If the changes [proposed by the president] were intelligent, parliament would take that into account."</p>
    <p>The government has defended its measure as promoting freedom of choice. The bill set guidelines for the introduction of digital terrestrial television in 2007, that would at least quadruple the number of channels.</p>
    <p>However, most expert commentators said it would be difficult to effect the changeover so quickly, and expressed fears that the new rules would carry over the existing "duopoly" from analogue to digital.</p>
    <p>The bill would also legalise cross-ownership of broadcast and print media from 2009 - a move which newspaper owners and editors argued could presage an invasion of the print sector by Mr Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>The opposition was not alone in its qualms. Twice during the bill's passage through the lower house, the government suffered defeats when amendments sponsored by the opposition were backed by rebel MPs of the conservative majority.</p>
    <p>When the bill cleared the upper house of parliament, RAI's head, Lucia Annunziata, announced her resignation. She said RAI was in a precarious situation in a market "distorted by conflict of interest".</p>
    <p>"Sending the bill back to parliament ... justifies 15 months of battle against an unconstitutional law which is the child of a conflict of interest," said Paolo Gentiloni of the opposition Margherita party.</p>
    <p>The head of press freedom at Europe's largest security and human rights watchdog attacked the law last week, saying it would strengthen Mr Berlusconi's grip on the media.</p>
    <p>"Italy is setting a very dangerous precedent," said Freimut Dove, the outgoing media rights monitor of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe.</p>
    <p>Parliament can now amend the bill, based on Mr Ciampi's recommendations, or vote on it again without making changes. If it passed a second time unchanged, he would be obliged to sign it.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is Italy's richest man, also owning a football team and insurance and property companies.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>