<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's naked Czech friend becomes the butt of jokes" author="Daniel McLaughlin; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-06-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/07/mirek-topolanek-czech-naked-photo" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Czech prime minister struggles to protect his dignity after being pictured naked" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Czech Republic,World news,Europe" fingerprint="fe8e522e92d058c7">
  <main>
    <p>Mirek Topolanek, the eccentric former Czech prime minister, is no stranger to problems with photographers. Last year he punched a Czech cameraman who took a picture of his sleeping baby. But this weekend he has found himself in an almost impossible struggle to protect his dignity, after being shown naked and in a state of arousal next to Silvio Berlusconi's swimming pool.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister had gained an injunction to prevent up to 700 photographs of private parties at his Sardinian villa appearing in the Italian media. But the decision by the Spanish paper El País to publish five images from May 2008 appears to have blown Topolanek's cover, even though the paper pixelated the faces. After denying that any embarrassing photographs could exist of his visit last year to Sardinia, Topolanek admitted that he was the naked man standing beside an unidentified woman on a sun-lounger.</p>
    <p>The Czech media had recognised his white rubber wristband - a sign of support for the anti-Castro movement in Cuba - given to Topolanek by George W Bush during a visit to the United States last year. "It is me in the photograph," Topolanek said. "But it has been modified. The picture is not authentic. This is absolutely insolent interference in my privacy. Besides, there is nothing wrong or compromising. It was a private holiday in closed premises, not outside on a beach."</p>
    <p>Noting that the pictures were published in the left-leaning El País on the day Czechs started voting in European elections, Topolanek said he "did not know that these elections were so important for European socialists that they had to come up with such ridiculous attacks and manipulations".</p>
    <p>As much of Prague has gone online to enjoy a laugh at the former prime minister's expense, Topolanek's opponents have been quick to deny his allegations of political skulduggery.</p>
    <p>Jiri Paroubek, whose Social Democrats are the main rivals to Topolanek's centre-right Civic Democrat party, called the accusations a sign of the former premier's "mental exhaustion".</p>
    <p>Professional photographer Hana Kalvachova said technical analysis suggested there had been no manipulation of the picture.</p>
    <p>Political analyst Jiri Pehe believes Czechs won't be too shocked. He said: "The pictures won't have any big effect on Topolanek's popularity ... Czech politics has so many strange birds that he is seen as one of the flock."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>