<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi joins Salvini on campaign trail as Italian right seeks gains" author="Angela Giuffrida" date="2019-02-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/07/berlusconi-campaigns-for-centre-right-in-regional-italian-election" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Ex-prime minister met Matteo Salvini in show of unity among rightwing parties in Abruzzo" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Politics,World news,Europe,Matteo Salvini" fingerprint="7394d175b3e0d31d">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has returned to the campaign trail alongside Matteo Salvini as his rightwing coalition is revived ahead of elections in the central Italian region of Abruzzo on Sunday.</p>
    <p>The former prime minister’s appearance at a press conference on Thursday was his first major campaign outing since March last year when the same alliance, made up of his Forza Italia and the two far-right parties, Salvini’s League and Brothers of Italy,<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ng-interactive/2018/mar/05/italian-elections-2018-full-results-renzi-berlusconi"> took 38% of the vote in general elections</ref>.</p>
    <p>The 82-year-old met Salvini, interior minister in the Italian government, and Georgia Meloni, who heads Brothers of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, in the regional capital of Pescara on Thursday to give a show of unity in a region that would be a strategic win for the group.</p>
    <p>The alliance has put forward Marco Marsilio, a politician with Brothers of Italy, to compete in the regional vote, which is likely to lead to the ousting of the centre-left Democratic party. Recent polls put the centre-right in the lead, with about 39%, followed by the anti-establishment populists of the Five Star Movement (M5S) at 32.2% and a centre-left coalition at 28.2%.</p>
    <p>Should Marsilio win, Berlusconi – who said he has always “been in love with Abruzzo” – has pledged to return to Pescara once a month for the first six months to assist him with a programme that includes investment in infrastructure and hospitals, and creating jobs to stop young people from leaving.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi’s campaigning has included a return visit to L’Aquila, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/06/italy-earthquake-victims">almost 10 years after over 300 people were killed and thousands left homeless by an earthquake</ref>. Berlusconi was prime minister at the time and kept a promise to build new homes for the displaced. “It was very emotional to go back there and to meet the people living in those homes,” he said.</p>
    <p>If the coalition wins in Abruzzo, it would be a blow for M5S, which is governing nationally alongside the League. M5S won almost 40% of the vote in Abruzzo at the general election.</p>
    <p>There had been speculation that Salvini, whose popularity has surged since becoming deputy prime minister and interior minister last June, might be tempted to ditch Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>But Berlusconi, who has led Italy three times, said in an interview with Corriere della Sera on Wednesday that the League “has no vocation for suicide”.</p>
    <p>“Relations with Salvini are always good, inspired by a mutual loyalty even when we disagree,” he added.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who has made comebacks from a tax-fraud conviction, sex scandals and health woes, also announced in January that he <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jan/17/silvio-berlusconi-intends-stand-european-parliament-billionaire-former-italian-prime-minister-tax-fraud">would run as a candidate</ref> in the European elections. Forza Italia belongs to the European People’s party (EPP).</p>
    <p>He said on Thursday that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> must return to being a continent “that counts” and not one of “divided states”.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>