<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The day Italy says no to Berlusconi | Roberto Mancini" author="Roberto Mancini" date="2009-12-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/dec/04/italy-demonstration-no-berlusconi-day" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Roberto Mancini: A demonstration organised online for 'No Berlusconi Day' could mark a shift in attitudes and bring hope for Italian politics" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Protest,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3fa5d26b9803c615">
  <main>
    <p>Tomorrow is <ref target="http://www.noberlusconiday.org/?page_id=499">No Berlusconi Day</ref> in Italy. Demonstrators will assemble in the centre of Rome, to call for the premier's resignation.</p>
    <p>The rally has been organised exclusively by word of mouth and – this is a first for Italy – via Facebook, blogs and tweets. Up to now, only <ref target="http://www.beppegrillo.it/en/">Beppe Grillo</ref>, the comedian and activist, had used a blog to assemble friends and sympathisers.</p>
    <p>Although the demonstration should attract an impressive turnout, the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_%28Italy%29">Partito Democratico</ref> (PD), the main opposition party, led by the newly elected secretary, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pier_Luigi_Bersani">Pier Luigi Bersani</ref>, has officially decided not to take part in it. The PD, as always, is torn between an inborn tendency to try to keep fellow members happy and a deeply felt desire to oppose Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>So while we wait for the Democrats to solve the Hamlet-like dilemma that has paralysed them for years, the No Berlusconi Day will be the day of the other parliamentary opposition party, <ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italia_dei_Valori">l'Italia dei Valori</ref> (IDV).</p>
    <p>In the IDV, the two most interesting characters – the founder of the party, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/profile/antonio-di-pietr">Antonio Di Pietro</ref> and the MEP, <ref target="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/members/public/yourMep/view.do?name=de+magistris&amp;partNumber=1&amp;language=EN&amp;id=97129">Luigi De Magistris</ref> – are both former public prosecutors with similar histories. Di Pietro was a prosecutor in the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani_pulite">Mani Pulite</ref> investigations and trials in the early nineties. De Magistris worked more recently on investigations (<ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luigi_de_Magistris">Poseidon and Why not</ref>) into political corruption and misuse of European community subsidies in the Calabrian town of Catanzaro. During their investigations, Di Pietro and De Magistris revealed their talents for detective work, both of them being methodical, reserved, incorruptible and totally devoted to upholding the law. They demonstrated their modern Sherlock Holmes qualities in their detection and understanding of the sophisticated inner workings of white-collar fraud.</p>
    <p>In any other country they would be considered the heroes of a civilised society. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> however, where a worrying proportion of the public sympathises with thieves, the two magistrates were forced to hang up their robes to save themselves from slanderous attacks.</p>
    <p>Their careers as magistrates recall that of the judge, <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00kjhv3">Giovanni Falcone</ref>. Falcone has been sanctified by his assassination but was continuously thwarted when he was alive, his investigations hindered by obstacles and sabotaged from within the bench.</p>
    <p>Di Pietro and De Magistris were persecuted for many years by accusations and disciplinary measures. They haven't been forgiven for adhering faithfully to the constitutional motto, displayed in every courtroom across the land, that "we are all equal in the eyes of the law".</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>The system has a built-in distrust of honest and respectable people who decide to become judges. If they also believe that the powerful must be held to the same standards as everyone else, they are considered dangerous subversives.</p>
    <p>As <ref target="http://sottoosservazione.wordpress.com/2009/12/03/falcone-la-verita-sui-pentiti/">Giancarlo Caselli</ref>, former public prosecutor in Palermo and one of the most honourable figures in the Italian judiciary, who was deliberately transferred from the anti-mafia public prosecutor's office said a few days ago: "As long as you investigate on [Salvatore] <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvatore_Riina">Riina</ref> or [Bernardo] <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Provenzano">Provenzano</ref> you're fine. But when, following real and legal assumptions, you start to look into "high-level" suspects, you have to take into account that it's then that trouble starts ... and instead of members of the mafia and their accomplices, it's the anti-mafia magistrates who end up in the dock."</p>
    <p>Will the IDV emerge as the most important opposition power in Italy on Saturday? By actively endorsing this protest it probably will. A demonstration like this, organised autonomously through the free initiative of the younger generation, who describe themselves as "not politically involved or belonging to any parties", is of great importance.</p>
    <p>If young web-literate Italians can show that they are immune to the propaganda on television from Mr B's media system, then maybe Italy can still hope to stop its decline. The road will still be long and hard but maybe on Saturday (get there if you can: meet at 2pm in Piazza della Repubblica in Rome) this new hope will be born.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>