<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi pleads for big election majority" author="John Hooper" date="2008-04-11" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/11/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Polls indicate media mogul is on the brink of a remarkable comeback, two years after being edged from power" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="77f973359237d74d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi yesterday appealed to Italian voters to give him a huge majority at the general election on Sunday and Monday.</p>
    <p>He said that "to really govern" he needed a margin of at least 20 seats in the senate, the upper house of the Italian parliament. That would allow him "to take, if necessary, difficult and unpopular decisions".</p>
    <p>Polls have indicated that the 71-year-old media mogul is on the brink of a remarkable comeback, two years after being edged from power. But, because of a ban on polling in the final fortnight of the campaign, the most recent soundings - showing Berlusconi leading by 5% to 9% - date from the end of March. They also suggested that a third of voters had yet to make up their minds.</p>
    <p>Though Berlusconi told La Stampa newspaper he was confident his right-wing Freedom Folk would secure the necessary majority in parliament, his rivals pounced on his appeal as evidence he was uncertain of victory. A narrow majority could also leave him a political hostage to the whims of the anti-immigrant Northern League, with which his party is allied.</p>
    <p>The billionaire candidate's tone has grown more shrill in the final days of the campaign. On Tuesday Berlusconi, who has been investigated - though never convicted - for a string of alleged financial offences, said he would introduce mental health checks for prosecutors. Yesterday he lashed out at his main rival, Walter Veltroni, saying: "The truth is, he remains a communist."</p>
    <p>Veltroni, 52, a former youth leader of the old Italian Communist party, leads a newly unified centre-left party. The Democratic party includes both ex-Marxists like himself and the more progressive wing of the defunct Christian Democrat movement.</p>
    <p>A former mayor of Rome, Veltroni won an endorsement from the actor George Clooney, who owns a house in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. Clooney said he "talks of hope".</p>
    <p>Italians will go to the polls against a background of economic gloom. Last week the International Monetary Fund forecast the economy would grow by 0.3% this year - less than a quarter of the rate in the rest of the euro zone.</p>
    <p>Veltroni's programme includes tax cuts funded by a huge sell-off of public assets. That, however, is exactly what Berlusconi is promising.</p>
    <p>Both men are also vowing to slash the cost of Italy's sprawling public administration. The similarity of their manifestos led to early speculation that they were preparing the ground for a German-style grand coalition if neither won an outright majority. But Berlusconi appeared yesterday to rule that out, saying the centre-left leader had "really disappointed me".</p>
    <p>Much will depend on the showing of two smaller groups, the centre-right Union of Christian and Centre Democrats, and the Rainbow Left, an alliance of Greens and Marxists.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>