<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi faces tax fraud inquiry" author="Dominic Timms" date="2003-06-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jun/13/pressandpublishing.broadcasting" hostname="theguardian.com" description="12.30pm: Italy's billionaire media mogul prime minister Silvio Berlusconi is being investigated over suspected tax fraud and false accounting, writes Dominic Timms." categories="Media" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Television industry,Media business,Media,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3e6a820a9064c55c">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's billionaire media mogul prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is being investigated by magistrates over suspected tax fraud and false accounting.</p>
    <p>Already on trial for allegedly bribing judges in the 1980s, Mr Berlusconi faces a further investigation into deals made by Italian broadcaster Mediaset relating to the acquisition of US film rights. Mr Berlusconi controls Mediaset through his family's holding company, Fininvest.</p>
    <p>The inquiry concerns deals made in 1994 and 1995 by which Mediaset channelled the rights through two offshore companies.</p>
    <p>Two magistrates quoted by Italian newspapers said Mediaset was suspected of using the two companies to artificially inflate the price of the rights declared to Italian tax authorities by around £100m.</p>
    <p>According to reports today in La Repubblica and Corriere della Sera details of the transaction emerged after magistrates approached the justice ministry in an attempt to enlist help from US investigators.</p>
    <p>The Mediaset chairman, Fedele Confalonieri, and other former executives of the company are also being investigated.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi was Italian prime minister for seven months in 1994 before taking up the post again in 2001.</p>
    <p>News of the investigation comes just weeks before Italy is due to take over the presidency of the European Union.</p>
    <p>Two years ago Italian tax authorities searched Mediaset's offices as well as those of parent company Fininvest, seizing company documents.</p>
    <p>Mediaset said at the time it had shown the "absolute correctness of its actions" and rigorously denied the allegations.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is already on trial in Milan for allegedly bribing judges in the 1980s relating to the takeover of food giant SME. He denies the charges.</p>
    <p>Although parliamentary immunity for crimes was abolished in 1993, allowing judges in Milan to purge Italy's old political class in the Tangentopoli trials, Berlusconi's allies are trying to rush through a bill giving him and other senior figures immunity from prosecution while in office.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who started out as a singer on a cruise ship, is Italy's richest man with a personal fortune estimated at £9bn. He owns 48% of Mediaset.</p>
    <p>As prime minister he also indirectly controls Italy's state broadcaster RAI, which he is accused of trying to run down to win more viewers for Mediaset's three channels, Canale 5, Italia 1 and Rete 4.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>