<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's problems go deeper than Berlusconi | Alberto Toscano" author="Alberto Toscano" date="2010-10-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/oct/06/italy-silvio-berlusconi-public-face" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alberto Toscano: The bungling prime minister is only the public face of a morally corrupt society to which a weak opposition poses little alternative" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="97ac710904a7eb41">
  <main>
    <p>In the last few years Italian politics has mainly featured in international media on the occasion of <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/5124606/Silvio-Berlusconis-top-10-gaffes-and-pranks.html">Silvio Berlusconi's countless gaffes</ref>, or the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/31/silvio-berlusconi-profile">scandals about his procurement of escorts and promotion of glamour models</ref> and TV hostesses to political office. This low spectacle has repeated itself with the latest governmental crisis, in which the president of the chamber of deputies, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/sep/29/silvio-berlusconi-mps-confidence-vote">Gianfranco Fini, and his followers broke away from Il Popolo della Libertà</ref> (Freedom People) party. Berlusconi's routine buffoonery and sexism have now <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/03/silvio-berlusconi-under-fire-jokes">been joined by blasphemy</ref> after he used the Italian language's most offensive religious oath – cue the insincere outrage of the opposition and the condemnation of the church, which he has long tried to woo with his views on euthanasia and abortion.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's persona, equal parts cruise-ship entertainer and megalomaniac company boss (<ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article6605531.ece">his previous vocations</ref>), has monopolised Italian politics for more than 15 years. Drawing attention to his character rather than his policies, and forcing the opposition on to a media terrain he dominates, Berlusconi's faux pas could almost be seen as part of a decoy strategy, averting any real discussion of the country and its problems.</p>
    <p>But one should resist the temptation – bolstered by his blatant use of political power to thwart numerous legal proceedings – to imagine that Berlusconi represents Italy's chief problem (the Economist magazine, for example, believes the Italian prime minister's conflicts of interests and endless buffoonery besmirch the honourable cause of free-market liberalism). This notion also lies behind the attempt to organise Italy's own "colour revolution" – the <ref target="http://www.wantedinrome.com/articles/complete_articles.php?id_art=1022">Popolo Viola (Purple People)</ref>, which recently brought together disgruntled communists and social-democrats, an anti-political movement around comedian Beppe Grillo, and followers of the <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article6857454.ece">ex-anti-corruption judge Antonio di Pietro</ref> for a <ref target="http://translate.google.co.uk/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=it&amp;u=http://noberlusconiday2.wordpress.com/&amp;ei=Xw2rTJL9J5G04AabkcHtBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=translate&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCMQ7gEwAQ&amp;prev=/search%3Fq%3DNo%2BB%2BDay%2B2%26hl%3Den">No B Day 2</ref> (a no-to-Berlusconi protest), the use of English Twitter-speak a further sign of opposition disorientation.</p>
    <p>Elections are likely in March, and with Berlusconi's star waning it is worth considering what may lie on the other side of <ref target="http://translate.google.co.uk/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=it&amp;u=http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlusconismo&amp;ei=ehCrTMmGOY2J4gbX0_jUBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=translate&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCEQ7gEwAA&amp;prev=/search%3Fq%3DBerlusconismo%26hl%3Den%26prmd%3Dvn"> Berlusconismo</ref>. The governing coalition, with its volatile blend of racist northern secessionism, postfascist authoritarian liberalism and Berlusconi's entrepreneurial populism, has deflected attention from the grim economic climate by persecuting migrants and catering to the propertied. Raw egotism – whether individual, corporate or regional – has been raised to the level of principle. The ubiquitous talk of "freedom" means licence for some, insecurity for the rest.</p>
    <p>Unemployment among the young and women <ref target="http://www.presstv.ir/detail/143765.html">is rampant</ref>, labour precariousness widespread, and Italy has one of the worst records in Europe <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/11/business/global/11trial.html">for deaths at work</ref>. The government, despite the massive burden of women's unpaid work (some statistics put their real working week at 60 hours), seeks to raise their retirement age. Legislation <ref target="http://www.nature.com/news/2010/100630/full/466016b.html">entrenching unpaid work for researchers and lecturers</ref> is yet another index of the utter disregard for social progress in any form. A country whose postwar constitution officially subordinated free markets to social welfare is now rife with forms of hyper-exploitation in which hunger for short-term profit translates into <ref target="http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/44/44/41524626.pdf">extreme inequality</ref> and a deplorable degeneration in civil and social rights – witness <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/a9e53516-cbf5-11df-bd28-00144feab49a.html">Fiat's latest attack on collective bargaining, in which the company's whole future in Italy is at stake</ref>.</p>
    <p>These are some of the realities behind Berlusconi's obscene clowning. Previous centre-left governments are by no means innocent in this regard, having themselves promoted many of the "liberalising" policies that have created such a dismal outlook for ordinary people. A possible realignment of politics to the centre (bizarrely, this may include the postfascist Fini) is unlikely to tackle any of these problems. Removing Berlusconi, without radically addressing how far the whole society has regressed in the last two decades, will simply mean <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> will become, to borrow one of the centre-left's slogans, "a normal country" – that is to say, in the present European and global context, increasingly unequal, prejudiced and fearful.</p>
    <p>Though they've yet to cohere into a unified platform, recent mobilisations against the privatisation of utilities and the dilapidation of education, together with union activism against the blackmail of "flexibility" threatened by Fiat, show that a social opposition to Berlusconi exists.</p>
    <p>In this supposedly post-ideological age of the "centre ground", electoral expediency would seem to counsel against radicalism and for moderation. Yet the trajectory of the Italian left, losing conviction and consensus the more concessions it made to the idea that capitalism is the only game in town, is instructive. It is time to abandon the delusion that one can enact social-democratic ends with neoliberal means, and to find a contemporary vocabulary to address the often one-sided conflict between labour and capital which lies behind rising inequality and work "flexibility". Otherwise, Italy will simply continue on the same disastrous path with a more presentable face at its helm.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>