<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi on the brink: key players in the Italian crisis" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2011-11-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/berlusconi-brink-key-players-crisis" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The political figures who have worked with the embattled Italian prime minister – and those who may replace him" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Eurozone crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news,Business" fingerprint="bcec822d9aaff461">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">Giorgio Napolitano</head>
    <p>Italy's president, a former communist, has won plaudits, influence and huge support from Italians for his calm monitoring of, and frequent intervention in, Silvio Berlusconi's attempts to bend the rules and disentangle himself from his trials.</p>
    <p>Once accused by Berlusconi of being incurably leftwing, Napolitano has recently been praised by the prime minister for giving him time to put together a package of much-needed economic reforms.</p>
    <p>Naples-born Napolitano, 86, boasts the stamina of a much younger man, recently listening to a speech attentively as Berlusconi, 75, slumbered beside him.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Gianni Letta</head>
    <p>Dubbed Silvio Berlusconi's Cardinal Richelieu, Gianni Letta may have to step out of the shadow of his long-time boss if called on to lead a new centre-right government.</p>
    <p>A former journalist who joined Berlusconi's business empire in 1987, Letta, 76, has been named cabinet secretary to successive Berlusconi governments and has toiled as the prime minister's fixer while taking a role in overseeing Italy's secret services.</p>
    <p>A devoted Catholic who was appointed a gentleman-in-waiting to the pope, Letta has also served as Berlusconi's point man with the Vatican, calming the nerves of cardinals as the media magnate's sex scandals broke.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Renato Schifani</head>
    <p>The Sicilian lawyer and former Christian Democrat Schifani joined Berlusconi's Forza Italia party in 1995 and rose to become chief speaker in the Senate, which means he would become president should the incumbent, Giorgio Napolitano, die.</p>
    <p>During Berlusconi's 2001-2006 government, Schifani put his name to the 2003 bill designed to give the prime minister legal immunity. The law was thrown out by Italy's constitutional court, as was a similar measure introduced in 2008.</p>
    <p>Schifani's senior role in government has been questioned given the mafia ties of some of his former business colleagues in Palermo, although Schifani was instrumental in toughening up jail time for mobsters in 2002.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Mario Monti</head>
    <p>An economist and former EU commissioner, Monti, 67, is the most widely touted candidate to run a possible technical government of experts who could pass the unpalatable reforms demanded by the EU and IMF.</p>
    <p>A graduate of Milan's Bocconi University and Yale, where he studied under the Nobel-winning economist James Tobin, Monti investigated and blocked the proposed General Electric-Honeywell merger in 2001.</p>
    <p>A member of the Bilderberg group, president of Bocconi and an adviser to Goldman Sachs, Monti recently called for the introduction of Eurobonds – which would be backed by all eurozone countries – as a way of solving the European debt crisis.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Pier Luigi Bersani</head>
    <p>A philosophy graduate and son of a mechanic from Emilia Romagna, Bersani joined the Communist party before switching to the centre-left and becoming the leader of Italy's main opposition Democratic party. Considered a reliable pair of hands, Bersani, 60, has lacked the quick wit and charisma to go toe-to-toe with Silvio Berlusconi. Blessed with a better sense of self promotion, he might have pointed out that as a minister in the 2006-2008 Prodi government he sought to pass the kind of liberalisation reforms that Berlusconi has failed to produce since, leaving the economy floundering and incurring the wrath of markets.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>