<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Q&amp;A: The David Mills affair" author="John Hooper" date="2009-02-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/tessajowell-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The lowdown on the corruption trial involving the estranged husband of Tessa Jowell" categories="Politics" tags="Tessa Jowell,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,UK news,Politics,World news,David Mills,Europe" fingerprint="39be808d90a514db">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">Why was the</hi>
      <hi rend="#b">husband of a British minister on trial in Italy?</hi>
    </head>
    <p>David Mills is a lawyer. For several years he advised Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, helping him create a network of offshore companies that has been the subject of several court cases in which Berlusconi has been a defendant. Italian prosecutors initially took the view that Mills was simply an adviser who bore no responsibility for any alleged wrongdoing. But in 2003 they began investigating him, too.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">What was he accused of?</hi>
    </head>
    <p>There are two linked cases. In both, Mills and Berlusconi denied wrongdoing. One involves the trading of film rights through offshore companies. He was accused of helping Berlusconi evade tax and launder money, but that case was suspended after the Berlusconi government passed a law giving Italy's PM and other officials immunity from prosecution. In the second case Mills was accused of taking a bribe to withhold evidence in two earlier trials in which Berlusconi was a defendant and Mills a witness for the prosecution.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">How did this case </hi>
      <hi rend="#b">come about?</hi>
    </head>
    <p>The prosecutors had a letter written by Mills to his accountant. In it, he said he had "turned some very tricky corners so as to keep Mr B out of a great deal of trouble". Mills was questioned by the prosecutors and confirmed the substance of the letter. He subsequently clarified this. He said the money came from a man called Diego Attanasio.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">What evidence is there that the money came from Berlusconi?</hi>
    </head>
    <p>Prosecutors only produced the letter from Mills to his accountant.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">What evidence has Mills produced that the money did not come from Berlusconi?</hi>
    </head>
    <p>His lawyer laid several hundred documents before the court.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>