<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's centre-left reaches out to Beppe Grillo" author="John Hooper" date="2013-02-26" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/26/italy-bersani-coalition-beppe-grillo" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Democratic Party leader Pier Luigi Bersani challenges the Five Star founder to bring his rising party into a new coalition" categories="World news" tags="Italian elections 2013,Europe,Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Beppe Grillo" fingerprint="87fdf9353120c56f">
  <main>
    <p>The leader of Italy's centre-left, Pier Luigi Bersani, set out to lure <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/beppe-grillo">Beppe Grillo</ref> and his Five Star Movement (M5S) into a coalition government after their spectacular breakthrough in the general election.</p>
    <p>At a press conference in Rome, a weary-looking Bersani said it was time for the upstart movement to do something more than just demand the removal of Italy's mainstream politicians.</p>
    <p>"Up to now, they have been saying: 'All go home.' But now they're here, too. So either they go home as well, or they say what they want to do for their country and their children."</p>
    <p>Grillo had earlier said his followers in parliament would not join a coalition, but would consider proposals "law by law, reform by reform".</p>
    <p>Bersani said that since his centre-left, four-party alliance had won an outright majority in the lower house of the Italian parliament, and more seats than any other grouping in the senate, it had a responsibility to suggest ways in which Italy could be governed, despite the deadlock in the upper house caused by the M5S's stunning gains.</p>
    <p>Pouring cold water on the idea floated by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> of a grand coalition with the right, he proposed a government committed to a radical overhaul of Italy's politics and institutions, outlining a five-point plan for sweeping reform.</p>
    <p>In a clear attempt to lure M5S into the mainstream, he hinted that Grillo's movement, as the party with most votes, should get the speakership of the lower house.</p>
    <p>Talking to reporters outside his home in Genoa, Grillo, who has always denied being the leader of the M5S, announced he would be representing his movement in the negotiations with President Giorgio Napolitano aimed at forming a new government. But he made clear that the movement he co-founded just over three years ago remained as anti-establishment as ever.</p>
    <p>He said he would like to see the iconoclastic Nobel prize winning playwright and actor Dario Fo succeed Napolitano as head of state. And he declared that Italy was in the midst of a "generational war".</p>
    <p>Grillo also predicted that Italy's next government would last no more than six months. "They won't be able to govern," he said. "Whether I'm there or not, they won't be able govern."</p>
    <p>Bersani made it clear that he considered his alliance to have been defeated in the election. "We have not won, even if we finished first," he said. He also acknowledged that the elections signified "a rejection of politics as it has been presented in recent years: [a rejection of] inefficient institutions and of politics that have appeared as morally non-credible."</p>
    <p>The five points on which he was inviting a consensus were: reform of the institutions; reform of political parties; legislation on public and private morality, an apparent reference to measures to tackle corruption; the defence of those most exposed to the effects of the recession; and a commitment to a new European employment policy.</p>
    <p>But, in a reference to the thorniest issue that is likely to lie between him and Grillo, Bersani made it clear he would not compromise on his party's policy towards the EU or the euro. Grillo has called for a referendum on membership of the single currency. But, said Bersani, "Italy out of the euro would run into disaster."</p>
    <p>Though at one point he left open the door a crack to Berlusconi's Freedom People (PdL) movement, he later said that he and the leader of the right would "confront each other in parliament".</p>
    <p>Bersani was not the only one to be courting Grillo, the new kingmaker of Italian politics. His overtures to M5S came as his leading partner in the centre-left, Nichi Vendola, dropped a hint he might be considering a separate deal with Grillo's movement. Vendola, the governor of Puglia, where the centre-left took one of its worst hidings in the election, is also the leader of the radical Left, Ecology and Freedom (SEL) party. In a message sent through Twitter, he flattered the founder of the M5S, saying: "Grillo is the true winner of the elections." And he added: "Phoney alliances will not be enough."</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>