<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Tim Parks on why Silvio Berlusconi is scandal-proof in Italy" author="Tim Parks; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-06-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/23/silvio-berlusconi-escort-girls-scandal" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Tim Parks: The intriguing thing is not Silvio Berlusconi but the Italian people" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="3efa921fc204c709">
  <main>
    <p>The intriguing thing is not <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> but the Italian people. So it is alleged that the prime minister has been paying escort girls to visit his parties. There are tapes and photos. Silvio breaks off a session with one girl to phone through congratulations to the newly elected Obama.</p>
    <p>Is anybody surprised by these claims? No. Is Berlusconi likely to fall over this, as the British papers wishfully suggest? Absolutely not.</p>
    <p>This is not Britain. This is not Gordon Brown. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> may have a single currency but it has many mindsets and they are not growing any closer. I have yet to meet an Italian who thinks Berlusconi should resign over this. The courts found British lawyer David Mills guilty of accepting money from Berlusconi to give false testimony but the prime minister did not resign. It is hard to imagine the crime that would force him out.</p>
    <p>No one in Berlusconi's party wants him to go. He created it. Everybody owes their position to him and will disappear, like the party itself, when he goes.</p>
    <p>The newspapers enjoy having it both ways: pages of juicy details, then editorials saying how tacky it is to reduce politics to gossip. The media controlled by Berlusconi complains of an orchestrated conspiracy. The concept of loyal opposition doesn't exist in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. There are supporters, such as former minister Vittorio Sgarbi ("If Berlusconi does not gain sexual satisfaction he governs badly"), and there are conspirators.</p>
    <p>The church, so loud on contraception, euthanasia and abortion, lies low. Berlusconi is seen as more pro-family and pro-life than the opposition. A family is still a family even when the husband is on the sofa promising an escort girl some help with her application for planning permission.</p>
    <p>One says "the opposition" but there is none. Since the collapse of Romano Prodi's hopelessly fragmented coalition the left has evaporated, not only in parliament, but in people's heads. Berlusconi has achieved the status of the renaissance Signore. More than popular, he is inevitable. There are no heirs, no credible opponents. Democracy has not been officially suspended but Berlusconi will win every election, and not just because he owns half the TV stations. The country is in the grip of a deep fatalism. At 72, Berlusconi will not go until the Lord takes him. Then the Italians will heave a sigh of relief, as people do when the boss finally kicks it.</p>
    <p>Tim Parks is a British author and long-time resident of the Verona area. His recent books include A Season with Verona, and Medici Money. His translations include works by Roberto Calasso, Antonio Tabucchi and Alberto Moravia.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>