<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Who else but Silvio Berlusconi? | Alexander Lee" author="Alexander Lee" date="2011-01-24" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/jan/24/silvio-berlusconi-scandal-italian-pm" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alexander Lee: The Italian PM is up to his neck in scandal, but you wouldn't know it from the polls. The problem is who would replace him" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" fingerprint="3eb6522b5627c705">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi is on the ropes. Under investigation for paying for sex with a 17-year-old girl, extortion, and abuse of power, Italy's flamboyant prime minister is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/14/berlusconi-investigated-teenage-prostitution-case">facing the biggest challenge of his life</ref>. Sex scandals often spell the end of a political career; and the more scandals that surround a party, the more it should suffer at the polls. But strangely enough, il Cavaliere – as Berlusconi is known – seems to be experiencing precisely the opposite.</p>
    <p>In a poll published in Sunday's Corriere della Sera, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/23/silvio-berlusconi-poll-party-support">support for Berlusconi's Freedom People party (PdL)</ref> has actually increased since December, from <ref target="http://in.reuters.com/article/idINIndia-54343720110123">27.6% to 30.2%</ref>. In the same period, support for every major opposition party has declined. The Democratic party (PD) and the Italy of Values party (IdV), the centre-left parties that have spearheaded the attacks on Berlusconi's probity, have <ref target="http://www.sondaggipoliticoelettorali.it/asp/visualizza_sondaggio.asp?idsondaggio=4322">declined from 25.0% to 24.5% and from 6.2% to 5.5% respectively</ref>. Berlusconi is defying political gravity.</p>
    <p>So why has he managed it? There are two reasons.</p>
    <p>First, however shocking it appears, the sex scandal fits very nicely with Berlusconi's carefully crafted public image. Since he first entered politics in 1994, Berlusconi has built his success on presenting himself as the sort of person with whom everyone can sympathise and whom everyone wants to be. A bon viveur who makes no secret of his love of wealth, wine, and women, he has projected an image of himself not only as a home-grown, self-made entrepreneur, but also as an ordinary Joe who doesn't hide his all-too-human failings, and who has the same worldly tastes as the average man on the street. He lives the Italian dream. He's a football lover who owns AC Milan, he's a businessman who made it big, he's a TV magnate who likes to surround himself with beautiful women. And his alleged involvement with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/17/berlusconi-paid-sex-women-milan-home">Karima "Ruby" el-Mahroug</ref> only serve to emphasise key elements of this image. Regardless of the morality of the case, Berlusconi continues to live a life to which many Italians aspire.</p>
    <p>Second, the more pressure builds on Berlusconi to resign, the more Italians are forced to contemplate the alternatives. They aren't pretty. There are really only three options if Berlusconi resigns. The most likely is an unstable centre-right coalition under the ambitious and divisive Gianfranco Fini. Not only is Fini a former fascist who has previously expressed admiration for Mussolini, but he has also thrown away his ability to marshal the centre-right effectively with at least two unsuccessful bids to topple Berlusconi in the past. Rightly, many Italians continue to perceive Fini as untrustworthy at best, and dangerous at worst.</p>
    <p>The next most likely possibility is a minority centre-left coalition headed by the ineffective leader of the PD, Pier Luigi Bersani. Bersani's big problem is that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/17/italy-left-silvio-berlusconi">the centre-left is hopelessly fragmented</ref>, and has failed to offer any coherent solution to Italy's worsening economic woes. Neither the PD nor any of its allies are able to convince Italians that they can be trusted with government.</p>
    <p>The final option is compromise. In the absence of an obvious successor, President Giorgio Napolitano could decide to appoint a technocrat to head a caretaker government before holding elections. The absence of a popular mandate and the debilitating effects of an election at a time of economic instability make this a deeply unpopular option.</p>
    <p>For a majority of Italians, therefore, it's a case of "better the devil you know".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>