<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi may be gone, but there is little unity in Italy | Alberto Nardelli" author="Alberto Nardelli" date="2011-11-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/14/silvio-berlusconi-unity-italy-mario-monti" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alberto Nardelli: Mario Monti is already coming under pressure from competing demands – and divisions aren't limited to the corridors of power" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" fingerprint="3e985a45d0a57f5d">
  <main>
    <p>The Silvio Berlusconi era is over. Following the approval of an economic package on Saturday, Italy's president Giorgio Napolitano asked <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/13/mario-monti-new-era-italy?newsfeed=true">Mario Monti</ref>, a former European commissioner, to form a new government on Sunday evening.</p>
    <p>Monti accepted the mandate conditionally, which in practical terms means he needs to consult Italy's political parties to confirm their support. Monti is expected to conclude his consultations and have a cabinet ready in the next 48 hours, and to then receive the confidence of both chambers of the house by the end of the week.</p>
    <p>With the exception of the Northern League, all of Italy's main parties have voiced their support for a Monti government and the need to implement measures <ref target="http://www.ilsole24ore.com/pdf2010/SoleOnLine5/_Oggetti_Correlati/Documenti/Notizie/2011/11/risposta-italia-ue.pdf?uuid=0b3a6d38-0d6b-11e1-bd65-63822369b075">agreed with the EU</ref>.</p>
    <p>But, reading between the lines of the parties' statements of support, each has indicated different preferences and conditions. Battlelines are being drawn up around the duration of the government and its mandate: Pier Ferdinando Casini's UDC (Italy's centre party) has indicated that he would like to see a Monti government until the end of the current parliament (2013); others ask that the government navigates the country through the winter ahead of a spring election; the left-leaning Democratic party is keen to see an electoral reform as part of Monti's tenure; Berlusconi's PDL insists that the new government stick to implementing measures agreed with the EU.</p>
    <p>The parties will be keen to show unity on the surface, but Italy's election campaign has, in fact, already begun. As Monti beavers away and foreign media wonders what Silvio will do next, in the smoky backrooms Berlusconi's Freedom party risks imploding and a void on the centre right is likely to emerge. On the left, Luigi Bersani, leader of the Democratic party – who would be favourite to win were there an election tomorrow – could soon be facing a leadership battle. As always, the kingmakers will be Italy's flirtatious centre and Catholic parties – recent polls show them above 10%, benefitting the most from the current crisis.</p>
    <p>Italy's divisions extend beyond its corridors of power, and into the country's streets and the pages of its media. For the jubilant majority, with Berlusconi gone, the country has been rescued from the precipice of certain destruction. Anti-Berlusconism was their sole mission and political programme. For others a "technocratic coup" is taking place and will inevitably end up with the centre-left in power; and for a moderate few, Italy's challenges begin now.</p>
    <p>A poll published on Monday by the daily La Repubblica shows 58% of voters supports a Monti government, yet popularity for the individual measures the prime minister is likely to introduce ranges from 4% to 37%.</p>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/06/silvio-berlusconi-bunga-bunga-trial">Bunga bunga antics</ref> and legal troubles aside, Berlusconi's biggest shortcoming is to have failed to implement the "liberal revolution" he promised in 1994. Instead he gradually became complicit, and eventually one, with the system that as an entrepreneur he was so adept at navigating. Yet, we must not forget that Berlusconi "only" governed for nine of the past 17 years.</p>
    <p>Italy has high public sector debt, which stands at about 120%/GDP, yet its aggregate debt is lower than the UK's; household savings are among the highest in Europe, at 4% of GDP its deficit is relatively low compared to others and below eurozone average, and unemployment is below EU average. Italy's deeper problem is that the country has been at a standstill for the past 10 years. The average Italian was worse off in 2010 than in 2000 as GDP per head has fallen over the decade. In the past decade only Haiti and Zimbabwe have grown more slowly and Italy has dropped below Zambia and Mongolia in the <ref target="http://www.doingbusiness.org/rankings">ease of doing business index</ref>. Each year, 90,000 people leave Italy – almost a million in the last decade; 50% of Italy's young people wants to leave the country to flee its <ref target="http://adrianofarano.com/2011/11/13/berlusconi-is-gone-but-italys-true-problems-are-there-to-stay/">flawed job market</ref> and statistics released by the Bank of Italy over the weekend show that only one in four people who loses their job finds work within a year.</p>
    <p>These are the challenges that face Monti and his government – controlling political bickering, bridging the divide between the electorate and politicians and enacting austerity and reforms within the framework of a possible recession, broader euro crisis and "currency war".</p>
    <p>Whatever and whoever rises from the ashes left behind by the unravelling of this government, it has a mountain to climb (and a €300bn debt bill to cover in 2012). On Monday morning, Italy held an auction of five-year government bonds; yields averaged 6.29%, Milan's stock exchange fell like a soufflé after an initial rally and the spread between Italian and German 10-year bonds remains dangerously wide..</p>
    <p>If I were a betting man, I would place my odds on Monti lasting at least until April (Italy needs to cover €200bn in maturing debt between now and then) as the parties understand the practical and political need to show support. If Monti succeeds in calming the markets, many will try to adopt the former European commissioner as one of their own. If he fails the parties will pounce, and the smoke in the backrooms will start rising just in time for Italy's warm and glorious spring.</p>
    <p>Post-Berlusconi Italy is going to be chaotic, and the political landscape set to dramatically change. But the risk, as the maxim in Giuseppe Tomasi di Lampedusa's The Leopard goes, is that "everything has to change so that everything can stay the same".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>