<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Your letters: Tell us what you think" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-11-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/nov/07/guardian-weekend-readers-letters" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Please, don't compare Profumo to Berlusconi. And thanks for the feature on larger models – but why use stick-thin women in your own shoot then?" categories="Global" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Fashion,Shirley Bassey,Property" fingerprint="ee941a3622608221">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi is one of my favourite politicians – he's the panto villain you can boo and hiss and throw rotten veg at. He heavy-handedly dictates and pays his way through politics, and, seemingly, does little to hide it. Our own politicians do dodgy deals and cheat on their wives, but it only seeps out later. Give me a Berlusconi over the Uriah Heeps any day.<hi rend="#b">Kim Batty </hi>Hastings, East Sussex</p>
    <p>What is the basis for John Hooper's claim in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/31/silvio-berlusconi-profile">his article on Silvio Berlusconi </ref>that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2001/apr/10/past.derekbrown">John Profumo</ref> paid <ref target="http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/SPYkeeler.htm">Christine Keeler</ref> for her services? I know of no evidence for this. What the former war minister did cost him and his family dearly, but he did more than enough in the rest of his life to redeem himself.<hi rend="#b">Terry Philpot </hi>Limpsfield Chart, Surrey</p>
    <p>Viv Groskop <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/oct/31/big-models-fashion">writes enthusiastically about enormous ladies – well, size 14, at any rate – modelling clothes</ref>, and that the fashion world is changing. Yet just a few pages later, the usual seriously slim ladies are modelling your recommendations in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/gallery/2009/oct/31/fashion-all-ages-embellishment">your All Ages shoot</ref>. Whose side are you on?<hi rend="#b">Ruth Coppard </hi>Sheffield</p>
    <p>It's refreshing to note that a high-earning Hollywood star such as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2009/oct/31/john-cusack-interview">John Cusack </ref>retains such a grounded sense of social justice that he's as incensed as the rest of us at the bonuses Wall Street bankers continue to pay themselves. But hold on, aren't these the same guys who bankroll Sony, the makers of <ref target="http://www.whowillsurvive2012.com/">2012</ref>, the disgustingly expensive blockbuster that Cusack graciously agreed to be interviewed about in order to boost its box-office takings? Or are they the guys who failed to bankroll the (unmade) <ref target="http://www.cinematical.com/2008/07/10/john-cusack-sues-over-stopping-power/">Stopping Power, which resulted in Cusack suing the producers for $5.6m</ref>. Wouldn't that be $5.6m for work not actually done? A bit like the bankers' bonuses, then.<hi rend="#b">Declan Heneghan</hi> Liverpool</p>
    <p>So Tim Dowling's children <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/oct/31/tim-dowling-mob-blood">go to the park over the road to play with "local kids"</ref>. Presumably there is something special about his kids that makes them not local, even though they live just across the road. Perhaps that's why the other children were following them.<hi rend="#b">Pamela Wales </hi>Ipswich, Suffolk</p>
    <p>Awful to read that Tim was punched in the mouth. Was the assailant a regular reader of his column?<hi rend="#b">John Nancollis </hi>Stockport, Cheshire</p>
    <p>To use <ref target="http://ww.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/oct/31/post-office-lucy-mangan">Lucy Mangan's comparison</ref>, Saturday's Guardian is roughly equivalent to five stamps. For that, we get her column and the rest of the paper as a bonus. She needs retaining as a perpetual parcel, to be unwrapped and savoured at times of national absurdity.<hi rend="#b">Paul Walker </hi>Buxton, Derbyshire</p>
    <p>Who selected <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/money/2009/oct/31/lets-move-to-bury-lancashire">the picture for Let's move to... Bury</ref>? Yards from the scene you used is a lovely railway bridge, <ref target="http://summerseat.ourwardfamily.com/mills_of_summerseat.htm">Brooksbottom Mill </ref>and the <ref target="http://www.waterscape.com/canals-and-rivers/river-irwell">River Irwell</ref>. Do renovated workers' cottages really symbolise the image of "It's not grim up north"?<hi rend="#b">Pat Long </hi>Bury</p>
    <p>Yotam Ottolenghi's individual take on meat-free recipes is usually interesting, but I was underwhelmed by his <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/oct/24/hot-carrot-salad-vegetarian-yotam-ottolenghi">Hot Carrot Salad on shop-bought crumpets</ref>. Was he secretly on holiday that week?<hi rend="#b">Amanda West </hi>Twyford, Berkshire</p>
    <p>A bungalow whose only drawback is that the bathroom is downstairs (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/money/gallery/2009/oct/29/snooping-around-homes-market">Wreck Of The Week</ref>). What stairs would those be, then?<hi rend="#b">David Collins </hi>Kidderminster, Worcestershire</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>