<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi spends fourth night in hospital after intruder alert" author="John Hooper" date="2009-12-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/16/berlusconi-attack-hospital" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Berlusconi doctors put off decision on his discharge from hospital for third time since he was admitted after attack" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="768993af01259707">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's doctors tonight put off again a decision on his discharge from hospital – the third time they have done so since he was admitted on Sunday after being attacked at a political rally.</p>
    <p>The surprise move is bound to raise queries about the 73-year-old prime minister's state of health. His personal physician, Alberto Zangrillo, said: "His condition is reassuring, and we are reassured." He said the tycoon-turned-politician was still in considerable pain and unable to eat normally.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi lost half a litre of blood after he was hit with an angular souvenir replica of Milan cathedral. He was left with a broken nose, two chipped teeth and cuts inside and around his mouth – unpleasant injuries, but not necessarily such as to warrant a four-day stay in hospital.</p>
    <p>Yesterday, Zangrillo said the blow to the prime minister's head had inflamed a longstanding neck complaint. A medical bulletin issued tonight by the San Raffaele hospital in Milan, where Berlusconi is being treated, said that was one reason for keeping him in, and that his general clinical condition was "good and satisfactory".</p>
    <p>As Italy's interior minister, Roberto Maroni, expressed concern over the possibility of copycat attacks, a man was arrested trying to reach Berlusconi's bedroom. Police said he had entered the hospital through the underground car park and taken the lift – an explanation that raised further doubts about the prime minister's security.</p>
    <p>Police said the 26-year-old man, from Turin, appeared to have psychological problems. They said he had not been carrying any weapon, although ice hockey sticks were found in his car.</p>
    <p>A judge approved the jailing of Berlusconi's assailant, Massimo Tartaglia, who is being held in the neuro-psychiatric observation centre at San Vittore prison in Milan. The judge ruled there was a risk of the 42 year-old committing other violent acts.</p>
    <p>The cabinet will tomorrow discuss controversial proposals to black out venomously anti-Berlusconi websites and tighten security at public gatherings. Maroni said the planned internet crackdown would not be put into effect at once but into a bill that would be debated in parliament.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>