<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Glee; Life of Riley; The Lady and the Revamp; The Berlusconi Show | TV review" author="Andrew Anthony" date="2010-03-21" url="http://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2010/mar/21/glee-life-of-riley-lady-revamp" hostname="theguardian.com" description="If only British sitcoms could match Glee's exhilarating mix of kitsch and killer sarcasm, says Andrew Anthony" categories="Television &amp; radio" tags="Television,Television &amp; radio,Culture,Piers Morgan,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy" fingerprint="3b4f923811a01119">
  <main>
    <p>When was the last time this country produced a contemporary drama or comedy series that was smart, ironic, optimistic, satirical, poignant, funny, innovative and aimed at a mainstream audience of adults and children? I don't know the answer, but it's somewhere between a long time ago and never.</p>
    <p>By contrast, in recent years American television has brought us <hi rend="#i">Scrubs</hi>, <hi rend="#i">Ugly Betty</hi> and now <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi>, shows that combine boldly imaginative approaches to narrative with a humour and humanity that is often exhilarating to behold. While we seem to be mired in an endless debate about platforms, content, news values and the multimedia revolution, the Americans have managed to retain an enthusiasm for the dramatic possibilities of television. And what's clear is that those possibilities are founded upon an enduring belief in sharp, savvy writing and deeply committed performances.</p>
    <p>At first sight, <hi rend="#b">Glee</hi> (C4) follows a stupefyingly familiar path. It's set in a midwest high school, amid the over-fictionalised world of geeks and jocks. And in a nod to the <hi rend="#i">High School Musical</hi> fad, it focuses on a glee club, or singing society. However, <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> takes these tropes and clichés and stretches them in surprising directions to create a whole new form, as different to its original source as a butterfly is to a caterpillar.</p>
    <p>Last week, teen pregnancy, the difficulty of coming out in high school, and sexual attraction between teacher and pupil were plot themes but, unlike many American shows, not moral "issues". <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> is possessed of a liberal heart but its balls, as well as some of its most memorable lines, belong to the politically incorrect coach, Sue Sylvester (played by Jane Lynch).</p>
    <p>Like two opposing grammarians, kitsch sentiment and killer sarcasm wrestle over every line. Yet, at the point where conventional drama plunges into pathos, <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> slips into song. At one moment the school quarterback was singing "I'll Stand by You" to the ultrasound of his unwanted child (which isn't his), the next his friends were rallying round in a stirring rendition of "Lean on Me".</p>
    <p>A lot of the humour stems from snappy social observation, but the show also boasts the kind of verbal extravagance that, in the wrong hands, can sound written rather than said. Typical was the scene in which a former schoolgirl stalker, who once responded to rejection by eating a lethally hot pepper, advised her equally deluded successor: "Let me tell you a few things I learned from two years of intense psychotherapy and an oesophagus transplant."</p>
    <p>The reason that line worked is the same reason the songs and outrageous storylines work: because the characters are immersed in their own reality. They never act as if they've said something funny. There's no pause for laughter, no nods or winks, as <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> shows the same faith in its audience as it does in its characterisations. Laughter isn't forced, so isn't false. In common with <hi rend="#i">Ugly Betty</hi> and <hi rend="#i">Scrubs</hi>, there is plenty of cultural commentary and knowing asides but failure to spot the reference doesn't undermine the scene. The action just moves swiftly on. If <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> is postmodern, it doesn't bother knocking twice.</p>
    <p>The show has attracted a lot of plaudits, particularly in America, so it's probably soon due for a backlash. This might be an opportune moment, then, to say that the hype is deserved. It's a rare and heartening pleasure to watch so much energy and emotion expended in the unfashionable cause of family entertainment.</p>
    <p>Some of its fans might say <hi rend="#i">Doctor Who </hi>performs a similar feat, though really the nearest British television comes, or attempts to come, to <hi rend="#i">Glee</hi> is in shows like <hi rend="#i">Strictly Come Dancing</hi>. Where US networks can be persuaded to invest in good writing and acting, our TV executives prefer to back the all-dancing duo of celebrity and reality.</p>
    <p>Only in an atmosphere in which originality is viewed as marginal or suspect could a series like <hi rend="#b">Life of Riley </hi>(BBC1) be produced. It may seem unfair to pick out this harmless sitcom as an illustration of the failings of British comedy drama, but perhaps not quite as unfair as the decision to recommission another series.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#i">Life of Riley</hi> is not the worst sitcom (a title for which competition is too fierce to contemplate), and it even featured one clever line – when his daughter asked him what he was doing drinking coffee at an Ikea-like warehouse, Neil Dudgeon (as Jim Riley) replied: 'Just wanted to see what our bookshelves look like when they're assembled.' The problem is that none of the cast, led by Caroline Quentin, is able to say the lines as if they mean them, because the lines – with that single exception – neither refer to a known reality nor create a new one. Instead, the dialogue is rooted in sitcomland, that dislocated place where everything is said for effect and nothing has any effect. <hi rend="#i">Life of Riley</hi> is the anti-<hi rend="#i">Glee</hi>, tired, predictable and pointless.</p>
    <p>If we're not very good at inserting the real world into comedy, we can still find comedy in the real world. <hi rend="#b">The Lady and the Revamp</hi> (C4) was everything that a behind-the-doors documentary should be. It's the opposite of <hi rend="#i">Inside John Lewis</hi>, which is taking three programmes to produce less insight than might be gained by a fleeting visit to the shop's loo. Access is all very well but what's really needed is excess. And any film that features Joan Collins, the Duchess of Devonshire and Rachel Johnson couldn't be accused of restraint.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#i">The Lady</hi> is the magazine for gentlewomen that was once the place to find domestic staff. But since its heyday in the 50s it has been on a steady decline to anachronism status. Enter Johnson, sister of Boris, with a brief to usher the 21st century into the magazine's funereal offices. Had a fighting bull been invited to Wedgwood's showrooms, it couldn't have had more fun.</p>
    <p>Johnson was charming, impressively dentured, bitchy and ruthless. In short, utterly delightful. But she had to contend with a publisher who combined a feudal sense of entitlement with a chronically timid character. "What's the point of buying a dog," he asked, "if you're going to do the barking yourself?"</p>
    <p>Then there was the staff, a brilliant cast of eccentrics led by the former editor, who sat in her heavily ornamented apartment, lacking only a white cat on her lap to complete the image of conspiratorial intrigue. It would be astonishing if Johnson managed to transform the fortunes of <hi rend="#i">The Lady</hi>. But on this evidence she's done her own no harm.</p>
    <p>I'd like to see Johnson interview <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. It's true that she's a bit long in the tooth for him, but you could imagine that the Italian prime minister might nonetheless find her <hi rend="#i">simpatica</hi>. In <hi rend="#b">The Berlusconi Show</hi> (BBC2), Mark Franchetti tried to understand why it is that while the man who made a fortune out of third-rate television is a laughing stock abroad he remains hugely popular at home.</p>
    <p>We heard about mafia links, corruption, call girls and how Berlusconi uses his frothy TV channels for propaganda, but none of it seems to bother his supporters. Even his attempt to recruit weathergirls and escorts to become MPs was backed by no less an authority than the Italian foreign minister, Franco Frattini. Using all his experience as a diplomat, he asked: "Why should he choose only among people who are ugly?"</p>
    <p>Put simply, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> is a lesson in where bad television leads.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Scene of the week</head>
    <p>Is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/piersmorgan">Piers Morgan</ref> auditioning to be the new Alan Whicker? In <hi rend="#b">Piers Morgan on Marbella </hi>(ITV1) we saw him in a summer suit and sunglasses, meeting the rich and tasteless, and getting very excited about the price of gold-plated taps – "quarter of a million euros on taps!" – and carpets – "£2m for the carpets!"</p>
    <p>He also said things – such as "If Marbella was a goose, this really is the golden egg" – that made you wonder if Chris Morris's career has been in vain.</p>
    <p>But the key moment came in the centre of town when he stood outside the earthly purgatory that is Linekers bar, with its bottle-blond, orange-skinned, drunken British hordes, and said: "You see, even though it might be cheesy, I can't wait to get in there."</p>
    <p>And, of course, we did see: confirmation that Morgan is the Whicker of the easyJet set.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>