<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: Did government planes fly women to private parties?" author="Staff; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" date="2011-09-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/sep/17/berlusconi-inquiry-government-planes-women" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian opposition leaders demand inquiry after wiretap indicates planes might have transported women to prime minister's parties" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" fingerprint="3fe1ca3d9227c70d">
  <main>
    <p>Opposition leaders in Italy are demanding an inquiry to see if Italian government aircraft were used to fly young women to Silvio Berlusconi's private parties.</p>
    <p>Leoluca Orlandi, of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Values party, is insisting that Berlusconi tell voters if the planes were used after intercepted phone conversations in an investigation indicated that they might have been.</p>
    <p>Italy's Sky TG24 TV on Saturday showed excerpts of transcripts in a probe of an Italian businessman who prosecutors allege paid women to have sex with the prime minister at the parties. Berlusconi has denied ever paying for sex.</p>
    <p>Italian newspapers carried excerpts from thousands of pages of transcripts on Saturday. In one call, Berlusconi allegedly boasts that 11 women were lined up outside his room but he only "did" eight of them because "you can't do all".</p>
    <p>The latest allegation comes a day after prosecutors charged eight people with supplying prostitutes for Berlusconi.</p>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/sep/15/silvio-berlusconi-claims-prostitutes-wiretap">The charges were made as investigators concluded an inquiry into a number of friends and associates of Berlusconi </ref>in the southern city of Bari. The suspects are alleged to have procured young women for Berlusconi, as well as several other of his business associates.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has not been charged in connection with this investigation</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>