<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: gone for good? Or waiting to snap back?" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/13/berlusconi-political-future" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The 75-year-old may have quit as prime minister, but he may not be politically dead just yet" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" fingerprint="76ab182fbe37df4d">
  <main>
    <p>Five years ago, Nanni Moretti, the acclaimed director of Dear Diary, made a film about Silvio Berlusconi. It was called <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2007/apr/08/comedy.romance?INTCMP=SRCH">Il Caimano</ref> ("The Caiman"). It was not exactly an obvious title and puzzled quite a few people, until they recalled that, like its cousin the crocodile, the deadly Caiman can wait motionless for unconscionably long periods of time on a river bank before slipping back into the water to snap up its prey.</p>
    <p>It is often forgotten that Berlusconi passed seven long years in opposition before returning in triumph in 2001.</p>
    <p>But could the 75-year-old tycoon really come back yet again from the political dead, as he hinted on Sunday? On Wednesday, after all, he told an interviewer he felt "liberated" by the thought that he would not have to run again in an election.</p>
    <p>Since then, however, he has been given at least two reasons to change his mind. One was the rumbustious send-off he was given on Saturday night. Berlusconi is a man with a giant ego; a man who, even before coming to power, had built a mausoleum for himself in the grounds of his mansion outside Milan with niches for his closest associates.</p>
    <p>As several of his collaborators have noted over the years, the outgoing prime minister also has a compulsive need to feel that he is loved.</p>
    <p>It is hard to think of anyone who would be more horrified by the thought that his political career had ended in a hail of insults from a jeering mob. One of his parliamentary followers, who led a party of young people to meet him on Sunday, said she found him "upset" by the demonstration that accompanied his resignation.</p>
    <p>Since the middle of last week, moreover, it has become dramatically apparent that, without Berlusconi, his party could soon fall apart. By Friday, two of the ministers in his cabinet were swapping insults in public over how to react to the prospect of a new, "technocratic" government.</p>
    <p>The disintegration of the Freedom People (PdL) would be a terrible blow to Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>A constant theme of his 17-year career in politics has been his advocacy of a two-party democracy. By merging Forza Italia!, the party he founded, with one spun out of the old neo-fascist movement, the media mogul thought he had created a lasting solution to one half of the equation.</p>
    <p>Were he to run again at a general election, his chances would not be as dismal as might be thought in view of all that has happened in recent weeks. The last national opinion poll was conducted for Sky Italia on 7 November. It showed that, despite everything – the bunga bunga parties, Berlusconi's indictment on juvenile prostitution charges, the trials for bribery and embezzlement, not to mention his government's failure to isolate <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> from eurozone contagion – the PdL was only 1.3 percentage points behind the biggest opposition group, the Democratic party (PD).</p>
    <p>Italy is a deeply conservative country and Berlusconi, with his grip on the media, may well have made it even more conservative.</p>
    <p>The same poll showed that, if an election were held tomorrow, the right would take 35.2% of the vote, the centre-left 45.2% and the mostly conservative parties between them, 13.1%.</p>
    <p>That is not exactly an unwinnable hand with which to start the game, especially not if you can count on the unconditional support of three television channels and the certainty that the new government – enthusiastically backed by the opposition – will have to impose some very painful sacrifices on the electorate.</p>
    <p>The big question – which is impossible to answer so soon after Berlusconi's resignation – is whether Italians have mentally consigned him to history.</p>
    <p>The gap of more than 4% between his personal rating and the voting intention for his party suggests many PdL supporters assumed Berlusconi would not be its candidate at the next election.</p>
    <p>Even if that is correct, though, he remains the leader of his party for now and if he decides to obstruct the new government, he could still do Italy terrible damage.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>