<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Milan players right to walk off after racism, says Silvio Berlusconi" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-01-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2013/jan/04/racist-chanting-pro-patria-milan-prosecutor" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Milan's president Silvio Berlusconi has said that he will back his players if they walk off the pitch in future in protest at racist abuse" categories="Football" tags="Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Race,Europe,European club football,Football,Sport" fingerprint="efed916f1803dbe1">
  <main>
    <p>Milan's president <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has said that he will back his players if they walk off the pitch in future in protest at racist abuse, including European matches, while Kevin-Prince Boateng has threatened to give up the game should he be targeted in the future.</p>
    <p>The former prime minister said in a statement: "I called Kevin-Prince Boateng a little while ago and I congratulated him for his reaction against the disgraceful episode of racism that took place in the stadium of Pro Patria in Busto Arsizio.</p>
    <p>"I am very happy by Milan's reaction and be assured that in all games where we experience episodes of this kind, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> will leave the field."</p>
    <p>That could put Milan at loggerheads with Fifa and Uefa, who have previously warned against players taking such action.</p>
    <p>Fifa would not comment directly on the Boateng incident but a spokesman said in a competitive match the referee would report the incident and then the disciplinary committee of the competition's organisers would make a decision. "It would be for the referee to report and the disciplinary committee would have to look into it."</p>
    <p>A public prosecutor is set to open a criminal inquiry <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2013/jan/03/milan-friendly-abandoned-racist-chants">after the friendly match between Milan and the nearby lower division club Pro Patria was abandoned</ref> following racist chanting.</p>
    <p>The prosecutor in the Lombardy town of Busto Arsizio is likely to pursue charges of inciting racial hatred against Pro Patria fans who abused Milan's black players, the Ansa news agency reported on Friday. One fan has admitted his involvement after being questioned by police.</p>
    <p>Boateng told CNN: "I don't care what game it is – a friendly, Italian league or Champions League match – I would walk off again.</p>
    <p>"I'm sad and angry that I'm the one that has to take action. All the people who support me would support me in a big game. Players like Rio Ferdinand and Patrick Vieira have supported me and I just want to say thank you."</p>
    <p>During the Pro Patria friendly, Boateng said he had told the referee three times he was being abused. "If it happens again I'm not going to play anymore," added the midfielder. "The referee said: 'Don't worry' but I said I do worry, it's not very nice."</p>
    <p>After repeated chants directed his way during Thursday's game, the Ghana midfielder kicked the ball in anger at a section of the crowd, took off his shirt and walked off the pitch with the rest of the team. Milan's Urby Emanuelson, Sulley Muntari and M'Baye Niang were also targeted by the chants. The Italian football federation announced its own inquiry on Thursday.</p>
    <p>Pro Patria's president, Pietro Vavassori, announced that he would open the club's stadium to "all people of colour" at their next match.</p>
    <p>"Our hope is that the other Lega Pro [third and fourth division] presidents also support this initiative," Vavassori said. "The people who made those chants are not regular fans, but rather people who came to the stadium with the intention of ruining a festive match."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>