<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's professional foul" author="John Hooper" date="2008-12-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2008/dec/08/berlusconi-vat-pay-tv" hostname="theguardian.com" description="His plan to double VAT on pay TV will clip the wings of Murdoch's Sky Italia. John Hooper reports" categories="Media" tags="Television industry,Silvio Berlusconi,Rupert Murdoch,Media,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Serie A,Sky,Italy,Sky,Football,Europe" fingerprint="7e8ac13e91b6df7d">
  <main>
    <p>When he launched his Italian satellite platform, Sky Italia, Rupert Murdoch airily dismissed the notion that Silvio Berlusconi's immense power, as both government leader and media tycoon, might represent a threat to his enterprise. Berlusconi was "a modern man with a broad vision", he was quoted as telling an interviewer. In any case, he added, "business is business".</p>
    <p>It would be interesting to know if the head of News Corp feels quite the same this week after his first big defeat in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and a bruising reminder that - especially in Berlusconi's Italy - business is never just business, but an activity intimately linked to politics.</p>
    <p>The tension between the two men that has been building up for years (see panel) finally broke into the open last week with a dispute that dominated the Italian news bulletins and front pages.</p>
    <p>In a package of measures approved by Berlusconi's cabinet eight days ago, VAT levied on pay-TV subscriptions will double from January 1. It is a measure that, as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/britishskybroadcastinggroup">Sky</ref> Italia's CEO, Tom Mockridge, admitted, could slow the impressive growth his company has achieved in its five years of existence.</p>
    <p>Despite a public relations fightback by Sky, Berlusconi's government has used European Union anti-competition guidelines to justify what opposition politicians have described as a ploy by Berlusconi the politician to protect the interests of Berlusconi the businessman.</p>
    <p>Having secured the rights to Italy's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/serieafootball">Serie A</ref> football fixtures, the growth rate of Sky Italia has alarmed its chief terrestrial rivals - Mediaset, which is controlled by Berlusconi, and the state-owned RAI. It has more than doubled the subscriptions it inherited in 2003 to 4.7m and on an average day reaches 9% of the audience.</p>
    <p>Until now, the VAT paid by Sky's subscribers has been half the normal 20% rate, a tax break designed to promote an alternative to the existing "duopoly". Sky made its first profit in Italy just last year. Most of the customers of its main pay-TV rival Premium, which is owned by Mediaset, pay full VAT.</p>
    <p>On Wednesday, a spokeswoman for the European commission confirmed that Brussels had told the Italian authorities that it would bring a case against them if they did not do something about the discrepancy.</p>
    <p>But the spokeswoman added: "The government had to decide if everyone went to 10% or 20%, because it is the [member state] that decides on the rate, and not us."</p>
    <p>Premium has only 6% of the pay-TV market, compared with the Murdoch subsidiary's 92%. It represents a tiny share of its parent company's revenue. According to one analyst's estimate, the government's decision will cost the company that the prime minister founded just €12m a year, compared with €230m for Sky. The VAT rise was bundled into legislation designed to stimulate consumption yet its effect will be the reverse: it represents a curb, albeit a modest one, on the spending power of the 4.7m Italian households that have signed up to Sky.</p>
    <p>"With the country in the grip of an economic crisis, Berlusconi is thinking about safeguarding his family firm and penalising his principal rival," stormed Antonio Di Pietro, the leader of the Italy of Principles movement. "It is a disgrace - a measure worthy of a banana republic."</p>
    <p>Arguably, though, the most damaging attack came from a different quarter. On Sunday, as millions of Italian soccer fans settled down in front of their screens for the day's Serie A fixtures, they found themselves being addressed by Sky's top presenter. Ilaria D'Amico had a message that tugged at both the heart and purse strings.</p>
    <p>The government, she said, had struck at the interests of "Italian families who had freely decided to subscribe to Sky". The station invited them to email their ire to the prime minister's office, whose email address it supplied. A reported half a million complaints arrived in the two hours that followed.</p>
    <p>Taken aback by the response, some of the prime minister's own followers have wavered, musing aloud that the decree containing the VAT increase can always be amended when it comes to be ratified by parliament. Even Berlusconi himself appeared to wobble at one point last week in the face of what seemed to be a public backlash.</p>
    <p>But after his finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, stressed the government had been told to act by Brussels, he swiftly corrected himself.</p>
    <p>It is less clear, though, whether Berlusconi will have the last laugh. It is not just that his government's move will penalise millions of voters. There is also a risk that the affair could bring about an important change in public perceptions of Italy's prime minister.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi rose to prominence in the guise of a free market crusader - an Italian Richard Branson who, in the 1980s, broke the stranglehold of RAI. The image of champion of the right to choice is one that he still likes to don, but in the past few days he has been made to look all too much like a defender of the status quo.</p>
    <p>As for the New Zealand-born Mockridge, even Il Foglio, a daily backed by Berlusconi's wife, Veronica, said his counter-attack - with its direct appeal to the viewing public - had been carried out in the best traditions of Italy's maverick prime minister. "Berlusconissimamente," the paper proclaimed.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Timeline</hi><hi rend="#b">1998 </hi><lb/> After months of talks, aimed at resolving the conflict of interest between Silvio Berlusconi's twin roles as politician and businessman, he rejects a €3bn offer from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/rupert-murdoch">Rupert Murdoch</ref> for his 50.6% stake in Mediaset.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2001</hi><lb/> Murdoch again tries and fails to buy Berlusconi's TV interests.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2003</hi><lb/> Murdoch launches Sky Italia after the EU approves his purchase of Telepiu, a company originally founded by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2005 </hi><lb/> Mediaset scoops up the digital terrestrial rights to the home games of three of Italy's top football sides in a deal that lays the groundwork for the launch of its Premium pay-per-view service.</p>
    <p>Sky challenges a €100m Berlusconi government subsidy for digital (but not satellite) decoders. Its appeal is upheld the following year.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2009 </hi><lb/> VAT levied on pay-TV subscriptions to double to 20%</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>