<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi nominates Angelino Alfano as his successor" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/silvio-berlusconi-successor-angelino-alfano" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister, who has promised to resign, says secretary of his party is in 'pole position' to lead the right" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Eurozone crisis,European Union,Europe,World news,European banks,Business" fingerprint="ff8ed03d30a4c77d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has anointed as his likely successor a 41-year-old Sicilian lawyer, Angelino Alfano, best known for trying, as justice minister, to guarantee the Italian prime minister immunity from prosecution in the courts.</p>
    <p>As investors fretted over the effects on the eurozone of a prolonged period of political uncertainty in Italy, the interest rate on Italian five-year government bonds shot above 7%. When 10-year bonds have gone beyond this level, other countries have sought a bailout. The move on the debt markets prompted a sharp about-turn on stock markets in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, which had opened higher.</p>
    <p>Alfano, the secretary of Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People, was in "pole position" to be the right's candidate at the elections he wants to see early next year, the departing PM told one of his own television channels on Wednesday. His appointment would signal a "generational change", Berlusconi said.</p>
    <p>In another interview, given late last night to the daily La Stampa, Berlusconi said: "I shall not be standing again. Indeed, I feel liberated. Now is Alfano's moment. He'll be our candidate for prime minister. He's very clever, better than one might think, and his leadership has been accepted by all."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi told the president, Giorgio Napolitano, on Tuesday evening he would resign once parliament had approved the economic austerity measures agreed with the European institutions. Interviewed on the state-owned RAI radio network, the prime minister said he would appeal to the opposition not to oppose the measures on their way through parliament.</p>
    <p>Early estimates suggested they could be approved in 10 to 15 days. But opposition politicians said Berlusconi and his allies might seek to drag out the process.</p>
    <p>With <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> still under a menacing financial cloud, the response to Berlusconi's departure after months of sex scandal, street riots and bitter parliamentary confrontation has been muted. The most strident reaction came from his family's newspaper, Il Giornale, which carried the headline: "Here are the Judases who have stabbed the government [to death]."</p>
    <p>Eight Berlusconi MPs sided with the opposition in a crucial vote on Tuesday to approve the 2010 public accounts. The result left the 75-year-old TV magnate the same number of votes short of an absolute majority in the lower house, the chamber of deputies, where he has been vulnerable since July of last year.</p>
    <p>Alfano stands out in a political landscape populated by the elderly. When Berlusconi returned to power three years ago he was made justice minister at the relatively young age of 37.</p>
    <p>He is known in particular for helping to draft and steer through parliament an intensely controversial law, which was overturned by the constitutional court in 2009. It granted immunity from prosecution to the four highest officers of state, including the prime minister.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>