<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy: rise of young mayor signals the end of 'grey power'" author="John Hooper" date="2013-12-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/08/matteo-renzi-italy-mayor-centre-left" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Matteo Renzi, 38, who is tipped to become head of centre-left party, is one of group of politicians hoping to rejuvenate country" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" fingerprint="afd0d33dcc2bd33d">
  <main>
    <p>Italian voters are poised to elect a 38-year-old as leader of their biggest party, completing a generational transformation in a country that, until a few months ago, was a redoubt of grey power.</p>
    <p>Matteo Renzi, mayor of Florence, is unanimously tipped by pollsters and bookies to win a three-way ballot for general secretary of the centre-left Democratic party (PD). Victory would raise him to the front rank of Italian politics alongside a prime minister, Enrico Letta, who at 47 is the same age as David Cameron, and a 43-year-old deputy prime minister, Angelino Alfano, who is three years younger than Nick Clegg. Laura Boldrini, the lower house's speaker, is a 52-year-old parliamentary novice. One of her deputies, Luigi Di Maio, of the Five Star Movement (M5S), is just 27.</p>
    <p>"For too long, older people have barred the doors of public life, not only to those who wanted to run for office, but to those who simply wanted to be heard," Di Maio said. "The [younger generations] have battered down the door and got in. But now they want to take their future into their own hands and they're looking for real innovation."</p>
    <p>"It is very similar to the Blair-Brown rivalry," said Roberto D'Alimonte, professor of politics at the LUISS university in Rome. Renzi has often been compared to Tony Blair, but now he faces a danger of being confined to a role more like that of the ill-fated Gordon Brown.</p>
    <p>It is a far cry from the years in which <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, now 77, was in charge. His contribution to Italy's rejuvenation was to bring three young women into his final government. Renzi was still in the Scouts when Berlusconi launched his political career. And in the very year the media tycoon swept to power for the first time, Renzi relieved his TV network of 48m lire (£25,000). The young Florentine was a contestant on the Italian version of <hi rend="#i">Wheel of Fortune</hi>, broadcast on one of Berlusconi's three channels. His winning streak lasted through five editions. Some would say it has continued ever since. The son of a local Christian Democrat councillor, he first became involved in politics while at school. He joined a party that offered a home to the more progressive members of the movement after the Christian Democrats dissolved in sleaze in the early 1990s. By the time he graduated from the University of Florence aged 24, Renzi was his party's provincial secretary.</p>
    <p>Five years later he was Italy's youngest provincial president. And in 2009 he was elected to run his native city at the age of just 34. His only real setback has proved temporary. Last year the business-friendly Renzi was trounced in another nationwide ballot to choose the PD's prime ministerial candidate for the general election last February. The PD includes not only left-leaning ex-Christian Democrats but also the heirs of the former Italian Communist party who form the bigger group, and it was their candidate, Pier Luigi Bersani, who won the chance to run for prime minister. However, after bungling the presidential ballot following the general election, Bersani stepped aside, opening the way for Renzi to both lead the party and be its candidate at the next general election.</p>
    <p>With the PD well ahead of M5S and Berlusconi's Forza Italia! in the opinion polls, today's vote had been slated as the young mayor's last big hurdle before assuming the premiership.</p>
    <p>But last week the constitutional court declared that the electoral law in force since 2005 was unconstitutional. It objected to a provision guaranteeing a majority in the lower house to whichever party tops the poll. So unless a new system is agreed, the next election will be fought using an extreme version of proportional representation. That, in turn, would guarantee a fractured parliament and a coalition government. It would be fatal for the charismatic Renzi and his decisive style of leadership. "That would be 'game over' for him," said D'Alimonte.</p>
    <p>Renzi's other problem is that agreeing a new electoral law is likely to prolong the life of the present government. That in turn could reinforce the appeal and reputation of its leader, Enrico Letta, another relatively young Tuscan who comes from the same, moderately progressive area of the PD as Renzi.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>