<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy hails businessman a hero after he launches appeal to save the economy" author="Tom Kington" date="2011-11-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/06/italy-hails-businessman-hero" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Entrepreneur pays for full-page advert in national newspaper urging Italians to buy up the country's debt to prevent meltdown" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news,Eurozone crisis,Business" fingerprint="7f88463d94a3476d">
  <main>
    <p>A businessman has become an unlikely national hero after urging Italians to buy up government bonds to help drag the country back from the brink of an economic meltdown.</p>
    <p>As the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, scrambles to deliver key reforms, the Tuscan financial services entrepreneur Giuliano Melani announced his appeal with a full-page ad in the leading daily Corriere della Sera, complete with his telephone number and email address.</p>
    <p>Melani says the bill for Italian government bonds expiring annually is €260-270bn (£223-232bn), a sum which would be taken care of if every Italian paid €4,500.</p>
    <p>Admonishing Italians for letting their €1.9 trillion debt pile up through wasted spending, tax dodging and trust in incompetent politicians, Melani wrote: "There are many things to do, but now there is just one thing – let's buy the debt!" Corriere della Sera asked Italy's banks to drop commissions on bond sales for a day, which Corrado Passera, the chief executive of Intesa Sanpaolo bank, has agreed to.</p>
    <p>With yields (interest rates) on Italian government bonds rising above an unsustainable 6%, Berlusconi on Sunday pushed on with his own plan to save Italy from meltdown claiming his majority was solid and outlining liberalisation measures he hopes to sign off in parliament this month, including asset sell-offs, tax breaks to boost employment and the prising open of closed professions.</p>
    <p>But details remain scarce. Berlusconi produced a mere letter of intent to win over fellow leaders at the G20 last week, labour reform will depend on talks with unions and a last-minute plan for a sell off of state farmland worth €6bn was reported on Sunday.</p>
    <p>"I would really like to see this law because no one up until now has read it. Can we go on like this?" said Isabella Bertolini, one of several MPs in Berlusconi's People of Freedom party who have threatened to desert the prime minister before he can pass the measures.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi survived a confidence vote in the lower house last month by 316 votes to 301, but the mooted walkout of up to 20 MPs fed up with his scandals and paralysed government would be fatal.</p>
    <p>Party officials moved quickly last week to name a party spokesman to succeed an MP who died in an accident, while Alfonso Papa, an MP under house arrest on suspicion of corruption, is lobbying judges to allow him to vote to support Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>Close advisers to the prime minister were reportedly hoping Berlusconi would resign to allow his cabinet secretary, Gianni Letta, to form an administration including centrist politicians and the former Berlusconi ally Gianfranco Fini.</p>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani, the leader of the opposition Democratic party, vowed to boycott a Letta government and threatened a vote of no confidence in parliament after addressing thousands of supporters in Rome on Saturday.</p>
    <p>"That would be a centre-right government and I don't see how it would behave differently to a Berlusconi government," he said.</p>
    <p>An alternative should Berlusconi lose his majority is an early election or a technical government appointed by the president, Giorgio Napolitano, probably run by the respected economist Mario Monti.</p>
    <p>But the solution was ruled out by Berlusconi and by Roberto Calderoli, a minister with the powerful Northern League party. "That would be a coup d'état, and you fight against coups d'état with revolutions," said Calderoli.</p>
    <p>Another minister from the League, Roberto Maroni warned on Sunday that Berlusconi's "majority no longer exists, it is useless to insist [it does]," as it was announced that Gabriela Carlucci, a former TV showgirl, had become the third Berlusconi MP to defect to the centrist UDC party in recent days.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>