<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Egypt needs reform not repression, say EU leaders" author="Ian Traynor" date="2011-02-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/04/egypt-reform-eu-leaders-summit" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Brussels summit demands transition towards democracy but fails to call for immediate removal of President Hosni Mubarak" categories="World news" tags="European Union,Egypt,Hosni Mubarak,Middle East and north Africa,World news,Obama administration,David Cameron,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="779cd14d25d6289e">
  <main>
    <p>European leaders today called for an immediate transition to "broad-based" government in Egypt, but declined to demand the quick resignation of President <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/hosni-mubarak">Hosni Mubarak</ref> amid divisions over how to view the Cairo regime.</p>
    <p>An EU summit in Brussels wrestled over a response to the drama unfolding in Cairo, with David Cameron urging more robust action on the Middle East in line with Washington, while leaders such as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> of Italy offered effusive praise of the Egyptian strongman and suggested Mubarak should continue in office.</p>
    <p>The summit called on the Mubarak regime "to meet the aspirations of the Egyptian people with political reform, not repression" and for "an orderly transition to broad-based government. This transition process must start now."</p>
    <p>The statement included a veiled threat of sanctions or withholding of aid to Egypt and also focused on the EU's potential medium-term role in democracy-building projects in Egypt rather than on the immediate crisis.</p>
    <p>Catherine Ashton, the EU's foreign policy chief who has come under renewed criticism for her low-profile role in the biggest foreign policy crisis since she assumed her position 15 months ago, was instructed to go to Cairo and come up with a package helping to organise free and fair elections. She is expected to go within a fortnight.</p>
    <p>British officials said Cameron was keen to get the summit to deliver a blunt response to Mubarak. But the summit statement did not mention the Egyptian leader's name. Cameron said: "Egypt and its regime would lose any remaining credibility and support it has in the eyes of the watching world if state-sponsored violence or the hiring of thugs" was used.</p>
    <p>His comments contrasted strongly with Berlusconi, who said Mubarak could remain in office while Egypt made the transition towards "a more democratic system". "For all the west, starting with the United States, [Mubarak] has always been considered a wisest man and a point of reference. Compared to a population of 80 million, the number of people on the streets is really low," he said.</p>
    <p>Ashton spoke by telephone yesterday to the Egyptian vice-president, Omar Suleiman, and reported that he was talking to the opposition and "moving towards some kind of national dialogue".</p>
    <p>"It is about change, it is about moving, it is about responding," said Ashton. "We've been very clear in everything we said that it's for the Egyptian people and government to move forward together. It's absolutely essential we see the movement necessary for people to feel confident that there is a plan in place."</p>
    <p>Martin Schulz, the leader of the centre-left in the European parliament, lambasted the EU for its perceived weakness. "On foreign policy issues, the EU too often behaves like a frightened rabbit in the headlights of a car," he said. "The EU summit should make a clear statement that Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak's time is up. They need to be much tougher and make it clear that Europe will not tolerate Mubarak clinging desperately to office."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>