<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi mistakenly arrives at leftist party rally in Italy local elections" author="Chris Johnston" date="2015-05-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/may/30/silvio-berlusconi-mistakenly-arrives-leftist-party-rally-italy-local-elections" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian premier, 78, tells supporters of Democratic party’s Paolo Micheli: ‘Young people, I’m counting on you to vote Paolo,’ before hastily departing" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe,The League" fingerprint="be18127dc7f787f5">
  <main>
    <p>Italy’s 78-year-old former premier, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, mistakenly turned up at a rally for a candidate from a left-leaning party on Friday night, instead of his own Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>The incident occurred in the town of Segrate, near Milan, during the rally for Paolo Micheli, a mayoral candidate in local elections taking place on Sunday.</p>
    <p>Supporters of Micheli, who is backed by the centre-left Democratic party, were astonished as Berlusconi and no less than six bodyguards swept into the square where the rally was being held.</p>
    <p>He wandered around the square for several minutes before asking someone the candidate’s name. Berlusconi then said: “Young people, I’m counting on you to vote Paolo,” before hastily departing after being informed of his error by a member of his entourage.</p>
    <p>Micheli later posted on his Facebook page: “With the support of the Cavaliere I can say I’ve won.”</p>
    <p>It seems that Berlusconi got lost while looking for the hall where the mayoral candidate for Forza Italia party, Tecla Fraschini, was holding a campaign event.</p>
    <p>20 million voters go to the polls on Sunday to elect governors in seven of Italy’s 20 regions, as well as the mayors of more than 1,000 cities and towns.</p>
    <p>The elections are the first in Italy since prime minister Matteo Renzi’s Democratic party scored a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/may/26/italy-democratic-party-win-european-elections-matteo-renzi-five-star-movement">resounding victory with 40% of the vote in the European elections</ref> last year.</p>
    <p>The ballots are seen as a test for both Renzi and for Berlusconi’s fading Forza Italia, which faces a growing challenge for rightwing votes from the anti-immigration Northern League, which is led by rising star Matteo Salvini.</p>
    <p>Five of the seven regions holding elections are governed by the left, one is led by the League and another by Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>Bookmakers suggest the left will win six regions, with Veneto in the north-east remaining with the League.</p>
    <p>Renzi, 40, appears to remain popular with voters after almost 18 months as prime minister.</p>
    <p>Giovanni Orsina, political scientist at the Luiss University in Rome, said: “The alternatives to Renzi are not very attractive – he remains the only serious political offer.”</p>
    <p>A poor performance could spell the end of Berlusconi’s political career, Orsina added.</p>
    <p>In March the billionaire businessman was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/mar/11/berlusconi-vows-political-comeback-after-sex-case-acquittal-upheld">acquitted by Italy’s top court</ref> of charges of paying for an underage prostitute and using his political clout to cover it up. He has also performed a stint of community service for tax fraud.</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>This article was amended on 1 June 2015. It originally stated that the elections are the first in Italy since Renzi’s Democratic party won power with just over 40% of the vote. They are the first since the party scored a resounding victory in the European elections last year, not since the general election in 2013. This has been clarified.</item>
    </list>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>