<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Said &amp; Done: the week in football – Rio, Silvo, and the ghost of Dragao" author="David Hills" date="2012-10-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2012/oct/28/said-and-done-rio-ferdinand" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The week in football: Rio's best campaigns; why skincare matters; the ghost of Dragão; plus an ugly affair" categories="Football" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Rio Ferdinand,Uefa,Football,Football politics,Race,Sport" fingerprint="342dca7175a2c3bf">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">The week in racism: best campaigner</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Rio Ferdinand </hi>– joining the protest against Kick It Out's "ineffective" campaign message. Rio's own campaign highlights: 2008, calling on Uefa to act against homophobic abuse, two years after calling Chris Moyles "a faggot" live on air; 2009, <ref target="http://www.campaignlive.co.uk/news/871082/">fronting a new Nike campaign</ref> aimed at deglamorising gang violence – a month after agreeing to co-fund gangland drugs movie <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1311699/"> Dead Man Running</ref>, starring 50 Cent.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Runner-up</head>
    <p>Serbia's FA president <hi rend="#b">Tomislav Karadzic:</hi> reacting to Uefa's misconduct charge by launching a new FA anti-racism campaign, sending "a clear, sincere message around the world: we are together in this fight" – seven days after <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2012/oct/17/serbian-fa-deny-racism-danny-rose-vulgar">denying "any occurences" of racist abuse</ref> at the Under-21 match. "Serbian people have never been, nor will be, racist."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Plus: Most consistent</head>
    <p>The <hi rend="#b">Spanish FA </hi>fining policy: <hi rend="#b">€3k: </hi>Fine for Luis Aragonés for calling Thierry Henry a "black shit" in 2005. <hi rend="#b">€3k: </hi>Fine for Real Madrid in 2009 after fans sang about gas chambers. <hi rend="#b">€3k: </hi>Fine last week for Celta Vigo for delaying a kick-off by four minutes due to their substitute keeper not being ready to come on. FA: "This betrayed a remarkable lack of foresight."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Other news: ban of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Uefa</hi> – 12 months after extending their 20-year sponsorship deal with Ford to 2015 – blocking Racing Genk's plan to wear T-shirts and armbands in support of 4,500 local Ford workers set to be laid off. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/uefa">Uefa</ref> ruled Genk could put out a video or PA message instead, "before kick-off".</p>
    <head rend="h2">PR news: big week for</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi: </hi>looking to protect Milan's image while fighting underage prostitution charges, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/oct/26/silvio-berlusconi-sentenced-four-years">his fraud conviction</ref> and the court's ruling that he has a "natural capacity for crime". Last year Berlusconi revealed he ruled out a Milan bid for Mario Balotelli due to the striker's negative "moral image". "There is a Milan code of behaviour that I don't think is very close to that of Balotelli. I just don't like his style."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Last week's exits</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">16 Oct: </hi>Senegal coach Joseph Koto: "Yes there are goals written into my contract, but bosses are reasonable when they set goals. I trust my bosses, and I thank them all for their confidence. I will continue the work I started." <hi rend="#b">24 Oct: </hi>Sacked. FA: "He did not realise his goals."</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">22 Oct: </hi>Paul Jewell, Ipswich: "If [owner] Marcus Evans was looking for somebody else he would have told me. We have a really open and honest relationship. He wants me to stay. I want to stay." <hi rend="#b">24 Oct: </hi>Chief executive Simon Clegg says replacing Jewell will be easy. "Marcus and I have been brainstorming for weeks."</p>
    <p> Plus<hi rend="#b"> Peter Taylor:</hi> sacked by Bahrain after 15 months, despite staying on-message. Asked in April about the arrest and torture of up to 150 pro-democracy athletes, including three of his players, Taylor told reporters: "Don't go there. You're getting boring."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Clarification of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Turkey: </hi>Besiktas board member Tamer Kiran, clarifying why vice-president Ahmet Nur Cebi told the press their winger Ricardo Quaresma had "urinated on the kit man" and "exposed himself to staff". Kiran: "Journalists were asking him outrageous questions. He gave those answers to get rid of them." Quaresma is "considering legal options".</p>
    <head rend="h2">Verdict of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Paraguay: </hi>Referee director Esteban Torres on why one of his officials at a youth game sent off all 22 boys plus 14 subs after a <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7yX8oQwsEXI">mass brawl</ref>. "He was agitated. He did it after retreating to the changing room, the only safe place. Young people today are very rebellious."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Reflection of the week</head>
    <p>Mario Balotelli's agent and advisor <hi rend="#b">Mino Raiola</hi>, reflecting on a run-in with Johan Cruyff: "When Cruyff starts talking, everyone else zones out. If he says that the world is flat, everyone says OK. But no one asks what the demented bastard actually means."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Ghost of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Monday: </hi>Portuguese press reprint a photograph "<ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=hs7SI-gw664#">clearly showing a ghost celebrating a goal</ref>" at Porto's Estádio do Dragão. Experts reveal the image, of a dark figure in "clothes from another era with an outdated haircut", could not have been doctored. <hi rend="#b">Tuesday:</hi> Other angles reveal it was actually "<ref target="http://www.mundodeportivo.com/20121023/fotos/el-presunto-fantasma-se-trataba-de-una-anciana-aficionada-del-porto_54353386349.html">an old person</ref>". Press: "There is no ghost of Dragão."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Skincare news</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Brazil: </hi>Atlético Mineiro's Richarlyson on why footballers must "be serious about skincare": "Am I am beautiful? Yes. I have three creams, for the night, for the day and for the eyes. You cannot take care of your image with dark eye circles, right?"</p>
    <head rend="h2">Plus: Model news</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Argentina: </hi>Model Cinthia Fernández says reports she responded to a Huracán fan calling her partner Matías Defederico "rubbish" by "beating him while swearing" are overplayed. Fernández: "I only reacted to defend my family. I thank all the nice people who intervened. This was an ugly affair."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>