<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian PM wins confidence vote after Berlusconi abandons revolt - as it happens" author="Graeme Wearden" date="2013-10-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/oct/02/italian-prime-minister-faces-crunch-confidence-vote-live" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Risk of eurozone crisis escalating eases as Enrico Letta survives a crucial confidence vote, leaving Silvio Berlusconi facing a divided party" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,European Central Bank,Mario Draghi" fingerprint="7faf1a15d60767ad">
  <main>
    <p>Italian Prime Minister Enrico Letta gestures next to Italian Interior Minister Angelino Alfano at the lower house of Parliament in Rome, Italy, tonight. Photograph: CLAUDIO ONORATI/EPA Photograph: CLAUDIO ONORATI/EPA</p>
    <p>Time to wrap up for the day. Here's a very brisk summary.</p>
    <p>It was a remarkable u-turn, given Italy was plunged into political crisis last week when Berlusconi pulled his ministers out of the government last week. But there were simply too many PdL rebels -- who chose to support Letta rather than their leader. Highlights of the debate start here.</p>
    <p>In a sombre, defiant speech, Letta warned that Italy would be plunged deeper into crisis and deadlock unless the Senate backed him.</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi looks wounded tonight, with a troop of senators seemingly defecting, led by his long-time ally Angelino Alfano. Berlusconi still faces the prospect of being thrown out of the Senate and a period of house arrest following his tax fraud conviction. Here's John Hooper's analysis.</p>
    <p>There is shock and anger in Greece after three Golden Dawn MPs were released from custody, having been arrested in a clampdown on the neo-Nazi party last week.</p>
    <p>My colleagues Larry Elliott and Phillip Inman report:</p>
    <p>The governor, speaking on ITV News Anglia, reinforced the message from another senior Bank official - Paul Fisher - in which he said both borrowers and lenders should be careful not to overstretch themselves.</p>
    <p>Fisher, Threadneedle Street’s executive director of markets, rejected the idea that a property bubble was emerging but stressed that the Bank was alert to the risks to the economy from another boom-bust. His comments came as the latest construction figures revealed a strong increase in private housebuilding, offering a counterpoint to mounting fears that the ground is being laid for a new housing crash.</p>
    <p>Fisher said the market was clearly gathering momentum after years in the doldrums and prices had again started to hit the headlines.</p>
    <p>“I must say that don’t see any evidence of bubble behaviour as yet, with mortgage lending still subdued relative to what is likely to be normal levels of activity. The housing market is recovering from a number of years of very low transactions, with house prices having risen well below the inflation rate.”</p>
    <p>Mark Carney warns of risk of rising interest rates</p>
    <p>Some late breaking news –Bank of England governor Mark Carney has warned prospective house buyers to prepare for higher interest rates once the recovery takes hold.</p>
    <p>That's an interesting intervention from Carney, at a time when mortgage approvals and house prices are rising, and the government is has accelerated its its Help to Buy scheme. The Bank itself has pledged to keep borrowing costs at record lows until the recovery is secure, and the unemployment rate has fallen to 7%.</p>
    <p>He made the comments to ITV News on a visit to East Anglia today. Details of the interview is breaking now (it was embargoed until 6pm, so half the country's economics correspondents have been eagerly sifting through local Norfolk news for the last 20 minutes, looking for it).</p>
    <p>ITV's economics editor Richard Edgar is tweeting the highlights:</p>
    <p>Mark Carney tells ITV Anglia "It's not enough just to have a recovery in London and the South East."</p>
    <p>Brenda Kelly of IG sums up the political state of play:</p>
    <p>It’s akin to entering a type of twilight zone when the world witnesses a quick fix in Italian politics, while the US languishes in uncertainty.</p>
    <p>Today's Berlusconi U-turn was deemed positive for Italy, politically and economically. Prime minister Enrico Letto won the confidence vote and so the market can expect to see the necessary Italian budget reforms.</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta gave a victory sign in the lower house of the Italian parliament a few minutes ago, after giving a similar speech to his address in the Senate.</p>
    <p>Photograph: ANDREAS SOLARO/AFP/Getty Images Photograph: ANDREAS SOLARO/AFP/Getty Images</p>
    <p>As Letta's party controls the lower house, there's no danger of losing a confidence vote there - the Senate was the key battleground today, and Letta was victorious.</p>
    <p>Alex Young of CMC Markets points out that Wall Street's decline was also due to weak job creation data released this in America today:</p>
    <p>Today’s monthly ADP employment figure became encumbered with greater significance than the private payroll figure is normally afforded after we’d learner earlier in the week that the non-farm payroll figure will not be produced by the US Federal Bureau of Statistics. The double whammy of a September miss, 166k versus the 180k expected, and revision down of Augusts numbers to 159k from 176k assured a negative open for US equities compounded by the political shambles that has resulted in a second day of shutdowns.</p>
    <p>Relief that Enrico Letta won today's confidence vote pushed up shares on the Milan stock market, while edginess over the US government shutdown hit shares elsewhere.</p>
    <p>Here's the closing prices:</p>
    <p>Italian FTSE MIB: up 121 points at 18,098, +0.68%</p>
    <p>FTSE 100: down 22 points at 6,437, -0.35%</p>
    <p>German DAX: down 59 points at 8,629, -0.7%</p>
    <p>French CAC: down 40 points at 4,155, - 1%</p>
    <p>Spanish IBEX: up 8 points at 9,350, + 0.1%</p>
    <p>While on Wall Street the Dow is still in the red, currently down 86 points at 15,106.</p>
    <p>University of Reading professor Christopher Duggan describes today's drama in the Italian senate as a humiliating u-turn for Silvio Berlusconi, and an enormous boost to prime minister Letta.</p>
    <p>Duggan explains:</p>
    <p>It leaves Berlusconi greatly weakened, and with the judicial noose tightening around him, his political star now looks to be firmly waning.</p>
    <p>However, the increasingly fraught and unstable character of the party political landscape in Italy leaves the government facing some difficult times ahead if it is to pass much needed reforms.</p>
    <p>From Rome, our correspondent Lizzy Davies reports:</p>
    <p>Italy's grand coalition government looks certain to limp on after Silvio Berlusconi, the former prime minister who had brought it to the brink of collapse with a threat to withdraw his MPs, backed down at the last minute when it became clear that rebels from his own party would allow a confidence vote to pass.</p>
    <p>In an unusually curt statement in the upper house of parliament, the 77-year-old – who was convicted of tax fraud in August – said his deeply divided centre-right Freedom People (PdL) party would vote as a block to support Enrico Letta's coalition.</p>
    <p>It was a humiliating defeat for the man who has dominated the Italian political landscape for two decades, even if, by choosing to support the government, he will no doubt reserve the right to present himself as a responsible statesman.</p>
    <p>Helena Smith: Greece stunned as Golden Dawn MPs leave custody</p>
    <p>Ultra-right wing party Golden Dawn supporters gathered outside the Athens' courthouse this morning. Photograph: ORESTIS PANAGIOTOU/EPA Photograph: ORESTIS PANAGIOTOU/EPA</p>
    <p>Our correspondent in Athens, Helena Smith, reports:</p>
    <p>To say there is shock at the release of the four far-rightists only hours before Golden Dawn’s leader was due to defend himself before an investigating magistrate in Athens is to understate the fact.</p>
    <p>Although the governing coalition is playing down the decision - with several ministers insisting that the penal process has “only just begun” – stunned reactions are coming through from the political opposition.</p>
    <p>Fotis Kouvelis, the leader of the small Democratic Left party that was in government until it broke ranks earlier this year, said allowing the three MPs to walk free “had undoubtedly created a political climate” – a coded reference to further political tensions. Dimitris Papadimoulis, the parliamentary representative of the main opposition Syriza party, went further questioning the point of arresting the MPs on charges of operating a criminal organisation at all.</p>
    <p>“If they were going to set them free then what was the point of the show with the handcuffs?” he tweeted.</p>
    <p>Αν ήταν να τους αφήσουν ελεύθερους, προς τι αυτό το σόου με τις χειροπέδες; Η πολιτική-επικοινωνιακή διαχείριση απο την Κυβέρνηση, πάσχει...</p>
    <p>High-powered lawyers wondered if this was the first step in the dissolution of the case – a shocking step in itself given that the case had been instigated at the highest level of executive and judicial power with a Supreme Court prosecutor leveling the charges.</p>
    <p>“This development shows that at least in the eyes of the court authorities the case was not substantiated enough,” said Harris Ikonopoulos, the publisher of the left-leaning daily Eleftherotypia and a leading lawyer himself. “It creates the perception of a failed state,” he told me adding that it would raise “all sorts of questions” not least that of the competency of Greek justice.</p>
    <p>If the reactions of the three MPs themselves are anything to go by it will also embolden Golden Dawn.</p>
    <p>The neo-Nazi party is quite clearly on a war path with the media in the wake of revelations since the fatal stabbing of Greek rapper Pavlos Fyssas. The obscenities hurled today at journalists – who in two cases were also kicked and shoved – takes that confrontation to a whole new level. “Now you will see you disgusting people,” Ilias Panaghiotaros, one of the deputies, roared. “You will only stop us with bullets.” The abuse came less than 24 hours after Eleni Zaroulia, the wife of Golden Dawn leader Nikos Michaloliakos, spat at a journalist and physically attacked a cameraman outside the court.</p>
    <p>This is the first thing they did after being released, they assaulted journalists outside the building http://t.co/AemUlC1Dgk#GD_arrested</p>
    <p>Looks like Wall Street may have finally woken up to the US government shutdown.</p>
    <p>With federal government services still shuttered, and no signs of progress on Capitol Hill, the Dow Jones industrial average has dropped by 140 points after an hour's trading, a loss of 0.9% to 15056.</p>
    <p>Analysts were surprised yesterday that investors reacted so calmly. Looks like it's second-thoughts time.</p>
    <p>Andrew Wilkinson, chief economic strategist at Miller Tabak, told Marketwatch that investors were:</p>
    <p>having a little rethink over the implications and longevity of the U.S. government shutdown.</p>
    <p>Good idea, I'd suggest, with America getting closer to hitting the US debt ceiling.</p>
    <p>For all the latest on the US government shutdown, follow Tom McCarthy's liveblog:</p>
    <p>An Italian lip reader has watched a recording of Enrico Letta, at the moment Silvio Berlusconi announced that People of Freedom would support him in today's vote.</p>
    <p>I mentioned earlierthat Letta wasn't delirious with joy -- turns out he also muttered "He's a great....." but didn't catch the final word. Any ideas? I suspect it wasn't "Statesman"</p>
    <p>#Italian crisis biggest #fail: lipreader says Letta reacted to #Berlusconi U-turn with "He's a great ..." But didn't get next word.</p>
    <p>John Hooper: Berlusconi faces party split and ejection from the Senate</p>
    <p>Former Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi in the Italian Senate today. Photograph: Franco Origlia/Getty Images Photograph: Franco Origlia/Getty Images</p>
    <p>Our Southern Europe editor, John Hooper, explains that Silvio Berlusconi's People of Freedom party is still likely to split, despite his decision to drop attempts to bring down Enrico Letta's government.</p>
    <p>New list circulating in lower house of 25 deputies ready to leave #Berlusconi. Including his erstwhile anointed successor, Angelino Alfano.</p>
    <p>And Berlusconi also faces the prospect of being ejected from the Senate in the coming days.</p>
    <p>Here's John's analysis:</p>
    <p>Corriere della Sera’s Berlusconi-watcher put it nicely in a tweet: he’s “the only person in the world who can win, lose and draw the same game”. But the same might almost be said of Enrico Letta.</p>
    <p>A real win would have been to crush a defiant Silvio Berlusoni in parliament and go forward with a new, more cohesive majority. That is the prospect that caused Tuesday's market euphoria. But it has not happened.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, the media tycoon has been challenged, and effectively so.</p>
    <p>And now it looks as if there is going to be a split, with perhaps 26 of his deputies (out of 97) and 18 of his Senators (out of 91) leaving to form a new group.</p>
    <p>Those numbers would probably have been enough to give Letta a bare majority. So Berlusconi no longer has an indisputable veto over the government, and that should make Letta’s life easier in future.</p>
    <p>But the future in Italy still looks tempestuous, and the prospects for radical economic reform distinctly uncertain. On Friday, a parliamentary panel is due to begin the process of ejecting Berlusconi from the Senate. He could resign rather than face that indignity. But thereafter the focus will shift from the parliament to the courts: there is a humiliating decision for the TV magnate to take as to whether he should do community service or accept house arrest; then the appeal in the ‘Bunga Bunga trial’ and another for leaking confidential judicial evidence; then possible indictment for bribery.</p>
    <p>It is small compensation for him that the shenanigans of the last few days have enabled him to disown what will doubtless be an unpopular VAT rise.</p>
    <p>Prime Minister Enrico Letta today. Photograph: Franco Origlia/Getty Images Photograph: Franco Origlia/Getty Images</p>
    <p>European central bank president Mario Draghi warned that the US government shutdown could hurt the global recovery if it is not resolved soon.</p>
    <p>Asked about the deadlock in Washington, Draghi said the shutdown, which began at midnight yesterday, "is a risk if it is protracted".</p>
    <p>At the present time, the impresson one has it that it will not be so. But if it were to be protected, it is certainly a risk to the US and the world recovery, so we need to have it present in our minds.</p>
    <p>And asked again about Italy, Draghi said that the financial markets have a simple message for governments - they want "stability and reforms".</p>
    <p>People of Freedom party leader Silvio Berlusconi dramatically announcing his support for Enrico Letta. Photograph: Gregorio Borgia/AP Photograph: Gregorio Borgia/AP</p>
    <p>In a dramatic move, the former prime minister announced that he would back prime minister Enrico Letta in today's crucial vote of confidence.</p>
    <p>This ensures that Letta will continue as PM, and spares Italy the risk of new general elections -- in the short term at least.</p>
    <p>That vote was called after Berlusconi ordered ministers from his own People of Freedom (PdL) party to withdraw from Letta's coalition late last week.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's hand was forced by a revoltfrom a group of his own senators, who vowed to defy their leader and vote with Letta. That raised the prospect of the PdL faction imploding.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's u-turn meant that Enrico Letta stormed to victory in today's vote, with 235 senators backing him and just 70 voting against.</p>
    <p>Draghi: political instability isn't as dangerous today</p>
    <p>Back at the ECB press conference in Paris, Mario Draghi is asked to comment on the Italian political crisis.</p>
    <p>He agrees to answer in general terms, and tells reporters that such dramas aren't as dangerous as before:</p>
    <p>While instability may be hampering hopes for a recovery in these countries, it doesn't really hurt the foundations of the eurozone as it used to do a few years ago.</p>
    <p>In other worlds, the eurozone and the euro is more resilient than a few years ago.</p>
    <p>Why? Draghi cited improved governance in the euro area, the ECB's own promise to buy eurozone government bonds if needed.</p>
    <p>It looks like an even bigger win for Letta than the provisional voting figures indicated - 235 votes in support in the confidence vote, and just 70 against.</p>
    <p>Mario Draghi revealed that the ECB governing council also considered a rate cut - before leaving borrowing costs unchanged. And he also brought up the possibility of another round of cheap loans for commercial banks, to encourage lending.</p>
    <p>"We are ready to use all available instruments , including an LTRO" - Draghi repeats willingness to extend more ultra-cheap loans to banks</p>
    <p>Squinting back at the ECB press conference in Paris...</p>
    <p>Mario Draghi remained concerned about the euro economy, saying risks remain to the downside [they'd be riskier if the Italian government had just sunk].</p>
    <p>He also urged eurozone governments to continue taking steps to tackle their deficits.</p>
    <p>Confirmation that Enrico Letta has won today's confidence vote comfortably, following Silvio Berlusconi's decision to back him (although he was on track to win anyway, it seems).</p>
    <p>Lizzy Davies provides the details -- although these look like provisional figures at this stage...:</p>
    <p>No early drama from Mario Draghi at the ECB press conference. He's reiterating that the ECB will keep interest rates at present or lower levels for an extended period of time -- given the low inflation and weak economic growth in the eurozone.</p>
    <p>And he's talking about the governing council standing ready to launch new monetary 'instruments' if needed to support the eurozone economy (that could be new cheap loans for banks).</p>
    <p>It will be fascinating to see what Mario Draghi, head of the European Central Bank, makes of the Italian situation when he begins a press conference in 20 minutes time (as expected, they have left interest rates unchanged)</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta, at the moment Berlusconi declared his support. Photograph: /RAI News Photograph: RAI News</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta definitely looked less than euphoric as Berlusconi yanked hard on the political handbrake, and declared with palpable understatement:</p>
    <p>we have decided, not without some internal strife, to support the government.</p>
    <p>The general view among Italian political journalists is that Letta would be much better off without Berlusconi around at all. Instead, Letta remains the prime minister of a shaky coalition.</p>
    <p>Sky TV presenter: "So the govt will continue with the same parties but the same problems." Quite.</p>
    <p>Having said that, Berlusconi is damaged by the antics of the last few days. The remarkable political gymnastics must have taken their toll -- and an optimist might argue that PdL is irrevocably on the path to a new future....</p>
    <p>Add all Berlusconi's PdL senators to Letta's existing support -- his PD party, plus small parties and senators for life -- and it's a healthy majority.</p>
    <p>So why did Berlusconi do it? Clearly, he concluded that he could not keep enough of his PdL party onside. The photo I included in the blog earliershowed a long list of rebels.</p>
    <p>If Berlusconi hadn't pulled such a SCREECHING u-turn, then he would presumably have seen his group shatter. The moderates would have followed Letta, and he'd have been left nursing a rump faction.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi himself buried his head in his hands after announcing that the PdL party will support Letta -- which means today's confidence vote is a WIN for the prime minister.</p>
    <p>It was not the speech of a winner -- rather of a man whose long grip on his party may be slipping .</p>
    <p>Former technocratic prime minister Mario Monti just gave a brisk speech, in which he urged senators not to risk Italy falling into the troika and its "neocolonial oversight". If Italy is forced to take a bailout, it could take years to recover, Monti warned.</p>
    <p>Debate in the Senate should be over soon. #Berlusconi expected to talk for the PDL before the confidence vote #Italy</p>
    <p>While we wait for that vote, here's Reuters' report on Letta's second speech to the Senate:</p>
    <p>Italian Prime Minister Enrico Letta said on Wednesday his government could achieve reforms even with a smaller majority, as he wound up a debate on a confidence vote in which he has been boosted by dissidents from Silvio Berlusconi's centre-right party.</p>
    <p>"Our government can reach its objectives despite the fact that the majority's numbers have changed," Letta said as he formally put a confidence motion to the Senate, which is expected to complete the vote in the early afternoon.</p>
    <p>Letta spoke at length about Italy's role in the European Union and his goal to push for greater integration during the country's rotating presidency in the second half of 2014, suggesting he sees his government lasting at least until 2015.</p>
    <p>The vote hasn't actually started yet. Senators are continuing to give their views. The latest word from Rome is that Berlusconi isn't expected to speak (but given today's twists and turns, let's see).</p>
    <p>To repeat, Enrico Letta has called for a vote of confidence.</p>
    <p>After a dramatic couple of hours in the Senate, we still don't know what's going to happen. There have been rumours that Berlusconi will back Letta, and also that he will order the entire PdL party to vote against. Speculation abounds.</p>
    <p>We do know that there is a solid bunch of 'dovish' PdL senators who are unlikely to bow to pressure from Berlusconi, and are highly likely to back Letta. But we do not know if it will be enough.</p>
    <p>As John Hooper flagged up, the Berlusconi rebels are talking about creating a new party called "Popolari per l'Italia".</p>
    <p>Wolf Piccoli, managing director at Teneo Intelligence, is as reliable as any, and he reckons Letta might get 171 votes -- that's a win, as he needs 160 for victory.</p>
    <p>A briefer speech from Letta this time -- his main message to the Senate is that today is a historic opportunity. Tomorrow the government must get back to work.</p>
    <p>Amid applause from some members of the senate, Letta calls for a confidence vote:</p>
    <p>Senators applauding Enrico Letta at the end of his speech. Photograph: RAI News Photograph: RAI News</p>
    <p>Italian prime Enrico Letta is beginning his second speech to the Senate, explaining that he didn't sleep last night as he worked to hold the government together.</p>
    <p>He's initially heard in silence (gosh it's tense), but there's some heckling as Letta bluntly tells the Senate that he's not prepared to keep taking "lessons in morality" from those who are holding him to ransom.</p>
    <p>Letta says he's had enough of taking lessons in morality from people threatening the govt. Then he's heckled by Scilipoti. Oh God.</p>
    <p>The rumour mill keeps swirling in Italy ahead of this lunchtime's confidence vote. One insider reckons Berlusconi is going to back Letta, the next says he's not. Confusion reigns (not for the first, or last time).</p>
    <p>John Hooper, our Souther Europe editor, reports that Berlusconi's rebels are talking of creating a new party called "Popolari per l'Italia" - even if the loyalist wing of PdL join them by supporting Letta.</p>
    <p>Three Golden Dawn MPs released on bail - lash out at press</p>
    <p>Breaking away to Greece briefly.</p>
    <p>Four of the Golden Dawn MPs who were arrested as part of the clampdown on the neo-Nazi party appeared in court today. Three of the men were promptly released pending a future trial, while party leader Nikolaos Michaloliakos is due back in court later today.</p>
    <p>TV footage from the scene shows one cameraman being pushed out of the way, while another man is kicked as the MPs and their supporters leave the scene.</p>
    <p>Here's the video clip showing the aggressive scenes:</p>
    <p>Only one of four Golden Dawn deputies arrested last week on charges of heading a criminal organization responsible for a range of felonies, including murder, assault, blackmail and money laundering, among others, was remanded in custody on Wednesday, while another three were released pending trial, one of them posting a 50,000 euro bail.</p>
    <p>Yiannis Lagos was expected to be transferred to a local jail on Wednesday following a unanimous decision reached by two investigative magistrates and two prosecutors.</p>
    <p>Party spokesman Ilias Kasidiaris was ordered to post a €50,000 bail and not to exit the country. Deputies Ilias Panayiotaros and Nikos Michos were also ordered not to leave the country.</p>
    <p>The clampdown followed the death of 34-year-old rapper Pavlos Fyssas two weeks ago. A Golden Dawn member was subsequently arrested over the stabbing.</p>
    <p>It is increasingly likely that Enrico Letta has enough votes for victory, even if Berlusconi decides to back him.</p>
    <p>Letta needs 161 votes for victory - although he would like more. Vincenzo Scarpetta of Open Europe reckons that he currently has 170 senators behind him, based on the latest reports and public statements.</p>
    <p>Here's how Barclays summed it up this morning:</p>
    <p>Letta has the numbers to survive the vote today. The Government needs the support of 161 Senators, and can count on 137.</p>
    <p>With the support of the life Senators, and defectors from the smaller parties (including M5S) it is likely to get to around 147-149. Letta therefore only needs around 12-14 PdL Senators to defect in order to survive. With the PdL split he is likely to get this.</p>
    <p>It would be a stunning u-turn from Silvio Berlusconi if, as reports suggest, he has now decided to back Enrico Letta in today's vote of confidence.</p>
    <p>But it wouldn't exactly be out of character -- and a number of political journalists and analysts were suggesting yesterday that this might happen, once we learned that his party were rebelling.</p>
    <p>As tweeted yesterday https://t.co/xvBrcPswmz - Berlusconi u-turn likely according to Sky reports.</p>
    <p>Remember, it was Berlusconi who triggered this crisis by threatening to bring the government down last week -- by withdrawing his PdL party from the Letta coalition.</p>
    <p>If he backs Letta today, then he could still trigger a crisis in future.</p>
    <p>Important: Sky Italia is reporting that the People of Freedom party are going to BACK Enrico Letta in the confidence vote.</p>
    <p>If true, that means Letta would win a solid majority. It would also suggest that Berlusconi has decided that he cannot bring his rebels back into line, and has decided to fall in with them.</p>
    <p>That is NOT the best result for Letta, though. While he'd still be in power, he'd also still be lumbered with the Berlusconi problem.</p>
    <p>If true, this wd present PM with hell of a headache. Govt wd survive but Berlusconi wd try to be the responsible man &amp; daily fights continue</p>
    <p>Italian government bonds are also strengthening, which has pushed the yield on its 10-year debt down to 4.37% . It as as high as 4.74% on Monday after Berlusconi launched his bid to bring the Letta government down.</p>
    <p>Five months isn't enough time to build a track record of leadership success -- and much of Letta's time as prime minister has been overshadowed by Berlusconi's legal defeats.</p>
    <p>It was a speech of vision -- asking Senators to choose between future of a more competitive, thriving Italy, or a future of political strife, fresh elections, and the prospect of another divided parliament at the end of it.</p>
    <p>Letta isn't the most thrilling orator in European politics, but he has a mature, sensible style.</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta concluded his speech by urging those in the chamber to give him their "courage and confidence". "A confidence that is not against anyone; a confidence that is for Italy" (quotes via Lizzy).</p>
    <p>He also urged senators to search their consciences, and avoid a result that would leave them feeling "shameful regret".</p>
    <p>There's also a European theme to the speech -- with Letta speaking of the need to dream of a "United States of Europe" one day. That fits with his tradition of being a solid Europhile (he was an MEP at one stage of his career)</p>
    <p>#Letta: We have the right to dream of the United States of Europe. #Italy</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta's speech is turning into a solid defense of his government's record in the five months since he took over (colleague Lizzy Davies dubs it a " very level-headed and systematic defense".</p>
    <p>But will that be enough to persuade PdL members to back him? As explained earlier -- Letta would like to see 30 rebels jump the fence. He needs more than 20 (I think 24 is the magic number).</p>
    <p>Letta is continuing to defend his government's record on the economy -- part of the strategy to persuade moderate members of the Berlusconi camp to back him.</p>
    <p>It is on ordinary people suffering in economic crisis that our actions will have biggest effect, he said.</p>
    <p>No sign of Silvio Berlusconi at the start of Letta's crunch speech. Angelino Alfano (deputy PM) is there, and there's a consensus that he looks nervous.</p>
    <p>Alfano seated next to Letta, looks tense and tired. #Berlusconi not present yet:most likely taking girlfriend's dog (Dudu) for a walk #Italy</p>
    <p>Looks like the confidence vote will come at midday -- earlier than the previous indications.</p>
    <p>And how many rebels will there be?</p>
    <p>Lizzy Davies writes:</p>
    <p>It's all about the numbers today. Giovanardi claimed yesterday there were "more than 40"- believed to be as many as 44- PdL MPs prepared to vote for the confidence vote. But the Italian press reports that Berlusconi's hawks told him the rebels were much- much- less numerous. Who's right?</p>
    <p>We'll find out soon. Letta needs over 20 rebels. He'd be happier with more than 30.</p>
    <p>(a reminder -- Italy's last election, in February, resulted in deadlock -- with no party winning a majority in the Senate. Eventually a coalition was agreed between the centre-left PD and Berlusconi's centre-right PdL, with Letta (a senior member of PD) as leader)</p>
    <p>Prime minister Enrico Letta has begun to give one of the speeches of his political life, in a bid to win enough support to continue as the head of Italy's shaky coalition government.</p>
    <p>Before he started, there was a standing ovation for the country's veteran president, Giorgio Napolitano.</p>
    <p>Letta began his speech in the Italian parliament by urging its members to "seize the moment". And, as expected, he insisted that the legal troubles of Silvio Berlusconi cannot be an excuse to bring the country's government down.</p>
    <p>But can he persuade enough of Berlusconi's PdL party to back him?</p>
    <p>Lizzy Davies is tweeting the key points, so I'll be embedding them in the blog now....</p>
    <p>Europe's stock markets are all in the red today, with the FTSE 100 shedding 73 points. There's nervousness about the situation in Italy, and also a knock-on effect from a bad day in Asia. The US Federal government shutdown isn't exactly helping sentiment.</p>
    <p>Overnight, the Nikkei tumbled 2% after the latest stimulus package from prime minister Abe failed to excite investors.</p>
    <p>In the City, Tesco's shares are leading the fallers on the FTSE 100 after issuing a trading statement, down over 3%.</p>
    <p>Britain's biggest supermarket reported zero growth in like-for like UK sales, excluding fuel and VAT sales tax, in the 13 weeks to 24 August.</p>
    <p>Tesco also warned that it faced 'challenging economic conditions' overseas. Europe was particularly tough, with profits down almost 70% and like-for-like sales down by 5% in the first half of the year.</p>
    <p>Sainsbury posted stronger figures in the UK (as expected) - sales at British stores open at least a year were up 2%. Its shares are also suffering, though, down 1.5%. More here.</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi carrying his pet dog as he arrives at his official residence on September 30, 2013. Photograph: REUTERS TV/Reuters Photograph: REUTERS TV/Reuters</p>
    <p>In the red corner, we have PM Letta, who has probably worked hard – together with the President – to convince some of Berlusconi’s senators that new elections at this point is in no one’s interest.</p>
    <p>A vote for a continuation of the current government and later on a vote for a budget and a new electoral law would make for a fresh start after spring elections. In the blue corner, we have Berlusconi. Media are full of stories about Berlusconi’s outstanding merits when it comes to winning tight political battles. But this time it seems that even members of his own party believes he has gone too far. Even Alfano – who has been seen as the crown prince in the PDL – said that he might vote for a continuation of the government.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, it may be the old Champs last fight, if he is stripped of his senatorial seat on Friday. It will be a close call. Italy, and to a lesser extent Spain, will sell off if the government falls.</p>
    <p>Jeremy Cook of World First agrees:</p>
    <p>We are heading for a good, old-fashioned political ding dong tonight in Italy; end of a government or the end of a Godfather?</p>
    <p>What might Letta tell parliament in his speech this morning?</p>
    <p>Lizzy Davies explains that his speech is likely to focus on the socio-economic suffering of Italy, and tell deputies that they cannot just let its government fall.</p>
    <p>His strategy will be to ram home the idea that the judicial woes of one man* have to be kept separate from the interests of the country – in an effort to split the doves in Berlusconi's party from the hawks.</p>
    <p>In the comments section, regular reader mrwicket has outlined the potential scenarios from tonight's vote.</p>
    <p>As he flags up, we're not 100% certain that a confidence vote will actually be called -- Enrico Letta will probably judge the mood of the Senate first, and if he feels he can't win then he might simply resign.</p>
    <p>So, Django Alfano is standing his ground and wants to support Letta in the vote of confidence, as do the other maybe ministers and a chunk of the party.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi says he wants the government to fall and to have new elections.</p>
    <p>The two will meet again this morning at 9'30 so things could change.</p>
    <p>Marina Berlusconi is said to be ready to enter into politics.</p>
    <p>I asked yesterday how you could have a vote of confidence in a government that didn't exist. On Monday, Letta's office said the resignations were irrevocable but yesterday afternoon, it announced that it had refused to accept them. The 'maybe ministers' will walk into parliament today as ministers.</p>
    <p>Giovanardi claimed yesterday that there were 40 PdL senators ready to vote for Letta (some reports in the evening said that number was dwindling). He even spoke of a new party called Nuova Italia</p>
    <p>There were some nasty exchanges last night between Sallusti, editor of Il Giornale and Cicchitto, an important PdL dissident. Sallusti said they were cowards, hitting the man when he was down and that they had forgotten what had happened to Fini. "They are stabbing him in the back in his moment of weakness. They are cowards because they didn't have the courage to do it when he was strong." "No! You are the coward!" etc...</p>
    <p>Letta has said he will refuse to govern with a weak majority.</p>
    <p>------------</p>
    <p>Possible scenarios;</p>
    <p>Letta wins vote of confidence with sufficient votes to continue in government.</p>
    <p>Letta wins vote of confidence with insufficient votes to continue in government and Napolitano sets up a technical government.</p>
    <p>Letta wins vote of confidence by a narrow margin and continues to govern</p>
    <p>Letta loses vote of confidence and Napolitano sets up a technical government.</p>
    <p>Letta doesn't call for a vote of confidence and Napolitano sets up a technical government.</p>
    <p>------------</p>
    <p>With regard to policy, there would be very little to distinguish between a Letta government and a technical government so we will be as we were after this dramatic little interlude. The change is likely to be inside the PdL.</p>
    <p>Lisa Jucca, Reuters chief financial correspondent in Italy, agrees that this could be the moment that Angelino Alfano, Berlusconi's right-hand man for so long, finally rises up:</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi is facing an unprecedented rebellion, opening up the possibility that Letta can surge to victory tonight. As our Rome correspondent, Lizzy Davies, explains:</p>
    <p>To win the confidence vote in the senate, Letta needs to attract extra votes from either the centre-right PdL or the anti-establishment Five Star Movement (M5S) to reach the magic number of 161. He has said, however, that he has no interest in continuing at the head of a government that only sneaks in by a handful of votes.</p>
    <p>His chances appeared to have been significantly boosted on Tuesday, when Carlo Giovanardi, a long-time ally of Berlusconi, struck the first major blow when he announced that "more than 40" PdL MPs were prepared to vote to keep the government afloat.</p>
    <p>Then, in a stunning move likened by one observer to an "Et tu, Brute?" moment, Angelino Alfano, the deputy prime minister long seen as Berlusconi's political heir, appeared to solidify the mutiny. "I remain firmly convinced that all our party should tomorrow back the confidence vote in Letta," he said, according to Ansa.</p>
    <p>Italian premier Enrico Letta, speaking last Sunday. Photograph: Mauro Scrobogna/AP Photograph: Mauro Scrobogna/AP</p>
    <p>Good morning and welcome to our rolling coverage of the eurozone, the financial markets, the world economy and the business world.</p>
    <p>After yesterday's foray into the US shutdown , we're back in familiar territory today – the political crisis in Italy, with a monthly meeting of the European Central Bank on top.</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta, Italy's prime minister, is heading to parliament this morning for a make-or-break confidence vote. It was triggered by Silvio Berlusconi's decision last Saturday to ordered his ministers out of the coalition, to bring Letta down.</p>
    <p>Does Letta still have the support of the lower house, and the Senate? If not, Italy could be plunged deeper into chaos.</p>
    <p>But Letta could win, and wins well, if Berlusconi's centre-right party defy their disgraced leader and through their support behind the PM. Yesterday, key members of the People of Freedom party (PdL) said they would support the coalition [an alliance between Letta's own centre-left PD and the PdL].</p>
    <p>The big question is how many PdL members of the Senate decide to throw their support behind Letta today.</p>
    <p>Letta is due to start giving his first speech at around 9.30am Rome time, or 8.30am BST. The actual confidence vote could be quite late (we'll update with firm timings when we have them).</p>
    <p>Big day for #Italy. PM Letta to make speech of his life in support of the govt in Senate speech starting 9.30am. Vote will be- much- later.</p>
    <p>The other key event in the eurozone today is the monthly meeting of the ECB's governing council. They're in Paris today. We're not expecting any change to interest rates. There's also a press conference at 2.30pm Paris time (1.30pm BST), where Mario Draghi will be quizzed over a range of issues, doubtless including his homeland of Italy.</p>
    <p>#ECBguesses "I wouldn't want to comment on the political situation in Italy right now".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>