<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi defiant as escort scandal grows" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-06-21" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/21/silvio-berlusconi-escort-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="A third woman has confirms details of the night Italy's PM allegedly had sex with an escort" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="ffd8cf3dd2bee6b1">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi today promised he would "hang tough" in the face of a growing scandal over the alleged procurement of women for his social events, as a third woman stepped forward to confirm details of the night last November on which he allegedly had sex with a paid escort.</p>
    <p>Italy's prime minister has vowed not to allow the furore over his supposed antics with young women deflect him from running the government. But today another woman from the southern city of Bari, Lucia Rossini, confirmed salacious details about a dinner held at Berlusconi's Rome residence on 4 November.</p>
    <p>Rossini said Patrizia D'Addario, an alleged escort, remained behind when guests left that evening. Her account backs that given by a fellow guest, model Barbara Montereale, who said that D'Addario claimed the next day that she had had sexual relations with Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>The man who brought the three woman to the dinner, hospital equipment vendor Gianpaolo Tarantini, is being investigated by magistrates in Bari on suspicion of abetting prostitution. Magistrates have questioned all three women.</p>
    <p>Tarantini claimed today that any payments he agreed with women to attend functions with Berlusconi were only to cover travel expenses. "Having received invitations from Silvio Berlusconi, I decided to go, accompanied by some of my friends, to look good and stand out," Tarantini said. "It is absolutely out of the question that Berlusconi could have known about my reimbursements."</p>
    <p>The investigation is currently limited to Bari, where Tarantini and the three women are based, but Corriere della Sera said that women from other towns in Italy who attended parties may soon be called for questioning.</p>
    <p>D'Addario, 42, went public last week about the dinner, claiming she was offered €2,000 to spend the night at Berlusconi's residence but complaining that the prime minister had failed to make good on promises to help her obtain building permits for a planned hotel.</p>
    <p>Montereale said D'Addario was also spurred on by the notoriety gained by Noemi Letizia, the teenage model whose birthday party Berlusconi attended in April, prompting his wife to accuse him of "frequenting minors" and to start divorce proceedings.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>