<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Europe must decide if it wants to be more than Greater Switzerland | Timothy Garton Ash" author="Timothy Garton Ash" date="2009-09-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/sep/30/german-election-lisbon-treaty-referendum" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Timothy Garton Ash: The centrist triumph in Germany is important for all Europeans. But more crucial still is another vote in Ireland" categories="Opinion" tags="European Union,Ireland,Silvio Berlusconi,Angela Merkel,Germany,Politics,US news,Media,Hillary Clinton,Roman Polanski,Poland,France,Russia,Europe" fingerprint="96f6d07db0722eac">
  <main>
    <p>Once upon a time, and a very bad time it was, the world trembled when Germany spoke. Now it hardly notices. If, for instance, I had relied solely on American television and newspapers over the last few weeks, I might not even have known that Europe's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/28/angela-merkel-germany-government-coalition">most important country was having an election</ref>. As for Gordon Brown at his party conference, offering a glossy cruise prospectus for his sinking ship – forget it.</p>
    <p>This is not just a reflection of America's changed priorities (an Afghan election matters more than a German or British one) and a general decline in foreign news coverage. If you were in China, India or Brazil, you would have a similar experience. The antics of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> or Prince Harry make the cut, but not Europe's serious politics. Europe is neither dangerous enough to demand attention (today's Nazis are in Waziristan) nor dynamic and impactful enough to command it, as China does. Europe is nice, boring and irrelevant.</p>
    <p>In many ways this is a great achievement. The last time Europe had such a serious financial and economic crisis, with high unemployment, Germany did not choose nice and boring. This time round, the centre triumphantly held. Small parties on the left did well, as did the socially and economically liberal Free Democrats, but there was no major splintering to the right. The politics of "blame it on the strangers" did not get anywhere. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</ref> confirmed her status as one of Europe's most remarkable politicians. Remarkable not least for her quite brilliant pretence of being unremarkable: plain-speaking, unpretentious, down to earth; the "Angie" next door.</p>
    <p>In a coalition with the Free Democrats, she will have a chance to push through some tax cuts, extend the life of nuclear power stations, and maybe free up the labour market a little more. But free-marketeers should not get their hopes up too much, nor social democrats their fears. Merkel II is not going to be that different from Merkel I. She governed from the centre – of necessity in a grand coalition with the social democrats, but also by choice. She won the election by standing in the centre.</p>
    <p>In fact, her campaign slogan was quite simply <hi rend="#i">Die Mitte</hi> , the centre. And the centre is where she will stay. Germany's elaborate system of checks and balances anyway militates against rapid, radical change. (She has a narrow majority in the upper house, but may lose it again next year.)</p>
    <p>Rumours of the death of social democracy have, in essence, been much exaggerated. Most European countries now have some mix of economic liberalism and social democracy. In Britain, Tony Blair won by adopting a lot of Thatcherism; if David Cameron wins next year, it will be because he has taken over much of Blairism. Britain's election, too, will be fought in the centre. The real challenge to this Europe-wide centrism will come if it fails to deliver sufficient growth – and above all, jobs. Everywhere the vote for smaller parties, such as the Greens and Die Linke in Germany, is growing. But for now, the centre holds.</p>
    <p>With Merkel, and most probably the liberal <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/28/guido-westerwelle-germany-elections">Guido Westerwelle</ref> as foreign minister, Germany's foreign policy will not change that much either. Germany will continue to be Russia's closest partner in Europe.</p>
    <p>(In this sense, incidentally, the Federal Republic has delivered on the promise that Helmut Köhl made to Mikhail Gorbachev 20 years ago: far-reaching economic co-operation in return for the Russian leader's assent to German unification.) It will try to be a good friend to the United States, while keeping German troops out of harm's way in Afghanistan and continuing to do as much business as it decently can with Iran. So Germany will be neither a major contributor nor a major obstacle to President Obama achieving his foreign policy goals.</p>
    <p>The details will be worked out in a month of coalition haggling. "When world leaders come to Berlin on November 9, I would prefer to welcome them with a new government," says Merkel. November 9 – <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/november/9/newsid_2515000/2515869.stm">the fall of the Wall</ref>. And suddenly you remember the hopes and fears of 1989. Germany at the heart of a United Europe, a model for the world. Or, in the overheated fantasies of conservative Brits and Poles, Germany as the Fourth Reich. Instead, we have … the cuckoo clock. Germany as Greater Switzerland.</p>
    <p>And not just Germany. The whole of Europe today is Greater Switzerland. It has larger cantons and smaller cantons, each fiercely defending its traditions and self-government. There's canton Slovenia and canton France, canton Britain and canton Luxembourg. Some are more important than others, but none of them are half as important as they used to be, or as – especially in the case of France and Britain – they still think they are. This Greater Switzerland secures a high level of security, prosperity, freedom and social welfare for most though not all of its citizens, and some, though not most, of its denizens. For its citizens, it is one of the best places in the world to live. Abroad, it concerns itself with such great matters as freedom for Roman Polanski – a subject on which the French and Polish foreign ministers have felt moved to write to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/hillary-clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref>. Perhaps they could follow up with a letter about cheese, or wine, or leather handbags.</p>
    <p>Now there's a great deal to be said for being Switzerland. Really. (Unless you're <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/romanpolanski">Roman Polanski</ref>, just at the moment, but that's another story.) The question is: are we Europeans happy to settle for that? Is that all we want to be in the 21st century? I suspect that in their hearts many Europeans will answer "yes". Or perhaps more accurately: they will not be prepared to vote and pay for doing the things that would be required if we wanted to be more than that. So the answer will come by default, rather than explicit choice.</p>
    <p>The trouble with this is that, in the longer run, by choosing to be only a Greater Switzerland we will gradually lose the conditions that make it possible to actually be a greater Switzerland. For the point of having a European foreign policy is not power in itself, but the power to protect and advance interests that are increasingly shared between all European countries, and challenged in a world of non-European giants.</p>
    <p>Germany matters to this choice. Britain matters to this choice – and will probably head in the wrong direction under the Conservatives. But this week, the country that matters most is Ireland. For <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8275265.stm">Ireland votes again</ref> on Friday on the Lisbon treaty. In order to get a stronger European voice in the world, we need the Irish to vote yes.</p>
    <p>Democratically, there was something problematic about not taking no for an answer first time round. But democratically, there is also something problematic about British newspapers owned by Rupert Murdoch playing such a part in the Irish debate. The Irish must make up their own minds; they will do so for their own reasons; and they should not be subjected to any threats of dire consequences from a "wrong" choice. But for the future of Europe, Ireland's choice may be more important even than Germany's.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>