<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Formula One's fascism fetish should not surprise anyone | Marina Hyde" author="Marina Hyde" date="2009-07-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/sport/blog/2009/jul/09/bernie-ecclestone-adolf-hitler-formula-one" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Marina Hyde: Talk to a sports supremo long enough and he will mention a historical fascist" categories="Sport" tags="Bernie Ecclestone,Formula One,Motor sport,Silvio Berlusconi,Sport,Formula One 2009" fingerprint="baddb11b3d83174f">
  <main>
    <p>These days, we are deemed incapable of understanding anything unless it is glossed by a celebrity, hence the commissioning of documentaries like Peaches Geldof on Islam. To this hallowed canon, then, let us welcome Sports Bosses on Fascist History, as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/bernie-ecclestone">Bernie Ecclestone</ref> explains that poor, talented reformer Adolf Hitler might have been unwittingly pushed into the Holocaust.</p>
    <p>In his subsequent non-apology apology, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/sport/formulaone">Formula One</ref> overlord lays further honours at the feet of the Jews. "Most of my mates are Jewish," he explained, with customary originality. "One of them said to me, 'Bernie, you're more Jewish than all of my friends'."</p>
    <p>Too kind, Bernie. Of course, Herr Ecclestone is not the first sports boss to offer a revisionist take on the Third Reich. Back in 2002, Ken Bates succumbed to the crippling diffidence that so often afflicts him by comparing then FA boss Adam Crozier with the Führer. "He's now in a situation where he reminds you of Hitler," reasoned the former Chelsea owner, "or the way Hitler took control of Germany on an unelected, unappointed basis."</p>
    <p>And it was on this iron grip on the history of the popular vote that Ken would rely again at Leeds, where he offered an unusual skew on the beleaguered politician's old line that they haven't met a single member of the public who believes they should resign. "Ninety nine per cent of the letters and emails are supporting us," said Ken. "That's as good as Saddam Hussein did, and he was fiddling the figures."</p>
    <p>Godwin's law states that the longer an internet discussion continues, the probability of a comparison involving Hitler and Nazis approaches one. Hyde's Law states that the longer an interview with a sports supremo goes on, the probability that he will bring up some historical fascist approaches if not one, then certainly a half.</p>
    <p>Of course, you've got the rare bleeding heart but even those tend to have lively views on punitive justice. Most are martinets themselves, more talented versions of those David Brent-esque middle managers who adorn their office walls with slogans like "The Romans didn't build an empire by having meetings. They did it by killing anyone who got in their way." Doubtless social psychologists would note the ease with which sport lends itself to ideas of martial spirit and nationalism.</p>
    <p>Think of our own Fabio Capello, who professed admiration for Franco's "rigorous order". Or consider <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the Milan owner who moonlights as a humpy prime minister in Italy's most-watched soap opera, and who once explained that "Mussolini never killed anyone. Mussolini sent people on holiday to confine them."</p>
    <p>European motor racing was inextricably linked with the more extreme aspects of futurism, while the Olympic movement has been positively littered with closet fascists, of whom the most out was the Nazi-sympathising, antisemitic IOC president, Avery Brundage, who went to his grave stubbornly declaring the Berlin games "the finest in modern history". We have yet to hear a senior sporting figure excuse the Great Leap Forward on the basis that Mao had admirable self-belief, but the minute La Liga gets a Sinophile manager, it will only be a matter of time.</p>
    <p>One always detects their tacit sense of kinship with the genius leader who gets almost everything right, then blots their copybook with one unfortunate genocide. Hell, you can bust a gut making a club efficient, but the small matter of your taking them from the Premier League to the Coca-Cola in two seasons sees those ingrates remember you uncharitably.</p>
    <p>Thus the reaction to Ecclestone's nonsense seems perplexing. What sort of person did people imagine runs Formula One? If only the German politician who has now cancelled his meeting with Bernie ahead of this weekend's grand prix had persuaded a tame Austrian counterpart – or possibly Brüno – to issue a statement along the lines of: "So Hitler wasn't an angel. But linking him with Formula One is offensive to his memory." Facetious, obviously, but the plain fact about such outbursts by cretins like Ecclestone is that they do more for the anti-fascist cause than 10 dreary marches.</p>
    <p>And frankly, we could all use the extra diversion. Almost my favourite moment in the Max Mosley affair was when the FIA president defended himself against condemnation from Mercedes and BMW by pointing out both firms' collusion with the Third Reich – and let's not even start on Enzo Ferrari. Don't you adore how hotly contested the Biggest Fascist in Formula One title is? It's quite the most exciting bit of the "sport".</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>