<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Aida Edemariam on Veronica Lario and Silvio Berlusconi's marital saga" author="Tom Kington; Aida Edemariam" date="2009-04-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/01/veronica-lario-silvio-berlusconi-marriage" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Veronica Lario denounced her husband, Silvio Berlusconi, in the press this week - for the second time in two years. Aida Edemariam on the marital saga that has Italy hooked" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Relationships,Women,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="6f6cd13d9ba59e2b">
  <main>
    <p>As a way of getting your husband's attention, it is difficult to better: a couple of days ago Veronica Lario wrote an email to a national news agency detailing exactly what she thought of her spouse's latest antics, and pointedly dissociating herself from them. As she is married to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the Italian prime minister, that country's press has since talked of little else.</p>
    <p>Lario was reacting to reports that he was considering selecting as MEPs four young, good-looking women who are, respectively, a trained ballerina, an actor, a professional singer and a former Miss <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> contestant, and she made no bones about what she thought about him treating women in this way. "What's happening today behind a front of bodily curves and female beauty is grave," she wrote, adding, in case no one got it, that it was wrong to use the women as "pieces of costume jewellery" to attract votes. "Someone wrote that all this is to sustain the enjoyment of the Emperor. I agree with this - what has emerged is shameful trash, all in the name of power. I want to make it clear that I and my children are victims and not accomplices in this situation," she said. "We must endure it and it causes us pain."</p>
    <p>Lario has form. Two years ago, after Berlusconi introduced a lawyer-turned-showgirl called Mara Carfagna to an audience with the somewhat ungallant words, "Take a look at her! I'd marry her if I weren't married already," she wrote a letter to La Repubblica, Italy's leading centre-left daily, which was duly printed on its front page. His public conduct was, she said, an affront to "my dignity as a woman", and "today for my female children, already adults," she wrote, "the example of a woman capable of defending her dignity ... takes on significant importance." She demanded a public apology. She duly and promptly got one - flowery, grovelling, colourful - but a few months later Berlusconi fielded Carfagna in the national elections; when his party won, he promptly appointed Carfagna minister for equal opportunities.</p>
    <p>In recent days, some sport has been made of pointing out that the women in Lario's sights are all just younger models of herself: the newspaper Libero even published an old topless photo of Lario, to show that she had no right to criticise showgirls (conveniently, they overlooked the fact that she has never attempted to parlay her charms into political jobs). In an editorial they claimed that her behaviour was "dangerous" for Berlusconi and that he could not afford to be "distracted by the noisy tantrums of his wife".</p>
    <p>It was left to Alessandra Mussolini, MP and granddaughter of the dictator, to stand up for Lario - if in a somewhat backhanded manner: "Italian women emerge in a very bad light from this episode." Souad Sbai, a Moroccan-born MP in Berlusconi's own party, also stood by her. "Veronica is a woman in love. I would have done the same thing, or even gone further, locking up the prime minister in a room and throwing away the key."</p>
    <p>There is a certain, obvious piquancy to the fact that the marital challenges of a media mogul should be played out in the media - but then he has never shied away from the obvious: the crude joke, the barely disguised peccadillo, the latest skimpily clad lovely. And he has, it seems, left his wife little choice. His behaviour, she said in 2007, had made her feel like "half of nothing"; she resorted to public means because he would not apologise in private. But public reaction may not be entirely with her - "Veronica should have stayed silent," Daniele Iacolucci, 41, a Rome bar manager, told the Guardian. "When you get married you need to make compromises based on the type of man your husband is." But the fact is that she did stay silent, for 27 years.</p>
    <p>She was born Raffaela Miriam Bartolini in 1956 - Veronica Lario is a stage name - and grew up in Bologna. Her father, who had been a low-ranking civil servant, died when she was a child; her mother worked at the local Standa supermarket, a chain that was later briefly owned by Berlusconi. She began acting at university. Her first film role was in a movie called Tenebrae (US title, Unsane) in 1982-83, a low-budget horror movie directed by Dario Argento in which her character was disembowelled and beheaded. She did stage work too: Berlusconi first noticed her in 1980, in The Magnificent Cuckold, which was playing at his Teatro Manzoni in Milan, and required her to appear topless. She was 20 years younger than him, and he was married at the time, with two children, but he headed directly backstage and introduced himself. "He made me a lot of compliments," she has said about their first conversation. "He said I was 'brava'. I believed him and have never stopped believing him."</p>
    <p>Their first child was born while he was still with his first wife; for six years he supported two families. They had three children by the time they were married themselves, on 15 December, 1990. Lario has never made any attempt to fashion a public role for herself. She seldom accompanies her husband on foreign tours (though when she does she wears, as one commentator put it, "eye-popping outfits [that] outshine every other political wife in sight"). "We are as different as night and day," she admitted in an authorised biography published two years ago. And yet, somehow - some suggest because they share similarly humble backgrounds - they have stayed together.</p>
    <p>While Berlusconi has done very well politically by seeming to have his cake and eat it - he has a loyal, beautiful wife raising his children at home, while being accompanied everywhere else by hand-picked bevies of young women - Lario said nothing about episodes that must have severely tried her patience. Carlo Caracciolo, the founding publisher of La Repubblica, recently told a British journalist that when Berlusconi was a property developer in Milan they would often have breakfast together, "and every time he brought a different girl. It was a sort of obsession with him." During his first term in office, Berlusconi boasted that he sent his wife flowers each day. Lario has alleged that someone else was in fact receiving them.</p>
    <p>When Carfagna entered parliament he commented that in his party, the leader enjoyed "droit de seigneur". He was photographed walking hand-in-hand not with one other young woman, but several. He was about to make his first speech to parliament in 2008 when a sharp-eyed cameraman caught a glimpse of a note he was writing to two young MPs: "Gabri, Nunzia, you look very good sitting there together. Thank you for sticking around [to listen to my speech] but it is not necessary. If you have any gallants who have invited you to lunch, I authorise you to go [underlined three times]. Many kisses to both of you!!! Your Prime Minister."</p>
    <p>It is true that this sometimes seems to have gone both ways. For a while, rumour was rife that Lario was having a relationship with Massimo Cacciari, a bearded, former Marxist mayor of Venice, and a professor of philosophy.</p>
    <p>But as Berlusconi's antics have become increasingly obvious (or slightly less covered up by those around him - for obvious reasons, the Italian media is mostly likely to turn a blind eye, and even if he doesn't own the paper or TV station concerned, Berlusconi is famously litigious) so Lario has begun to come (comparatively) clean about the cost to herself. In 2004 an authorised biography, Veronica's Tendency, betrayed her isolation.</p>
    <p>"Silvio eats lunch whilst attached to the phone and dinner is the same. We will be in the countryside, looking at a beautiful sunset, and Silvio will have his mobile glued to his ear. Even at Christmas dinner he will take a mouthful of turkey and start talking on the phone ... he's never silent ... he even talks when he sleeps." But despite all the background raucousness she had, she said, "no one with whom to share a concert, or a book, or a walk, or even a shopping trip."</p>
    <p>She has betrayed a somewhat bleak sense of humour about it. "Your husband is a busy man, do you get to see him or speak to him often?" asked a journalist who accosted her at the theatre one day (she is a frequent theatregoer, often attending plays that satirise Berlusconi's government). "Yes," she replied, "I not only speak to him on the telephone, sometimes I even see him on television."</p>
    <p>A year ago, on Valentine's day, Corriere della Sera printed an article in which she did not mention her husband, but pointedly urged women not to try to be like men who thought only of "success, power, money and career"; men, in particular, who did not value women as "moral angels" whose "female qualities" kept families and society together.</p>
    <p>Her intervention this week is in some ways an extension of this: a concern about dignified roles for women, about a work-life balance: her husband had, as she put it, shown a "lack of discretion in his exercise of power, which offends the credibility of all women" - and she is uniquely placed to point it out.</p>
    <p>But many think that while this is genuine, there may be something else going on too. The clue is in the timing. On Sunday evening, driving through the outskirts of Naples, Berlusconi dropped in on a birthday party for a young woman, Noemi Letizia. Her father is apparently an old associate, her mother runs a perfume shop. Although he later insisted that it was a last-minute invitation, it wasn't so last-minute that he could not bring with him a gold pendant set with diamonds.</p>
    <p>Why did he come, Corriere della Sera asked the girl, who has already done some lingerie modelling. "Because he's a friend of the family," she said. "He's known me since I was teeny-weeny. For me it's normal to see him, but I didn't expect him at the party, and I didn't tell my friends ... I've never even told them about Daddy."</p>
    <p>Which must have been an interesting word for Lario to hear, from a girl who has just turned 18, and is thus younger than all her own children. A news reporter asked her if the visit had surprised her. "It surprised many people, including me," she answered, with a kind of barbed poignancy. "Mainly because he has never attended the 18th birthdays of any of his children, even though he was always invited." One feels this may not be the last we hear from her.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>