<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi recovering after Milan statue attack" author="Haroon Siddique" date="2009-12-14" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-milan-statue-attack" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian PM still in hospital with fractured nose after man threw souvenir cathedral at him" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="76bb16ad92275747">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, will stay in hospital for at least one more day after being hit in the face when a statuette of Milan cathedral was thrown at him during a political rally yesterday.</p>
    <p>A medical bulletin issued by the San Raffaele hospital in Milan confirmed that Berlusconi sustained a broken nose and two broken teeth.</p>
    <p>It said he was taking antibiotics and painkillers because the pain was "persistent" and he was having difficulty eating.</p>
    <p>His personal doctor, Alberto Zangrillo, said surgery would not be necessary but Berlusconi would remain in hospital until at least tomorrow.</p>
    <p>The attack happened as the 73-year-old Italian leader signed autographs and greeted the crowd outside the cathedral.</p>
    <p>He fell to the ground before being ushered into a car by aides but repeatedly tried to get out to show his bloodied face to the public and cameras in the square.</p>
    <p>Zangrillo said he would be kept under observation and would need up to 15 days to recover.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister asked to see the newspapers as soon as he woke up today, the Italian Ansa news agency reported.</p>
    <p>He told Ansa he was "fine" and considered it a "miracle" that he had not been hit in the eyes.</p>
    <p>Massimo Tartaglia, a 42-year-old Milan resident with a history of mental illness, was detained by police and was being questioned, Italian media reports said.</p>
    <p>The attack was condemned across the political spectrum. Umberto Bossi, the leader of the Northern League party and Berlusconi's closest ally, described it as "an act of terrorism".</p>
    <p>The opposition leader, Pier Luigi Bersani, said it was an "unspeakable gesture that must be firmly condemned".</p>
    <p>Earlier in the evening Berlusconi told a rally to mark the opening to public membership of the People of Freedom party that his popularity rating stood at 63%.</p>
    <p>He said his government had saved the world economy by persuading the US government to intervene "after they had left Lehman Brothers to their fate" in order to avoid "the failure of 400 banks, saving the world from an incredible and tremendous crisis".</p>
    <p>At one point he interrupted the rally to address protesters who had been chanting "buffoon", telling them they should be ashamed of themselves.</p>
    <p>He boasted that he was still "young and on form", opening his shirt to show that he "was not even wearing a vest".</p>
    <p>According to opinion polls his popularity has slipped to just over 50% after a year during which he has been plagued by <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/dec/04/silvio-berlusconi-linked-mafia-court">legal troubles</ref> and lurid newspaper headlines about his <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">alleged involvement in sex scandals</ref>.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>