<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: Three may face trial over 'bunga bunga' parties" author="John Hooper" date="2011-05-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/06/silvio-berlusconi-bunga-bunga-trial" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prosecutors want Nicole Minetti, Emilio Fede and Lele Mora to be put on trial, charged with aiding and abetting prostitution" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="6e62c3a290e6579c">
  <main>
    <p>Prosecutors in Milan have asked for an Anglo-Italian former showgirl and two other people to be put on trial, charged with procuring 33 young women for so-called bunga bunga sex sessions at the home of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>Nicole Minetti, whose mother was born in Britain, denies any wrongdoing. So do the other two accused: Emilio Fede, the best-known newsreader on Berlusconi's television channels, and Lele Mora, Italy's leading showbusiness talent scout.</p>
    <p>Minetti, a former dancer who qualified as a dental hygienist, met the prime minister during his dental surgery to repair the injuries he suffered in December 2009 when he was hit in the face by a mentally unstable assailant. She subsequently became a candidate for his Freedom People party and holds a seat in the Lombardy regional assembly.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors who have been overseeing an investigation of the three since last year asked a judge in Milan to put them on trial, charged with aiding and abetting prostitution "from early 2009 until January 2011". The latter date means it is alleged that any wrongdoing continued right up until Berlusconi was indicted, and for three months after news of the investigation into his private life was made public.</p>
    <p>One of the women who visited his home, Moroccan-born Karima el-Mahroug, was aged 17 at the time and thus under the minimum age for prostitution. She is at the centre of the case involving Berlusconi himself. On 6 April, the 74-year-old TV magnate-turned-conservative politician was put on trial, accused of paying an underage prostitute and abusing his official position to cover up the alleged offence.</p>
    <p>In a 36-page document submitted to the judge, the prosecutors separately accused the three of aiding and abetting juvenile prostitution from September 2009 until May 2010.</p>
    <p>The earlier date refers to a beauty contest in Sicily in which Mahroug, then 16, was a contestant. Fede was among the judges. The prosecution claims that he lured her to Milan where Mora found her work dancing in nightclubs.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi and Mahroug, who also calls herself "Ruby the heartstealer", have denied having sex with each other. Under Italian law, paid-for sexual contact of any kind qualifies as juvenile prostitution.</p>
    <p>According to the prosecutors, the parties at Berlusconi's mansion outside Milan took place in three stages. First came a dinner; then "bunga bunga", which they said consisted of "striptease and erotic dances". Finally, Italy's prime minister would select one or more girls "with whom to engage in intimate relations during the night".</p>
    <p>The judge, Maria Grazia Domanico, will now fix a date for the start of committal proceedings, leading to a decision on whether all, or some, of the accused should be sent for trial.</p>
    <p>Fede said he was not surprised by the prosecutors' move and fully expected to be indicted.</p>
    <p>"There's no hope until the case reaches trial," he said. "I'm placing my faith in the trial court and in the truth of the case being established there."</p>
    <p>Fede is famed as the presenter of a nightly news bulletin on the Rete 4 channel in which he routinely throws in comments backing the prime minister or disparaging his critics. Mora is best-known outside Italy for an appearance in a feature-length documentary, <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pYiEQUaCE9s">Videocracy</ref>, in which he lauds Mussolini and plays a fascist anthem stored on his smartphone.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>