<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="G20 summit was a lesson in disunity – and the markets passed judgment" author="Larry Elliott" date="2011-11-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/04/g20-summit-markets-judgment" hostname="theguardian.com" description="World leaders argued, haggled and ganged up on each other. But thanks largely to dithering Europeans, little was agreed" categories="World news" tags="G20,World news,Eurozone crisis,European banks,Business,France,Europe,Nicolas Sarkozy,Angela Merkel,Barack Obama,David Cameron,Politics,Financial crisis,Banking,Financial sector,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,George Papandreou,International Monetary Fund (IMF),Economics,Global economy,European Central Bank" fingerprint="375699153190c608">
  <main>
    <p>It was a fiasco from start to finish. Ambushed by Greece, dogged by the threat of looming disaster in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, overshadowed by the rapid deterioration in the global economy, this was the bleakest global meeting since the World Trade Organisation talks broke down in riot-torn Seattle in 1999.</p>
    <p>The best that could be said for the G20 gathering was that it allowed world leaders to unbutton and give vent to their frustration and anger. But nothing of substance was agreed. There was no extra money for the IMF and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> got short shrift from China when it rattled the tin for contributions to its bailout fund.</p>
    <p>For two days members of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g20">G20</ref> – who came together in adversity in London 30 months ago – gave an object lesson in how to put on a show of disunity.</p>
    <p>They ganged up on each other; they argued and they haggled right up until the death, with Washington and Beijing for once on the same side against the common enemy – the dithering Europeans.</p>
    <p>Normally, summit communiques are precooked long in advance of the meetings, allowing world leaders to glad-hand in front of the TV cameras.</p>
    <p>The intention this time was for the G20 to be seen putting the world to rights against the backdrop of autumnal Côte d'Azur sunshine.</p>
    <p>It didn't work out like that. With rain falling incessantly from lowering skies, the mood in the conference room matched the weather.</p>
    <p>Financial markets passed swift judgment on the summit. Shares and the euro fell, while yields on Italian bonds rose sharply. Hopes were raised prematurely on Thursday that the G20 was close to agreeing an increase of $250-$300bn to strengthen the IMF's firewall ahead of what is expected to be a tough winter ahead. When these hopes were dashed, markets sold off.</p>
    <p>Rightly, they were unimpressed by talk of structural reform and the pledges of surplus countries – China, Germany and Japan – to boost their domestic economies, warm words they have heard many times before.</p>
    <p>David Cameron and Barack Obama, while trying to put a good gloss on what by any standards was a damp squib of a summit, underlined the precarious state of the global economy. The prime minister said Europe's debt crisis was having a "chilling" effect on Britain. Obama said the eurozone had to implement the rescue plan agreed in Brussels last month "fully and as quickly as possible".</p>
    <p>Yet, having criticised the Europeans for creating the mess by repeatedly kicking the can down the road over the past 18 months, the G20 did the same itself.</p>
    <p>G20 finance ministers will look at ways of increasing the resources of the IMF; the non-eurozone members of the G20 will consider providing capital for the European Financial Stability Facility only when Europe has sorted itself out, and a taskforce has been created to look at what can be done about youth unemployment.</p>
    <p>It was not supposed to have been like this. Originally, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref> saw Cannes as a way of kickstarting his presidential re-election campaign, with measures to cement global economic recovery, outreach to both business and unions, and progress on a financial transaction tax.</p>
    <p>Even as late as a week ago, a small-scale summit success still looked feasible, even though the economic backdrop to the summit was far gloomier than could have been imagined six months earlier. Then Europe showed how skilled it has become at snatching defeat from the jaws of victory, with the Greek prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/george-papandreou">George Papandreou</ref>, announcing that he would be holding a referendum on the terms of his country's bailout package.</p>
    <p>That was a cue for market mayhem. Sarkozy and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</ref> summoned Papandreou to a pre-summit meeting on Wednesday and gave him a dressing-down. The message was simple: hold your referendum if you want, but if the vote goes the wrong way, Greece's future as a member of the single currency will be at risk. And, by the way, don't expect any more bailout cash in the meantime.</p>
    <p>A chastened Papandreou returned home to call off the plebiscite, but significant damage had been done. The summit began badly and never really recovered, with the attention quickly shifting from Greece to a much more strategically important country, Italy.</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi arrived in Cannes empty-handed, with no new proposals for dealing with his country's large national debt. But it quickly became clear that China, the US, the UK and all the other non-eurozone members of the G20 wanted to see concrete measures to prevent the single currency's third biggest country going the way of Greece.</p>
    <p>Merkel and Sarkozy called in Obama to put the frighteners on Berlusconi at a meeting on Thursday, forcing the Italian leader to agree to an IMF team doing a quarterly health check on its public finances.</p>
    <p>Italy became a touchstone for a broader grievance: that the Europeans had been laggardly in sorting out their problems, with knock-on effects for the rest of the G20. Hence the reluctance to put money into either the EFSF or the IMF. Cameron said he had put Britain's view to eurozone members of the G20 "clearly, consistently and forcibly" and he was not the only one.</p>
    <p>The problem is that nothing being demanded of the eurozone – a credible bailout fund, a recapitalised banking system and decisive resolution of the Greek crisis – can be achieved that easily.</p>
    <p>Washington and Britain believe a willingness on the part of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> to act like a genuine lender of last resort would help greatly in easing market tension. Germany strongly resists this idea. Privately, many G20 leaders await the day when Berlusconi's government is replaced by an administration made up of boring technocrats. Berlusconi said on Friday he had no intention of stepping down.</p>
    <p>In the meantime, the economic news got worse and worse. Friday provided evidence of a sharp drop in German industrial orders and a slide in the Eurozone's service sector. The G20 was required to do three things in Cannes. It needed to show that it could act together, as it did in London. It needed to stop the bleeding in the eurozone. And it needed to announce measures that would help roll back the threatening recessionary clouds.</p>
    <p>It failed on all three counts.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Financial transactions tax</head>
    <p>Sarkozy has pledged that the eurozone will press ahead with work on a new financial transactions tax (FTT) after the Cannes summit endorsed the right of G20 countries to impose the levy.</p>
    <p>The French president announced that South Africa, Brazil and Argentina now supported what he called a "morally indispensible" levy and he hoped to have it implemented at a European level by the end of 2012.</p>
    <p>Opposition from Britain and some other EU countries will almost certainly mean the FTT will initially be confined to the eurozone but Sarkozy was delighted at the progress made in Cannes. He said "just putting the words financial transaction tax in a communique" would have been unthinkable not long ago. He said the Tobin tax or Robin Hood tax, as it is also known, was something talked about among NGOs and "never at the tables of heads of state". This was one development that showed "it's now a totally different world, it has progressed in a stupefying way".</p>
    <p>Max Lawson, spokesman for the Robin Hood Tax campaign, said: "We are delighted that a growing group of G20 nations from Brazil to Germany to South Africa have answered the call of millions who want the financial sector to contribute to the fight against poverty and climate change."</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, the European commission indicated that it was considering curbs on bankers' pay and bonuses. Michel Barnier, the commissioner responsible for financial services, told the Independent newspaper that remuneration had returned to unjustifiable levels.</p>
    <p>"After a couple of years of calming down, [banks] have gone back to pre-crisis levels of distributing pay and bonuses which are just not justified," he said.</p>
    <p>He did not provide detailed proposals but said the commission would be "preparing the next framework so we can limit bonuses and pay further".</p>
    <p>"It's not about penalising the banking sector. It's about asking that everyone play their role and make an effort to preserve the money available to finance the real economy," he said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>