<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Said &amp; Done | David Hills" author="David Hills" date="2011-09-24" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2011/sep/24/said-and-done-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi's clean PR; top three votes of confidence; model wars; plus dog of the week" categories="Football" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Fifa,Football,Sport" fingerprint="ba01996188c2e7c3">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">Man of the week</head>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi: looking to end a tough run of corruption, tax evasion and "sexy nun" bunga bunga claims with some uncomplicated clean PR – revealing Milan's new "premium sponsor". Albanian oil baron Rezart Taci told the press how Silvio's Milan "has always been a symbol of strength, determination and success, the values on which I have based my career". (2010: Taci's bodyguards beat a journalist unconscious after he linked their boss to corruption and tax evasion. Taci, cleared of assault, told the court he was sad to see his staff convicted: "I condemn all violence.")</p>
    <head rend="h2">Money news</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">'Big Society' latest: </hi>Liverpool launch their Go Forward grassroots scheme in Mumbai, sponsored by Standard Chartered – part of the bank's "strong focus on sustainability and giving back to the communities in which we operate". (<hi rend="#b">March</hi> – Standard Chartered's UK tax contribution falls to £106m as global profit rises to £3.7bn. Bonus pool "increases modestly" to £770m.)</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Best wake-up call: </hi>Ivan Gazidis on his core values as Arsenal's CEO: "It is challenging to operate in a responsible and sustainable way when other clubs have far bigger budgets …The message of responsibility and continuity is very important for the game … we must recognise economic realities and concerns." (Gazidis's 2010 pay deal: £1.7m, including £669k bonus.)</p>
    <head rend="h2">Quote of the week</head>
    <p>Still working in Zurich: <hi rend="#b">Fifa's cash-for-votes inquiry </hi>into alleged £25k bungs paid to executives. Among last week's evidence, an account of Guyana FA head Colin Klass's behaviour at the venue. "Mr Klass asked: 'Why is this door locked? Are there people getting bribed around here?' The male [CFU official] then allowed Mr Klass to enter the room, which he exited after a few minutes … Mr Klass had a smile on his face and was slightly giggling." <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/fifa">Fifa</ref> banned Klass for 26 months; the hearings continue.</p>
    <head rend="h2">More legal news</head>
    <p>Next month in Holland: <hi rend="#b">Ajax</hi> being sued by an antisemitism group over fans chanting "We are the super Jews". The group says Ajax have "no Jewish roots and few Jewish fans", and the chants provoke opponents. In August, ADO Den Hague were censored after fans targeted Ajax with songs including "Hamas Hamas Jews to the gas", and "Horrible cancer Jews". ADO said their officials "heard nothing".</p>
    <p> Also this year: ADO player <hi rend="#b">Lex Immers </hi>says "sorry for the offence" after being filmed partying with fans following a win over Ajax, singing "We're going hunting Jews". "It all seemed innocent to me.")</p>
    <head rend="h2">Last week's exits</head>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Top three votes of confidence before last week's sackings</hi>
    </p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">1) 16 Sept: </hi>Inter president Massimo Moratti on coach Gian Piero Gasperini: "There will absolutely not be any change in the next few days. It is not up for debate. Give the coach time to do his work."</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2) 22 Sept: </hi>Doncaster chairman John Ryan on Sean O'Driscoll: "I've never responded to hotheads who want to sack somebody. Clubs who sack managers willy-nilly end up relegated. We're not going down that path."</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">3) 18 Sept: </hi>Hamburg director Frank Arnesen on coach Michael Oenning: "We are playing Stuttgart on Friday. Michael Oenning will be sitting with me and the team in the plane on the way there – and on the way back."</p>
    <p> Plus: best failed attempt to hold on: <hi rend="#b">11 Sept</hi>, Lothar Matthäus, Bulgaria: "It is perfectly clear that my contract will be extended. We have a verbal agreement, sealed with a handshake. Gentlemen never shirk their promises. So I am calm."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Bulat's week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">2: </hi>Number of weeks since Xamax owner <hi rend="#b">Bulat Chagaev</hi> sacked someone. Among last week's Xamax stories in Switzerland: the club's debt revealed to be £2.3m, most of it arising since Chagaev took over in May. Chagaev's lawyer says the situation is "normal… This doesn't put Xamax in danger."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Owner of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Argentina: </hi>Independiente president Julio Comparada says claims he used the club's barra brava hardcore to suppress a protest against him are "gross". <hi rend="#i">Diario Show</hi> alleged a club employee was ordered to climb a ladder to disable a CCTV camera "so it could not record what happened as the detractors were silenced". Comaparada: "The barras are the scourge of football."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Hysteria news</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Mexico: </hi>José Padilla, president of Monclova's female league, says claims he banned two players for being lesbians are "fraud". Padilla, facing a possible criminal case, says his critics are hysterical. "I will face this down. It was just a paperwork problem."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Falling down</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Brazil: </hi>Referee Rodrigo Nunes de Sa has denied diving after footage showed him <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eUFZpl0I-3k">apparently pretending to be butted</ref> by a player he sent off. Operário's George Santos said the official "reacted in a way worth an Oscar". Nunes de Sa: "I felt my forehead grazed. Then I fell down."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Dog of the week</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Tanzania: </hi>Police say a police dog that ran on to the pitch to chase players during Simba SC's game against Toto Africans was "bad". The dog slipped its leash in the first half and <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CbkNXdliy6Q#t=0m55s">chased players from both sides</ref>, but was stopped before it caught one. Police: "It was not our intention to destroy the match."</p>
    <head rend="h2">Plus: model wars</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Argentina: </hi>Model Victoria Santos has denied "chasing publicity" by dating San Lorenzo's Jonathan Ferrari three days after he left rival model Cinthia Fernández. Santos reacted to claims she tipped off the press by holding a live TV debate with Fernández: "She lies and is bitter. I don't need this, you know."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>