<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="New audio tapes put Silvio Berlusconi sex allegations back in spotlight" author="John Hooper" date="2009-07-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/20/silvio-berlusconi-recordings" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Lawyers for prime minister deny Italian website clips are of him and and an escort in conversation" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="cf8ccdaf9cbfdfa7">
  <main>
    <p>The furore over Silvio Berlusconi's private life was revived today when an Italian newspaper website produced what it said was a <ref target="http://espresso.repubblica.it/multimedia/home/6949372">recording of the Italian prime minister</ref> as he prepared to get into bed with an escort.</p>
    <p>La Repubblica posted recordings that the escort, Patrizia D'Addario, said she made during and after two visits to Palazzo Grazioli, Berlusconi's residence in the centre of Rome, in November last year.</p>
    <p>In one fragment of conversation, Berlusconi appears to direct D'Addario to wait for him in bed while he showers. In another, she protests to the man who set her up with the Italian prime minister that she had not received the €5,000 (£4,300) she was expecting.</p>
    <p>In a third snippet, it is claimed she confides to the same intermediary that Berlusconi asked her whether next time they met she would agree to a menage a trois with another of the prime minister's girlfriends.</p>
    <p>"He said that he has a girlfriend and would like to have me licked by this girlfriend," D'Addario says, according to the posted recordings.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's lawyer Niccolo Ghedini disputed the authenticity of the recordings. He said they were "without any merit, completely improbable and the fruit of invention." A spokesman for Berlusconi's governing Freedom People movement described the dissemination of the tapes as "pathetic".</p>
    <p>The content of the conversations was reported in broad terms last month, but this is the first time that the alleged recordings themselves have been made available, along with full transcripts.</p>
    <p>One of them, claimed to have been made by D'Addario in the prime minister's bedroom, appeared to back up reports that Berlusconi's guests were entertained on a giant bed, which according to the transcripts, is in some way associated with the Russian prime minister, Vladimir Putin. The recording is of poor quality, however.</p>
    <p>After an exchange in which the prime minister seems to be offering D'Addario a present, the conversation continues as follows:</p>
    <p>SB: I'm taking a shower too. And then, then you wait for me on the big bed if you finish before me.</p>
    <p>PD: Which big bed? Putin's.</p>
    <p>SB: Putin's.</p>
    <p>PD: Oh, how lovely! The one with the curtains.</p>
    <p>In a recording allegedly made the following morning, D'Addario rings the man who introduced her to Berlusconi. She tells him: "We didn't get a wink of sleep". But adds, "no envelope, though".</p>
    <p>She said that she had received: "I don't know, a little turtle", but not "the envelope – 5000 euros", mentioned by a friend who had also visited Palazzo Grazioli.</p>
    <p>The allegations about Berlusconi's private life have escalated since he was accused of consorting with minors after attending the 18th birthday party of Noemi Letizia, an aspiring model who called the 72-year-old "Papi" during phone conversations. That was enough to push Berlusconi's wife to ask for a divorce.</p>
    <p>Since then, details of his alleged dealings with escort girls emerged by chance, during a separate investigation into supposed prostitution rackets in the southern city of Bari.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>