<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi believed the world revolved around him – not any more" author="John Hooper" date="2013-10-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/04/silvio-berlusconi-senate-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="As a panel considers whether to expel him from the Italian Senate, the former PM's iron self-belief is being tested as never before" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="7eaac22d9a16573f">
  <main>
    <p>One of the most telling anecdotes from Silvio Berlusconi's long career is to be found in a book published in 1994 by a journalist and a sociologist, just as the former Italian leader was entering politics.</p>
    <p>The writers' aim was to observe him "in his natural habitat", and they tracked him to a training session for sales reps of the advertising subsidiary of his TV empire.</p>
    <p>Every morning, Berlusconi told them, he stood in front of a mirror and repeated: "I like myself. I like myself."</p>
    <p>It was a way of building that unassailable self-confidence that has kept him at the top level of international politics for longer than any leader except maybe Zimbabwe's president, Robert Mugabe. Combined with boundless optimism and titanic energy, it has enabled Berlusconi to achieve an ascendancy over the life of his country without parallel in the democratic world.</p>
    <p>"Berlusconi believes that the world revolves around him – the ultimate narcissistic fantasy," his American biographer, Alexander Stille, observed. "But he has bent reality to fit his fantasy, so that much of life in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> does indeed revolve around him."</p>
    <p>As he stood in front of his mirror on Thursday morning, however, even Berlusconi must have realised this was suddenly no longer true: for the first time in almost 20 years, he is no longer the undisputed master of his party, and for the first time since 2001, he neither leads the government of Italy nor has any credible prospect of destroying it if it fails to do his bidding.</p>
    <p>The previous morning, a visibly humbled Berlusconi announced to an incredulous senate that he would instruct his party to vote against a motion of no confidence in Enrico Letta's left-right coalition government that he himself had inspired.</p>
    <p>It was a tacit admission that he had lost the backing of a sizable number of his own politicians and – more importantly – that he no longer had power of veto over government policy.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has climbed back out of his political coffin so many times – in 2001, 2008 and 2012 – that it is a brave commentator who pronounces him politically dead. But the odds are now stacked against him, not just politically, but judicially and even financially. Italians who have achieved undisputed dominance over their contemporaries have usually come to sudden and violent ends. Julius Caesar was stabbed to death by members of the Senate a few hundred metres from where Berlusconi this week addressed their modern-day successors. Cola di Rienzo, who seized power in Rome in the 14th century was hacked to pieces by the mob. Benito Mussolini was shot dead on the shores of Lake Como, then strung up in a Milan square for passersby to spit at his corpse.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, too, faces execution. But it will be legitimate, democratic and less brutal, though excruciatingly protracted.</p>
    <p>First, in all likelihood, will be his expulsion from parliament. Berlusconi is a criminal, convicted in August of tax fraud, and under a law passed last year, he must be thrown out of the senate – a process that began on Friday when a panel voted for his removal. The full house will take a final decision later this month.</p>
    <p>By 15 October, he will have to decide on the punishment for his crime. Berlusconi is 76 years old and Italian courts seldom imprison anyone of his age. But that still leaves a choice between community service, which he has discounted as insufferably humiliating, and the constraints of 12 months under house arrest. Neither would necessarily make it impossible for Berlusconi to continue leading his party.</p>
    <p>But the looming problem for Berlusconi is which party he can now lead. His crisis moment came on Wednesday as he was changing the name of his party from the Freedom People (PdL) back to Forza Italia! (Come on, Italy!).</p>
    <p>Leading the rebellion in his ranks is Angelino Alfano, the 42-year-old interior minister who had an almost filial relationship with Berlusconi until the split. As secretary of the PdL, Alfano is the legal owner of its name.</p>
    <p>According to a source close to him, his aim is to lure into – or rather, keep in – the PdL a majority of Berlusconi's elected representatives: a kind of political reverse takeover that could leave the former prime minister as the leader of a radical rightist rump.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's legal situation also looks certain to deteriorate. Under law, defendants have the right to two appeals.</p>
    <p>He is currently contesting a one-year sentence for leaking judicial evidence and seven years in the bunga-bunga trial: 12 months for paying for the services of an underage prostitute and six years for taking advantage of his position as prime minister to try to cover up their relationship. He is also under investigation for allegedly paying a senator €3m to switch sides in his 2008 effort to topple the then centre-left government.</p>
    <p>The billionaire's iron self-belief has enabled him to achieve remarkable things: embark on the construction of an entirely new town on the outskirts of Milan aged 34; create a party out of nothing and lead it to victory within a year, and – not least – persuade world leaders to hold a G8 summit amid the ruins of an earthquake.</p>
    <p>Such a man will not easily accept the time has come for him to leave centre stage and quietly withdraw into the wings.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>