<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Tessa Jowell's husband offers 'deepest apologies' to Silvio Berlusconi in court case" author="John Hooper" date="2009-01-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jan/20/silvio-berlusconi-tessa-jowell-david-mills-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="David Mills apologises to Italian prime minister after involving him in bribery trial" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Tessa Jowell,UK news,Italy,Politics,David Mills,Europe" fingerprint="20aa020d178f5559">
  <main>
    <p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the Olympics minister, Tessa Jowell, today proffered his "deepest apologies" to Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, for having involved him in a trial for alleged bribery.</p>
    <p>A court in Milan is hearing the final stages of a case in which the British lawyer is accused of accepting a sum of $600,000 (£430,000) to withhold evidence in two corruption trials in which Berlusconi was a defendant. Last December, the prosecution asked for him to be sentenced to four years and eight months and yesterday Mills learned that, if convicted, he could also face a €250,000 ($230,000) bill from the Italian state.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's prosecution was suspended by a law drafted by his government, which was passed last year and provides him with immunity.</p>
    <p>The judge read out a statement from Mills in which he said: "I have made mistakes. I have conducted my business poorly and I have caused a lot of trouble to people who in no way deserved such difficulties."</p>
    <p>But the lawyer, who helped set up a network of offshore companies for Fininvest, the firm at the apex of Berlusconi's business empire, added: "I have never been corrupted by anyone, neither by Carlo Bernasconi [a Fininvest executive], nor by Berlusconi, nor by any other person."</p>
    <p>Mills said: "In the course of my professional activity, many people have trusted in my integrity. None of them ever had reason to regret it."</p>
    <p>The minister's husband first admitted that he had taken the money as payment for his evidence. In a letter to his accountant, obtained by investigators, he wrote that he had "turned some very tricky corners" in court and thus "kept Mr B out of a great deal of trouble he would have been in had I said all I knew".</p>
    <p>But Mills later retracted his statement and said the money was from a Neapolitan businessman and former client. In his statement today , he said Berlusconi and the businessman had been "victims of my errors". He added: "I would like to take advantage of this opportunity to proffer my deepest apologies to both for the trouble this affair has caused."</p>
    <p>A government lawyer earlier set damages it was seeking from Mills at €250,000. Italian law takes the view that perverting the court of justice impairs the functioning of the state and requires compensation to be paid.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>