<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Did he really say that? Some classic Silvio Berlusconi moments" author="Emine Saner" date="2009-04-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/01/silvio-berlusconi-quotations" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Referring to Barack Obama's 'good tan' is just one of the Italian prime minister's many gaffes and offensive remarks" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3efa902d9027c74d">
  <main>
    <p>"Working with Mr Berlusconi you will never be bored. It is absolutely impossible to predict what he is going to do next," says Lucio Malan, former director of communications for Silvio Berlusconi's Forza Italia party. Well, not quite. You can pretty much guarantee that what he will do next is offend and infuriate people. Earlier this month, while on a tour of the camps set up for the survivors of the recent earthquake in L'Aquila, which claimed more than 290 lives and made 17,000 homeless, Berlusconi told a reporter: "They have everything they need, they have medical care, hot food ... Of course, their current lodgings are a bit temporary, but they should see it like a weekend of camping." Just a few days later, Berlusconi said to a female doctor working in the disaster area: "I wouldn't mind being resuscitated by you."</p>
    <p> In January, following a series of reported rapes, Berlusconi said that he would increase the number of soldiers helping police patrol the streets of Rome, but that it might not be effective because, "we would need as many soldiers as there are beautiful girls in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> - which we will never manage." Vittoria Franco, the shadow minister for equal opportunities, said, "Berlusconi would do better to stay silent rather than make offensive remarks about women. In effect he is saying that if women go out alone, they risk being violated or attacked because the whole territory cannot be garrisoned."</p>
    <p>In Moscow last November, while on a visit to the Russian president, Dmitry Medvedev, Berlusconi explained the reasons he thought Obama, newly elected, would make a good ally: "He's young, handsome, and even has a good tan." When he was criticised, he said that those who were offended by his comment were "imbeciles", that the Italian left "lacked a sense of humour" and that his comment was meant to be a "compliment". In March at a press conference, after a journalist likened Berlusconi to President Obama for his reponse to the global economic crisis, Berlusconi said, "I'm paler, because it's been so long since I've been in the sun."</p>
    <p>At an awards dinner in 2007, Berlusconi told a dancer, "I'd go with you anywhere." He then turned his attentions to Mara Carfagna, a former television showgirl and topless model turned politician, declaring to assembled guests: "Take a look at her! I'd marry her if I weren't married already." This proved too much for his wife, who wrote an infamous open letter to her husband, which was printed in La Repubblica newspaper, seeking a public apology. When Carfagna was elected a year earlier as a candidate for Forza Italia, he said, "We have a rule inside Forza Italia, the rule of ius primae noctis" (the Latin term for the old right of a feudal lord to take the virginity of the young women on his estate on her first night of marriage). Last year he made Carfagna minister for equal opportunities. He has also said that rightwing female politicians are better-looking than their leftwing counterparts. "The left has no taste, even when it comes to women."</p>
    <p>At the start of the 2006 election campaign, Berlusconi declared "I am the Jesus Christ of politics. I am a patient victim, I put up with everyone, I sacrifice myself for everyone." He also said that any Italian who didn't vote for him would be "a dickhead". He lost.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>