<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Eurozone crisis live: Vatican backs Monti; Schäuble suggests worst is over" author="Graeme Wearden; Guardian staff reporter" date="2012-12-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2012/dec/27/eurozone-crisis-italy-mario-monti-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Vatican’s Osservatore Romano newspaper says Monti’s message is “an appeal to recover the higher and more noble sense of politics”, as Germany’s finance minister suggests next year will be easier" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,Business,Italy,Mario Monti,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="1f84889598a01c64">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">And that appears to be all for the eurozone crisis today. Thanks for reading, and enjoy what's left of the holidays. </hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Until tomorrow...goodnight!</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">And that appears to be all for the eurozone crisis today. Thanks for reading, and enjoy what's left of the holidays. </hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Until tomorrow...goodnight!</hi>
    </p>
    <p>A quick look back to Italy, where <hi rend="#b">Mario Monti</hi> has again been praised by the Vatican's newspaper.</p>
    <p>Osservatore Romano wrote that Monti's message was:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>an appeal to recover the higher and more noble sense of politics that is ... to take care of the common good.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Reuters argues that the move has significant implications for next year's election, given the Catholic church's influence in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <quote>
      <p>During most of the 19 years that Berlusconi led the center right he enjoyed the backing of the Church hierarchy. He stepped down last year amid a burgeoning euro zone debt crisis and was replaced by Monti.</p>
      <p>The Church began distancing itself from the 76-year-old Berlusconi before he resigned, after a sex scandal involving an underage prostitute and details of so-called "bunga-bunga" parties in his Milan villa emerged.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Those gloomy comments from senator Harry Reid about the fiscal cliff have sent the Dow Jones index falling by over 100 points, and wiped out the early rally in London too:</p>
    <p>Here's a closing summary:</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">FTSE 100 - flat at 5954</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">German DAX: up 19 points at 7655, + 0.26%</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">French CAC: up 21 points at 3674, +0.6%</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Italian FTSE MIB: up 74 points at 16408, + 0.46%</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Spanish IBEX: down 18 points at 8280, -0.2%</hi>
    </p>
    <p>With the 40th anniversary of British accession to the European Economic Community looming (on 1 January 2013), Herman Van Rompuy has warned that David Cameron's push to repatriate powers from Brussels could cause great damage to the EU.</p>
    <p>Herman Van Rompuy, president of the European council, also questioned whether EU treaties could be reopened - a key part of Cameron's strategy.</p>
    <p><ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/dec/27/david-cameron-eu-herman-van-rompuy">Our Europe editor Ian Traynor reports</ref>:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>In his first remarks on the vexed issue of Britain's future in the EU, Van Rompuy told the Guardian that a British exit would cause immense damage to Europe, hurting both Britain and the 26 other countries.</p>
      <p>"If every member state were able to cherry-pick those parts of existing policies that they most like, and opt out of those that they least like, the union in general, and the single market in particular, would soon unravel," he said.</p>
      <p>"All member states can, and do, have particular requests and needs that are always taken into consideration as part of our deliberations. I do not expect any member state to seek to undermine the fundamentals of our co-operative system in Europe."</p>
    </quote>
    <p>And earlier, deputy prime minister Nick Clegg had argued strongly against trying to reshape Britain's relationship with the rest of the EU</p>
    <quote>
      <p>[Clegg] insists he is "not frightened" of a referendum, but adds: "For the life of me I still don't know what is the question we're supposed to be putting to the British people because we don't yet know what we're reacting to in terms of the further integration of the eurozone."</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Our Wall Street correspondent, Dominic Rushe, has the full details of the latest twist in the fiscal cliff drama:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>The Democratic leader in the Senate has declared that US politicians are likely to fail to find a solution to the the fiscal cliff budget crisis.</p>
      <p>With five days to reach a political solution before massive tax hikes and spending cuts kick in, Nevada senator Harry Reid said the deadline would probably be missed. “It looks like that’s where we’re headed”, he said on the Senate floor on Thursday.</p>
      <p>His gloomy acknowledgement of the failure of bipartisan negotiations triggered a sell-off on US stock markets.</p>
      <p>The Senate returned to work Thursday after the Christmas break, and Barack Obama cut short his Christmas vacation in Hawaii to fly back to Washington in search of a deal. But the House of Representatives is not in session, prompting Reid to to accuse the Republicans of being “out watching movies” with the fiscal cliff deadline looming.</p>
      <p>“I don’t know time-wise how it can happen,” said Reid. "I would hope that the speaker and the Republican leader here in the Senate would come to us and say here's what we think will work," Reid said.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Another worrying signal from the US: American consumer confidence took a nasty dive this month, falling to 65.1 from 71.5 in November. Those interviewed for December's consumer confidence index were much less optimistic about future expectations - perhaps a sign that the fiscal cliff farrago is alarming the public.....</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Senator Harry</hi><hi rend="#b">Reid</hi>, the leader of the Democratic Party in the US senate, has just warned that "it looks like" America is going to head over the fiscal cliff.</p>
    <p>Reid's comments suggest little optimism that Barack Obama can hammer out a last-ditch deal, having returned early from holiday (<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/dec/27/eurozone-crisis-italy-mario-monti-berlusconi#block-50dc1b6495cb94a7be21b489">see 9.56am</ref>). Without an agreement, Bush-era tax cuts will expire and billions of dollars of spending cuts will begin from the start of 2013.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The comments have helped to send US stocks down in early trading, with the Dow Jones dropping 74 points, or almost 0.6%, at 13040.</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Incidentally, do check out <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/fiscal-cliff-blog/2012/dec/27/fiscal-cliff-translated-around-the-world">this piece</ref> by our US finance and economics editor, Heidi Moore, about how the Cliff is being reported around the world (I rather like Norway's "budget ravine")....</p>
    <p>Germany's finance minister has claimed that Europe has survived the darkest days of the financial crisis, in an upbeat assessment of the situation as 2013 approaches.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Wolfgang Schäuble</hi> told <hi rend="#b">Bild</hi>, in an interview published this afternoon, that countries such as Greece and France have realised that they must implement tough reforms.</p>
    <p>Asked about the state of the euro crisis, <hi rend="#b">Schäuble</hi> replied that:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>I think the worst is behind us.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>adding that he was certain France will "meet its obligations" as</p>
    <quote>The [French] government knows very well that each country must constantly carry out reforms in order to remain competitive.</quote>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Schäuble</hi> also suggested that the German economy would perform well in 2013, saying the situation was "better than expected" thanks to demand from the US and Asia. <ref target="http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/wolfgang-schaeuble/in-der-europkrise-haben-wir-das-schlimmste-hinter-uns-27871302.bild.html">Full interview here</ref>.</p>
    <p>But for a counter-argument, check out DeAnne Julius in today's Financial Times warning that Global Financial Crisis II may be close:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Prolonged austerity is undermining political support for mainstream parties and encouraging the fringes, both left and right. The peripheral eurozone countries are at particular risk. A weak coalition in Italy after Spring elections or a separatist win in Catalonia could not only be the beginning of the end of the euro but the trigger for GFC II.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>More here: <ref target="http://blogs.ft.com/the-a-list/2012/12/24/another-global-financial-crisis-may-be-on-the-way/#axzz2GGKJjI4y">Another global financial crisis may be on the way.</ref></p>
    <p>Shares in Spain's <hi rend="#b">Bankia</hi> have tumbled by another 14% today after it emerged that investors in the deeply troubled bank will be all-but wiped out.</p>
    <p>Last night, Spain's bank rescue fund revealed that Bankia has a negative valuation of €4.2bn. The price of recapitalising the group, it seems, is that its shareholders will see their stakes cut to virtually nothing.</p>
    <p>The news is another bitter blow to hundreds of thousands of small shareholders who took part in Bankia's floatation in the summer of 2011, and have already seen their investments shrivel (<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/may/09/spain-bankia-market-turmoil">it was nationalised back in May after being brought down by its toxic debt mountain</ref>)</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Bankia</hi> is receiving €18bn through the recapitalisation of the Spanish banking sector but as one source explained to Reuters:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Are we looking into leaving shareholders with something? Yes. How much? That's too soon to say. Will it be very little? For sure.....</p>
      <p>But that will be purely symbolic. I can assure you they will lose up to the shirt on their back.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Bankia shares lost another €0.093 to €0.59 today, having floated at €3.75 17 months ago. <hi rend="#i">Shareholders may feel they lost their shirts some time ago....</hi></p>
    <p>Amid a quiet day for economic news, the number of Americans signing on for unemployment benefit for the first time has fallen close to its lowest level in four and a half years.</p>
    <p>The US labour department has just reported a weekly jobless claims total of 350,000, a drop of 12,000, suggesting that America's economy is ending the year healthily. However, Reuters cautions against reading too much into the data - as the numbers for 19 states had to be 'estimated' because federal workers were on holiday...</p>
    <p>Protests have been taking place in Madrid today against the Spanish government's plans to cut health spending, and proposals to privatise some public hospitals and health centres.</p>
    <p>Medical staff again urged Spain's politicians to ditch the plans, warning they will hurt patients by eroding the quality of care:</p>
    <p>Looking through the European papers, Der Spiegel is reporting that Christine Lagarde fears Germany may hamper the eurozone recovery by imposing domestic spending cutbacks after autumn's general election.</p>
    <p>The head of the IMF has apparently warned that Germany should resist any major fiscal consolidation efforts until the euro periphery is stronger.</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Germany and other countries "can afford to move ahead with consolidation at a slower pace than others," Lagarde said. "That serves to counteract the negative effects on growth that emanate from the cuts made in crisis countries."</p>
    </quote>
    <p>The comments follow a report - denied by Berlin - that the German finance ministry is preparing a programme of tax hikes and spending cuts for 2014 (even though <ref target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887324894104578107163451656582.html">Germany appears to be on track to hit its target of a balance budget early</ref>)</p>
    <p>The euro has been gaining ground in the currency markets this morning, up 0.4 of a cent against the US dollar now at $1.3265.</p>
    <p>Stock markets also remain calm (<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/dec/27/eurozone-crisis-italy-mario-monti-berlusconi#block-50dc1d25b579a9dd79231d75">see also 10.04am</ref>), while traders await a breakthrough in the US fiscal cliff talks.</p>
    <p>As fund manager <ref target="http://topics.bloomberg.com/arnaud-scarpaci/">Arnaud Scarpaci</ref> of Montaigne Capital in Paris put it to Bloomberg:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>If there isn’t an agreement tonight, we can start worrying. If there is an agreement, we can have a little rally.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Meanwhile the FTSE 250 (composed of mid-value companies) hit a new lifetime high this morning. It's gained around 23% this year -- underlining how share prices shrugged off the eurozone crisis and the general economic malaise.</p>
    <p>Over in Greece, the saga of the "Lagarde List" of alleged tax evaders rumbles on.</p>
    <p><ref target="http://www.ekathimerini.com/4dcgi/_w_articles_wsite1_1_26/12/2012_475962">Greek newspaper Kathimerini reported last night</ref> that government officials have collected a new copy of the list (which was originally handed to Athens in 2010 and then curiously mislaid) from the French government.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors are now checking whether this new list matches the existing version (which was produced by former finance minister Evangelos Venizelos in October).</p>
    <p><ref target="http://greece.greekreporter.com/2012/12/26/first-lagarde-list-missing-600-names/">Some media outlets claim</ref> that the new copy contains <hi rend="#b">hundreds of extra names </hi>- running to 2,500 potential tax dodgers, not the 2,000 or so on the Venizelos list.</p>
    <p>One source told Kathimerini:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>The lists are being crosschecked name by name, amount by amount and if any differences are found, political and judicial responsibilities will be sought.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>The Italian government has successfully raised almost €12bn this morning, despite the country's political uncertainty.</p>
    <p>The Italian treasury sold €8.5bn of six-month bills at an average yield (interest rate) of 0.949%, up from 0.919% in November - and the highest borrowing rate since October.</p>
    <p>It also sold €3.25bn of two-year bonds at lower yields - 1.884% compared with 1.923% last month.</p>
    <p>With fewer bond traders around, the sale looks like a success:</p>
    <quote><p>Yields little changed but mixed at Italian auction vs Nov.</p>— Emese Bartha (@EmeseBartha)<ref>#Italy</ref><ref>#fixed</ref>income<ref>December 27, 2012</ref></quote>
    <p>Back to Italy, and the head of the Bundesbank has warned that investors would lose faith in the Italian government if the reform programme put underway by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref> faltered.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Jens Weidmann</hi>, Germany's top central banker, told business news magazine <hi rend="#b">Wirtschaftswoche </hi>that it would be "disastrous" if the country's targets were called into question by next February's election:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Italy suffers from low growth, low productivity and lack of innovation. But under the Monti government, Italy has set ambitious goals for reform in order to regain the confidence of investors, and had success with it.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Weidmann added that central bankers were not "sweepers", there to clean up the mess created by politicians.</p>
    <p>He was also cautious about suggesting the worst of the eurozone crisis was over, saying:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>We have progressed a long way, but we must not underestimate the distance ahead.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>The full interview is <ref target="http://www.wiwo.de/politik/europa/interview-mit-jens-weidmann-wir-sind-nicht-ausputzer-fuer-politikerversagen-seite-all/7547164-all.html">online here</ref>.</p>
    <p>The financial markets are calm this morning as traders return to work following the Christmas break.</p>
    <p>The major European indices are slightly higher, despite <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/dec/27/eurozone-crisis-italy-mario-monti-berlusconi#block-50dc1b6495cb94a7be21b489">the fiscal cliff deadlock</ref> (see 9.56am). Here's the latest prices:</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">FTSE 100:</hi> up 13 points at 5967, + 0.2%</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">German DAX:</hi> up 15 points at 6751, + 0.2%</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">French CAC:</hi> up 23 points at 3675, + 0.6%</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Spanish IBEX:</hi> up 4 points at 8303, + 0.05%</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Italian FTSE MIB:</hi> up 83 points at 16415, + 0.5%</p>
    <p>And earlier this morning, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/dec/27/japan-nikkei-share-index-high">Japan's Nikkei closed at a 21-month high</ref>.</p>
    <p>The other big news this morning is that negotiations over the US fiscal cliff have still not reached a conclusion.</p>
    <p>With the deadline to reach a deal looming, US Treasury secretary Tim Geithner warned yesterday that "extraordinary measures" might be needed to prevent the US hitting its $16.4tn (£10.16tn) debt ceiling.</p>
    <p>Geithner warned Congress that the uncertainty over America's tax and spending policies for 2013 meant the country risked breaching its borrowing limits.</p>
    <p>He said the Treasury could raise $200bn through "extraordinary measures" - but warned that it wasn't clear how much time that would buy.</p>
    <p>US president Barack Obama has now cut short his holiday in Hawaii, heading back to Washington late last night....</p>
    <p>Here's our full story from late last night: <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/dec/26/us-treasury-fiscal-cliff-barack-obama">US Treasury warns of 'extraordinary measures' amid fiscal cliff deadlock</ref></p>
    <p>The battle has already escalated this morning -- with SIlvio Berlusconi launching an attack against <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref> on Italian TV today.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi told Rai 1's <hi rend="#i"> Unomattina</hi>that Monti's government had been 'crushed' by pressure from the rest of the eurozone, and repeated his pledge to abolish a key property tax.</p>
    <p>Linkiesta's <ref target="https://twitter.com/fgoria">Fabrizio Goria</ref> has tweeted the key quotes:</p>
    <quote><p>Berlusconi: The Monti government crushed under German and Europeans diktats</p>— Fabrizio Goria (@FGoria)<ref>December 27, 2012</ref></quote>
    <quote><p>Berlusconi: I confirm that I wil abolish real estate tax IMU. Who said (Monti) it's not possible, does not know public finance management</p>— Fabrizio Goria (@FGoria)<ref>December 27, 2012</ref></quote>
    <quote><p>Berlusconi says he has higher rank (international diplomacy, business and politics) than Monti. Omits to say only for Bunga Bunga. His life.</p>— davide serra (@davidealgebris)<ref>December 27, 2012</ref></quote>
    <p>This comes after Monti was notably scathing about Berlusconi on Sunday, telling reporters that he was "struggling trying to follow" the PDL leader's thinking...</p>
    <p>In case you're been distracted by Christmas, here's how events have unfolded in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> in the last few days:</p>
    <p> The election battle really got underway last Friday, when Mario Monti formally stepped down: <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/dec/21/mario-monti-resigns-italy">Mario Monti resigns as prime minister of Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p> On Sunday, Monti declared that he would be prepared to lead a group of parties who backed his reform agenda: <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/dec/23/mario-monti-return-italy-prime-minister">Mario Monti considers return as Italian prime minister</ref></p>
    <p> That agenda - including economic reforms and fiscal responsibility - was launched online on Christmas Eve: <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/9765097/Mario-Monti-announces-reform-agenda-for-Italy.html">Mario Monti announces reform agenda for Italy</ref></p>
    <p>Monti also appears to have joined Twitter, tweeting late on Christmas Day that:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Together we have saved Italy from disaster. Now politics is due for renewal. Complaining does not help, you must work. "Let's go" in politics!</p>
    </quote>
    <quote><p>Insieme abbiamo salvato l'Italia dal disastro. Ora va rinnovata la politica. Lamentarsi non serve, spendersi si. "Saliamo" in politica!</p>— Mario Monti (@SenatoreMonti)<ref>December 25, 2012</ref></quote>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Good morning, and welcome back to our rolling coverage of the eurozone financial crisis - and other events across the world economy as we edge nearer to the end of 2012.</hi>
    </p>
    <p>With Boxing Day behind us, a meaty scrap is underway in Italy. Having resigned as Italian prime minister, <hi rend="#b">Mario Monti</hi> is holding negotiations that could see him stay on as PM after next February's elections.</p>
    <p>Monti is expected to meet with prospective coalition partners today to discuss electoral strategy, and 'candidate lists' for the upcoming election.</p>
    <p>He published <ref target="http://www.agenda-monti.it/">his agenda for Italy</ref> last weekend -- the big question for Italy (and arguably the eurozone too) is whether he will rally enough support for a credible election bid.</p>
    <p>The Financial Times believes Monti is gearing up for a clash with his predecessor, <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>, <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/8332aa48-4f79-11e2-a744-00144feab49a.html#axzz2GEb0LDMp">reporting this morning that</ref>:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>Italy’s centrist politicians are rallying behind Mario Monti’s offer to lead an alliance into elections in February, setting the stage for a confrontation with Silvio Berlusconi in his attempt to return to power.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>adding:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>His decision to seek a second stint as prime minister, while not yet official, could lead to an even more fragmented parliament than had been expected. It injects a fourth element into a battle between the centre-left Democrats, Mr Berlusconi’s centre-right People of Liberty and the anti-establishment Five Star Movement.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>And Berlusconi's party has already hit back, accusing Monti of mishandling the Italian economy over the last 13 months.</p>
    <p>As PDL member Anna Maria Bernini put it:</p>
    <quote>
      <p>It is shocking to see how a man can present himself as a saviour after bringing the country to recession, taking all the merit (for successes) and attributing all the disasters to others.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>So it's looking like a tasty battle, which will play a significant part in Europe's fortunes in 2013.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">I'll be tracking the developments in Italy, and beyond, through the day....</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>