<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Carla Bruni brushes off Berlusconi paper's barb" author="Angelique Chrisafis" date="2009-07-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/10/bruni-sarkozy-berlusconi-paper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Paper owned by Italian PM's brother rebukes 'boorish' French first lady for snubbing group tour of L'Aquila in favour of solo trip" categories="Culture" tags="Carla Bruni-Sarkozy,Culture,Italy,France,Silvio Berlusconi,Nicolas Sarkozy,G8,World news,Newspapers,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,Politics,Europe" fingerprint="fc2c9a259371573f">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi once interrupted a speech by Nicolas Sarkozy to jeer "I gave you your wife", in reference to the Italian-born former supermodel Carla Bruni. But relations between the Berlusconi clan and the French first lady have turned to ice.</p>
    <p>Bruni-Sarkozy today made her own tour of earthquake-hit L'Aquila after opting not to join a visit with other first ladies yesterday on the margins of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit.</p>
    <p>The singer, who recently began campaigning for global health programmes on Aids, tuberculosis and malaria, announced that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref> would contribute €3.2m to the restoration of a church dome in the town. But she was attacked in a Berlusconi family newspaper for crassly snubbing other wives and fancying herself as another Mother Teresa.</p>
    <p>"Someone tell the first lady that snobbery to the nth degree where we come from is called boorishness," wrote a columnist in the rightwing <ref target="http://www.ilgiornale.it/">Il Giornale</ref>, owned by Berlusconi's brother. The editorialist said her behaviour made even charity "stink". Her actions reeked of "the uncontrollable desire to be the centre of attention" and she saw herself as "the world's best thing since the death of Mother Teresa".</p>
    <p>Bruni-Sarkozy was known for privately criticising Berlusconi long before her marriage to Sarkozy. Last year, when the Italian prime minister repeatedly joked about Barack Obama's "sun tan", Bruni said she was glad to have recently taken French nationality.</p>
    <p>Touring L'Aquila before a trip to her native Turin with her husband, she brushed off the Giornale article, saying she never paid attention to comments in the press.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>