<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi: The women now thrust under the media spotlight" author="Tom Kington" date="2011-01-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/29/silvio-berlusconi-women-under-spotlight" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian press is besieging models and showgirls alleged to have accepted cash from Italy's PM in return for sex" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="6fc0abbf109fc76b">
  <main>
    <p>María Ester García Polanco, one of the women at the centre of the scandal engulfing the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, is bouncing her daughter on her knee – but that doesn't mean she's not a worried woman.</p>
    <p>"With the newspapers full of this story, I am concerned about my child and what other mothers are saying at school," says the 27-year-old model and showgirl. Two weeks ago police woke her at 6am to search for evidence that she was accepting cash gifts and free rent from the Italian prime minister, allegedly in return for sexual favours.</p>
    <p>Since then journalists have laid siege to the smart apartment complex on the fringes of Milan that is home to María and a "stable" of other beautiful women, all suspected of participating in Berlusconi's alleged "bunga bunga" nights of striptease and sex at his villa an hour's drive to the north.</p>
    <p>The investigation into the prime minister's sexual activities, following suspicions that Berlusconi paid an underage Moroccan dancer, Karima El-Mahroug, thousands of euros for sex when she was 17, is deadly serious. But its ramifications took on a tragi-comic dimension when the owners of the Via Olgettina apartment complex tried to evict the models for "lowering the tone" of the neighbourhood. That eviction notice has been shelved, but the journalists remain.</p>
    <p>Following the police raid, García Polanco has finally put straight her belongings – a high-kitsch collection of feather boas, fake orchids, a carpet featuring the face of Marilyn Monroe and red-and-white-striped walls with the words "Family", "Art" and "Seduction" daubed on them. Next to a painting showing a scene from her native Dominican Republic, the novel <hi rend="#i">Memoirs of a Geisha</hi> can be seen on her bookshelves.</p>
    <p>However, García Polanco rejects the notion that she is a kept woman. "I pay the €1,300 monthly rent here myself, not Berlusconi, and I never said I had sex with him," she told the <hi rend="#i">Observer</hi>, after convincing her daughter to play in her bedroom. "The truth is that Berlusconi's dinners were just normal events followed by karaoke and Berlusconi singing in French," she said.</p>
    <p>Her version of events echoes the stories told by numerous fellow party guests to Niccolò Ghedini, Berlusconi's lawyer, who has taken signed statements to use in the prime minister's defence if magistrates succeed in putting him in the dock this year.</p>
    <p>It would be their word against hundreds of pages of wiretaps and depositions in which Berlusconi is described by other guests as reaching out from his chair to fondle women as they paraded half-naked past him.</p>
    <p>Via Olgettina is in the heart of Berlusconi-land. The road overlooks Milano Due, the high-maintenance collection of apartment buildings and shops that Berlusconi built in the 1970s, boasting a tree-lined artificial lake, gushing fountains, handy underground parking and studios for Berlusconi's Mediaset TV channels.</p>
    <p>It was here that, after the latest scandal to plague the prime minister broke, El-Mahroug was carefully rehabilitated in a televised interview, in which she cried as she described being abused by her Moroccan uncles. "To flee from the pain you began to construct a parallel life?" asked her host, suggesting that her wiretapped talk of prostituting herself and blackmailing Berlusconi for her silence was the fantasy of a lost girl.</p>
    <p>García Polanco remembers "Ruby the Heartstealer", as she is now known, very well. "Ruby was very tall, dressed outrageously, and she talked about setting up health centres," she said. "She looked older than her age."</p>
    <p>García Polanco said she launched her own modelling career in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> at the age of 15, after a tough upbringing in Nagua in the Dominican Republic, where her brother is a priest. To prove her pluck, she pulled down the back of her shirt to reveal the words "Never Give Up" tattooed across her shoulders.</p>
    <p>After meeting Berlusconi at a party three years ago, the wiretaps suggest she was not afraid to pull the new strings available to her. In Milan, when she wanted a passport, she used Berlusconi's name to get an appointment with the prefect himself. He asked her to "say hello to the president". Berlusconi also handed over funds that she needed to pay funeral expenses for relatives in the Dominican Republic and medical expenses for her daughter.</p>
    <p>One block along on Via Olgettina, another frequent party guest, Barbara Guerra, is evasive over cash received from Berlusconi, mentioning a "small" gift of €5,000 to cover expenses.<hi rend="#i"> La Repubblica</hi> reported yesterday that police found another €18,000 hidden in a Louis Vuitton bag in her flat. "Otherwise it was normal presents like this," she said, producing a silk scarf from exclusive Neapolitan tie-maker Marinella. For Guerra, too, life in Berlusconi-land has become an uncomfortable experience.</p>
    <p>"The morning after the police raid, I opened my front door to find the hall packed with paparazzi," she said. "And since the magistrates' evidence was leaked on the internet – including our mobile phone numbers – I have been getting calls from maniacs in the night."</p>
    <p>Aged 32 and a mainstay of TV variety shows, Guerra is a star in her own right, whose career survived revelations that two years ago she frequented a previous round of Berlusconi's parties in Rome.</p>
    <p>Guerra uses the standard "very normal dinners" line of defence to describe those occasions. The frequent presence of Giampaolo Tarantini – the Puglian businessman who has admitted bringing prostitute Patrizia D'Addario to the gatherings – casts a shadow over this account, but Guerra is adamant. As for the incriminating accusations made about the latest "bunga bunga" parties in Milan, Guerra blames "people trying to attract attention to themselves".</p>
    <p>Guerra's neighbour is fellow showgirl Arisleida Espinosa, who has had her own problems since the interrogation by magistrates of a friend she took to a Berlusconi party. The friend told the magistrates that Espinosa received envelopes of cash from the prime minister because she had slept with him more than once.</p>
    <p>Via Olgettina models, such as García Polanco, Guerra and Espinosa, have become Berlusconi's first line of defence in a battle now shaking Italy's institutional framework. The prime minister has demanded "punishment" for the magistrates whom he accuses of persecuting him.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, the women he gathered around him remain at the centre of the storm. This week there was more bad news for García Polanco when magistrates released a second batch of wiretap transcripts and evidence, revealing that police found more than 2kg of cocaine in her storeroom last summer. "It was my boyfriend's; he said he was in investment and travelled," she said. "The police saw that I didn't know anything."</p>
    <p>On Via Olgettina, every day brings another allegation and another denial.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>