<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The Silvio Berlusconi political circus doesn't end here | Dino Amenduni" author="Dino Amenduni" date="2013-08-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/aug/02/silvio-berlusconi-tax-fraud-political-circus" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Dino Amenduni: You would think Berlusconi's tax fraud conviction would be a landmark moment in Italian politics. In fact it changes very little" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="5eeed2ff9022d74d">
  <main>
    <p>After Thursday's ruling by the Italian supreme court, we can now say it for certain: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/01/silvio-berlusconi-prison-sentence-upheld">Silvio Berlusconi is a tax dodger</ref>. The longest-serving prime minister of the Italian republic (3,340 days in charge) has committed a crime against the state. From a historical perspective, the ruling is therefore of enormous importance. Does it also mean that something will change in Italy? Absolutely not, at least not any time soon.</p>
    <p>There are two components, by now well-established, that have reduced the impact of the former prime minister's conviction on Italian political life. First of all we must consider that Italians have already, and for a long time now, passed judgment on Berlusconi. He is seen as a shrewd political strategist, a terrible administrator of public affairs and an incisive communicator (thanks partly to his economic means, and to the power of a media empire no other politician in a fully fledged democracy would have been allowed to own). He is also seen as morally questionable.</p>
    <p>The other fixed element is the way in which Italians perceive and talk about Berlusconi's trials. Regardless of his acts of negligence and effective responsibility, the right wing has maintained for years that the Italian judicial system has been in dogged pursuit of Berlusconi. As a result of this campaign, the substance of the lawsuits is hardly ever discussed and the context instead established is: are the judges prejudiced?.</p>
    <p>The years of continuous investigations, indictments and rulings have been accompanied by the same dynamic throughout: the leader of the Freedom party is seen as a "martyr" by the ruling classes and voters of the right, and as a criminal by the ruling classes and voters of the left, albeit with varying degrees of sentiment. This scenario has played out over and over, without any distinction for the type of trial, the strength of the prosecution evidence, and most of all without any consideration for the effective outcome of the various lawsuits.</p>
    <p>The idea that prosecutors may have "exaggerated" is therefore strongly entrenched not only among his voters but also in segments of the Italian population that have never voted for Berlusconi. For these reasons, Thursday's definitive ruling for tax fraud does not alter this frame of mind.</p>
    <p>Incredibly, the ruling is less destabilising than an acquittal because it reinforces the opinions of those who regard Berlusconi as a victim of persecution and of those who see him as a repeat offender. It is therefore wrong to assume Berlusconi will be bowing out, or that he is at the end of his political career.</p>
    <p>He will never go to jail, because he is too old and because he will effectively serve only one year of a four-year sentence, possibly under house arrest (the first three years are covered by a pardon voted for in 2006, hence after the episode for which he has been found guilty). A recent law passed by the justice secretary of the Mario Monti government will now prevent him from running in elections for the next six years because of the length of his sentence (over two years) and its crime (fraud). But it will not stop him from being politically active even if it is outside of parliament.</p>
    <p>In any other country it would be reasonable to think that a political leader sentenced to jail would vanish from the public eye or be rejected by his own party. This will not happen in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, because the Freedom party belongs to Berlusconi in the most literal sense: he funds it with his own money and the successes of the Italian right in the past 20 years have relied on the appeal of the Berlusconi brand. Without Berlusconi, the Italian right does not exist.</p>
    <p>In any other country it would also be reasonable to imagine that a political organisation that is allied to another whose leader is guilty of tax evasion would be asking for a leadership change as a condition to renew the coalition. This means that today the Democratic party (centre-left) is actually in more trouble than Berlusconi's Freedom party, as it needs to answer the question: "Is it possible to be in government with Berlusconi after what has just happened?" They know that to say yes will cost them millions of votes; and a no would bring down a coalition government led by one of his representatives, Enrico Letta, with all the economic and political repercussions that would follow in its wake.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>