<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Cardinal fashion sins! Headlines to look out for in My Pope magazine" author="Tim Dowling" date="2014-03-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/shortcuts/2014/mar/05/my-pope-francis-silvio-berlusconi-glossy-magazine" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Tim Dowling: Silvio Berlusconi's publishing house has launched a glossy magazine dedicated to Pope Francis, with photographs and a pull-out centrefold. Here are a few ideas for the next issue …" categories="World news" tags="Pope Francis,Religion,Catholicism,Christianity,The papacy,Silvio Berlusconi,Magazines,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,World news" fingerprint="82b73b4804adb6b4">
  <main>
    <p>Pope Francis is no ordinary celebrity, but until recently he was lacking one of global fame's most common accessories: a dedicated fanzine.</p>
    <p>That has changed. The first issue of Il Mio Papa (My Pope) magazine, a weekly glossy featuring papal pronouncements, news, personal details and photographs – including a pull-out centrefold – hit shelves in Italy this week.</p>
    <p>Il Mio Papa is not an official Vatican publication, but a product of Silvio Berlusconi's publishing house, Mondadori, responsible for titles including TV Sorrisi e Canzoni ("TV Smiles and Songs") and the gossip magazine Chi.</p>
    <graphic src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/3/5/1394036230720/Il-Mio-Papa-left-and-a-mo-009.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="Il Mio Papa (left) and a mock-up of the magazine, imagined by the Guardian"/>
    <p>Here are a few cover lines we imagine we'll be seeing in future:</p>
    <p>▶ White is the new purple: 20 infallible looks for summer</p>
    <p>▶ Eat, pray, lose – The Ephesians 5:2 diet</p>
    <p>▶ Holy See! We look inside Il Papa's minimalist living space</p>
    <p>▶ Nun Direction: 7 Habits of highly effective religious orders</p>
    <p>▶ Father, Son, Holy Ghost: the ultimate love triangle?</p>
    <p>▶ Deliver Us From Sleeve Hell: chasubles to flatter every figure</p>
    <p>▶ Lenten Tarantino: 20 films you must not see between now and Easter</p>
    <p>▶ Smells like teen spirit: altar boys choose their favourite incense fragrances</p>
    <p>▶ Surplice to requirements: how to strip down to your beach cassock with confidence</p>
    <p>▶ Thank God It's Friday: easy fish recipes</p>
    <p>▶ 40-day detox: look and feel your holiest</p>
    <p>▶ Cardinal sins: what not to wear for an audience with the pontiff</p>
    <p>▶ Kill the fatted calf: the slimming power of red slippers.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>