<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Mario Monti considers return as Italian prime minister" author="Tom Kington" date="2012-12-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/dec/23/mario-monti-return-italy-prime-minister" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Outgoing technocrat premier throws hat back into ring and launches stinging attack on rival Silvio Berlusconi" categories="World news" tags="Mario Monti,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,European Union,World news,Europe" fingerprint="1f88c8259ce1dd65">
  <main>
    <p>Mario Monti says he will consider returning as prime minister of Italy after elections in February – and has launched a stinging attack on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who brought down his technocratic government this month.</p>
    <p>Monti, commenting on the attacks on his austerity programme, as well as the offers he has had to lead a new centre-right coalition, said: "I am struggling trying to follow [Berlusconi's] line of thinking."</p>
    <p>While throwing his hat back into the ring, Monti refused to name parties he would ally with, merely stating that he would consider politicians who sign up to a programme of reforms he wanted carried out in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
    <p>"I would be ready to offer my appreciation, encouragement, and if asked, leadership" to parties that backed the programme, he said, adding that it would soon be posted online.</p>
    <p>Monti said he would not join a party ticket before the election, but added: "If one or more political forces who adhere to the programme propose me as a candidate for prime minster, I would consider it."</p>
    <p>His <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/dec/22/mario-monti-italian-elections">keenly awaited</ref> speech, following his resignation as technocrat premier on Friday, partly cleared up the confusion surrounding Italy's return to fully democratic government after Monti's appointment last November.</p>
    <p>But he left doubt over whether he would front a coalition of centrist parties, including the descendant of the Christian Democrats, which has been lobbying him to stand as their leader.</p>
    <p>Monti is unlikely to win the election, and his statement allows him time to see how the centrist parties fare in the polls. Italy's centre-left Democratic party, which has asked Monti not to stand, is leading the polls. In an interview published by La Repubblica on Friday, Monti criticised the centrists: "They have been politicians since they were children and people can't tolerate professional politicians anymore," he said.</p>
    <p>By not committing, the former EU commissioner has also left open the door to becoming Italy's next president in 2013.</p>
    <p>He was surprisingly fierce in his criticism of Berlusconi, who pulled his support for Monti this month, triggering his resignation, and who this weekend condemned Monti's government as a "complete disaster".</p>
    <p>Monti said Italians could "hold their heads high" after his government implemented fiscal restraint to restore Italy's credibility following Berlusconi's resignation in November 2011.</p>
    <p>He said his new programme promoted collaborating with the EU to improve Italy's future, as opposed to Berlusconi's constant attacks on the bloc. A simple "slap on the back" in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> would not get results, Monti added, an apparent reference to his rival's bonhomie at summits.</p>
    <p>Monti also warned against dropping a controversial property tax that Berlusconi was campaigning against, adding that scrapping it would only result in reintroducing it doubled the following year.</p>
    <p>A much-needed anti-corruption law had been "impoverished" by Berlusconi's opposition, he said, warning that Italy required laws on false accounting and conflicts of interest.</p>
    <p>Monti also called for the next government to undertake a "drastic simplification" of the country's labour laws and a strengthening of the reforms launched by his government. He advised the Italian left to accept laws to open key sectors of the economy.</p>
    <p>"I hope Italy does not need to be saved every year," he said in reference to his 13-month administration, and urged politicians to focus on the next generation rather than the next election.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>