<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Mario Monti to announce new Italian government" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/16/mario-monti-announce-italy-government" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prime minister designate has 'defined picture' of administration amid concern over possible role for Berlusconi ally" categories="World news" tags="Mario Monti,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" fingerprint="3f8cca34d8a3ff6d">
  <main>
    <p>Mario Monti is grappling with the problem of whether to include Silvio Berlusconi's right-hand man, Gianni Letta, in his government as the price of securing the outgoing prime minister's support.</p>
    <p>Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, asked the former European commissioner on Sunday to form a new government. Monti is due on Wednesday to tell the president whether it would enjoy credible support in parliament.</p>
    <p>Monti told a press conference that he had a "well-defined picture" of his administration, but did not confirm whether he would accept the challenge of leading <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> through its mounting debt crisis.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi lost the backing of the lower house last week. But with the support of his coalition partners in the Northern League, who are opposed to a Monti government, he has enough votes to topple an incoming administration – or block its legislation– in the upper house, the Senate.</p>
    <p>Angelino Alfano, the secretary of Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People (PdL), said on Tuesday it was up to the prime minister designate to decide whether to make Gianni Letta, the TV magnate's eternal Mr Fixit, a minister.</p>
    <p>In a remark worthy of the wiliest Renaissance diplomat, he added: "If I may give a bit of dispassionate advice, I would never deprive myself of someone – like Gianni Letta." He added that the PdL would have no objection if Monti included in his cabinet Giuliano Amato, the leftwing former prime minister.</p>
    <p>While Amato is very much his own man, Letta has stood at Berlusconi's side for more than 20 years. His presence would send a signal that Monti's mainly technocratic government was ultimately dependent on the outgoing prime minister's goodwill.</p>
    <p>The PdL's subtly announced ultimatum came after a second day of consultations on the shape and programme of Monti's prospective government. The talks, with representatives of parliamentary parties, trade unions, employers' federations, women and youth, were held against a background of alarming developments in the financial markets.</p>
    <p>A <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/blog/2011/nov/15/eurozone-crisis-gdp-germany-france-italy">surge in the yields</ref> demanded for riskier eurozone debt pushed Italy's borrowing costs back over the hazardous 7% mark. No eurozone state has seen the return on its benchmark government bonds exceed that level without needing a bailout.</p>
    <p>Monti had been expected to confirm he was ready to become prime minister on Tuesday evening, but he has postponed the announcement until Wednesday morning.</p>
    <p>As the protracted process of forming a government continued in Rome, the president of the European council, Herman Van Rompuy, warned Italy that it was facing its "<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/15/mario-monti-italy-moment-truth?newsfeed=true">moment of truth</ref>".</p>
    <p>On Monday night Monti upped the stakes with the PdL when he said he would not go ahead if a time limit were put on his government. A general election does not have to be held in Italy until spring 2013.</p>
    <p>The PdL had originally demanded that a Monti government be given a short lifespan and a restricted mandate. It wants the new administration to implement economic reforms and deficit-cutting measures agreed by Berlusconi last month with the European institutions and then stand down to make way for an early election.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>