<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Letters: Berlusconi at fault for economic failure" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2010-12-18" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/18/berlusconi-italy-economic-failure" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Letters: From 2001 to 2009, Italy has been the only major country whose economy shrank over the period as a whole" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" fingerprint="5fc2953d5b53ee18">
  <main>
    <p>Your editorial (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-italy-conflict-too-far?INTCMP=SRCH">A conflict too far</ref>, 14 December) rightly records a few of the many scandals that render Berlusconi unfit to govern, but omitted the one with the greatest impact on ordinary Italians. This is the macroeconomic catastrophe that has occurred since 2001 – the year Berlusconi came to power, to remain there for seven of the nine subsequent years. In the eight years up to 2001, when Berlusconi was out of office for all but seven months, Italy's economic performance was mediocre but roughly in line with that of other large European countries. In the eight years from 2001 to 2009, Italy has been the only major country whose economy shrank over the period as a whole.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi entered politics in 1993 promising a liberal revolution that would shrink the size of the state. Public spending was 53% of GDP at that time, and this share fell steadily to reach 46% in 2000. Once he came to power in 2001, the steady fall was reversed, and it was back up to 49% when he left office in 2006. It remained unchanged in the two ensuing years, and, since Berlusconi's re-election in 2008, has risen back to 53%. In this regard, he has delivered the precise opposite of what he promised. This outcome is the consequence of the economic stagnation that he has brought. It is now clear that anybody seeking a liberal economic revolution would be unwise to entrust the task to a monopolist.</p>
    <p>While the conflict of interest and bunga bunga scandals can be laid at Berlusconi's door, it must be recognised that blame for the macroeconomic catastrophe must be shared by the Northern League, his partner in government throughout the period since 2001.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Charles Young</hi>
    </p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Oxford</hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>