<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="George Clooney and Cristiano Ronaldo named as witnesses in Berlusconi trial" author="Tom Kington" date="2011-03-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/mar/29/george-clooney-cristiano-ronaldo-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Hollywood actor and footballer could be called to give evidence when Italian prime minister answers 'bunga bunga' charges" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,George Clooney,Cristiano Ronaldo,Europe,World news,Italy" fingerprint="daeac18bf163c476">
  <main>
    <p>George Clooney and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/ronaldo">Cristiano Ronaldo</ref> may be called to testify in defence of Silvio Berlusconi when he stands trial on charges of underage prostitution.</p>
    <p>The Italian prime minister's lawyers have submitted a list of 78 witnesses they intend to call at Berlusconi's trial which starts on 6 April, including Italian government ministers, the Italian news agency Ansa reported.</p>
    <p>They have also called Karima El Mahroug, known as Ruby, the Moroccan runaway who was 17 when she allegedly attended sex parties held by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors deposited their own list of 132 witnesses, which also includes Mahroug and 32 other women they believe attended bunga bunga parties at Berlusconi's mansion near Milan in 2010.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors are likely to ask Mahroug about Berlusconi's parties and the gifts of cash and jewellery she reportedly received from him.</p>
    <p>Defence lawyers seeking to undermine Mahroug's credibility may question her about claims she made to investigators that Clooney was present at a dinner she attended at Berlusconi's mansion. Clooney's Italian girlfriend, Elisabetta Canalis, has already told investigators that neither she nor Clooney attended a dinner at the mansion.</p>
    <p>Mahroug, who has given widely conflicting accounts of her past, also told investigators she was paid for sex by footballer Ronaldo, a claim denied by Ronaldo. The trial judges will decide which witnesses to admit.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is also on trial for pressuring Milan police to release Mahroug from custody when she was arrested on suspicion of theft last year. Berlusconi told officers Mahroug could be a relative of the then Egyptian president Hosni Mubarak.</p>
    <p>Officers who released of Mahroug will be called for the prosecution.</p>
    <p>The prosecution will also call Nicole Minetti, a regional politician and habitué of Berlusconi's parties, showbusiness agent Lele Mora and TV presenter Emilio Fede, who are likely to stand trial separately charged with procuring prostitutes for Berlusconi, 74.</p>
    <p>The defence, which claims Berlusconi's dinners were sober affairs, will call Mara Carfagna, a topless model turned government minister in the Berlusconi administration, who attended a dinner.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>