<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Readers recommend: songs about promises … and choices | Peter Kimpton" author="Peter Kimpton" date="2015-05-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/music/musicblog/2015/may/07/readers-recommend-songs-about-promises-and-choices-general-election-voting" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Broken or kept, pledged, sworn or signed, whether political or personal, make your musical choices in our special ballot on this very promising topic, says Peter Kimpton" categories="Music" tags="Music,Pop and rock,Culture,Folk music,Reggae,Hip-hop,Country,General election 2015,Politics,UK news,Conservatives,Labour,Liberal Democrats,Silvio Berlusconi,Richard Nixon,Jonathan Swift,Books,The Kinks,Ray Davies,David Cameron,Nick Clegg,Ed Miliband,Liberal-Conservative coalition" fingerprint="fe8a10b381f0f2bc">
  <main>
    <quote>
      <p>“We are sick and tired of being promised this and that. We work all day, we sweat and slave to keep the wealthy fat. They fill our heads with promises, bamboozle us with facts, they put on false sincerity, then laugh behind our backs. Money and corruption are ruining the land. Crooked politicians betray the working man, pocketing the profits and treating us like sheep. We’re tired of hearing promises we know they’ll never keep.”</p>
    </quote>
    <p>Sounds familiar? These words, written by Ray Davies in the early 1970s, could be applied to any era, for party politics or any other setting since any human being took steps to lead others. But are promises the verbal bargaining tools that make us unique? The writer Hannah Arendt said that “promises are the human way of ordering the future”, but in the end, no one knows the future and promises are always a risk. As Henry Ford put it: “You can’t build a reputation on what you are going to do.” Perhaps this is the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinocchio_paradox">Pinocchio paradox</ref>, meaning you cannot trust someone who says they are telling the truth, especially if promising something in the future. And the cynic, or realist, depending on your point of view, might say, as Jonathan Swift did, that “promises and pie-crusts are meant to be broken”.</p>
    <p>And so this week, as polls begin to close on election day, we tuck into a new pie. But who will have the biggest slice? It is that time, once every five years, when the fruit of promises appear to ripen and are ready to be picked. But what of the ingredients? Does it comprise blueberries or red fruits, or indeed gooseberries? Or perhaps a sticky old jam of xenophic floor scrapings? Some of the produce may prove to blossom perfectly from an orchard of ideals, others will undoubtedly stink like a rotten <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2014/feb/03/durian-worlds-smelliest-fruit-sale-britain">durian</ref>.</p>
    <p>Your song suggestions, on the subject of promises, need not touch on politics at all, but don’t hold back if you want to discuss the UK general election or any other parallel issues in the light of song. So is hypocrisy inextricably linked to democracy, or is that just a handy rhyme for songwriters? Promises in songs could also be in the context of love, friendship, family, greed, or record contracts, or, on the flip side, gratitude for faith and loyalty when oaths are kept rather than broken. But let’s face it, it’s the broken promise that more likely inspires a song, and with this comes a side-dish subject of choice – as to whether to accept or reject that promise and its consequences and what to do about it.</p>
    <p>Your own choices of songs, however, might also refer to some of the many dubious promises made by politicians of the past, perhaps in the last 50 years or so, and here are some of the biggest howlers. In his 1968 campaign, Richard Nixon promised that the “new leadership will end the war”, but having come to power, the Vietnam conflict wasn’t ended until 1973. His term of office ended sank with the Watergate scandal a year later. Before being elected in 1988, George HW Bush famously said: “Read my lips: No new taxes.” You’ll never guess what he did next. In 1994 the now notorious “bunga-bunga” Italian media tycoon and later three-times prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> promised to sell his TV networks and advertising assets if he came to power – on a promise it would end a conflict of interests. Did he give up his powerful monopoly Italian TV? No. He remains Mediaset’s controlling shareholder.</p>
    <p>And so to the present UK government. I’ll do my best and promise to be neutral on this. Some 2010 Conservative promises first: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2010/may/14/cameron-wants-greenest-government-ever">“The greenest government ever</ref>.” So then, what happened? Frack that! - perhaps? “<ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/election-2010/7625873/General-Election-2010-Cameron-dismisses-claim-Tories-would-put-up-VAT.html">We have absolutely no plans to raise VAT,</ref>” added David Cameron, with value. Perhaps then it was a slight misunderstanding that VAT was immediately increased by George “we’re all in this together” Osborne in his first budget? “<ref target="http://www.newstatesman.com/blogs/the-staggers/2011/01/ema-cameron-rid-plans-january">We don’t have any plans to get rid of education maintenance allowance.</ref>” Was it possible that this also got accidentally left behind, a bit like <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2012/jun/11/david-cameron-daughter-behind-pub">Cameron’s daughter in the pub</ref>? “There will be no more of those pointless reorganisations that aim for change but instead bring chaos. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/sep/24/david-cameron-faces-day-reckoning-nhs-labour">There will be no top-down reorganisation of the NHS</ref>.” Ooops. The disastrous health and social care bill, anyone? And, last but not least, deputy PM Nick Clegg’s famous pledge to “<ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jTLR8R9JXz4">Say goodbye to broken promises</ref>” and that “We will not raise tuition fees.” So how about <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/nov/19/nick-clegg-raising-tuition-fees-not-deterred-poor">tripling them</ref>? There’s a lesson for the voter, perhaps. Well at least he at least appeared to look <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/video/2012/sep/20/nick-clegg-apology-tuition-fees-video">sorry</ref>.</p>
    <p>But what of main challenger and Labour leader Ed Miliband, vilified by so much of a heavily <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2015/may/06/sun-ed-miliband-labour-mail-telegraph-election">rightwing, paranoid UK press</ref>? He hasn’t had his chance as PM yet, so time can only tell a man of promise can only ever become a man of promises. And as for me, I’m breaking my promise on neutrality. I recommend kicking this coalition government out by any means possible. Sounds like the title of a song …</p>
    <p>Readers Recommend, I now remind myself, is all about the music, so let us examine what our promise-making main party leaders have, in the context of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2013/nov/24/ed-miliband-desert-island-discs1">BBC4’s Desert Island Discs</ref>, chosen, or at least their advisers have chosen for them. Cameron picked, in a rather self-congratulatory way This Charming Man by the Smiths, only for guitarist <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2010/dec/03/johnny-marr-david-cameron-twitter">Johnny Marr, with proper angry northern disdain, to bar the PM from any future association with his work</ref>. Cameron also chose Bob Dylan’s Tangled Up in Blue. What? As in the Conservative colour? Are you kidding? Miliband’s choices were a little more eccentric, perhaps more about hope and ambition, and included Aha’s Take On Me and Edith Piaf’s Je Ne Regrette Rien.</p>
    <p>Could there have been better choices? To join some election fun, I now break another promise not to recommend any particular songs, and offer some starter suggestions of my own for some key candidates. Please add your own, either in the context of promises, or at anytime later in the thread and feel free to nick these ideas too.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">David Cameron and George Osborne - Conservative</hi><lb/> All Men Are Liars - Nick Lowe<lb/> (We’re All In This) Together Now - The Farm<lb/> The Final Cut - Pink Floyd<lb/> The Eton Rifles - The Jam<lb/> Paper Cuts - Nirvana<lb/> In Da (Bullingdon) Club - 50Cent / McBusted<lb/> Cuts Like A Knife - Bryan Adams<lb/> Mansion Tax on the Hill - Bruce Springsteen<lb/> You Never Give Me Your Money - Beatles</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Nick Clegg - Liberal Democrat</hi><lb/> Turn Your Love/Policy Around - George Benson<lb/> Stuck in the Middle With You - Stealers Wheel<lb/> Don’t Turn Around - Aswad<lb/> Dance Little Liar - Arctic Monkeys<lb/> Who’s Sorry Now - Connie Francis</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Ed Miliband - Labour</hi><lb/> Highway to Hell, Yes! - AC/DC<lb/> Joy of Labour - Motorhead</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Natalie Bennett - Green party</hi><lb/> Green Grass and High Tides - The Outlaws<lb/> I Forgot to Remember to Forget - Elvis Presley</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Nicola Sturgeon - SNP</hi><lb/> Miss Independent - Kelly Clarkson<lb/> Anarchy in the UK - Sex Pistols<lb/> I Want to Break Free - Queen<lb/> Close to the Ed - Yes</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Nigel Farage - Ukip</hi><lb/> Making Plans for Nigel - XTC<lb/> Borderline - Madonna<lb/> The Immigrant Song - Led Zeppelin<lb/> City of Immigrants - Steve Earle<lb/> Beer Money - Kip Moore<lb/> Idiot Wind - Bob Dylan</p>
    <p>So then, this week’s pollster of enormous promise, but also guaranteed delivery, is RR’s very own returning officer <ref target="https://id.theguardian.com/profile/bluepeter/public">bluepeter</ref>, who will sort of the genuine from the duplicitous, and create a final list from your song suggestions <hi rend="#b">next Thursday 14 May</hi>. Please place your songs in the ballot box of comments below and optionally in Spotify, for the results. <hi rend="#b">Polling booths close at 11pm (UK BST) this Monday 11 May.</hi> Get voting!</p>
    <p>To increase the likelihood of your nomination being considered, please:</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>