<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Does Silvio Berlusconi secretly have it in for Tony Blair? | Alexander Chancellor" author="Alexander Chancellor" date="2009-10-15" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/oct/16/alexander-chancellor-berlusconi-blair" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alexander Chancellor: How odd that the Italian prime minister may just have inadvertently derailed his great friend's bid to be EU president" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Tony Blair,Panto season,World news,Politics,Stage,European Union" fingerprint="634fd3779a075cc9">
  <main>
    <p>Does <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> harbour some secret hatred of Tony Blair? He claims to regard him as a tremendous friend, but this hasn't stopped him delivering a potentially killer blow to our former prime minister's ambition to become the first president of the European Union. As Blair sidles furtively towards his goal, the last thing he needs is Berlusconi's public endorsement. Berlusconi is not only widely despised among the other European leaders who will, if the Lisbon treaty is ratified, decide whether or not to give Blair the job; he is also increasingly friendless at home.</p>
    <p>An opinion poll published in Rome yesterday showed that the sex and corruption scandals that have engulfed him are finally taking their toll. Trust in Berlusconi as prime minister has fallen to its lowest ever level – to 45% from 62% a year ago. The leftwing opposition, thanks to its dismal leadership, still lags a little behind Berlusconi's rightwing governing coalition; but the spell that Berlusconi has cast for so long over the Italian electorate with his vast wealth and media power seems at last to be breaking.</p>
    <p>His reaction to the constitutional court's decision to lift his immunity from prosecution may have something to do with this, for it was that of a ranting tin-pot dictator, of a man lacking all respect for the institutions of the state. Screaming accusations of political bias at the constitutional court, he appealed to the supposedly higher authority of the "people" who had elected him, ending with the now notorious cry: "Viva l'Italia! Viva Berlusconi!" Even those Italians who had come to accept him as the father of his people must have found this performance a little scary and undignified.</p>
    <p>This is the same man who wrote a letter this week in support of Blair's EU candidacy to a small rightwing newspaper called Il Foglio whose main shareholder is, curiously, Berlusconi's wife Veronica Lario, who is divorcing him because of his alleged affection for underage girls. Il Foglio is conducting a campaign to have Blair made EU president, and Berlusconi weighed in with a letter saying that Blair has "all the right credentials" for the job and would bring to it "a great political legacy made up of courage, steadiness, and prudence, always shown without indecision". The newspaper, in its own editorial, was even more gushing. It said that Blair had both "revitalised the international left and become a model for the most modern right", and was the "ideal" candidate – "a figure of great international standing, able to warm our hearts and to earn respect both within and outside the boundaries of Europe".</p>
    <p>This codswallop only serves to remind us how inappropriate Blair's appointment would be. He has none of "the right credentials"; for instead of keeping his promise to put Britain "at the heart of Europe", he distanced it from France and Germany by joining the Americans in the invasion of Iraq and made Britain the only important European country to stay out of the euro. And what is all this about him "revitalising the international left" when there has not been a squeak of support for his candidacy from Europe's leftwing parties (hardly surprising, when he did nothing to roll back the legacy of Margaret Thatcher)? The European presidency will not be a powerful office; to achieve anything, its holder would need to be a person of modesty and humility, working behind the scenes. That wouldn't suit Blair, so one must hope that Berlusconi's intervention, by infuriating Angela Merkel in particular, will have inflicted fatal damage on his candidacy.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Mickey Rooney and me</hi>
    </p>
    <p>I was barely aware that Mickey <hi rend="#b"/>Rooney<hi rend="#b"/>was still alive, let alone kicking, until I got an email this week from the Milton Keynes Theatre announcing that he would be hoofing it on the stage in its Christmas pantomime. That was surprising not only because Rooney is 89 and perhaps deserving of something better than being in Milton Keynes in December; but also because he really is a Hollywood legend, had a famous 1930s film partnership with Judy Garland, and might therefore feel it a little beneath him to play Baron Hardup in Cinderella, with Anthea Turner as the Fairy Godmother.</p>
    <p>A glance at his website shows that he simply cannot bear to be off the stage. He has a touring revue called Let's Put on a Show! that has just made a tour of Ontario. He stars in it with his eighth – yes, eighth – wife Jan (Ava Gardner was his first). His "personal motto", the website says, is "Don't retire! Inspire!" I don't think I'll make it to Cinderella, because I don't believe I would be inspired. I'd be more likely to think how sad it was that some people who had spent all their lives in the limelight could not bear to be without it.</p>
    <p>I did once meet Rooney. It was on the eve of President Clinton's first inauguration, 16 years ago, at a party in Washington given for his mother, Virginia Kelley, the first mom-elect. She wanted someone to sing her favourite song, Billy Joel's Just the Way You Are, and I asked Rooney if he would do it. He agreed, but then limited himself to plucking the inside of his mouth with a finger and making funny faces while somebody played the tune on a piano. I don't feel this bodes well for his performance in Cinderella.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>