<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roy Greenslade: Italian law will stop reporting of criminal cases" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2010-05-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2010/may/28/press-freedom-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian journalists are said to be united in anger at a draft law aimed at banning the media from reporting on criminal investigations before they come to trial, despite the fact that most cases take years to reach court" categories="Media" tags="Media,Press freedom,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="db5291261c008815">
  <main>
    <p>Italian journalists are said to be united in anger at a draft law aimed at banning the media from reporting on criminal investigations before they come to trial, despite the fact that most cases take years to reach court.</p>
    <p>The draft bill outlines penalties of more than €450,000 for publishers and up to €20,000 for journalists who flout the ban. Anyone who records or films without the approval of the person who is being recorded or filmed may also be jailed.</p>
    <p>Only "professional journalists" (journalists belonging to the Italian National Order of Journalists) would be allowed to record and film individuals without previous authorisation.</p>
    <p>The bill is due to go before Italy's full upper house of parliament next week. It follows soon after newspapers ran leaked transcripts from a graft investigation into public works contracts that have cast a shadow over <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi's</hi> government.</p>
    <p>"It is shocking and disturbing that in a democratic country such as Italy the government is proposing a law that is a blatant slap in the face to free journalism and the public's right to know," said the <ref target="http://www.freemedia.at/">International Press Institute's </ref> director <hi rend="#b">David Dadge</hi>.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Source:</hi>
      <ref target="http://www.freemedia.at/singleview/4964/">IPI</ref>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>