<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi trial: testimony of Tessa Jowell's husband delayed" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2011/nov/28/silvio-berlusconi-tessa-jowell-husband" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Lawyers and judges in London and Milan debate whether – and how – David Mills should give evidence in the bribery case" categories="UK news" tags="David Mills,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,UK news,World news,Europe" fingerprint="fe2f8b0d1ca156d3">
  <main>
    <p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the former Labour cabinet minister Tessa Jowell, sat in a London court on Monday as lawyers and judges wrangled over a video link to Italy about whether – and, if so, how – he should give evidence to a court trying <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> for allegedly bribing him.</p>
    <p>Mills said he would travel to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to give evidence, but only if he knew what evidence was expected of him. James Hines, representing the former Italian prime minister at Westminster magistrates court, said Mills "shouldn't be ambushed, and the prosecution should set out its case from the outset".</p>
    <p>That highlighted a difference in court practice between the two countries and provoked a riposte from the presiding judge in Milan. Francesca Vitali said: "There are no such things as expected replies from a witness, whose sole duty is that of replying truthfully."</p>
    <p>In Milan, Berlusconi's counsel, Nicolo Ghedini, complained that the Italian prosecutors had last month sent 255 documents to London, asking that Mills not be informed of their contents. But Vitali said Mills could not "study non-spontaneous replies. That is the purpose of the immediacy of testimony, without knowledge of the documents."</p>
    <p>The discussions were translated by a single interpreter who, at one point after the video feed broke down, was overwhelmed by a clash of voices in Milan.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who attended the proceedings in Milan, said during a recess: "I had difficulty not falling asleep."</p>
    <p>Mills, who set up a web of offshore companies for Berlusconi, was tried in Italy on charges of accepting a $600,000 bribe from his former client to perjure himself by omission. He was found guilty in 2009, and his appeal was rejected.</p>
    <p>Last year, Italy's highest appeals court quashed his conviction. But the judges, in their written ruling, said they had done so because the case had been "timed out" by a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>After Italy's constitutional court threw out crucial parts of a law passed by Berlusconi's government that shielded him from prosecution, the media tycoon was put back on trial, accused of giving Mills the alleged bribe. Berlusconi has repeatedly denied the charge, arguing he is the victim of a witch-hunt by politically inspired prosecutors.</p>
    <p>Mills told the court on Monday: "There are certain circumstances which I would be willing to go to Italy, but I am not sure what evidence I would be expected to give." His counsel, James Lewis QC, applied for the hearing to be adjourned until the Italian prosecutor explained what evidence his client would be asked for.</p>
    <p>"It is not at an investigation stage of the proceedings but it is a trial," he told the Italian judges. "Mr Mills is to be treated as a witness and he must know what evidence the public prosecutor believes he will give to your court."</p>
    <p>In Milan, the proceedings were further complicated when Mills's counsel argued that his client should be given special guarantees to be heard as a defendant in connected cases – a status that would give him the right not to answer questions. Two other charges against the British lawyer in Italy have been declared timed out, but their formal status is unresolved.</p>
    <p>The hearing was adjourned in Milan until 19 December, when a decision will be taken on the way in which Mills can give his evidence.</p>
    <p>Mills was originally called to appear at Westminster magistrates court on 28 October and a TV link was set up with Milan. But Berlusconi obtained an adjournment by insisting on his right to be present at the trial hearings and then citing his duties as prime minister as a reason for being unable to attend. His trial is due to be timed out early next year.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>