<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roy Greenslade: Murdoch on how he plans to charge for online access" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2009-07-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2009/jul/06/rupert-murdoch-new-york-times" hostname="theguardian.com" description="More proof that Rupert Murdoch is still agonising over how to charge for access to his media websites. In a phone interview last week with TheStreet.com, he was asked whether micropayments are a workable model for selling news online. He replied:" categories="Media" tags="Rupert Murdoch,New York Times,Myspace,Google,X,Silvio Berlusconi,Media,Social media" fingerprint="eda3191f215625ee">
  <main>
    <p>More proof that <hi rend="#b">Rupert Murdoch</hi> is still agonising over how to charge for access to his media websites. <ref target="http://www.thestreet.com/story/10532921/1/murdoch-talks-media.html">In a phone interview last week with TheStreet.com</ref>, he was asked whether micropayments are a workable model for selling news online. He replied:</p>
    <quote><p>"I don't think people will pay for it. We're still thinking our way through this and there will be micropayments as part of it, but I'm thinking much more along the lines of subscriptions like the</p><hi>Wall Street Journal</hi>does."</quote>
    <p><lb/> During the interview he denied that he was interested in buying the <hi rend="#b">The New York Times</hi>. "I haven't even thought about it," he said. "But I would imagine that it would be legally and politically almost impossible, so I'm not thinking about it."</p>
    <p>On <hi rend="#b">MySpace</hi>, he was asked: Why are you shutting down your global ambitions?</p>
    <quote>
      <p>"We're not. We're just getting first things right first. The business sort of grew out of control and really out of size. I blame myself and it had to be brought back in size, but we feel that we've got new creative people and it will be a very strong force in many ways."</p>
    </quote>
    <p>On <hi rend="#b">Google</hi>: "We'll be more outspoken on the whole issue of payment for copyright material and that goes to every aggregator… there are billions of dollars spent, probably every month, but certainly every year in the collection and the creation of copyright by organisations and they cannot do that and have that material which they own stolen from them or the business will be destroyed."</p>
    <p>On <hi rend="#b">Twitter</hi>: "It's an amazing phenomenon but I have no idea how they can monetize it. No one monetises the web today to any extent other than search."</p>
    <p>On <hi rend="#b"> Silvio Berlusconi</hi> (who has accused Murdoch of using his newspapers to make personal attacks on him): No comment.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>