<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Draquila: the film Berlusconi doesn't want you to see" author="Agnès Poirier" date="2010-05-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2010/may/19/draquila-silvio-berlusconi-film-cannes" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Agnès Poirier: A documentary film shown at Cannes has used the L'Aquila earthquake to expose the Italian prime minister's abuse of power" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Cannes film festival,Freedom of speech,Censorship,Film,World news,Cannes 2010,Earthquakes" fingerprint="7db41aadd365bd48">
  <main>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2010/may/16/peter-bradshaw-cannes-round-up">Draquila: Italy trembles</ref>, the latest documentary by the Italian satirist Sabina Guzzanti, has caused controversy ever since its selection at the Cannes film festival was confirmed. A few weeks ago, Sandro Bondi, Silvio Berlusconi's culture minister, said he <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/13/world/europe/13rome.html">wouldn't come</ref> to Cannes as a protest. An outspoken critic of Berlusconi's regime, Guzzanti was the author, in 2005, of an incendiary documentary called <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viva_Zapatero!">Viva Zapatero!</ref>, which ventured to show Berlusconi's control of state media and its daily censorship.</p>
    <p>A la Michael Moore, Guzzanti opens Draquila – a pun on Dracula and L'Aquila – with a cartoonesque introduction: "Era pena iniziata la primavera nella bella peninsula e per Silvio Berlusconi era una giornata de merda, come tante altre" – "Spring had just begun in the beautiful peninsula, and for Silvio Berlusconi it was just another shitty day" (see the trailer <ref target="http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xdai8w_cannes-trailer-draquila-trembling-i_news">here</ref>). Another shitty day made of <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article6550609.ece">various sex scandals</ref> and judges' attempts at cornering him for alleged abuses of power.</p>
    <p>However, on 6 April 2009, Italy woke up with the news of a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/07/laquila-italy-earthquake">severe earthquake</ref> in the Abruzzo region, which killed more than 300 people and affected the lives of 70,000 inhabitants of L'Aquila, one of Italy's historic and artistic centres. An opportunity Berlusconi wasn't going to pass, says Guzzanti. Like Zorro, Berlusconi hurried to L'Aquila. He is seen hugging children and kissing grandmothers, and promising on a news programme "a new home before the autumn, completely furnished with a cake on the table and a bottle of champagne in the fridge".</p>
    <p>L'Aquila's inhabitants were swiftly placed in hotels or in <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/5262449/Italy-earthquake-LAquila-one-month-on.html">tent cities</ref> guarded by the army, and waited for Berlusconi's masons to build a new city. Guzzanti interviews some inhabitants who weren't allowed to go back to their homes – even those whose homes had been left unscarred by the earthquake. In the film, we see the mayor of L'Aquila walk alone, at night, in his ghost city, passing a church whose Renaissance masterpieces, cracked and stained, have been left waiting and decaying.</p>
    <p>Even more importantly, the film shows how the civil protection agency has been given full powers to oversee the reconstruction. Guzzanti shows how the agency is run by Guido Bertolaso (who has himself <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/21/italy-sex-bribes-berlusconi-elections">faced an investigation</ref> for alleged corruption) and alleges that he gave out <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/21/italy-sex-bribes-berlusconi-elections">building contracts to private companies</ref> of his choice. Thanks to a series of decrees, Berlusconi is said to have empowered the agency to make decisions in cases of national emergency and any "big events", which temporarily override existing laws – not only does the agency intervene when there's been an earthquake, but also whenever the pope visits a city or when <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/4eba8690-625b-11df-991f-00144feab49a.html">national sport games are organised</ref>.</p>
    <p>"Where is the opposition? Where are the journalists?" we ask ourselves. According to Guzzanti, nowhere to be seen – or rather <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/773fe27a-306c-11df-bc4a-00144feabdc0.html">unable to make themselves heard</ref> or to report the facts. At the end of the film, an old Italian man is seen telling the camera: "After the earthquake, had I been 25, I would probably have left. Then, I thought that the dictatorship we're living under is not a dictatorship of terror or of torture. It is just a shitty dictatorship." <ref target="http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gOuHoi1EgtXK3ih9DJgCwfkH4Shg">For Guzzanti</ref> "the movie is a reflection on the <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/faith/article6111316.ece">authoritarian drift</ref> in this country".</p>
    <p>Draquila is the Italian film Berlusconi doesn't want you to see. All the more reasons to go and see it as soon as it hits the screen or reaches a DVD shop near you.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>