<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="So it's Sarah Brown v Samantha Cameron | Alexander Chancellor" author="Alexander Chancellor" date="2010-03-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/mar/12/alexander-chancellor-sarah-brown-samantha-cameron" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alexander Chancellor: Will the leaders' wives really bring their husbands electoral popularity? I'm not so sure" categories="Opinion" tags="Samantha Cameron,Sarah Brown,Gordon Brown,David Cameron,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,World news" fingerprint="a629937db912d269">
  <main>
    <p>So now <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/samantha-cameron">Samantha Cameron</ref> is to be let off the leash – or maybe dragged unwillingly out of the kennel – to play her part in the election race. "You are going to see a lot more of her on the campaign trail," her husband told Alan Titchmarsh in a television interview on Wednesday, "so Britain get ready!" It was nice of David to warn us, but he really didn't need to. It always seemed probable that the engaging Mrs Cameron would at some stage be press-ganged into political service; but as her husband's lead in the polls began to shrink and the prospect of a hung parliament (or even, God forbid, of another Labour victory) started to loom ominously on the horizon, it became inevitable.</p>
    <p>David Cameron must realise that his personal appeal to the electorate is in decline. Even his charm has begun to arouse suspicion. Could it be masking the fact that he is actually no more than a clever smoothie on the make? Could he be just a cynical "Tory boy" at heart? He knows he needs "humanising", and the only person in a position to do this plausibly is his wife. Sarah Brown has shown the way by seeking to persuade the public that her dour husband is not just consumed by personal ambition, but is a warm-hearted, high-principled old buffer. "I know he's not a saint," she told the Labour party conference last autumn. "He's messy. He's noisy. He gets up at a terrible hour. But I know he wakes up every morning and goes to bed every evening, thinking about the things that matter. I know he loves our country."</p>
    <p>Asked by Titchmarsh to give a description of himself, Cameron said he was a "young guy" who was passionate about his country, cared for his family, and was relaxed, normal and reasonable (unlike <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/gordon-brown">Gordon Brown</ref>, by implication). Samantha's job will be to convince people that David is not only young, relaxed etc, but also a steadfast man of character, as in Sarah Brown's depiction of her husband. And her first attempt to do so will be made this Sunday, when she is to be interviewed on television for the first time during an hour-long profile of the Tory leader by Sir Trevor McDonald. In one sentence leaked in advance, she speaks of their 18-year relationship and says: "I can honestly say that I don't think in all that time he has ever let me down." That is a rather puzzling claim, but its implication is presumably that he would never let the British people down either.</p>
    <p>While <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/sarah-brown">Sarah Brown</ref> and Samantha Cameron are both likeable women and potentially more popular than their husbands, it is questionable how useful their support will actually turn out to be. It may well suggest to the public a lack of self-confidence by a party leader to make his wife campaign on his behalf. None of our most successful prime ministers – Winston Churchill, Clement Attlee, Harold Macmillan, Margaret Thatcher, even Tony Blair – have resorted to this tactic. And while Sarah Brown's professed hero-worship of Gordon may have made an impression on the public, he would appear to have benefited even more from Andrew Rawnsley's claims that he bullies his Downing Street staff. This suggested a man of rugged, independent spirit, and Brown himself has tried to build on this idea by saying in a speech this week that the test of a leader was "whether you have a clear idea of what you want to do, whether you are determined to push that through, and whether you are sufficiently impatient and strong-willed to push aside the barriers that stand in your way". Rawnsley may have done more to narrow Cameron's lead over Brown than any of Sarah's talk of his lovability. People don't necessarily want their leaders to be lovable. Margaret Thatcher was never thought lovable, but that didn't stop her winning election after election.</p>
    <p>There is no sign yet that Nick Clegg, the leader of the Liberal Democrats, will seek to exploit his wife Miriam in this way, which is perhaps not surprising, given that she is both Spanish and a Roman Catholic. But it may all the same work to his advantage in the election that he, alone among the main party leaders, won't seem to rely on the endorsement of a spouse to commend himself to the electorate. In this respect Clegg, who has Dutch and Russian ancestry, is more typical of continental politicians, for they don't feel the need to enlist the political support of their wives. Of course, if you were <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, you wouldn't want to, since his wife Veronica Lario is divorcing him because of what she has called his tendency to "consort with minors". Similarly, you wouldn't really expect Nicolas Sarkozy to rely on the advocacy of Carla Bruni, who even now won't confirm that her marriage to the French president is "for ever".</p>
    <p>Sarkozy has a habit of marrying beautiful but independent-minded women, not the sort that a politician would necessarily invoke as witnesses to his solid, bourgeois virtues. But he probably regards the fact that such women are drawn to him as in itself an electoral asset. Berlusconi also hopes that his interest in young women will be both understood and approved by Italian voters, and the indications are that he is probably right. I wonder how British voters would react to an openly philandering party leader. It is just conceivable that they would respect him for his honesty.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>