<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Has Berlusconi turned prudish? TV channel slams Venice for racy films" author="Ben Child" date="2012-08-21" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2012/aug/21/berlusconi-prudish-venice-film-festival" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Entire film festival should be rated 18, says news bulletin on network owned by disgraced former PM" categories="Film" tags="Venice film festival 2012,Venice film festival,Film,Culture,Festivals,Awards and prizes,Terrence Malick,Paul Thomas Anderson,Silvio Berlusconi,Harmony Korine,Italy" fingerprint="f2e2cc3d99a7dbb5">
  <main>
    <p>An Italian news bulletin on a network owned by disgraced former prime minister Silvio Berluconi has chided the Venice film festival for putting on its <ref target="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/venice-festival-rating-italian-news-program-364044">raciest lineup</ref> in many years.</p>
    <p>TG 24 said the entire event would benefit from an adults-only rating – though its diatribe is thought to be at least partially tongue-in-cheek – due to a programme of "sapphic sex, violence and religion". This year's lineup, which runs from 29 August to 8 September, with Alberto Barbera taking on organising duties for the second time, includes potentially controversial celluloid from Terrence Malick, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/paul-thomas-anderson">Paul Thomas Anderson</ref>, Harmony Korine, Brian DePalma and Marco Bellocchio.</p>
    <p>TG, the main news programme on one of the three channels owned by Silvio Berlusconi, described <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1595656/">To The Wonder</ref>, Mallick's forthcoming romantic drama starring <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/benaffleck">Ben Affleck</ref>, Olga Kurylenko, Rachel McAdams, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/rachel-weisz?INTCMP=SRCH">Rachel Weisz</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/javierbardem?INTCMP=SRCH">Javier Bardem</ref>, as a film which was unsuitable for young people due to a high degree of sex and nudity. Korine's <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2101441/">Spring Breakers</ref>, it said, was full of "sexual transgression", while DePalma's <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1829012/">Passion</ref> was described as centring on a dark sexual relationship between a "cynical businesswoman" played by Rachel McAdams and her "sweet assistant" portrayed by Noomi Rapace. Anderson's <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1560747/">The Master</ref>, already under the spotlight because its storyline hints at the history of Scientology, was also highlighted, as was Bellochio's <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2184227/">Bella Addormentata</ref> (Sleeping Beauty), a drama set during the final six days of Eluana Englaro, a young woman who lived for 17 years in a vegetative state. The latter film stars <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/isabelle-huppert?INTCMP=SRCH">Isabelle Huppert</ref>, Tony Servillo and Alba Rohrwacher.</p>
    <p>All of the above are competing for the festival's top prize, the Golden Lion. Barbera, who took over from Marco Mueller in a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2011/dec/28/venice-film-festival-alberto-barbera">surprise move in December</ref>, said last month that the opening night film would be Mira Nair's <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2032557/">The Reluctant Fundamentalist</ref>. The closing night film was previously confirmed as <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1946289/">L'Homme Qui Rit</ref> by Jean Pierre Ameris.</p>
    <p>The festival's new director said in May that this year's 69th edition would be a "more sober" event than previous iterations. It has been slimmed down to fewer than 50 films in total, with just 18 in competition. "We're starting a change in Venice's skin, in which within two or three years we will have a nice rebirth," Barbera told Italian journalists. "The festival is like a grand old lady, a refined lady, but one in need of being freshened up. I believe a festival should take responsibility for its choice, and not to simply select dozens and dozens of titles."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi himself has been the subject of a series of salacious stories during the past couple of years, including <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/16/silvio-berlusconi-trial-imane-fadil">suggestions that he took part in "bunga bunga" sex parties</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/20/silvio-berlusconi-surprise-visit-trial">paid an under-age girl for sex</ref>. The former politician and media magnate stepped down as prime minister in November 2011 but recently hinted that he would seek re-election for a fourth time in 2013. He is awaiting trial on a number of charges relating to the sex scandals.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, LoveFilm has revealed that British cineastes are developing an increased appetite for "saucy" fare in the wake of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/books/fifty-shades-of-grey">Fifty Shades of Grey</ref> publishing phenomenon. The DVD rental and film streaming service says viewing figures for salacious movies have leapt by 55% since the explosion in popularity of EL James's erotic knee-trembler, which last month became the country's bestselling book of all time with 5.3m copies sold.</p>
    <p>The news bodes well for the novel's forthcoming big screen adaptation, which is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2012/jul/10/fifty-shades-grey-film-social-network">being put together</ref> by the producers of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/movie/137709/social-network">The Social Network</ref>, Michael De Luca and Dana Brunetti. Studio Universal plans a trilogy based on the novel and its two sequels.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>