<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Barack Obama, you used to say that we had a special relationship" author="Michael White" date="2011-05-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/29/barack-obama-uk-special-relationship" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Now that the American-British bond is 'essential', just imagine how the US president would descibe other nations" categories="US news" tags="Barack Obama,Silvio Berlusconi,Dmitry Medvedev,Nicolas Sarkozy,China,Mexico,France,Ireland,Canada,Israel,Italy,Americas,Asia Pacific" fingerprint="9154bfd21d121f5">
  <main>
    <p>So, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/barack-obama">Barack Obama</ref> is two-timing us Brits again. Only last Wednesday he was shamelessly flattering us as if we were his favourite auntie. No cliche about Anglo-American relationships was too corny to be overlooked; our relationship was more than just "special", it was "essential". Just how special is that?</p>
    <p>But that was days ago. Next came France, for the G8 summit, and he had other people to butter up. Russian president Dmitry Medvedev, for example. Obviously Obama couldn't bang on about shared values and the rule of law because the Kremlin has been a consistent source of autocratic rule since Moscow princes got ideas above their station and started calling themselves Caesar – or czar. But "<ref target="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2011/05/26/medvedev-uncorks-stunner-russia-missile-defense-shield/">outstanding</ref>" – as the Russian-American relationship was characterised – that's a suitably ambiguous adjective. And for the visit to Ireland, the White House lexicon came up with the "<ref target="http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0523/breaking1.html">enduring</ref>" relationship, which is certainly true genetically – given the ever-expanding number of Americans who claim to be Irish.But who are we to complain? It's a big world and everyone wants a White House adjective to copyright. How about a few more?</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b"> The on-off relationship</hi> That would be <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref>. It helped the US win independence from You Know Who but has been rescued so often since then that it needs to show ingratitude. Being shorter than De Gaulle, Sarko is sucking up. It won't last.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b"> The open relationship</hi> That must be <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/canada">Canada</ref>. Nuff said.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b"> The failed relationship</hi><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mexico">Mexico</ref>, perhaps, after the drugs and migrant battles. "Poor Mexico, so far from God, so close to the US," as one Mexican dictator put it.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b"> The loving relationship</hi> If it can't be <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ireland">Ireland</ref>, it must be Italy, which has better food.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>