<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi faces new questions over relationship with model Noemi Letizia" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-05-24" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/24/silvio-berlusconi-noemi-letizia-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's prime minister insists relationship with 18-year-old is a private matter after growing pressure from opposition" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="57da432d99d6d755">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> faced new questions yesterday about his relationship with Noemi Letizia, 18, after claims that he flew the aspiring model to his Sardinian villa for New Year's Eve after seeing her modelling portfolio.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has previously said that he knows Letizia through her parents, who he has described as old friends.</p>
    <p>But Letizia's former boyfriend, Gino Flaminio, 22, told La Repubblica newspaper yesterday that "Noemi's parents have nothing to do with this, the link was just with her". Letizia's father challenged his version of events as "gravely defamatory, because it attributes to Noemi things that have never been done, said or thought," and said he would take legal action.</p>
    <p>After Berlusconi was photographed last month attending Letizia's 18th birthday party outside Naples, his wife said she intended to divorce him, accusing him of "frequenting minors".</p>
    <p>Flaminio claimed yesterday that the prime minister had been passed Letizia's photographs by Emilio Fede, a newsreader on one of his television channels.</p>
    <p>Flaminio claimed that Berlusconi tele–phoned Letizia on numerous occasions, complimenting her on her "angelic face", and developing a "father-daughter like relationship" with her, before flying her on a private jet to his Sardinian villa over the New Year period, where she joined "30 to 40" other young female guests who were put up in bungalows.</p>
    <p>Flaminio said he split up with Letizia shortly after her return from Sardinia.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has insisted that his relationship with Letizia is a private matter, but Dario Franceschini, leader of the opposition Democratic Party, called on him to respond to questions. "It is not possible that the free press continues to ask questions, continues to show where he has lied and he continues to stay silent," he said.</p>
    <p>The cabinet undersecretary, Paolo Bonaiuti, replied that Franceschini was "clinging on to gossip", fearing defeat by Berlusconi's governing coalition in forthcoming European elections.</p>
    <p>On Saturday, Berlusconi said he was "tempted" to brief parliament about Letizia, but needed to reflect on it first.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>