<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="David Mills could escape jail over Silvio Berlusconi bribe case" author="John Hooper" date="2010-02-25" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/25/david-mills-berlusconi-bribe-timed-out" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian corruption charges against British lawyer subject to statute of limitations, says prosecutor" categories="World news" tags="Italy,David Mills,Silvio Berlusconi,Tessa Jowell,World news,Europe" fingerprint="4ab20a0751b916db">
  <main>
    <p>In a dramatic about-turn, the representative of the prosecution in the final appeal by Tessa Jowell's estranged husband, David Mills, against his conviction for corruption in Italy yesterday asked for the case to be "timed out".</p>
    <p>Gianfranco Ciani, the assistant chief prosecutor of Italy's top appeals court, told a hearing in Rome that in his opinion the charges against Mills were already subject to a statute of limitations. But he added: "There are not the grounds for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/david-mills">David Mills</ref> to be acquitted on the facts of the case." And, without an acquittal, the British lawyer faces having to pay up to €250,000 (£220,000) to the Italian state in compensation.</p>
    <p>The judges of the Court of Cassation can decide to ignore the prosecutor's argument, but his plea made it more likely that the four-and-a-half-year prison sentence imposed on Mills would not be upheld. The British lawyer was initially convicted last year of taking a $600,000 bribe from Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>The court is expected to give its verdict later today. A key issue in the appeal, which will be settled on points of law, is the exact moment at which the alleged crime was committed. That will determine whether the case is already subject to a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>The prosecutors who brought the case argued successfully in two lower courts that the key date was the moment at which Mills entered into possession of the money. But there was disagreement between the two sides over whether that was in February 2000 or November 1999.</p>
    <p>The prosecutor in the Court of Cassation, unlike his colleagues at the earlier hearings, said he believed the offence had been committed "at the latest on 11 November 1999". Berlusconi's trial for allegedly giving the bribe, which was due to resume on Saturday, may well be called off as a result of today's move.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>