<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi barracked as video shows women being ushered into house" author="Tom Kington" date="2010-11-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/10/silvio-berlusconi-women-video" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Magazine scoop further strains Italian prime minister after his party loses three votes in parliament" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Media" fingerprint="7eb5d0a492a7f345">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi was today under renewed pressure after he was barracked in public and his party outvoted in parliament as a new video emerged appearing to show miniskirted women being ushered into one of his properties.</p>
    <p>Already reeling from revelations that he had entertained Karimael Mahroug, a 17-year-old Moroccan belly dancer before intervening to free her when she was arrested on suspicion of theft, the Italian prime minister was accused of hosting a Cuban model and a Romanian reality TV star at his mansion near Milan.</p>
    <p>The Oggi gossip magazine posted video footage, shot in July, of the celebrity agent Lele Mora allegedly helping the women into a car with tinted windows at his Milan office before driving them into the grounds of Berlusconi's property without stopping at a police checkpoint at the gate.</p>
    <p>Mora is already being investigated on suspicion of aiding and abetting prostitution.</p>
    <p>Opposition politicians argued that Berlusconi was making himself an easy blackmail target. "There is a certain ease with which women who admit to being involved in prostitution gain access to the prime minister's residence," Luigi de Magistris, of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Values party, said.</p>
    <p>"It is clear that this makes Berlusconi a potential blackmail victim, and that puts national security at risk."</p>
    <p>Massimo D'Alema, the head of the parliamentary security committee, again demanded today that Berlusconi inform the committee about his security arrangements.</p>
    <p>The prime minister also came under fire as a magistrate involved in handling the case of the belly dancer contradicted Berlusconi's claim that he had not pressured police into freeing her.</p>
    <p>Annamaria Fiorillo said legality and justice had been "trampled" on.</p>
    <p>Renewed focus on Berlusconi's private life came as his parliamentary group was outvoted three times on amendments to an immigration treaty with Libya as followers of his former ally Gianfranco Fini voted with the opposition.</p>
    <p>Fini, who defected from Berlusconi's ranks in July, leaving him without a guaranteed parliamentary majority, has warned him he will withdraw his supporters from government posts as early as this week unless he resigns and forms a new government with a revised programme.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has told supporters he will stay put, pressuring Fini to try and win a no-confidence vote.</p>
    <p>Umberto Bossi, the leader of the Northern League party on which Berlusconi is increasingly dependent, is due to hold peace talks with Fini tomorrow.</p>
    <p>The three defeats in parliament yesterday were seen as a flexing of muscles by Fini's supporters, stopping short of bringing down the government but a dry run for coming battles.</p>
    <p>Gianni Letta, the cabinet secretary and a trusted Berlusconi aide, admitted that the prospects for the government "seem to be narrowing", suggesting a return to the polls or the appointment of an interim government.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi sought to shore up support yesterday by visiting areas in the Veneto region devastated by floods which have left 10,000 temporarily homeless, shut down factories and drowned 200,000 livestock.</p>
    <p>But as he met local officials, protesters clashed with police. Demonstrators waving banners reading "You Bunga Bunga, Us rubble rubble" also dogged his visit to a ceremony in Abruzzo honouring rescue workers involved in last year's earthquake later in the day.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>