<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="How one newspaper's 'shameful' questions have rattled Silvio Berlusconi" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-05-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/24/silvio-berlusconi-la-repubblica-inquiry" hostname="theguardian.com" description="La Repubblica's inquiry into leader's friendship with young model divides Italy and provokes right-wing backlash" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Newspapers,Media,World news,Europe" fingerprint="7faed22f93d7ff0d">
  <main>
    <p>For a man who controls almost half of Italy's television stations, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has become remarkably exercised by the activities of a single daily newspaper. When recently riled by another bout of questioning on his notorious visit to the birthday party of a teenage model, Noemi Letizia, the Italian prime minister jabbed his finger repeatedly at the correspondent from La Repubblica who had dared to pose it.</p>
    <p>"Shame on you!" Berlusconi hissed. "The Italians are with me!", he added, tapping his own chest proudly before storming out of the room, followed by his bodyguards.</p>
    <p>It is now 10 days since the left-leaning La Repubblica first published 10 questions for Berlusconi about his expedition last month to the 18th birthday party thrown in a Naples suburb for Letizia, who commonly refers to Berlusconi as "daddy". Days later his second wife, Veronica Lario, asked for a divorce.</p>
    <p>Curious about inconsistencies in Berlusconi's account of how he knew Letizia's father, and by Letizia's suggestion that Berlusconi was grooming her for politics, La Repubblica sent the prime minister a list of questions such as: "Is it true that you promised Noemi you would help her career in show business or in politics?" It also asked for details of the prime minister's previous meetings with her.</p>
    <p>According to La Repubblica editor Ezio Mauro, the visit - and alleged discrepancies in the Italian prime minister's subsequent explanation of it - have provided a test case for journalism in Berlusconi's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. "There are contradictions here and when the powers that be don't explain something, journalism has a job to do," Mauro said.</p>
    <p>What is at stake goes far beyond the immediate details of Berlusconi's meetings with a young Neapolitan apparently in search of a career in show business. In recent months there have been numerous accusations from the left that Berlusconi is establishing a form of authoritarian populism that has little respect for parliament, less for judges routinely described as politicised, and is far too easily able to dominate the media.</p>
    <p>The Letizia affair - and the reporting of it - is becoming a kind of litmus test. "Berlusconi has one thought in his head," said Dario Franceschini, the leader of Italy's main opposition, the Democratic party (PD), " - 'I was elected by the people and no one can judge me any more.' His strong reaction to investigative journalism is because he thinks it is immoral to have a free press and an opposition."</p>
    <p>More than 40,000 Facebook users have joined the 10 questions campaign, signing up to a page called "Berlusconi Rispondi!" (Berlusconi reply!) But, according to Berlusconi, La Repubblica is being driven by "jealousy and hatred" as he basks in historical poll ratings. "The motives behind the campaign of denigration by La Repubblica and its editor against Berlusconi are obvious," said a statement put out by his office.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's surprise appearance at Letizia's party, where he gave a €6,000 (£5,300) gold necklace to the teenager, might have strayed no further than the gossip columns had it not been for Mrs Berlusconi, who told newspapers she could not stay with a man who "frequents minors", adding that her husband was "not well".</p>
    <p>"When Veronica Lario went public it was no longer a private matter," said Mauro. "Moreover, if anyone broke down the barriers between public and private it was Berlusconi when he sent his biography to 50 million Italians before an election."</p>
    <p>"In the Anglo-Saxon world, there would have been a competition between papers to investigate the affair. Here they talk about other things," said La Repubblica journalist Giuseppe D'Avanzo, who compiled the questions.</p>
    <p>Maurizio Belpietro, editor of Panorama magazine, which is controlled by Berlusconi, dismissed D'Avanzo's complaint. "The point is La Repubblica has been waging a campaign and Berlusconi has done well to ignore questions which are more political provocation than a search for truth," he said.</p>
    <p>Pressure grew last week when it emerged that Berlusconi had brought Letizia to a government dinner in Rome in November honouring the fashion industry, where he sat her at the top table alongside Santo Versace, Paolo Zegna and Leonardo Ferragamo, introducing her as "the daughter of very good friends in Naples", La Repubblica reported.</p>
    <p>Mauro commented: "This emerged after Berlusconi said he had only ever met Noemi in the company of her parents. After the dinner, Letizia jetted to Milan for an audition as a weather girl on one of Berlusconi's channels, missing out on a job only because of her poor diction. She and her mother were then invited to the Christmas party held by Berlusconi's football team, Milan, La Repubblica wrote. "If Berlusconi wants to explain all this, we would be ready to listen and understand," said Mauro.</p>
    <p>But Berlusconi is not in a conciliatory mood. His tirade at La Repubblica's correspondent was merely a warm-up for Thursday when he let rip on all fronts in a speech to Italian employers, branding the Italian parliament a "useless" institution that is stopping him from running the country.</p>
    <p>The problem for La Repubblica is that Italians are apparently, as Berlusconi claims, "with him", judging by the lead his party enjoys in polls ahead of next month's European elections "When Berlusconi argues with journalists, he is just being direct and undiplomatic," said Belpietro. When the German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, did the same, no one talked about a regime."</p>
    <p>Opposition MPs plan this week a formal request that Berlusconi clears up the Letizia mysteries with an address to parliament. But judging by the Prime minister's present mood, La Repubblica may be waiting for its 10 answers for a long time yet.</p>
    <head rend="h2">The prime minister's other enemies</head>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Judges</hi>
    </p>
    <p>"Penal justice is an illness in our system. This morning the papers say you can't even criticise judges. I believe instead it's a right of every citizen to criticise judges and to point out that no one would appoint (Inter Milan FC coach José) Mourinho as referee at an Inter Milan-AC Milan game. I don't think anyone would accept that."</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">Parliament</hi>
    </p>
    <p>"The prime minister has practically no powers; all the powers were given to parliament. There are 630 deputies. You would need 100 or so. You would need a popular initiative on this; you cannot expect turkeys to bring forward Christmas."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>