<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Eurozone crisis: Deadlock in Italy as Grillo rejects centre-left" author="Graeme Wearden; Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-02-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/feb/27/eurozone-crisis-italy-elections-bond-auction" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Satirist-turned-politician refuses to support Democratic Party,damning its leader as a “dead man talking’" categories="Business" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,Italy,Italian elections 2013,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="97ac109d18325764">
  <main>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani, leader of the Democratic Party, has seen his olive branch rebuffed by Beppe Grillo. Photograph: TONY GENTILE/REUTERS Photograph: TONY GENTILE/REUTERS</p>
    <p>Pier Luigi Bersani, leader of the Democratic Party, has seen his olive branch rebuffed by Beppe Grillo. Photograph: TONY GENTILE/REUTERS Photograph: TONY GENTILE/REUTERS</p>
    <p>Italian politics remains deadlocked tonight after efforts to form an alliance between the centre-left bloc, the Democratic Party, and Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement collapsed.</p>
    <p>However, calm has returned to the financial markets after yesterday's heavy losses.</p>
    <p>Grillo unleashed a characteristic tirade of insults on Pier Luigi Bersani, leader of the Democratic party (PD), who on Tuesday extended an olive branch to the M5S in a bid to create a reformist government. The ex-comic ruled out giving a crucial confidence vote in parliament to a centre-left government and reiterated that the M5S's new legion of deputies and senators would vote on laws on a case-by-case basis.</p>
    <p>"The M5S will give no confidence vote to the PD (or to anyone else)," Grillo wrote on his blog. "It will vote in the chamber for laws which chime with its programme, whoever proposes them."</p>
    <p>Grillo's move appears to thwart Bersani's hopes of forming a working majority in the Senate with Five Star - there is speculation that Italy could face a year of instability.</p>
    <p>European Central Bank president Mario Draghi has given a speech tonight in which he acknowledged the deep pain being caused by Europe's austerity programmes.</p>
    <p>Draghi, Italy's former central bank governor, insisted though that economic reforms and fiscal cutbacks can deliver a fairer society in the long term.</p>
    <p>In his first public comments since the Italian election results, Draghi said:</p>
    <p>The benefits of the painful actions undertaken so far have not yet materialized.</p>
    <p>And this means that economic adjustment is coming at a heavy social cost... We are fully aware of the human dimension that lies behind it.</p>
    <p>Draghi cited the record youth unemployment levels -- more than half of young people in Greece and Spain are out of work. That is unfair, he said.</p>
    <p>Is that fair, that as a result, this generation has to bear the bulk of the burden in the downturn? That's why I say that reforms that make economies work better also make them fairer.</p>
    <p>Draghi has previously argued that 'structural' problems with Europe's economies have worsened the impact of the crisis.</p>
    <p>Here's some analysis of the political situation in Italy tonight from Alberto Nardelli:</p>
    <p>He explains that Beppe Grillo's decision to refuse to form an alliance with the centre-left Democratic Party (read it at 4.50pm) isn't a surprise, but it is very significant.</p>
    <p>It effectively sinks Pier Luigi Bersani's chances of running a minority government.</p>
    <p>An abstention in Italy’s Senate in a confidence vote would be akin to a no-vote, meaning a Bersani government wouldn’t have the majority required to install a government. Italy’s President, Napolitano, is unlikely to send Bersani to parliament to seek a confidence vote unless he believes there is a majority.</p>
    <p>Alberto also believes that Silvio Berlusconi is waiting for Bersani to cave in and seek a grand coalition. Today's video statement (see 6.15pm) shows that Berlusconi wants a deal on tax cuts and institutional reforms.</p>
    <p>And his conclusion is that we are unlikely to get new elections, if needed, within the next six months, because:</p>
    <p>1) the new parliament sits in 2-3 weeks, and needs to elect presidents for each chamber, and parliamentary groups need to be formed.</p>
    <p>2) President Napolitano consults with all stakeholders - presidents of the chambers, parliamentary groups and parties to explore if there is a parliamentary majority around a potential government/s.</p>
    <p>3) whatever happens, the current president’s terms is ending and Napolitano cannot dissolve parliament and call new elections - parliament needs to elect a new president.</p>
    <p>4) internal party dynamics - should Bersani be unable to form a government and new elections needed it is unlikely Bersani would lead the PD into these elections - this means: party congress, primaries, selection of candidates etc. The same on the centre-right - would Berlusconi stand again? What would Monti &amp; Co. do?</p>
    <p>On not blaming 'the markets' for Europe's austerity drive</p>
    <p>If you're interested in the debate about Europe's austerity programme, check out this new blog post by an influential London fund manager (regularly quoted in this blog in the past as @pawelmorski).</p>
    <p>It's a brisk rebuttal of a recent research paper which argued that the fiscal consolidation being imposed on European countries was largely the fault of the "fear and panic that erupted in the financial markets".</p>
    <p>The paper (by Paul De Grauwe and Yuemei Ji) was published last week and got a lot of attention in the media (here's a good piece). Its broad theme is that from 2010 to 2012 the markets acted irrationally, recklessly ditching sovereign debt, and forcing painful, unnecessary and self-defeating cutbacks and tax rises on swathes of Southern Europe.</p>
    <p>Well, here's a flavour of the counter-argument:</p>
    <p>Panic is a funny word. Jumping out of a moving bus can look like panic. However, if the driver – let’s call him Jean-Claude – is absolutely adamant that he wants to drive said bus off a cliff (think of M. Trichet’s threats to pull the repo-able status of Greek debt and later refusal to allow the ECB to get involved in a rescue), and the conductor (Wolfgang) is similarly vehement about fiscal assistance – jumping out starts to look quite rational.</p>
    <p>The ECB (especially) and the core countries spent most of 2010-mid-2012 declaring an absolute refusal to assist the peripheral nations. As a result, Europe’s money supply began to resemble a badly-sloping field, where all the liquidity is drained from one end (the periphery) and swamps the core.</p>
    <p>Bank deposit data Photograph: /@pawelmorski</p>
    <p>That changed when the European Central Bank finally took bold sweeping steps last summer, at which point the governments of Spain and Italy saw their borrowing costs fall to safer levels.</p>
    <p>In this case, blaming the markets actually is therefore blaming the alarm for the fire, and measures to control spread volatility like measures to prevent fire casualties by removing the alarms.</p>
    <p>The point is that the recent recovery in market optimism has been driven by the actions of central bankers like Mario Draghi - not ever-deeper fiscal cutbacks.</p>
    <p>More here. (don't be offended by the opening paragraph. he loves us really).</p>
    <p>Ok @pawelmorski's new blog is a must read etc etc. Lucky to have such a brilliant mind giving his thoughts away for free.</p>
    <p>A grim reminder from Athens tonight that the situation in Greece remains perilous.</p>
    <p>The drugs shortage in the country, already bad, is getting much worse, warns Elizabeth Sukkar and Helena Smith from Athens:</p>
    <p>Hundreds of drugs are in short supply and the situation is getting worse, according to the Greek drug regulator. The government has drawn up a list of more than 50 pharmaceutical companies it accuses of halting or planning to halt supplies because of low prices in the country.</p>
    <p>More than 200 medicinal products are affected, including treatments for arthritis, hepatitis C and hypertension, cholesterol-lowering agents, antipsychotics, antibiotics, anaesthetics and immunomodulators used to treat bowel disease.</p>
    <p>Separately, it was announced on Tuesday that the Swiss Red Cross was slashing its supply of donor blood to Greece because it had not paid its bills on time.</p>
    <p>Video: Silvio Berlusconi pushes for Grand Coalition</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has just released a video clip in which he argues that Italian political parties must prioritise political stability.</p>
    <p>As he puts it:</p>
    <p>No political force can not ignore the value of responsible governance.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi goes on to pledge that, if involved in the next government, he will push for an end to European-imposed austerity, and reform Italy's democratic systems to provide stability.</p>
    <p>With Beppe Grillo refusing to make a deal with the centre-left, Berlusconi appears to making another bit for a Grand Coalition.</p>
    <p>Nicolò Cavalli, an economics student and researcher, comments:</p>
    <p>Translation of Berlusconi: PD+PDL coalition, I will be President of the Senate, focus on jobs and reform electoral law to obstruct Grillo</p>
    <p>Italian news agency Adnkronos is reporting that Italy's president has now rebuked Germany's Peer Steinbrück over his comments about clowns winning the election (see 2.24pm)</p>
    <p>***Adnkronos: Italian President Napolitano says Italy respects Germany and demands the German respect***</p>
    <p>Bersani is a political stalker. He's been pestering the Five-Star Movement for days with indecent proposals, instead of resigning as everyone else would do in his situation."</p>
    <p>"Over the past twenty years, [Bersani's] Democratic Party was in government for ten years, and over the past year-and-a-half it even took part in the grand coalition government with [Berlusconi's] PdL party, backing any sort of junk proposed by Rigor Montis [Grillo's nickname for Mario Monti]."</p>
    <p>"The Five-Star Movement won't give any confidence vote to the Democratic Party or others. It will support in parliament only the laws that mirror its programme - whoever proposes them.</p>
    <p>Grillo also regaled his readers with a list of comments which Bersani made about Five Star Movement during the campaign, which don't look quite so clever now:</p>
    <p>"There's little democracy in the Five-Star Movement."</p>
    <p>Five-Star Movement people are "web fascists. Come out call us zombies."</p>
    <p>Here's the political situation in Italy this evening:</p>
    <p>1) Beppe Grillo has rejected the overtures of the centre-left, dashing Pier Luigi Bersani's hopes of an alliance that would give his centre-left party a majority in the Senate - see 2.36 GMT onwards.</p>
    <p>2) Grillo made the move alongside a brutal attack on Bersani - dubbing him a stalker and a dead man talking who should quit.</p>
    <p>3) Bersani's junior partner has ruled out the other option, a Grand Coalition with Silvio Berlusconi - see 3.15pm GMT.</p>
    <p>Conclusion: we are no further towards a functional government in Italy</p>
    <p>The Financial Times agrees that it's a significant step:</p>
    <p>Italy’s political deadlock following inconclusive elections took a turn for the worse on Wednesday when Beppe Grillo announced that his Five Star Movement would not give a vote of confidence in parliament to any government led by the two main parties.</p>
    <p>The man on whom the spotlight has shone is, unsurprisingly, Beppe Grillo, the mane-haired former comedian and blogger who created the movement in 2009. But what is now on the minds of many are the dozens of people who have lined up behind him and have, out of nowhere, got to prove their political mettle at a time of crisis.</p>
    <p>"These are ordinary people. They are all completely new. None of them have ever stepped into any kind of chamber in their life," said Duncan McDonnell of the European University Institute in Florence.</p>
    <p>"Any single new party, if it has a sudden spurt of growth, always has the problem of how to handle it, because it doesn't have the structures and the rules and the personnel to handle this kind of vote. But now, of course, on top of this you've also got the fact that we've got a log-jam [in the parliament]. And the M5S has become very important."</p>
    <p>And if you've never seen Grillo in action....Genoa's newspaper, Il Secolo XIX, has a good video clip of the M5S leader speaking to reporters. It's here:</p>
    <p>It's official - the Left Ecology Freedom party, which teamed up with Pier Luigi Bersani in the election, is refusing to take part in a coalition with Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>Reuters has the full details:</p>
    <p>The junior partner in Italy's centre-left coalition on Wednesday rejected forming a governing alliance with the centre-right after neither side won enough seats to govern in this week's election.</p>
    <p>"No grand coalition," said Nichi Vendola, leader of the Left Ecology Freedom party, after a meeting with centre-left leader Pier Luigi Bersani.</p>
    <p>In a statement, Vendola said he hoped populist leader Beppe Grillo did not want a right-left government either, and called for a government that would "give an electric shock" to the country.</p>
    <p>Beppe Grillo's decision (see 2.36pm) leaves Pier Luigi Bersani in a very difficult position. If an alliance with Five Star is ruled out, then his only hope of a majority is through a grand coalition with Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>Political analyst Alberto Nardelli explains:</p>
    <p>Bersani is in a lose-lose-lose situation: deal with Berlusconi, resign from PD, or stand again and probably lose election. #Italy</p>
    <p>Big news from Italy - Beppe Grillo has ruled out forming an alliance with the centre-left, dashing hopes that the two sides could form a stable government.</p>
    <p>The leader of the Five Star Movement made the announcement in a blog post in which he blasted Pier Luigi Bersani as "a stalker" and a "dead man talking" who should have resigned rather than attempted to woo his rivals - as he did last night.</p>
    <p>Writing on his blog, Grillo reiterated his opposition to any form of formal alliance with Bersani's Democratic Party. Instead, Grillo said, Five Star would only support policies which it agreed with.</p>
    <p>The news was accompanied with a remarkable graphic of Pier Luigi Bersani presented as a corpse:</p>
    <p>Italian president blows out Peer Steinbrück over clown comments</p>
    <p>Italian President Giorgio Napolitano (centre) at Munich airport yesterday. Photograph: CHRISTOF STACHE/AFP/Getty Images Photograph: CHRISTOF STACHE/AFP/Getty Images</p>
    <p>German politician Peer Steinbrück has paid a heavy price for joking yesterday that the Italian election had been won by a couple of clowns - Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, has cancelled a meeting with him.</p>
    <p>The rebuke comes after Steinbrück's, the SPD's candidate for the chancellorship in this autumn's general election, told voters at an event called Straight Talk with Peer Steinbrück that</p>
    <p>To a certain degree I am appalled that two clowns have won.</p>
    <p>In fairness to Steinbrück, he's not the first person to connect Beppe Grillo's career as a satirist with Silvio Berlusconi's long record of being, well, Silvio Berlusconi - or "a clown with a testosterone boost", as he put it.</p>
    <p>But Napolitano - on a trip to Germany - is most unamused.</p>
    <p>In the UK, one of the Bank of England's deputy governors has tried to shoot down speculation that Britain might experiment with negative interest rates -- a day after a fellow deputy suggested it might.</p>
    <p>Speaking at a conference organised by the Institute of Economic Affairs, Bean said:</p>
    <p>Any suggestion that we have a plan to introduce negative interest rates immediately, I should make absolutely clear, is not the case.</p>
    <p>The ECB cut its deposit rate to 0.0% last year, in an attempt to get banks to lend. But as our economics correspondent, Phillip Inman, reports, Bean says the Bank of England couldn't easily folow.</p>
    <p>Bean did his best to demolish the policy, saying it would create huge problems for banks that have tied mortgages to the current bank base rate of 0.5%.</p>
    <p>"It has significant negative side-effects which is why I do not support it," explained Bean.</p>
    <p>He pointed out that the European Central Bank has a separate rate for some commercial bank deposits because they are forced to keep particular reserves, whereas UK banks are allowed flexibility.</p>
    <p>Disaggregating some bank deposits with Threadneedle Street from others would be a minefield, Bean added.</p>
    <p>I just chatted with economist Shaun Richards, who argued that the ECB's move hadn't worked:</p>
    <p>Zero rates had zero effect. The ECB cut the deposit rate to zero, and all the money just moved to another account in the ECB.</p>
    <p>Richards said he wasn't surprised to see Tucker discussing negative rates, given the weak state of the UK economy and the Bank's failure to stimulate output. But he pointed out that previous rate cuts haven't had much effect, and warns that savers would inevitably suffer.</p>
    <p>Just to be clear, this is different from the Bank of England's base rate, which is at a current record low of 0.5%. Our Q&amp;A explains all....</p>
    <p>...unlike a certain radio station this morning, it seems:</p>
    <p>Re: LBC radio yes I was Shaun from Battersea and yes I was cut off when I explained the consequnces of -ve interest rates for savers!</p>
    <p>Over in Greece, the former mayor of Thessaloniki has been jailed for life after being convicted of stealing almost €18m from the city.</p>
    <p>Vassilis Papageorgopoulos was convicted of embezzlement after a trial where four others were also convicted and received lesser sentences, including the municipality's former general secretary, Michalis Lemousias, ex-cashier Panayiotis Saxonis.</p>
    <p>Papageorgopoulos and 17 other officials stood trial for allegedly embezzling almost 52 million euros from the municipality’s coffers, though the Thessaloniki court on Wednesday said that there was proof of 17.962 million euros having been misappropriated by the former mayor and his cohorts.</p>
    <p>Herman Van Rompuy, president of the European Council, has joined the ranks of Eurocrats warning Italy that they cannot avoid fiscal consolidation.</p>
    <p>Speaking after meeting the prime minister of Hungary, Viktor Orbán, Van Rompuy said the pair had spoken about " the economic and social situation in Europe".</p>
    <p>As I have said before - and others like me - I believe that 2012 marked a turning point in the crisis in the eurozone - and that the worst is now hopefully behind us.</p>
    <p>But we should not become complacent - neither in Member States nor at the level of the European Union and the eurozone. There is no real alternative to keep up reforming our economies. There is no way back for any of our Member States.</p>
    <p>Pope Benedict XVI waves to the faithful as he arrives in St Peter's Square to hold his last general audience at the Vatican February 27, 2013. Photograph: ALESSANDRO BIANCHI/REUTERS Photograph: ALESSANDRO BIANCHI/REUTERS</p>
    <p>There's very little political action to report in Italy yet (where the Pope is making an emotional farewell to huge crowds in the Vatican).</p>
    <p>But Beppe Grillo's Five Star group are making murmurings about a potential deal with Bersani, it seems:</p>
    <p>Five Star official says may weigh support for Bersani government (Democratic Party)</p>
    <p>Word from Brussels that the European Commission president, José Manuel Barroso, will meet Italy's current prime minister, Mario Monti, to discuss the situation.</p>
    <p>European Commission says prez Barroso to meet Italian PM Monti tonight. Will discuss elections, statement will follow #Italyvote#wsjeuro</p>
    <p>The news that Italy's much-watched bond sale went smoothly (see 10.24am) has cheered analysts, although some traders are muttering darkly that we don't know who bought the bonds (so perhaps domestic banks mopped most of them up to ease the panic).</p>
    <p>Nick Spiro of Spiro Sovereign Strategy said the sale had gone "relatively smoothly", but warned:</p>
    <p>The higher yields show that Italian sovereign debt is now caught in a tug-of-war between the reassurance provided by the ECB's fiscal backstop and the confusion and instability in Italian politics.</p>
    <p>...While there's still none of the panic of November 2011 or July 2012, sentiment towards Italy has deteriorated markedly since Sunday's inconclusive parliamentary election.</p>
    <p>Nick Stamenkovic of RIA Capital Markets said the results would generate "some relief", with buyers calculating that an Italian government will be carved out, somehow.</p>
    <p>They got reasonable demand, but clearly investors demanded a higher risk premium to take it down.</p>
    <p>Demand reflected by the bid/cover ratio suggests that despite the uncertain outlook, investors believe that some sort of a coalition will be cobbled together in coming weeks.</p>
    <p>And Elisabeth Afseth of Investec agreed that the important point is that the Italian debt management office "got it done".</p>
    <p>The yields are higher than anything they've done for quite some time but that's hardly a big surprise but they got the amount they wanted.</p>
    <p>But some were more cynical:</p>
    <p>None of traders I work with can confirm that there was real money in today's auctions. It smells like a well-orchestrated PR event from ECB.</p>
    <p>Breaking: the results of the Italian debt auction are in, and it has gone better than feared.</p>
    <p>Borrowing costs are up compared with the previous auctions (no surprise there!), but they are not at dangerous levels. And there certainly wasn't a buyer's strike - Italy sold the full €6.5bn on offer.</p>
    <p>Here's the details:</p>
    <p>Italy sold €2.5bn of 5-year bonds at an average yield of 3.59%, up from 2.94% last time.</p>
    <p>It also sold €4bn of 10-year bonds at an average yield of 4.83%, up from 4.17%</p>
    <p>And the bid-to-cover ratio (the amount of bids compared to the amount on offer) actually rose, to 1.6, from 1.3 last time.</p>
    <p>The better news in today's UK GDP data is that the economy actually grew over the last 12 months.</p>
    <p>Britain's economy was 0.3% higher than a year ago - not flat as expected. That's because the ONS have revised two other quarters last year. It now thinks GDP in Q1 2012 only fell by -0.1% (from -0.2%), while Q3 2012 GDP is now estimated at +1.0% (from +0.9%).</p>
    <p>On the one hand, this is much weaker than the UK government had expected (via the independent Office for Budget Responsibility)</p>
    <p>In June 2010 the OBR assumed 2012 would be a year of booming recovery (+2.8%). The fiscal plans are based on this. We got growth of 0.3%.</p>
    <p>Rating agency Moody's weighed in on the Italian election deadlock last night, warning that it could downgrade the country's credit rating if a government can't be formed, or if its economic reform agenda now stalls.</p>
    <p>In a statement, Moody's said:</p>
    <p>We would consider downgrading Italy's government debt rating in the event of additional material deterioration in the country's economic prospects or difficulties in implementing reform</p>
    <p>A deterioration in funding conditions as a result of new, substantial domestic economic and financial shocks from the euro area debt crisis would also place downward pressure on Italy's rating.</p>
    <p>Moody's currently rates Italy just two notches above Junk status, at Baa2.</p>
    <p>City traders also appear to be taking comfort from US central bank chief Ben Bernanke - who yesterday calmed fears that the Federal Reserve will tighten monetary policy.</p>
    <p>Mike van Dulken, Head of Research at Accendo Markets, explains:</p>
    <p>While Italian political chaos likely to persist as discussions take place on coalition formation, investors still looked to put more onus on US Fed Chairman’s statement that quantitative easing was here to stay.</p>
    <p>After yesterday's drama, Europe's stock markets are rising in early trading.</p>
    <p>Italy's FTSE MIB: up 106 points at 15657, + 0.7%,</p>
    <p>FTSE 100: up 29 points at 6299, + 0.5%</p>
    <p>German DAX: up 35 points at 7629, +0.4%</p>
    <p>French CAC: up 24 points at 3646, +0.7%</p>
    <p>Spanish IBEX: up 64 points at 8044, +0.8%</p>
    <p>So why the change? One argument is that investors would actually welcome some grit being thrown into the wheels of the eurozone austerity machine.</p>
    <p>The prospect of a Bersani-Grillo government, providing some stability but less fiscal consolidation, isn't a reason to panic.</p>
    <p>Investors haven't been demanding that economic growth is choked off recklessly across Europe -- their concern is simply that they get their money back.</p>
    <p>Or as one London fund manager put it:</p>
    <p>Markets don't have a problem with democracy. They get uneasy when the potentially bankrupt piss off their patrons.</p>
    <p>Deadlocked Italy holds bond sale as EU faces turmoil</p>
    <p>Good morning, and welcome to our rolling coverage of the eurozone financial crisis following the dramatic Italian election results, and other key events in the world economy.</p>
    <p>It never really went away, but there's no doubt that the eurozone crisis is now getting everyone's full attention again.</p>
    <p>The deadlock in Italy following the weekend's election is a very nasty shock to those who thought the worst was somehow over for Europe.</p>
    <p>With a majority of voters rejecting the reform plans favoured by the EU, we might be looking at months of drama:</p>
    <p>Three years of German-led austerity and budget cuts aimed at saving the euro and retooling the European economy was left facing one of its biggest challenges as Italian voters' rejection of spending cuts and tax rises opened up a stark new fissure in European politics.</p>
    <p>The governing stalemate in Rome and the vote in the general election – by a factor of three to two – against the austerity policies pursued by Italy's humiliated caretaker prime minister, Mario Monti, meant that the spending cuts and tax rises dictated by the eurozone would grind to a halt, risking a re-eruption of the euro crisis after six months of relative stability.</p>
    <p>That was yesterday. Now, Italy's first challenge is to sell up to €6.5bn of long-term government bonds this morning.</p>
    <p>Investors are certain to demand a higher rate of return, with Italy's future so uncertain. How much higher (and how many bond traders take part), will show how nervous the markets are today.</p>
    <p>And the big question remains - who will govern Italy?</p>
    <p>Last night Pier Luigi Bersani threw down a challenge to Beppe Grillo and his Five Star Movement (M5S) -- you've won influence, now use it.</p>
    <p>At a press conference in Rome, a weary-looking Bersani said it was time for the upstart movement to do something more than just demand the removal of Italy's mainstream politicians.</p>
    <p>"Up to now, they have been saying: 'All go home.' But now they're here, too. So either they go home as well, or they say what they want to do for their country and their children."</p>
    <p>Such an alliance would scupper the Grand Coalition favoured by Silvio Berlusconi. Your move, Beppe.</p>
    <p>We'll be watching all the latest political and financial developments through the day....</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>