<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Debt crisis: Silvio Berlusconi unveils reforms to avert Italian crisis" author="John Hooper" date="2011-08-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/aug/07/debt-crisis-berlusconi-italy-crisis" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prime minister announces measures to eliminate the budget deficit by 2013 and to give firms a freer hand" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Financial crisis,Economics,Credit crunch,Market turmoil,Global economy,Business" fingerprint="574ad10d12b7a559">
  <main>
    <p>For the capital of a nation in the eye of a financial hurricane, Rome was appropriately calm at the end of a fortnight that has seen 11% wiped off the value of shares worldwide, with investors' fears now focused on Italy's ability to repay its vast debts.</p>
    <p>With the temperature at 31C (88F), and intense humidity making it feel a great deal hotter, the overwhelming majority of people in the <hi rend="#i">centro storico</hi>, the historic centre, were tourists. The Romans themselves had either fled on holiday, or were huddled behind shutters at home. Even on Piazza Santi Apostoli, a square lined with offices, drivers could take their pick of spaces to park in.</p>
    <p>Rome implodes when parliament rises, and on Wednesday, after hearing a comforting speech from the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, Italy's lawmakers headed off to the beaches and mountains. They were not meant to have come back until 12 September. But, with Italy's shares plunging, its borrowing costs soaring and the opposition screaming for a new government initiative, the speaker agreed they should return six days earlier.</p>
    <p>That may now change. At a press conference late on Friday, Berlusconi finally unveiled the sort of reforms he had been expected to announce two days earlier in his speech to parliament: measures to eliminate Italy's budget deficit by 2013, instead of 2014 as originally planned, and to give firms a freer hand.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's instinct, when faced with a crisis, is to radiate his trademark, salesman's optimism. When it first looked as if Italy was being sucked to the very centre of the storm in world markets, he and other ministers reacted either by pointing to what they claimed was the underlying health of the nation's economy, or by asserting that the crisis was European, or global, in character and thus beyond their power to affect.</p>
    <p>After an earlier scare in mid-July the government rushed through parliament a package of measures that aimed to trim €48bn (£42bn) from the budget deficit and enable Italy to start paying off its €1.8tn public debt in 2014. As late as last Thursday evening Berlusconi was signalling that the steps taken had been quite enough to deal with the problem.</p>
    <p>Asked at a press conference about the sell-off that had just sent the Milan bourse plunging by more than 5%, he replied: "The stock exchanges are a long way from economic reality. My father used to say to me: they're like broken watches; they only tell the correct time twice a day."</p>
    <p>Even in a semi-deserted Rome, however, it was not hard to find Italians who doubted their government's blithe assurances. Berlusconi told them the credit crunch crisis of 2007-8 would affect Italy less than any country in the EU. And though its banks rode out the storm as he had predicted, in 2009, Italy's GDP dived 5.2%. "He said the crisis wouldn't affect us. But it has affected us. And how," said Catia Brenci, a security guard. She described how each new company entering the market was offering its guards less, gradually dragging down earnings across the industry.</p>
    <p>Across the river Tiber in an area of media studios and lawyers' chambers, there were still clients in suits and ties sipping their <hi rend="#i">cappuccini</hi> at the Bar Griffe on Viale Mazzini. The manager, Roberto Introzzi, said there were more people around than usual for August. "But we saw a big fall [in takings] in July. People went on holiday then to take advantage of special offers. They're being more careful with their money," he said. "Italy could go the same way as Greece."</p>
    <p>Introzzi told a story you hear a lot nowadays: of middle-class families selling off assets, or running down savings, to subsidise their children, who are living at home because they cannot find jobs. "How long can that go on?", he asked.</p>
    <p>The strength of family ties is one of several factors that have, until now, masked the gravity of Italy's economic situation. In the south, unemployment among the young is approaching Spanish levels. Yet it has seen neither violent protests as in Greece, nor the sort of generally peaceful marches and sit-ins mounted by Spain's <hi rend="#i">indignados</hi>.</p>
    <p>Perhaps the most important shock absorber has been that Italians have grown accustomed to their economy being in the doldrums. It has barely stirred since the turn of the century. At one point last year, the only countries with lower growth over the preceding 10 years were Zimbabwe and Haiti.</p>
    <p>Not before time, said Roger Abravanel, the international financial community had woken up to the implications of Italy's inability to grow.</p>
    <p>"The markets are telling us that it is not any more a question of fiscal balances. They're saying: 'Even if you cut your deficit to nothing, we're not going to buy your bonds because, without growth, you're not going to be able to meet your debts'," said Abravanel, the Milan-based author of two bestselling books that probe the causes of Italy's economic underperformance.</p>
    <p>The most important, he argued, was that "the landscape of Italian companies is old-fashioned: Italians still believe 'small is beautiful'." Hundreds of thousands of family firms, which played an invaluable role in the 'economic miracle' of the 1950s and 1960s, had become a dead weight, making it impossible for Italy to make the leap to a post-industrial, knowledge-based economy.</p>
    <p>One of many incentives to remain small is a law exempting firms with fewer than 18 workers from strict legislation forbidding involuntary redundancies. "Because of this companies that want to grow, that want to hire graduates, want to invest in R&amp;D and IT, don't do so", he said.</p>
    <p>He reeled off a string of other factors: exam results that gave employers no idea of the educational level of graduates and school leavers; four levels of government – national, regional, provincial and municipal – each with their sets of laws, and the market distortions introduced by Italy's mafias.</p>
    <p>It remains to be seen just how far Berlusconi's government will be prepared to take his promised liberalisation of the economy. So far, he has been deeply reluctant to take on the many vested interests which stand in the way of Italy becoming more competitive.</p>
    <p>Locked into the euro, unable to devalue its currency as it did routinely in the past, Italy has lost ground steadily to Germany, the eurozone's other big export-led economy. So might it be better off without the single currency?</p>
    <p>Tito Boeri, economics professor at the Bocconi university in Milan, admitted "many" of his colleagues were now thinking the once-unthinkable. His own view was that the advantages outweighed the disadvantages.</p>
    <p>"We've had a big reduction in interest rates that has reduced the cost of servicing the debt. The euro has been important in insulating Italy from some of the international shocks of recent years, such as the crisis after 9/11. It has put competitive pressure on firms. It has increased price transparency and generated trading opportunities," he said.</p>
    <p>But he added: "One might wonder whether, it might have been better to be able to use the exchange rate in these circumstances and have a central bank intervening on the markets to buy Italian bonds."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>