<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi told to face showgirl inquiry or quit" author="Fiona Winward; Guardian staff reporter" date="2009-06-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/19/silvio-berlusconi-inquiry-escorts-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Pressure grows as the embattled Italian prime minister insists there is 'nothing to clarify'" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="eee85a3db0a2c35d">
  <main>
    <p>Despite a growing number of calls for him to reveal all or resign, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> today insisted he had no intention of answering questions about allegations that paid escorts attended parties at his homes.</p>
    <p>The embattled Italian prime minister even likened his approach to the claims to his removal of rubbish from the streets of Naples last year after a garbage collection crisis.</p>
    <p>But leading political figures, including the deputy speaker of the house, have called for Berlusconi to explain himself or step down, after a former showgirl claimed she had been paid by a Bari businessman to attend dinners at the prime minister's Rome residence, receiving an extra fee if she stayed the night. Speaking in Brussels at the end of the EU leaders' summit, Berlusconi said there was "nothing to clarify. It's all very clear: it's all rubbish. I already got rid of [the rubbish] in Naples and I'll do the same with this."</p>
    <p>But the deputy house speaker, Rosy Bindi, of the centre-left Democratic party, said: "Either Berlusconi explains what happened or he must go."</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, Antonio Di Pietro, leader of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Principles party, called for a no confidence vote in parliament, describing Berlusconi as a modern-day Nero whose "weakness" for women left him open to blackmail.</p>
    <p>"How many people have already blackmailed him? What have they received in return? What is Berlusconi forced to offer to regain international credibility? Sending soldiers to Afghanistan? Hosting former Guantánamo prisoners?"</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, undergoing his second divorce, was also asked to clarify his position by the Catholic newspaper Avvenire. But government politicians closed ranks around the prime minister.</p>
    <p>The defence minister, Ignazio La Russa, told the newspaper Il Giornale he "categorically excluded" the possibility that Berlusconi would be forced to quit as a result of the row. "Everyone (behind) ... this campaign of false and libellous accusations against the prime minister ... is going to be disappointed," La Russa said, backing the claim that it is an attempt to smear Berlusconi's image before Italy hosts next month's G8 summit.</p>
    <p>"It's unacceptable for the prime minister's private life to be investigated in contemptible violation of his rights ... without the least evidence of behaviour that would constitute a crime."</p>
    <p>Bari prosecutors have opened an investigation based partly on wiretapped conversations into whether payments allegedly made to women by a local entrepreneur, Gianpaolo Tarantini, to attend parties "in exclusive locations in Rome and Sardinia" were an "induction into prostitution".</p>
    <p>Tarantini denied the claims last night, which he said were "false and malicious". One of the women, 42-year-old Patrizia D'Addario, told Corriere della Sera she had been offered €2,000 (£1,700) to attend parties and stay the night at Berlusconi's Rome residence, Palazzo Grazioli.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors are examining secret audio tapes D'Addario said she made there as well as video footage allegedly filmed inside a bedroom where a photo of Berlusconi's wife, Veronica Lario, can be seen.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's lawyer has said even if the allegations were true the prime minister would be only the "end user" of the women and therefore not criminally liable.</p>
    <p>Lario asked for a divorce in May, saying she could not stay with a man who "frequents minors" after Berlusconi attended the 18th birthday party of aspiring model Noemi Letizia.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>