<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="David Mills guilty of taking bribe linked to Silvio Berlusconi trials" author="John Hooper" date="2009-02-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-silvio-berlusconi-trial" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Estranged husband of Olympics minister Tessa Jowell sentenced to four and a half years' jail by Italian court for taking $600,000 bribe as reward for withholding court testimony" categories="Politics" tags="Tessa Jowell,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Law,World news,UK news,Politics,David Mills,Europe" fingerprint="c32e90059030df56">
  <main>
    <p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the Olympics minister, Tessa Jowell, was today sentenced to four and a half years in jail by an Italian court after being found guilty of taking a $600,000 (£400,000) bribe as a reward for withholding court testimony to help Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>The verdict is a potentially serious embarrassment not only for Berlusconi but also for Gordon Brown because it turns the spotlight back on to the role played by one of his ministers in the affair. Jowell signed a document crucial to the receipt of what a foreign court has now decided was a bribe.</p>
    <p>Mills was not present in court when Judge Nicoletta Gandus read out her verdict, but said in a statement that he was "very disappointed" by the verdict and would appeal against it.</p>
    <p>"I am innocent, but this is a highly political case," he said. "I am hopeful that the verdict and sentence will be set aside on appeal, and am told that I will have excellent grounds."</p>
    <p>Jowell said today: "This is a terrible blow to David and, although we are separated, I have never doubted his innocence."</p>
    <p>Gandus said Mills would have to pay €250,000 (£220,000) in damages for the perversion of justice caused by his distorted evidence. And she ordered him to pay a further €25,000 in costs.</p>
    <p>Mills's lawyer, Federico Cecconi, told reporters afterwards: "This is a verdict based on a prosecution case that was anything but consolidated. It contravenes the logic and dynamics of the trial."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi – who was indicted alongside Mills, his former legal adviser on offshore dealings – is no longer a defendant. His government passed a law last year giving the prime minister and some other top Italian officials immunity from prosecution.</p>
    <p>It is thought to be the first time in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> that someone has been found guilty of taking a bribe without the giver of the money being identified. Gandus's reasons for her verdict will be released in writing at a later date.</p>
    <p>Mills is entitled under Italian law to two appeals and the crucial issue now is whether they can be heard before the offence of which he has been convicted is "timed out" in February 2010 by a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>The prosecutor, Fabio de Pasquale, said: "It is possible, if they get a move on."</p>
    <p>The fact that Mills failed to appear at his trial was criticised by the judge.</p>
    <p>Mills initially admitted having accepted what he had considered a gift or loan. But he subsequently retracted his statement, leaving the prosecution with the formidable task of trying to establish how the money had reached him through a chain of offshore trusts and hedge funds.</p>
    <p>In 2000, Jowell and her husband took out a loan, securing it on their terraced house in Kentish Town, north London, and invested the proceeds in a hedge fund. The following month, the loan was repaid with the $600,000 at the centre of the trial.</p>
    <p>After the transaction came to light, Jowell said she only became aware four years later – in August 2004 – that her husband had received money he "had reasonable grounds to believe was a gift".</p>
    <p>Today Mills told the Guardian: "The whole thing was arranged by me."</p>
    <p>The then-prime minister, Tony Blair, accepted her assurance.</p>
    <p>The issue of Berlusconi's immunity is being considered by Italy's constitutional court. His government recently secured his position further with a clause inserted in a bill to reform the judiciary. If approved by parliament, it will mean that, even if his immunity were lifted, the judge in the case that ended today would not be able to apply its outcome automatically to Berlusconi. She would have to begin proceedings all over again.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>