<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy's quest for justice | Sabina Castelfranco" author="Sabina Castelfranco" date="2011-04-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/apr/08/italy-justice-system-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Sabina Castelfranco: It's not just about Berlusconi's trials going nowhere – our snail-paced justice system is in desperate need of wider reform" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Europe,Silvio Berlusconi,World news" fingerprint="bfed112a31c7ed53">
  <main>
    <p>Can justice ever be served in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>? The absolute need to reform Italy's dysfunctional justice system is not in question, but many doubts exist as to whether, if such a reform were to finally be carried out, it would even start to resolve the system's enduring problems.</p>
    <p>The matter is increasingly the subject of debate, not least since the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, faces a number of trials that seem to be going nowhere. For anyone who is not Italian, and even for those who are, it is difficult to comprehend how a much-awaited hearing is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/apr/06/silvio-berlusconi-sex-trial-begins">adjourned after just seven minutes</ref> and the next hearing set for eight weeks later. This happened at the opening of the premier's trial this week in Milan on charges of paying for sex with a minor and abuse of office. And this is not the exception in this country, but the rule.</p>
    <p>Without a doubt the main problem in administering justice in Italy is the speed of the process. "Because reaching a definitive sentence takes so long, we have a result that is equivalent to non-justice," says Giancarlo Laganà, a Rome-based criminal lawyer.</p>
    <p>The European court of human rights in Strasbourg recently again condemned Italy for the excessive duration of its civil and criminal trials. The <ref target="http://www.lifeinitaly.com/news/human-rights-court-condemns-italys-slow-justice-again">Council of Europe</ref> also passed a resolution in December urging Italy to "come up with an efficient strategy" to speed up "snail-paced" trials and bring its justice system in line with European standards.</p>
    <p>But why do the wheels of Italian justice turn so slowly? Laganà says it has to do with the "excessive workload" magistrates face, "cumbersome legal mechanisms" and "individual failures to be productive". Will these issues be resolved? Unlikely.</p>
    <p>Italy's justice minister, <ref target="http://www.trust.org/trustlaw/news/analysis-is-italys-legal-reform-just-a-favour-to-berlusconi">Angelino Alfano</ref>, is determined to carry out judicial reform. But too many people in Italy fear his plans are political – tailor-made to resolve the prime minister's legal woes rather than the country's sluggish system. A related issue is whether magistrates who make mistakes in administering justice should be held accountable, allowing offended parties to request compensation. Those who oppose this idea say magistrates would be unsettled in their decision-making, being fearful their actions could be used against them. This appears to be a lame excuse.</p>
    <p>One positive issue that is often raised is the fact that Italy has an independent judiciary, which enjoys special constitutional protection from the political authority. This gives it strong powers, and Berlusconi has long accused the magistrates of using these powers to conduct an endless crusade against him.</p>
    <p>For Italians it is not just about bringing the prime minister to justice but also about having a system that works. The institutional independence of the judiciary is in no way sufficient to promote the effective administration of justice. No reform under discussion has the true potential to change the state of affairs, and much deeper political commitment is required.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>