<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi threatens constitutional war over sex trial moves" author="John Hooper" date="2011-02-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/09/silvio-berlusconi-sex-trial-prosecutor" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Prosecutors in Milan call for Italian PM to go on trial immediately charged with sex-related offences" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="7ff1ab20bbe6c6d5">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi has raised the spectre of a full-scale constitutional showdown in Italy after prosecutors in Milan asked for him to be put on trial immediately, charged with sex-related offences.</p>
    <p>Italy's prime minister accused them of breaking the law and going against parliament. Soon afterwards his chief ally, Umberto Bossi of the Northern League, said the indictment request marked the start of a "total war" between Italy's judiciary and its legislature.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi and his allies have argued that the case should have been dropped last week after a vote in the lower house of parliament, where they have a narrow majority. The house adopted a resolution that meant, in effect, that the prosecutors had no right to pursue their investigation.</p>
    <p>Milan's chief prosecutor, Edmondo Bruti Liberati, said his colleagues had asked for the prime minister to be put in the dock without a preliminary hearing because of the "obviousness of the evidence" against him.</p>
    <p>A judge, Cristina Di Censo, is expected to rule early next week on the prosecutors' application. If it is granted, Berlusconi could be put on trial as early as April.</p>
    <p>The latest move piled yet more pressure on the media tycoon-turned-conservative politician, whose Freedom People movement was hit by a split last year. His government has since survived two make-or-break confidence votes in parliament, but it is struggling to pass legislation Bossi has said is essential to the Northern League's continued support.</p>
    <p>Clearly enraged by the prosecutors' determination to press ahead, Berlusconi told a press conference in Rome: "It's a disgrace. It's disgusting." He added: "I wonder who is going to pay for this activity, whose only aim is subversive."</p>
    <p>He then indicated that it would be the taxpayer who paid, because "I shall attempt to sue the state." The prime minister did not make clear on what grounds he would try to do so.</p>
    <p>The evidence laid before Di Censo ran to almost 800 pages. It included witness statements and wiretap transcripts suggesting the prime minister had invited dozens of women, including prostitutes, to his mansion near Milan for dinners that degenerated into debauches.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who denies any wrongdoing, is accused of paying an underage prostitute and then committing the offence under Italian law of abusing his official position to cover up his alleged crime. Among his guests was a young Moroccan runaway, Karima el-Mahroug, who adopted the nickname Ruby Rubacuore (Ruby Heartstealer).</p>
    <p>The prosecutors maintain she was under 18 years old at the time, the minimum age for prostitution; Berlusconi's lawyers are expected to argue that she is older than indicated on official documents.</p>
    <p>Last May, Mahroug was taken to a Milan police station accused of theft. Instead of being returned to care, however, she was released to a regional parliamentarian from Berlusconi's party, who has since been placed under investigation suspected of aiding and abetting prostitution.</p>
    <p>The young Moroccan was handed over after the police took a call from Berlusconi in which he claimed that she was the granddaughter of the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's lawyers insist he believed this was the case. At the press conference, the prime minister said: "The abuse of office does not exist. I stepped in because I was worried about an international diplomatic incident."</p>
    <p>Last month, the constitutional court effectively emasculated the billionaire prime minister's latest device for evading prosecution. As a result, two trials in which Berlusconi is accused of financial misconduct are due to resume between late February and early March; the pre-trial hearing of a third case involving the prime minister is set to open on 5 March.</p>
    <p>He is also at risk from an investigation overseen by prosecutors in Naples. On Wednesday Police acting on their orders searched the Milan home of another woman claimed to have been a guest of the prime minister. According to leaks from the inquiry, she is suspected of links with the Neapolitan mafia, the Camorra.</p>
    <p>Normally, decisions on whether to indict a suspect accused of paying a juvenile prostitute are taken by a judge after a preliminary hearing. But Bruti Liberati said his office had decided to follow a practice, already established in Milan and elsewhere in cases where one of two alleged related offences qualified for direct indictment of the accused, of applying the same fast-track procedure to both. The decision was taken despite a warning from Berlusconi's lawyers that they would argue it was unconstitutional.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi affected unconcern over the latest developments on Thursday.</p>
    <p>"I'm not worried about myself," he said. "I'm a rich gentleman who can go on to setting up hospitals for children around the world, as I have always wanted to. But I am performing a service for the country and making a lot of sacrifices."</p>
    <p>His doctor, Alberto Zangrillo, confirmed the prime minister's state of mind was that "of a person who is living in the knowledge that he is in the right. And I say that also from a clinical-diagnostic standpoint."</p>
    <p>Dr Zangrillo was speaking to reporters at a conference in Rome on vegetative states.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>