<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Roy Greenslade: British editors sign up to Italian press freedom petition" author="Roy Greenslade" date="2009-09-22" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2009/sep/22/press-freedom-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, has sued the country's second biggest-selling daily newspaper La Repubblica for libel. He has objected to the paper's call for him to answer 10 questions about his relationships with several women." categories="Media" tags="Press freedom,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Alan Rusbridger,Lionel Barber,John Witherow,Roger Alton,Media,Europe" fingerprint="7885db2a13dafe19">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's prime minister, <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>, has sued the country's second biggest-selling daily newspaper <hi rend="#b">La Repubblica</hi> for libel. He objected to the paper's call for him to answer <ref target="http://temi.repubblica.it/repubblicaspeciale-repubblicaspeciale-ten-new-questions-to-silvio-berlusconi/">10 questions about his relationships with several women.</ref></p>
    <p>With Berlusconi's widespread media interests, there is mounting pressure on the paper and the situation is said to be growing more serious by the day.</p>
    <p>La Repubblica's journalists believe the libel action is an attempt to stifle a free press. In <ref target="http://temi.repubblica.it/repubblicaspeciale-repubblicaspeciale-ten-new-questions-to-silvio-berlusconi/2009/08/28/appeal-by-three-jurists/">a statement on its website</ref>, the paper says: "The questions addressed to our prime minister are real questions that have prompted people's interest not only in Italy but also in the media across the world."</p>
    <p>It has therefore launched an online petition in defence of press freedom that has attracted more than 420,000 signatories. It is hoped to reach 500,000 by 3 October, when a public demonstration is due to take place in Rome.<lb/> Among the signatures on the petition are those of four British national paper editors: <hi rend="#b">Alan Rusbridger</hi> (The Guardian), <hi rend="#b">Lionel Barber</hi> (Financial Times), <hi rend="#b">John Witherow</hi> (Sunday Times) and <hi rend="#b">Roger Alton</hi> (The Independent). Editors in Germany, France and Spain have also signed. But no Italian editor is on the list.</p>
    <p>La Repubblica, which is published in Rome, sells about 540,000 copies a day. Founded in 1976 as a radical paper, it has maintained a centre-left political stance ever since.</p>
    <p>To give you some idea of how Berlusconi's loyal media empire is attacking the paper, <ref target="http://www.libero-news.it/">here's the photomontage</ref> that appeared on page 3 of <hi rend="#b">Libero</hi> today, lampooning <hi rend="#b">Ezio Mauro</hi>, editor of La Repubblica.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#i">Source:</hi><ref target="http://temi.repubblica.it/repubblicaspeciale-repubblicaspeciale-ten-new-questions-to-silvio-berlusconi/">La Repubblica</ref><hi rend="#i">Petition:</hi><ref target="http://temi.repubblica.it/repubblica-appello/?action=vediappello&amp;idappello=391107">Sign here</ref>/<ref target="http://www.libero-news.it/">Libero</ref></p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>