<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi makes surprise visit to own trial" author="John Hooper" date="2012-04-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/20/silvio-berlusconi-surprise-visit-trial" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian prime minister puts in first appearance at Milan court where he is being tried for paying for underage sex" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="efa2ca6c38e3df13">
  <main>
    <p>It may have been considered the last place on Earth that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> would want to be seen.</p>
    <p>But on Friday Italy's former prime minister put in a surprise first visit to the courthouse in Milan where he is on trial for paying for underage sex, and sat through crucial police evidence. Defendants in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> do not have to attend their trials.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi confirmed to reporters outside the court that young female guests at "bunga bunga" parties in his mansion near Milan had dressed up as police officers, but only for the purpose of "burlesque shows". He also explained why he had paid large sums of money to some of the women who are to testify: "Because they have had their lives ruined by this trial".</p>
    <p>Earlier this month, it was reported that he had paid €127,000 (£104,000) to three women, including his former dental hygienist Nicole Minetti. Now a regional politician for Berlusconi's party, Minetti is a key figure in the trial, which centres on the TV mogul's relationship with a young Moroccan runaway-turned-dancer, Karima el-Mahroug.</p>
    <p>Mahroug, who denies she was a prostitute, attended several parties thrown by Berlusconi when she was 17. Paying for the sexual services of anyone under 18 is an offence in Italy.</p>
    <p>In 2010, after she was detained in Milan on suspicion of theft, a senior police official was telephoned by the then prime minister. "He told me that there was a girl at police headquarters who, he had been informed, was the granddaughter of [the then Egyptian president, Hosni] Mubarak, and that the parliamentarian Nicole Minetti would come and take care of the situation with regard to care," Piero Ostuni said in evidence.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who is also charged with taking advantage of his official position, denies all wrongdoing. He has insisted he believed the girl was a relative of Mubarak.</p>
    <p>Another police officer, Giorgia Iafrate, said Mahroug had admitted she was not related to the Egyptian leader, and she had informed Ostuni. He testified, however, that he had not relayed this information to the prime minister's office.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>