<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italy: the eurozone's moment to choose" author="Nils Pratley" date="2011-11-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/nils-pratley-on-finance/2011/nov/07/italy-silvio-berlusconi-euro" hostname="theguardian.com" description="With Silvio Berlusconi seemingly on the brink and soaring yields on Italian debt, the country's problems cannot be ignored" categories="Business" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Euro,Business,Eurozone crisis,Bonds,European Central Bank" fingerprint="3fe441afdda15d3c">
  <main>
    <p>"In the coming days, lower Italian bond yields will be absolutely vital for calming down fears of fresh contagion," said Goldman Sachs' Jim O'Neill at the weekend. Oh dear. I<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/blog/2011/nov/07/greece-coalition-government-george-papandreou-crisis">talian bond yields soared this morning</ref>, hitting 6.66%, up from 6.35% when markets closed on Friday - an enormous move, and one that decisively shifts the centre of the euro crisis to Rome.</p>
    <p>Why has it happened? At least three reasons. IMF inspectors have entered Italy, as announced at the G20 summit last week, which could only be viewed as good news for the survival prospects of the single currency if you believe a financial support programme was in the offing. In reality, the IMF officials' job is merely to monitor and survey Italy's compliance with economic reform programmes - in other words, the IMF is in town because Germany and others suspect Italy lacks the will or ability to embrace an aid-for-austerity package. Meanwhile, prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> takes the view that assistance is not needed because "the restaurants are full".</p>
    <p>Second, while German and Italian leaders stick to their respective positions ("you're not doing enough" says the former; "we're doing fine," says the latter), it's very hard for the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> to sanction massive buying of Italian bonds, even if new boss Mario Draghi was minded to panic (and we know from his comments last week that he doesn't regard the central bank's role as being a buyer of last resort).</p>
    <p>Bond market specialists have been saying for weeks that Italian prices are not "real" in the sense that they are set by the informed choices of buyers and sellers operating in a liquid market: instead, yields have moved according to the volume of purchases made by the ECB via its modest Securities Market Programme, they think. And we now know what else was going on: French bank BNP Paribas said last week that it had dumped 40% of its Italian bonds. The bank was widely applauded for this 'de-risking' effort but the acclaim has created an incentive for every other bank to take similar precautionary action, thus increasing the pressure of Italian yields. Bank bosses don't want to be asked in a few months' time: why didn't you get ahead of the plot like BNP did?</p>
    <p>Third, the Italian political picture is suddenly as hard to read as Greece's. Berlusconi may soon be on his way out - after surviving 51 votes of confidence since 2008, the arithmetic for him becomes harder as supporters peel away - but there can very little clarity on what government would take its place if elections were held earlier next year. In any case, how do you easily solve the decline of Italy's competitiveness - the reason why the country's debt-burden is now increasingly judged unmanageable? That task, if attempted within a currency union with Germany, looks like the work of at least a decade, even if things were to go well. Is there an Italian government that could remain in office long enough to stay the course?</p>
    <p>Add it all up, and the eurozone seems to be running out of options to save itself. The 26 October deal, which imagined that €106bn would be enough to recapitalise banks, is clearly out of date if institutions were obliged to carry their Italian bonds at today's market prices. Moreover, the European Financial Stability Facility clearly won't get close to €1 trillion of firepower if China is not prepared to cough up.</p>
    <p>In practice, one suspects, the Italian political drama will run for several instalments before hard choices are made. But the logic, as ever, leads back to the ECB. Unlimited bond-buying, the policy Draghi opposes, would calm markets. In Germany it would be seen as a mutualisation of debt, or the writing of a blank cheque to no great purpose if economic reforms cannot be imposed on the debt stragglers. If that policy proves too objectionable for German voters to swallow, the only real alternative is to make the eurozone smaller.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>