<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Europe on the breadline: hopelessness and Berlusconi | Jon Henley" author="Jon Henley" date="2011-10-18" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/blog/2011/oct/18/jon-henley-breadline-europ-hopelessness-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Jon Henley is travelling in search of the human stories behind the European debt crisis. Here he meets a Naples bookshop owner who says the sense of despair can be traced to Berlusconi" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Financial crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,Global recession,Banking,Business,World news" fingerprint="a3a0135b3ccfae5d">
  <main>
    <p>Giancarlo Di Maio is 23 and doesn't know many other people his age who are working. He's one of the lucky ones, he says in the secondhand bookshop he runs in a corner of the Piazza del Gesu in central Naples: "University here is like a car park. You stay there as long as you can, because in there'll be nothing to do when you come out."</p>
    <p>Di Maio left Naples University last year with a degree in political science. His father runs two bookshops and a place like this had been his dream since he was a small boy. "Every morning, I wake up with a smile," he says. "How fortunate am I? Because otherwise, the only other work around here is black. The black economy is a huge, monumental issue for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>."</p>
    <p>Many of his friends, Giancarlo says, are working in bars or restaurants; 10 hours' work for maybe €30 in a bar, or €20 for an evening's waiting in a restaurant. The jobs are undeclared, so the government misses out on tax, and employees also risk missing out on benefits should they need them.</p>
    <p>"I know plenty of people in their 30s, even some in their 40s, still living with their parents," says Giancarlo. "That's not normal. For me, that's one of the biggest problem in Italy – opportunities, any kind of prospects for young people."</p>
    <p>There are others, obviously. He sighs and shrugs at the mention of politics. "We have the worst political class in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, no question," he adds. "Twenty years of Berlusconi, and not a single reform, nothing for the unemployed, nothing to address the economic crisis. Instead we talk about his sex life. The first 10 pages of La Repubblica every day, bunga bunga.</p>
    <p>"But really, we have a political class who do nothing. They don't have solutions, and even if they did they wouldn't try to do anything. They just speak air, it's all they can do. Posturing." Part of why politicians are not held to account here, he says, is the prime minister's media empire: "He's created the news culture that decides what we should be told."</p>
    <p>He was optimistic about <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/17/occupy-movement-global-protest">the Occupy protests</ref>, he says, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/16/rome-riot-damage-ringleaders-police?newsfeed=true">until things degenerated into violence in Rome</ref>. "Maybe 1,000 people ruined it. They just gave the politicians an excuse not to listen." He's a fan of the Five Star Movement, an anti-corruption campaign launched last year by comedian Beppe Grillo with the aims of preventing politicians convicted in court from representing the people, and of limiting political mandates to two terms.</p>
    <p>Belated public spending cuts to tackle Italy's budget problems, though, are beginning to make themselves felt. "I take public transport every day, the rapid transit system. It used to be a train every 10 minutes – I know that's crazy in itself, where you come from – but now it's a train every 20 minutes. Here in Naples, there are police cars in car parks because they can't afford to get repairs done. Or sometimes even buy petrol."</p>
    <p>While Italy lacks the kind of widespread grassroots protest movement typified by Spain's Indignados and 15M ("I don't have the impression there's as much personal hardship here; on the whole most people are still able to get by"), Giancarlo says people here are "finally starting to get angry. They are beginning to see that really, we can't carry on like this. Italy really is sick. We can't pretend to be the doctor any more; we need curing ourselves."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>