<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi and Gordon Brown: the Italian job" author="Simon Hoggart" date="2009-07-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/jul/09/simon-hoggart-sketch-parliament-g8" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Simon Hoggart: At Westminster Harman was exchanging with William Hague the same ludicrous figures that Brown and Cameron swapped a week ago" categories="Politics" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,G8,Gordon Brown,Harriet Harman,Politics,World news" fingerprint="3fe7d96f810ed771">
  <main>
    <p>Gordon Brown was in Italy for the G8, the guest of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. It was a dank day in London, and we were about to be harangued by Harriet. No wonder one's thoughts drifted towards the sun-dappled jewel of the Mediterranean.</p>
    <p>I imagined our prime minister being greeted by his host. "Ah, ha, my fren' Gordon! Ees good to see you!" (Berlusconi, as well as sounding like Chico Marx, bears some physical resemblance to him, though Chico was more or less sane.) "I 'ave, 'ow you say, a leetle surprise waiting for you in your room!"</p>
    <p>At Westminster Harman was exchanging with William Hague the same ludicrous figures that Brown and Cameron swapped a week ago.</p>
    <p>Hague asked if she would put into plain English what Brown had meant when he said that total spending would continue to rise, and that the rise would be zero per cent in 2013.</p>
    <p>She replied: "The shadow chancellor says he spends 40% of his time thinking about economics; it's amazing that he spends all his time thinking about doing absolutely nothing!"</p>
    <p>Hague snapped back. Perhaps she would spend 100% of the next minute answering his question.</p>
    <p>Back in L'Aquila, Gordon goes up to his room, looking forward to a quiet hour with some world output figures.</p>
    <p>Instead he is greeted by a young woman in a babydoll nightie who, it appears, is not the chambermaid. "Meester Berlusconi, 'e sent me – to make you 'appy!"</p>
    <p>"Noo," replies Gordon. "I am a son of the manse and can have nothing to do with happiness. Be away with you!"</p>
    <p>Back in London, Harman was explaining how a reduction in public expenditure from £44bn to £24bn was actually an increase. Hague said that was exactly the sort of statement that damaged the credibility of politicians.</p>
    <p>In L'Aquila, the young woman in the babydoll has rushed downstairs in tears.</p>
    <p>"Meester Brown, 'e no wants me! 'E send me away! 'E made me vair, vair sad!"</p>
    <p>The Italian premier is furious. "Okay, so this Eenglish, ziss Scottish Eenglish, 'e insults ze flower of Italian womanhood! 'E will not get away wiz ziss!"</p>
    <p>In the Commons chamber there is a strange silence. Normally the recital of meaningless statistics would call forth loud cheers from each side. Instead everything seemed to be greeted with a mild, sullen chuntering, like a platform full of people who've just learned that the 7.55 has been cancelled.</p>
    <p>Vince Cable asked if Harriet had suggested that Gordon took her "progressive views on gender equality" to Berlusconi, which elicited some laughter.</p>
    <p>In Italy, Gordon slips gratefully into bed after a long day instructing other world leaders to follow Britain's shining example.</p>
    <p>His foot meets something warm and wet, but it is only after he has thrown back the sheets that he sees the full horror of the severed horse's head.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>