<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi is just PM to avoid trial, claims foe as revolt falters" author="John Hooper" date="2010-12-12" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/12/silvio-berlusconi-rebellion-escape-italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Gianfranco Fini makes unprecedented allegation as mutiny against Italy's prime minister threatens to end in failure" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="7fec819cd031d77d">
  <main>
    <p>Gianfranco Fini, whose rebellion has brought Silvio Berlusconi's rightwing government to the brink of collapse, said today what the media tycoon's leftwing critics have been claiming for years: that he wants to cling to power solely to avoid criminal trials relating to his business activities.</p>
    <p>Fini's unprecedented allegation electrified the atmosphere ahead of two make-or-break censure motions in the Italian parliament on Tuesday. Berlusconi was reported to be furious with his former ally and deputy, who told a television interviewer that, whatever the outcome, the votes would leave the government paralysed.</p>
    <p>But, Fini said, Berlusconi did not care because he "doesn't want to govern; he wants to remain in the premier's office" to avoid trial.</p>
    <p>There is growing evidence that Fini's revolt risks ending in embarrassing failure. At the weekend, tensions among the rebels burst into the open when it emerged that six of their representatives in parliament had signed an appeal for peace talks between Fini and the billionaire prime minister.</p>
    <p>Five of the signatories are members of the lower house, the chamber of deputies, where Berlusconi is most vulnerable to defeat on Tuesday. Only one of the signatories had previously indicated that he might side with the prime minister when the ballot is called. At least two more are now thought likely to abstain.</p>
    <p>Even by Berlusconi's eel-like standards, a victory this week would represent an astonishing escape from what seemed like inevitable doom. In the last two months alone he has faced claims that he is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/02/wikileaks-cables-berlusconi-putin">profiting from energy deals with Russia</ref>; been found by a court to have <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/20/silvio-berlusconi-ally-sicilian-mafia">paid "enormous sums" to Cosa Nostra</ref> for protecting his family and business interests; weathered the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/15/silvio-berlusconi-gianfranco-fini-resignations">resignation of four members of his government</ref>; and been accused by a prostitute of having <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/04/silvio-berlusconi-italy-stories">twice paid her for sexual favours</ref>.</p>
    <p>He has also brushed off claims that he intervened with the police to secure the release from custody of a 17-year-old belly dancer who told prosecutors she had been a guest of the prime minister at parties in his villa that ended in an erotic game known as bunga bunga.</p>
    <p>News of the deputies' defections sparked <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/10/silvio-berlusconi-italy-mps-votes">accusations that Berlusconi was buying votes</ref>, claims that are to be investigated by the prosecution service in Rome.</p>
    <p>The latest developments suggest the government could now win by a majority of up to eight votes. "I fear Fini ran ahead of himself," said Sofia Ventura, a lecturer in political science at the University of Bologna, who is close to the rebel Future and Freedom for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> (FLI) movement.</p>
    <p>Fini, a former neo-fascist who now presents himself as the standard bearer of a less autocratic and hardline form of conservatism, split with the prime minister in July when he was virtually expelled from Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People (PdL). More than 30 deputies rallied to his cause, stripping the government of its majority in the lower house.</p>
    <p>From the outset, however, the mutineers' bold rhetoric hid an innate weakness: the FLI is not yet registered as a party and, even if it were, would be in no condition to fight a successful campaign if Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, called an election as a result of the rebellion. Nor is Fini – apparently fearful of being branded a traitor – ready to create a new majority in parliament by allying with the centre-left opposition.</p>
    <p>He instead demanded that Berlusconi form a new government with radically different policies that the FLI could back. When the prime minister refused to oblige, the FLI's representatives quit the government.</p>
    <p>Gaetano Quagliariello, Berlusconi's acting deputy leader in the senate, said the rebels then fatally exposed their weakness by signing up to the second of two censure motions tabled for Tuesday.</p>
    <p>"Until then, Fini's position had a certain logic," he told the Guardian at his office in the upper house. "He was saying, 'You threw me out of the PdL and I'm going to make you pay. You can't pretend I don't exist.' But when you table a motion of no confidence, you have to know what you're going to do if it succeeds. You can't go on saying, on the one hand, that Berlusconi is the problem and then, on the other, that you'd accept a second Berlusconi government."</p>
    <p>The question now is what happens after Tuesday's vote. Even if Berlusconi survives, he will be in trouble. He has been bleeding support in the polls and his government has done little to revive an economy that is recovering painfully slowly from the recession.</p>
    <p>Enrico Letta, deputy leader of Italy's biggest opposition group, the Democratic party (PD), said: "The political fact is that this government and this majority cannot go on."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's decision last year to insist, in the face of the evidence, that Italy was weathering the global economic crisis better than other countries had become an achilles heel, Letta said. "It just doesn't make sense to people that Berlusconi is asking them for sacrifices having said everything was going fine."</p>
    <p>The PD is calling for a "government of national responsibility", with a respected prime minister not drawn from any one party. That is unlikely to materialise if Berlusconi wins on Tuesday.</p>
    <p>Even the prime minister said at the weekend that it would be more difficult to enact reforms with his majority cut to a bare minimum by Fini's rebellion. Quagliariello believes he needs to rely on at least 320 votes in the 630-member chamber, "otherwise it is possible that he'll appeal to a sense of national responsibility and try to widen the basis of his majority".</p>
    <p>The obvious place to look for support would be at the rightmost tip of the opposition, in the Christian Democrat Union of the Centre (UDC), which formed part of Berlusconi's last government in power from 2001 to 2006.</p>
    <p>The snag is that, under Italy's cumbersome procedures, the negotiations could take weeks, if not months, and Italy can ill afford a renewed bout of political uncertainty. The financial markets, which have already wrought havoc in Ireland and Portugal, are jittery about Italy's huge debts and its ability to fulfil its commitments as a member of the euro.</p>
    <p>They have already pushed up the cost of Italy's borrowing. Any further increase could leave the government with an unenviable choice between losing control of its budget deficit and imposing painful spending cuts and/or tax increases.</p>
    <p>"My impression," said Ventura, "is that the closer that the various players get to Tuesday, the greater their fear of the outcome."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>