<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi prostitution trial shaken up as three suspects argue" author="John Hooper" date="2011-04-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/apr/19/silvio-berlusconi-prostitution-trial-defendants" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Alleged members of Italian vice ring said to have procured young women bicker in public, creating problems for defence lawyers" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Sex work,Society" fingerprint="6eba41b712c3c696">
  <main>
    <p>The alleged members of a vice ring who are claimed to have procured young women for Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, have fallen out spectacularly, creating a potentially grave problem for his defence.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/apr/06/silvio-berlusconi-sex-trial-begins">denies paying an underage prostitute and then abusing his position to cover up the alleged offence</ref> in a trial that began earlier this month.</p>
    <p>Three of his associates are also under investigation in related proceedings, on suspicion of aiding and abetting prostitution, juvenile and otherwise.</p>
    <p>They include Nicole Minetti, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/31/berlusconi-italy-nicole-minetti-questioned">an Anglo-Italian dental hygienist and former TV variety dancer</ref> whom Berlusconi made a regional parliamentarian.</p>
    <p>Also under investigation are Emilio Fede, who presents a news programme on one of Berlusconi's TV channels, and Lele Mora, a showbusiness talent scout.</p>
    <p>Minetti's lawyer handed the prosecutors a document outlining her defence on Monday night.</p>
    <p>According to reports, the document blames the other suspects for introducing the prime minister to Karima El Mahroug, the then 17-year-old Moroccan runaway known as Ruby who is at the heart of the case.</p>
    <p>Minetti and her lawyer both denied the reports. "I am not accusing either Emilio Fede or Lele Mora," Minetti said.</p>
    <p>But that was not Fede's view. After being guided through a summary by Minetti's lawyer, he said: "The memorandum submitted by Nicole Minetti is bullshit ... I deny it."</p>
    <p>Interviewed by a local TV station, Fede complicated matters further by accusing Mora. "Karima El Mahroug – known as Ruby – got to Arcore [Berlusconi's home near Milan] thanks to Lele Mora," he said.</p>
    <p>Mora then accused Fede of having fallen into a trap laid by Minetti's lawyer.</p>
    <p>The TV presenter's involvement stems from a beauty contest in Sicily at which he was a judge and Mahroug a contestant.</p>
    <p>Fede told his interviewer he had not seen her again after that until one evening at Arcore.</p>
    <p>Mahroug, he said, had come to Milan on her own initiative and been introduced, through a third party, to Mora.</p>
    <p>It has been reported that Mora helped her get a job as a nightclub bellydancer.</p>
    <p>Mahroug herself, who denies being a prostitute, tells a different story – that she was taken to Arcore by Fede in a limousine belonging to Berlusconi's network, accompanied by police outriders.</p>
    <p>Minetti, Fede and Mora all deny the offences for which they are being investigated.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>