<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi survives crucial vote of confidence after defection of ally" author="John Hooper" date="2010-08-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/aug/04/silvio-berlusconi-gianfranco-fini-vote" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's lower house votes in support of government despite abstentions by Gianfranco Fini loyalists" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" fingerprint="5fb7923194e49715">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi survived a crucial test of his government's strength in parliament tonight following the defection of more than 30 MPs led by his erstwhile ally, Gianfranco Fini.</p>
    <p>After an emotional and at times heated session, the lower house voted by 299 to 229 in support of the government. But 75 deputies, including 25 loyal to Fini, abstained – enough to have defeated the government if they voted against it.</p>
    <p>The outcome sent a clear warning to Berlusconi that he is now a hostage of his former ally and Fini's new partners in the centre of the political spectrum. His group had agreed its policy of abstention with a Christian Democrat party and two smaller groups.</p>
    <p>The house rejected an opposition motion calling for a junior justice minister who is a suspect in a criminal inquiry to be sacked. Berlusconi had hinted his government would fall if it lost the vote.</p>
    <p>But the ballot nevertheless marked a watershed for Berlusconi's two-year-old conservative administration. The rebels' abstentions gave visible shape to a split that began last week when the rebels announced they were forming a separate group in parliament to press for reform in the governing party. A former neo-fascist, Fini has gradually altered his views and, since the return of the right to power in 2008, become a standard-bearer of a more progressive conservatism.</p>
    <p>His group's causes include more liberal policies and a tougher approach to corruption in high places. But even though Fini had earlier said members of the government should step down if formally under investigation, his followers held back from endorsing the opposition's motion.</p>
    <p>Its target was Giacomo Caliendo, who is accused of forming part of a secret society that allegedly conspired to fix judicial and political appointments, discredit Berlusconi's political enemies and make contact with judges due to rule in cases involving the prime minister.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>