<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Bill Gates urges Silvio Berlusconi to put aid before beauty" author="Tom Kington" date="2010-01-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/jan/28/bill-gates-silvio-berlusconi-hair" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Microsoft boss outlines bald facts of Berlusconi's foreign aid as Italy's asks: 'Where has the PM's hair gone?'" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Bill Gates,Italy,World news,Global development,Society,Technology,Aid,Europe" fingerprint="f7bbda2c194f890b">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's hair transplant took centre stage today when it was ridiculed by Bill Gates during a blistering attack on Italy's poor foreign aid record.</p>
    <p>In interviews with German newspapers, the Microsoft founder turned philanthropist said <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> was on his "shame list".</p>
    <p>"Dear Silvio, I am sorry to make things difficult for you, but you are ignoring the poor people of the world," he told the Frankfurter Rundschau.</p>
    <p>And in a clear reference to the notoriously image-conscious Berlusconi, Gates told Süddeutsche Zeitung: "Rich people spend a lot more money on their own problems, like baldness, than they do to fight malaria."</p>
    <p>In an annual report issued on Monday by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, Italy's aid was listed in 2008 at 0.21% of GDP, compared withthe UK's 0.48%. Italy then decided to halve aid in 2009, which made it "uniquely stingy among European donors", Gates wrote.</p>
    <p>The jibe came as photographs revealed that whatever Berlusconi spent on his transplant, even he has bad hair days.</p>
    <p>Italians were mystified to see shots of Berlusconi arriving at a wedding on 23 January with a healthy thatch, then reappearing two days later outside a hospital in Milan, apparently without most of his hair.</p>
    <p>Appearing pale and tired, Berlusconi, 73, was entering the San Raffaele hospital for a court-ordered inspection of the facial wounds he received in December when a man attacked him with a statuette of Milan cathedral. The extent of Berlusconi's wounds will help magistrates determine charges against his alleged assailant, Massimo Tartaglia.</p>
    <p>Piero Rosati, the surgeon who performed Berlusconi's hair transplant in 2004, told Italian daily Il Fatto that if Berlusconi had lost hair, stress could be the cause. But a second doctor, Franco Buttafarro, told magazine Novella 2000 that Berlusconi had simply neglected the powders, creams, make-up pencils and sprays he is likely to use to darken his scalp in order to appear less bald.</p>
    <p>"If the transplant had been done well there would be no need," he said, alleging the transplanted hair had been spread too thinly across Berlusconi's head.</p>
    <p>Candida Morvillo, editor of Novella 2000, which first published the photos, added the final piece of the jigsaw. "Because of the medical inspection, Berlusconi was probably not wearing his usual facial make-up that day," she said. "And if he had used his scalp colouring the contrast would have been too much, so he did without."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>