<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi faces rebellion from allies after pulling out of coalition" author="Lizzy Davies" date="2013-09-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/30/silvio-berlusconi-rebellion" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Make-or-break confidence vote for Italy's fragile coalition government this week" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="f6aa1b5517279761">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's precarious government will face a make-or-break confidence vote this week after <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> pulled his ministers out of the grand coalition and, amid growing dissent in his own ranks, called for new elections as soon as possible.</p>
    <p>Speaking a day after the move, which reignited fears for the health of the eurozone's third-largest economy, prime minister Enrico Letta said on Sunday that a parliamentary vote – probably on Wednesday – was needed in order to clarify whether the five-month-old government still had the numbers to continue.</p>
    <p>"Everyone will assume their responsibilities," he said in an interview on state broadcaster Rai. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, a country known for its volatile politics, needed to move away from a cycle of recurring crises reminiscent of the film Groundhog Day.</p>
    <p>Confirmation of the vote, which had first been suggested last week by the increasingly irate and embattled prime minister, came after Berlusconi appeared to soften his do-or-die stance in the face of mounting internal rebellion.</p>
    <p>Letta, whose allies are trying to see if an alternative parliamentary majority can be found to enable him to continue as Democratic party (PD) PM, said he hoped part of the People of Freedom party (PdL) might be prepared to go against its leader.</p>
    <p>On Sunday, four of the five ministers asked to resign by the media magnate broke ranks to say that, though they were willing to quit, they did not approve of the direction in which the party – recently relaunched as Forza Italia – was going.</p>
    <p>The most stinging blow came from Angelino Alfano, Berlusconi's right-hand man, who has been acting as deputy PM and interior minister in the Letta coalition. He said that if Forza Italia were to be dominated by extreme positions, he would have to be "a Berlusconi-ite in a different way".</p>
    <p>The unprecedented dissent from within his own party appeared to prompt the three-times prime minister to tone down his high-stakes strategy, which earlier in the day saw him triumphantly declare that he was "ready to take up the battle again".</p>
    <p>Declaring that he had slept properly for the first time in more than 50 days, Berlusconi said, to cheers on his 77th birthday: "The only way is to proceed with conviction to elections as soon as possible. All the opinion polls tell us that we will win." He later issued a statement appearing to soften his stance and offer an olive branch to Letta. He said the PdL would support a 2014 budget next month, along with some other measures, if it was truly useful to Italy.</p>
    <p>On Saturday, Berlusconi said his decision to withdraw support from the government was due to its failure to pass economic measures, notably a postponement of a sales tax hike due to take effect this week. Keen to point the finger at the PD for the crisis, his brother's newspaper Il Giornale had the headline "Letta brings down the government".</p>
    <p>Letta gave this suggestion short shrift, saying that the centre-right leader was motivated exclusively by his own affairs.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi suffered his first definitive conviction in two decades of legal tussles on 1 August, and the ensuing sentence for tax fraud ratcheted up tension on the fragile coalition formed in late April.</p>
    <p>A senate committee vote due on Friday is expected to strip him of his seat in the senate, and by mid-October he will have to decide whether he wants to serve his sentence under house arrest or in community service.</p>
    <p>Some analysts saw the decision to pull the plug on the government as the last roll of the dice for a life-long gambler. However, they said, it was a big gamble, the logic of which was not entirely clear.</p>
    <p>The shockwaves sent through Italy's already fragile political landscape have raised fears of a rise in Italy's borrowing costs.</p>
    <p>Fabrizio Saccomanni, the economy minister, sought to play down those fears, telling business daily Il Sole 24 Ore that he had faith in the credibility which he said Italy had built up in recent months.</p>
    <p>"I think the uncertainty connected to the government's instability has been largely already factored in during the last few weeks," he said.</p>
    <p>But with unemployment at 12% – and nearly 40% among young people – and a public debt of €2tn (£1.75tn), Italy's recession-mired economy is in desperate need of decisive government.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>