<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Patrizia D'Addario: Silvio Berlusconi knew I was an escort" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-10-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/02/patrizia-daddario-silvio-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Live television interview with woman at centre of sex scandal adds to pressure on Italian prime minister" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Sex work,World news,Europe" fingerprint="7b72d32d924df50b">
  <main>
    <p>The woman at the centre of the sex scandal involving <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has claimed the Italian prime minister knew she was an escort when she spent the night with him last November.</p>
    <p>In her first live interview on Italian television, Patrizia D'Addario, 42, said: "Certainly he knew that I was an escort."</p>
    <p>She added she was not the only escort present at two parties she attended at Berlusconi's Rome residence. "When I arrived it seemed like a harem," she told the current affairs programme Annozero last night.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has denied ever paying for sex and has said he was unaware escorts were brought to his parties by Gianpaolo Tarantini, a Bari businessman being investigated for drug dealing and prostitution. Berlusconi is not under investigation.</p>
    <p>D'Addario's visits to Berlusconi's residence were revealed in June. She has been widely interviewed by newspapers but had never appeared live on Italian television.</p>
    <p>A spokesman for Berlusconi, Paolo Bonaiuti, said Annozero was relying on "gossip and peeping through a keyhole".</p>
    <p>The state network RAI faces sanctions for violating its public service remit after the programme aired clips from a Spanish TV interview with D'Addario last week.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has sued newspapers for libel for coverage of the scandal and was reportedly "indignant" about D'Addario's live interview.</p>
    <p>RAI lawyers unsuccessfully pressured the show's host, Michele Santoro, to cancel D'Addario's appearance. "The public does not want censorship," Santoro said.</p>
    <p>D'Addario's interview was watched by 7.3 million Italians, a 30% share of viewers.</p>
    <p>Political allies of the prime minister have listed other RAI shows they believe are biased against Berlusconi, including the widely respected investigative programme Report. A newspaper owned by Berlusconi's brother has urged Italians not to pay their licence fee.</p>
    <p>Italian journalists will lead a nationwide protest tomorrow against perceived curbs on the press by Berlusconi, who owns three private television stations.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>