<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="David Mills awaits Italian bribery conviction appeal ruling" author="James Sturcke" date="2010-02-25" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/25/david-mills-verdict-bribe-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Estranged husband of Olympics minister Tessa Jowell was sentenced to four and a half years by Italian court last year" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,UK news,Tessa Jowell,Gordon Brown,Tony Blair,Politics,David Mills,Europe" fingerprint="7366c21d978af656">
  <main>
    <p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the Olympics minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tessajowell">Tessa Jowell</ref>, was today expected to find out whether his conviction for bribery would be overturned by the highest court in Italy.</p>
    <p>Last February, Mills was sentenced to four and a half years in prison by an Italian court after being found guilty of taking a $600,000 (£400,000) bribe as a reward for withholding court testimony in order to help the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>Today's decision, by the court of cassation, will have implications for Berlusconi, whose Milan trial on related corruption charges was put on hold pending the outcome of Mills's final appeal.</p>
    <p>If the court upholds Mills's conviction, it will strengthen prosecutors' position in the case against Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>The decision will also turn the spotlight back onto the role played by one of Gordon Brown's ministers in the affair – Jowell signed a document crucial to the receipt of what a foreign court decided was a bribe.</p>
    <p>Mills, a tax lawyer, gave Berlusconi advice on overseas investments. The trial judges ruled that he received the bribe to give false testimony in two 1990s trials to shield Berlusconi and his Fininvest holding company from charges relating to the purchase of US film rights.</p>
    <p>An appeals court upheld the decision in October. Both Mills and Berlusconi deny the charges.</p>
    <p>In 2000, Jowell and her husband took out a loan, securing it on their house in Kentish Town, north London, and invested the proceeds in a hedge fund.</p>
    <p>The following month, the loan was repaid with the $600,000 at the centre of the trial.</p>
    <p>Mills initially admitted having accepted what he had considered a gift or loan. But he subsequently retracted his statement, leaving the prosecution with the task of trying to establish how the money had reached him through a chain of offshore trusts and hedge funds.</p>
    <p>After the transaction came to light, Jowell said she only became aware four years later, in August 2004, that her husband had received money he "had reasonable grounds to believe was a gift".</p>
    <p>The then prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tonyblair">Tony Blair</ref>, accepted her assurance.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>