<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi's media attack Gianni Agnelli's reputation amid inheritance feud" author="Tom Kington" date="2009-09-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/06/gianni-agnelli-inheritance-fiat-taly" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Revered Fiat tycoon accused of tax evasion and womanising" categories="World news" tags="Italy,Fiat,Business,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Media,Europe" fingerprint="3b0e580ca7b0fd3c">
  <main>
    <p>He was the man who ran the Fiat empire for three decades, dated Rita Hayworth and was hailed as Italy's "last true gentleman" when 100,000 turned out for his funeral in 2003.</p>
    <p>But a bitter inheritance battle between Gianni Agnelli's descendants – often described as Italy's answer to the Kennedy dynasty – has sparked a series of allegations that now risk ruining the patriach's reputation.</p>
    <p>An unseemly shouting match began when Margherita Agnelli, the industrialist's 53-year-old daughter, claimed that Agnelli spirited up to ¤2bn (£1.7bn) of his wealth abroad.</p>
    <p>The allegation has prompted a tax evasion probe, a family feud and – perhaps worst of all – attracted the attention of the rightwing Italian press, which has grabbed the opportunity to distract attention from the sexual scandals that have engulfed the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, throughout the summer.</p>
    <p>"Agnelli the bad example – a model for tax evaders", crowed <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi>, which is owned by Paolo Berlusconi, the prime minister's brother, in an attempt to place Berlusconi's scandals in a better light.</p>
    <p>"If it was to be proven that Agnelli was not a praised, imitated, exemplary gentleman but a crook, it would be worth asking why in Italy there are progressive types who consider stealing from the people less serious than touching the bottoms of girls who like their bottoms to be touched."</p>
    <p><hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi> also claimed that Agnelli dated an 18-year-old Italian actress when he was a married man of 55, and that he was branded "an Italian pig" by actress Anita Ekberg when she thought he was deceiving her. For good measure, the paper suggested that, if Margherita was looking for her father's assets, she could start with the yacht Agnelli reportedly gave to Italian actress Silvia Monti. "Between Silvio and Agnelli, look who the sinner is," the newspaper's editorial column said.</p>
    <p>As the reputation and moral probity of Italy's most famous industrialist was placed under a microscope, John Elkann, Agnelli's grandson, hit back. "I am indignant," he said, "and I know I am not the only one, over how things have been exploited and manipulated, over the violent words and lies spread about my grandfather."</p>
    <p>Agnelli, who at one time controlled a quarter of the companies on the Italian stock exchange, was a noted collector of fine art and young actresses, once claiming: "There are men who talk about women and men who talk to women."</p>
    <p>The Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev recognised his dominance over Italian capitalism when he brushed aside local politicians in the early 1960s to tell Agnelli: "I want to talk to you, because you will always be in power."</p>
    <p>But tragedy struck the family regularly. Agnelli's drug addict son, Edoardo, jumped to his death from a motorway flyover in 2000, while his nephew and designated heir died from cancer at the age of 33. His distant relationship with his son and daughter prompted his second grandson, Lapo, to say this month: "He was an exceptional man, with unequalled talent; with me he was fantastic and a huge inspiration, but it was my good luck to be his grandson, not his son." After Agnelli's death from prostate cancer at 81, his surviving child, Margherita Agnelli de Pahlen, traded her shares in the family business for a one-off inheritance worth about $2bn, including a huge villa next to the presidential palace in Rome and a share in an art collection boasting works by Klimt, Bacon, Warhol and Lichtenstein.</p>
    <p>Of Margherita's three children by her first marriage, Lapo, Ginevra and John, Gianni Agnelli had picked the latter as his heir, grooming him to take over at <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/fiat">Fiat</ref>. Margherita also has five children from her second marriage to the Russian count Serge Graf von der Pahlen.</p>
    <p>She broke family ranks when she declared that she suspected assets had been hidden from her by Agnelli's advisers when she agreed to her share of his wealth. Instead of backing her, Margherita's mother, Marella, a former <hi rend="#i">Vogue</hi> model, and her son John, 33, turned on her. "I am very hurt as a son and surprised by this private matter, which was resolved in 2004 with everyone's consent and agreement," said John. Marella accused her daughter of betraying her father's wishes. Margherita said she was under so much pressure to back down that she also nearly leapt from a bridge.</p>
    <p>A final ruling on the case is expected in November. In the meantime tax police have opened an inquiry, reasoning that, if Margherita's claims are true, part of the Agnelli fortune may belong to them.</p>
    <p>The newspaper <hi rend="#i">Italia Ogg</hi>i claims Margherita and her mother have been jointly summoned by tax inspectors to answer questions this month. A spokesman for Margherita said yesterday she could not confirm or deny the report.</p>
    <p>Agnelli's old friends are rallying round. A pained Henry Kissinger, the former US secretary of state, said the idea that Agnelli ducked taxes was "inconceivable". "He did not live for money. This row risks discrediting a family whose history is intertwined with that of Italian industry. This man does not deserve the mud someone is throwing at him."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>