<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi's enemies happy that three female judges will decide his fate" author="John Hooper" date="2011-02-15" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/15/silvio-berlusconi-three-female-judges" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Catholic newspaper talks of 'nemesis' as it welcomes fact that all-female bench will judge Italian prime minister" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Catholicism,Europe,World news,Judiciary,Law,Sex work,Society" fingerprint="3a13b22e7a31e3df">
  <main>
    <p>One of the first publications to deliver an opinion on Silvio Berlusconi's indictment was the Catholic weekly, Famiglia Cristiana. "So," it said in an editorial, "the verdict is in the hands of three ladies. [The word that] comes immediately to mind is nemesis."</p>
    <p>But no one was claiming that the appointment of three female judges to sit at his trial was anything but an odd turn of fate. Judges in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> are assigned to cases strictly by rota.</p>
    <p>His adversaries could barely suppress their delight, however, while his followers did not hide their dismay.</p>
    <p>The announcement of the composition of the bench that will sit on 6 April came just two days after half a million people demonstrated against Berlusconi and in defence of the dignity of Italian women.</p>
    <p>Gaetano Pecorella, an MP for Berlusconi's People of Freedom party and formerly his lawyer, said the all-female bench was "the worst that could have been thought of".</p>
    <p>He added: "It really would be opportune for the principle of equality [between the sexes] to be respected in the courts too. There are offences, in particular sex offences, to which women are more attentive and sensitive, and also more motivated with respect to the extent of the sentence."</p>
    <p>The presiding judge will be Giulia Turri, who until a few months ago was one of a team of magistrates in Milan charged with overseeing investigations and holding committal proceedings.</p>
    <p>In that role, she presided at the pre-trial hearing of a high-profile case in 2007 involving the extortion of celebrities by paparazzi using compromising photographs.</p>
    <p>The defendant, Fabrizio Corona, who later served a 77-day sentence, was a business partner of talent scout Lele Mora, who is formally under investigation with two others, suspected of supplying prostitutes to Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>The prime minister's lawyers will not be encouraged by the fact that in 2008, Turri sent for trial a close Berlusconi associate. Massimo Maria Berruti was cleared of money laundering.</p>
    <p>Judge Carmen D'Elia (above) has had even closer contact with Berlusconi. She was on the bench at his trial for allegedly bribing judges in a takeover battle he won before entering politics. He was acquitted four years ago.</p>
    <p>Orsola De Cristofaro, the third judge, sat with D'Elia on another all-female bench in a sensational trial that ended last year with a 15½- year sentence being given to a senior Milan doctor convicted of performing unnecessary operations on patients to inflate his earnings.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>