<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi convicted over publication of wiretapped conversations" author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" date="2013-03-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/mar/07/silvio-berlusconi-convicted-publication-conversations" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian prime minister sentenced to one year in jail by Milan court, but no orders issued on carrying out term" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" fingerprint="7b3ba039d6c3f754">
  <main>
    <p>A Milan court has convicted former Italian premier <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> of breach of confidentiality for the illegal publication of wiretapped conversations related to a failed bank takeover in a newspaper owned by his media empire.</p>
    <p>The court sentenced him to one year in jail, but issued no orders on the carrying out of the sentence. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, it is rare for anyone to be put behind bars pending a possible appeal except in the case of very serious crimes such as murder.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's brother, Paolo Berlusconi, was convicted of the same charge and sentenced to two years and three months. Paolo Berlusconi is publisher of the Milan newspaper il Giornale that published the transcript of the conversation.</p>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's defence team had accused the court of seeking a speedy verdict for political impact.</p>
    <p>The verdict does not directly affect Berlusconi's eligibility to participate in a new government. Despite several attempts to pass such legislation Italy has no law banning people convicted of minor crimes from parliament. Berlusconi's centre-right coalition last week finished third in parliamentary elections that saw no clear winner. Talks on forming a new government are expected to begin on 20 March.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's charge relates to the 2005 publication of a wiretapped call that was part of an investigation into the Unipol financial services company's failed bid to take over the Banca Nazionale del Lavoro. The bid was blocked by Italy's central bank, contributing to the forced resignation of then-Bank of Italy chief Antonio Fazio.</p>
    <p>Wiretapped conversations are widely published in Italian media, despite the risks of prosecution.</p>
    <p>In a potentially more damaging case, a verdict is also nearing in Berlusconi's appeals trial on a conviction of tax fraud. Prosecutors have demanded the court uphold the October conviction and four-year sentence. They are also seeking a five-year ban from public office.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi is also on trial in Milan for allegedly paying an underage teenager for sex and lying to cover it up, with a verdict likely this month. Prosecutors in Naples are investigating him for corruption for allegedly paying an opposition lawmaker €3m (£2.6m) to join his party, a move that significantly weakened the previous centre-left government of Romano Prodi.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>