<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's replacement as Italy's PM: will it be the fixer or the technocrat?" author="John Hooper" date="2011-11-10" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/10/berlusconi-pm-successor-alfano-monti" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Profiles of contenders Angelino Alfano and Mario Monti, one from Sicily's poor south, the other from the rich north" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Mario Monti" fingerprint="5ec0c01accf1d5ed">
  <main>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">Angelino Alfano</hi>
    </head>
    <p>If <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> took a leaf out of the book of his old friend Vladimir Putin, and named as his successor a kind of Dmitry Medvedev <hi rend="#i">alla italiana</hi>, he could scarcely find a better candidate than Angelino Alfano.</p>
    <p>At age 41, Alfano is young by the standards of Italy's gerontocracy of career politicians. He is also clever.</p>
    <p>But he has been unswervingly loyal to the cause, and interests, of the outgoing prime minister.</p>
    <p>Secretary of Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People, Alfano was previously minister of justice.</p>
    <p>In this role, he oversaw the enactment of a law that was to be overturned as inadmissible by the constitutional court in 2009, granting immunity from prosecution to the four highest officers of state, including the prime minister. Earlier this year, Alfano sponsored another measure that could guillotine legal proceedings, which opposition politicians said was intended to stop any result in Berlusconi's trial for allegedly bribing his British lawyer, David Mills.</p>
    <p>Born at Agrigento in Sicily, Alfano left the poor south and its provincial ways to study law at the Catholic Sacro Cuore university in Milan, the sophisticated and rich north. He practised as a lawyer before entering parliament at 31 when Berlusconi returned to power in 2001.</p>
    <p>Four years later, he was made regional co-ordinator for Sicily of Berlusconi's earlier party, Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>Alfano's name has twice been linked with the mafia, but in two very different contexts.</p>
    <p>In 2002, the daily La Repubblica drew attention to an amateur video demonstrating that he attended the wedding, six years earlier, of the daughter of an alleged Mafia "godfather". Alfano said he'd been invited by the groom and did not know the bride's family. Last month, a petty criminal told prosecutors he heard in jail of a Cosa Nostra plot to "get rid" of Alfano because of his role in enforcing the tough regime imposed on mafia prisoners.</p>
    <head rend="h2">
      <hi rend="#b">Mario Monti</hi>
    </head>
    <p>It would be hard to think of anyone more unlike the flamboyant, scandalous and erratic outgoing prime minister than <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref>.</p>
    <p>His chief claim to fame lies in economic and financial circles, where he is impressively known for lending his name to the Klein-Monti model of monopolistic competition in the banking industry.</p>
    <p>The affable Monti is decidedly a technocrat's technocrat. Born in Varese north of Milan, he studied in Italy's financial capital at its business-oriented Bocconi university, and then did graduate studies in economics at Yale under a Nobel winner, the late James Tobin, another otherwise obscure economists whose name is also in the news, for his advocacy of a "Tobin" tax on foreign currency transactions.</p>
    <p>While Tobin was a neo-Keynesian, Monti is self-avowedly not. His liberal credentials are doubtless among the qualities that make him the markets' preferred choice as prime minister.</p>
    <p>After returning from the US, he taught economics in Turin before going back to the Bocconi, where he was rector for five years from 1989. In 1994, after Berlusconi led his new party to electoral victory, the TV magnate chose Monti as one of Italy's two EU commissioners. He took up his post in Brussels the following January, one day after the fall of Berlusconi's government.</p>
    <p>For four years, Monti was responsible for the internal market and held a range of financial portfolios. He made such a success that in 1999 the then government of Massimo D'Alema, a former Communist, asked him to stay on in Brussels.Until 2004, Monti's was competition commissioner. One of his initiatives was to launch monopoly proceedings against Microsoft.</p>
    <p>Monti is married with two children. He is a long-standing contributor to the Milan daily Corriere della Sera; his first article was published back in 1978.</p>
    <p>He is also a member of the influential but secretive Bilderberg conference of world business and political leaders.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>