<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi, Gaddafi and the viral blog | John Hooper" author="John Hooper" date="2009-09-09" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/sep/09/berlusconi-gaddafi-media-business-ownership" hostname="theguardian.com" description="John Hooper: It's rare that reporters find themselves at the centre of a national controversy. But that's what's just happened to me" categories="Opinion" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Muammar Gaddafi,Italy,Libya,Media,Media business,World news,Europe,Africa" fingerprint="202cc753daa5d744">
  <main>
    <p>Things move so quickly in Italy I really ought never to leave the country. On Sunday, I flew to London for the presentation of <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/6149414/Venice-in-peril-new-shipping-terminal-endangers-lagoon.html">Venice in Peril's new report</ref>, to which I was an adviser. Yesterday morning, I found I was at the centre of a national controversy over <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/sep/04/gaddafi-berlusconi-business">my last blog on this site</ref>.</p>
    <p>The blog went viral in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and the centre-left daily La Repubblica picked up on it at the weekend. On Monday, Berlusconi's TV group Mediaset put out a statement denying one aspect of what I had said. And on Tuesday, La Repubblica and Italy's other leading daily, Corriere della Sera, both carried extensive interviews prompted by my blog.</p>
    <p>In short, my blog said two things: that Berlusconi and the Libyan leader, Colonel <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/muammar-gaddafi">Muammar Gaddafi</ref>, had become business partners; and that the company in which they had a common stake was in turn a part-owner of a new satellite television station for the Maghreb, Nessma TV, whose target market includes Libya.</p>
    <p>Amid all the kerfuffle, nobody is denying the first of my assertions: that a subsidiary of the Gaddafi family's investment company has taken a 10% stake in Quinta Communications, a French company founded back in 1990 by Berlusconi and his longstanding friend and business partner, the Tunisian-born, French-based media tycoon <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarak_Ben_Ammar">Tarak Ben Ammar</ref>.</p>
    <p>So the Italian prime minister and the Libyan leader, who have to represent their respective nations in negotiations on such delicate issues as oil, terrorism, colonial reparations and illegal immigration, are co-owners of the same firm (albeit through subsidiaries). In an interview in yesterday's La Repubblica (not apparently available on its website), Ben Ammar confirms my figure for Berlusconi's new shareholding, of 22%.</p>
    <p>But he goes on to say that on the other point I was wrong. Quinta Communications "has no interest in, or link with, Nessma". His group's holding in the Tunisian-based satellite TV operation, he said, was through another, Italian subsidiary called Prima TV. The same point was made in Mediaset's press release which said that "Quinta Communications SA ... is not even among the shareholders".</p>
    <p>So what was the source of my information? Well, actually, it was Berlusconi's own company, Mediaset.</p>
    <p>On 21 May last year, the communications and image directorate of the prime minister's TV empire put out a press release about how it had bought into the North African satellite venture, originally launched by two local media entrepreneurs, the Karoui brothers. "After the signing of agreements," Mediaset's press release said, "the capital of Nessma is thus sub-divided: 50% Karoui &amp; Karoui World, 25% Mediaset Group, 25% Quinta Communication." <ref target="http://cs-comunicatistampa.blogspot.com/2008/05/mediaset-acquisisce-il-25-di-nessma-tv.html">You can see it here</ref> and at several other places on the web. I rang Mediaset yesterday to confirm that the press release was genuine, but the company did not return my call.</p>
    <p>The same version – that it was Quinta that had the stake in Nessma – appears from reports at the time to have been repeated at two events, in Tunis and Cannes, staged by Mediaset to launch the restructured firm.</p>
    <p>Yesterday, Ben Ammar called me from Paris. He said he thought the confusion had arisen because there were two companies of the same name. There is Quinta Communications SA in France, in which Berlusconi and Gaddafi have their interests. But then there is another, Quinta Communications Italia. This is 100% owned by Ben Ammar's Dutch-based holding company and owns a 95% of stake in Prima TV, which in turn has the holding in Nessma TV in north <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/africa">Africa</ref>.</p>
    <p>I do not doubt him when he says that means the Libyans do not have a stake in Nessma. But I did make the point that a great deal of misunderstanding could have been avoided had Mediaset not taken the strange course of naming as its new partner last year not the company making the investment (Prima TV), but that company's parent company (Quinta Communications Italia).</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>