<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Silvio Berlusconi Italy digital TV Mediaset Prodi RAI" author="John Hooper" date="2006-10-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/oct/13/italy.digitaltvradio" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy has approved a bill that would force one of Silvio Berlusconi's three TV channels to go digital at least three years before the country switches away from analogue. By John Hooper in Rome." categories="Media" tags="Media,Italy,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2fe891be9ab1cbd9">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's centre-left government has approved a bill that would force one of Silvio Berlusconi's three TV channels to go digital at least three years before the country switches away from analogue.</p>
    <p>RAI, the public broadcaster, RAI, would also lose one of its three free-to-air channels.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who was ousted as prime minister earlier this year by Romano Prodi, called the move "banditry". His Mediaset company said it was "tailor-made for political revenge" and could savage the group's profits.</p>
    <p>The idea is to let new players into a market dominated by just two corporations. Between them, Mediaset and RAI have 85 per cent of the audience.</p>
    <p>It would also reverse one of the most blatant anomalies in the former government's legislation, which failed to classify so-called tele-promotions as advertising.</p>
    <p>This is a form of marketing particularly favoured on the Mediaset channels, in which programme presenters abandon their normal role to urge viewers to buy specified goods or services.</p>
    <p>JP Morgan said that the newspaper groups owning Italy's two biggest dailies, Corriere della Sera and La Repubblica, might each be interested in tendering for a channel.</p>
    <p>Paolo Gentiloni, the communications minister, said the proposed law would require Mediaset and RAI to abandon their existing frequencies within 15 months of its approval by parliament.</p>
    <p>That could mean the two channels - almost certainly the left-leaning RAI 3 and Mediaset's Rete 4 - going digital at the end of 2008. The bill puts back Italy's analogue switch-off to 2012.</p>
    <p>Mr Gentiloni's bill is in large part a response to a law that took effect two years ago when Mediaset's owner was also the Italian prime minister.</p>
    <p>The then government argued that the law opened the air waves to competition by speeding up the changeover to multi-channel digital TV. Opposition critics said it consolidated the existing duopoly and enhanced Mediaset's position within it.</p>
    <p>Most controversially, the 2004 law allowed any one media concern a share of up to 20 per cent of the overall advertising market. But the market was so generously defined that Mediaset did not exceed the limit, even with two-thirds of the commercials on Italian television.</p>
    <p>The centre-left government's bill would cap the share of Mr Berlusconi's group at 45 per cent.</p>
    <p>MPs of Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party have vowed to fight the bill clause by clause through parliament, and since Mr Prodi's coalition has a majority of just one seat in the upper house, they could well secure important changes.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 7278 2332.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>