<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi trial outcome delayed for years by court" author="Sophie Arie" date="2003-05-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/may/17/citynews.silvioberlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, was released from the threat of an imminent corruption conviction after an Italian court made a surprise decision that could delay his trial for years. By Sophie Arie." categories="Media" tags="Media business,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Television industry,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7a82c91f3fa2c7b4">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, was released from the threat of an imminent corruption conviction yesterday after an Italian court made a surprise decision that could delay his trial for years.</p>
    <p>The court said that it was separating the prime minister from the rest of the defendants in an ongoing bribery trial, and would be rescheduling Mr Berlusconi's trial from next week.</p>
    <p>There had been fears that the whole trial could be dragged out endlessly as the prime minister claimed he was too busy to attend forthcoming hearings. The court's decision is seen as a way of avoiding such delays and allowing the trial of his co-defendants to be wrapped up relatively quickly.</p>
    <p>Before the court's decision, Mr Berlusconi had faced the threat of a corruption conviction being handed down while <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> held the EU presidency later this year, as the three-year trial was drawing to a close.</p>
    <p>Now his trial is set to last several more years - after which the statue of limitations may save him from a conviction.</p>
    <p>The billionaire prime minister, who could face a prison sentence over allegations that he bribed judges to swing a multi-million-pound merger deal in the 1980s, has denied the charges and said he has "never done anything immoral or that could cause damage."</p>
    <p>The case was the most serious among scores of other investigations into the prime minister's business dealings. He has been cleared in several cases because of the statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>Since he made history earlier this month by becoming the first serving Italian prime minister to appear at his own trial, Mr Berlusconi has failed to turn up to two hearings. His aides say he has not got time to attend.</p>
    <p>Yesterday Mr Berlusconi said he would continue to attend his trial until it became clear that he "probably ought to receive a medal rather than the opposite".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi had proposed that the Italian constitution be changed to reintroduce parliamentary immunity, which would have halted the trial. The court's decision now makes that less likely.</p>
    <p>Some, however, have pointed out that while Mr Berlusconi may welcome a delay to the outcome of his trial, a speedy verdict on his colleagues may not be so welcome.</p>
    <p>One of the defendants, Mr Berlusconi's political ally and a former defence minister, Cesare Previti, has already been sentenced to 11 years in a separate but similar bribery case.</p>
    <p>Judgment on Mr Berlusconi's friends, possibly within weeks, could taint him by association right up until the verdict on his own conduct is returned.</p>
    <p>"This is a trap," said Carlo Taormina, a defence lawyer and a member of Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party. "By separating the trials, I think the judges want to hang Berlusconi out to dry for a long time."</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's lawyer said he could not understand the court's decision, because the prime minister had already agreed to attend a rescheduled hearing next week.</p>
    <p>"It seems bizarre to me that the court couldn't wait seven more days," he said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>