<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi: Match-fixing trial is 'unfair'" author="Staff; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" date="2006-07-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2006/jul/13/newsstory.acmilan" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi, president of AC Milan, is unsurprisingly unhappy at the prospect of his club being relegated and his television station losing revenue." categories="Football" tags="Football,Sport,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Match-fixing" fingerprint="3f608125d0633f2f">
  <main>
    <p>AC Milan president <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has launched a fierce attack against the ongoing match-fixing trial in Serie A.</p>
    <p>Milan are among four Italian top-flight clubs - along with Juventus, Fiorentina and Lazio - that face possible relegation if found guilty of wrongdoing. The verdict is expected to be announced tomorrow afternoon in Rome, but Berlusconi believes that relegation would not be a fair punishment for all the clubs involved.</p>
    <p>"The eventual punishments shouldn't hit players or penalise fans who have no responsibility whatsoever," Berlusconi said. "I am against relegation and I don't speak just as president of Milan.</p>
    <p>"Should Juve be relegated it would hinder other clubs that would lose the revenue they take when they play against a team like Juventus. One also has to think of the damage this would create to sponsors and televisions companies that have signed contracts with these clubs."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi also believes that the current trial is unfair. "The judges have not listened to all the telephone conversations," he said. "Not all the testimonies have been heard and the results on the pitch have given a different perception of what took place.</p>
    <p>"In all of this story there has never been a smell of money, that is why you cannot really speak of corruption in those terms."</p>
    <p>The former Italian prime minister is, however, hopeful that those who have breached the sporting code should pay. "Let's leave the players and the fans out of it and hit those who are really responsible, the executives and the referees," he said. "But with a serious and fair trial, different to what we are witnessing."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>