<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian media chief resigns in row over senate bill" author="John Hooper" date="2003-07-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jul/23/broadcasting.silvioberlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The head of Italy's state broadcasting corporation resigned minutes before the upper house of parliament approved a bill that critics say will enhance the power of Silvio Berlusconi's commercial TV empire. By John Hooper." categories="Media" tags="Television industry,Media business,Italy,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2bea49b6a2abcfc8">
  <main>
    <p>The head of Italy's state broadcasting corporation, RAI, announced her resignation last night, minutes before the upper house of parliament approved a bill that critics say will enhance the immense power of Silvio Berlusconi's commercial TV empire.</p>
    <p>Lucia Annunziata, the president of a board which is set to be removed by the bill, said: "The only way to respect the will of parliament and the interests of RAI is to allow for the early formation of a new board under the rules of the new law."</p>
    <p>But, in a clear reference to Mr Berlusconi's double role as media tycoon and prime minister, she said RAI was in a precarious situation in a market "distorted by conflict of interest".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who owns all three main commercial channels, is also - as prime minister - ultimately responsible for the wellbeing of the state broadcaster's three channels. The opposition argues that the bill passed last night after a stormy passage through the senate blatantly favours the interests of Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset group.</p>
    <p>Among other things, it allows Mediaset to keep all three of its free-to-air channels, despite a ruling by Italy's highest court that one of them should be put on satellite; to raise the limit on its overall advertising revenue; to abolish curbs on the broadcasting of profitable sponsored promotions, and to buy into the newspaper market.</p>
    <p>The ethical questions posed by his extraordinary influence over what Italians can see and hear surfaced earlier this month when the main RAI evening news bulletin failed to broadcast the insulting remarks he made in the European parliament to the German MEP who challenged him over his apparent conflict of interest.</p>
    <p>Last night, shortly after the senate passed the government's communications bill, the chamber of deputies, the lower house, approved a separate measure intended to deal with the conflict of interests question. This too has come in for savage attack from the opposition.</p>
    <p>The bill contains a clause barring from high office those who manage companies, but not those who own them - a provision which critics say was specifically introduced to let Mr Berlusconi off the hook. He controls Mediaset through a stake of almost 50 per cent, but no longer holds executive office within the group.</p>
    <p>One opposition MP called the conflict of interests bill "a symbol of, and metaphor for, the sickness of our democracy".</p>
    <p>The government's position is that the communications bill will dispel all of these interrelated controversies by opening the way for digital terrestrial television and an increase in the number of channels available to viewers. But the leftwing opposition is not alone in believing that, on the contrary, it will help Mediaset to crush its competitors, inside and outside television.</p>
    <p>Paolo Serventi Longhi, secretary of the Italian national press federation, said the measure would act to "the detriment of RAI and the written press". It was "a licence to kill off newspapers".</p>
    <p>The new communications bill was sent to the chamber of deputies for a third reading. Ms Annunziata said she would step down on the day it passed its final parliamentary hurdle.</p>
    <p>The conflict of interest bill has effectively completed its passage through the legislature and is expected to become law by the end of the month.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>