<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Letter: Berlusconi on a collision course" author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" date="2008-06-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/28/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Letters: The decree has shown that Berlusconi's transformation into a serious statesman is just an illusion" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2fa8dabdd423df7e">
  <main>
    <p>You report (Berlusconi tells Vatican to lift ban on taking communion, June 23) the Italian prime minister's informal and relatively trivial request to a bishop in Sardinia to change the Vatican rule that prevents those - like Berlusconi - who have divorced and remarried from taking communion. You refer in passing to the fact that Berlusconi spent a week "seeking to suspend his trial for allegedly bribing the British lawyer David Mills while preparing a blanket law which would give himself immunity from all prosecution".</p>
    <p>This seems to us much more worthy of detailed coverage. A government decree suspending all "less urgent trials" - including the Mills trial and the trial against police involved in alleged acts of brutality against protesters during the G8 summit in Genoa in 2001 - with the excuse of the need to free up time for more urgent ones, has been approved by the senate. It will be examined now by the chamber of deputies. The Consiglio Superiore della Magistratura - the highest judicial body - has warned that Berlusconi's decree would suspend more than half of all trials. Berlusconi's decree has created tensions with his rightwing allies, put him on a collision course with the president and attracted criticism from quarters ranging from Italy's main Catholic weekly, Famiglia Cristiana, to Amnesty International. The decree has shown that Berlusconi's transformation into a serious statesman is just an illusion. His priority seems to remain securing immunity for himself through carefully tailored laws, and by constantly attacking the work of prosecutors and judges. <hi rend="#b">Franco Bianchini, Matteo Morandi and Viviana Perino</hi><lb/> Leicester</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>