<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Snap decisions" author="Anna Masera" date="2007-04-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2007/apr/20/itsvallettopoli2therevenge" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Anna Masera: Italy has found itself in the midst of another paparazzi scandal, as Silvio Berlusconi threatens to sue a magazine for violation of privacy." categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7a83514eb914c655">
  <main>
    <p>It's <ref target="http://commentisfree.theguardian.com/anna_masera/2007/03/what_is_worse_for_italy.html">Vallettopoli</ref> II: The Revenge. "Silvio paparazzato" (Silvio photographed by the paparazzi) ran the headline on <ref target="http://qn.quotidiano.net/politica/2007/04/19/6601-silvio_paparazzato_sardegna.shtml">Quotidiano.net</ref>, the online network of three major Italian newspapers (La Nazione, Il Giorno and Il Resto del Carlino). But watch out: there are two Silvios. This time it's not Silvio Sircana. It's <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article1673854.ece">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
    <p>It is only a couple of weeks since the <ref target="http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/03/30/news/journal.php">scandal</ref> of photographers blackmailing public figures with compromising pictures crept off the front pages and Silvio Sircana (the Italian centre-left government's top spokesman, forced to admit that he addressed a transsexual prostitute from the window of his car) returned to his usual post. But now Italian magazine Oggi has published photographs of Berlusconi entertaining himself with five young women at his villa in Sardinia. This time, there was no blackmail. But there's a warped "political" twist to the matter: Oggi, owned by publisher RCS (Rizzoli Corriere della Sera) which is generally seen to favour the centre-left coalition, is the same magazine that bought the Sircana pics at a high price but refused to publish them.</p>
    <p>The Italian privacy authority has opened an investigation and the centre-right former premier and media tycoon is ready to sue for violation not only of his privacy, but also of his private property - even if the paparazzi say they didn't trespass, they simply zoomed in. But Berlusconi is irritated: earlier this year his unhappy wife <ref target="http://commentisfree.theguardian.com/open_thread/2007/01/post_1033.html">humiliated</ref> him into a public apology for flirting with TV showgirls. And now this: one of the girls recognisable in the pictures appeared on TV in a series of Big Brother. She admitted being there and said it was a reunion of <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forza_Italia">Forza Italia</ref> (Berlusconi's political party) fans.</p>
    <p>Oggi's editor in chief justified the disparity of treatment saying that Sircana's pictures were unpublishable. That is to say that a politician seen with a transsexual prostitute is not acceptable, but an aged politician seen with a girl young enough to be his granddaughter sitting on his lap, or holding hands in the park, is.</p>
    <p>"Those images show more tenderness than passion," writes Massimo Gramellini on <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/speciali/elezioni2006/default.asp">La Stampa</ref>, who portrays Berlusconi as an old man who has lost his macho appeal.</p>
    <p>The questionable issue is Oggi's choice to publish these pictures, after choosing not to publish the others. "Privacy is not like our mother. There is not just one privacy: there are at least two," warns Gabriele Canè on Quotidiano.net, referring to the fact that the editor of Oggi decided to go ahead and publish Berlusconi's compromising pictures. And one could add that there are also at least two kinds of Silvio. "This scoop couldn't make things worse for his wife. Her relationship with her husband is already down the drain ... And anyway, the context of the pictures is joyous," justifies Oggi referring to Silvio, the former premier. Why, was the other Silvio, the government's spokesman, sad?</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>