<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Disguise in love - and he's called Berlusconi" author="Barbara McMahon" date="2006-07-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jul/30/italy.barbaramcmahon" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Renowned for his flamboyant nature, Italy's former Prime Minister, Silvio Berlusconi, staged a typically over-the-top surprise for his wife's 50th birthday that relied heavily on her ability to enjoy his sense of humour, it was revealed last week." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7687d3283a4ed4a3">
  <main>
    <p>Renowned for his flamboyant nature, Italy's former Prime Minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, staged a typically over-the-top surprise for his wife's 50th birthday that relied heavily on her ability to enjoy his sense of humour, it was revealed last week.</p>
    <p>The 69-year-old billionaire sent his wife, Veronica Lario, to Morocco, claiming to be too busy to join her. But secretly he arrived on another flight, disguised himself as a traditional gnawa dancer and was the star attraction of a cabaret held in her honour in a Marrakesh restaurant. According to the newspaper Aujourd'hui Le Maroc, the former actress was unaware her husband was in the cabaret act.</p>
    <p>'One dancer stood out, in his blue costume and with a blue handkerchief wrapped around his face,' reported the paper. 'He seemed particularly interested in the bella signora, and sprang in front of her like a warrior and invited her to dance. She resolutely refused.' But a scene was averted when Berlusconi whipped off his disguise, took a diamond necklace out of his pocket and sang 'Happy Birthday' to her.</p>
    <p>It was the final surprise of a two-day trip for the glamorous former first lady - she only realised her destination was Morocco when her private plane landed. She was taken to the terrace of the Cafe de France overlooking Jemaa el-Fna square for mint tea, where seven veiled women in Berber dress approached her, looking her up and down and openly commenting on her appearance. Lario was discomforted until the women removed their veils to reveal themselves as her closest friends, sent in on yet another private aircraft.</p>
    <p>The women were at the Dar Marjana, a restaurant noted for its musical shows, when Berlusconi, formerly a cruise ship crooner, appeared.</p>
    <p>Friends said Lario had been down in the dumps because her eldest daughter is away, studying in America, and the trip had 'lifted her spirits'.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi and Lario married in 1990 and have three children, but rarely appear together in public. Lario has said she does not see her husband often, due to his political and business commitments.</p>
    <p>The Italian newspaper Corriere della Sera called the birthday another example of Berlusconi's 'exuberantly creative imagination'. It noted that the party returned to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> in three private planes. 'After all, a nice surprise is always nicer when you can do it in style,' said writer Paolo di Caro.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>