<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="The Observer Profile: Silvio Berlusconi" author="Ed Vulliamy" date="2008-01-27" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jan/27/italy.edvulliamy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Ed Vulliamy: Former Prime Minister and media mogul Silvio Berlusconi is energetically orchestrating his political comeback after the collapse of the current regime. No stranger to scandal, the charismatic and eccentric billionaire is still a strong contender" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7faad26f9256cf09">
  <main>
    <p>Incredibly, only 18 months since half of the nation was euphoric at getting rid of him, Italy is now considering a reprise for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and his new People of Freedom party following the resignation last Thursday of Prime Minister Romano Prodi.</p>
    <p>Already on Friday, Berlusconi was out on the stump in Naples, demanding snap elections in April, and suggesting that his dream was to follow the example of Tony Blair, 'stay for three years, modernise Italy' before handing over to an 'Italian Gordon Brown'. In a typical flourish, he claimed that the people were 'asking for him'. Opinion polls suggest that he might well be right, and he stands a good chance of returning to power.</p>
    <p>Perhaps Berlusconi is viewed as a man for a crisis - for Italy is certainly facing one or two. Even Italians, who rightly pity the way others live, lament the malaise. It does Italy no good to have rubbish piling up in Naples because the Camorra, seemingly involved in the collection, refuses to be bowed. It hurts Italy's pride to be overtaken by Spain's economy and have its seat at the G8 questioned. 'We have lost a little of our will for the future,' admits Walter Veltroni, mayor of Rome and Berlusconi's next probable opponent.</p>
    <p>Perhaps it is also now fashionable to hanker for 'corporate' political leaders - the idea that because billionaire Berlusconi runs a conglomerate, he will run Italy with the same guile and gusto. Then there is his eccentricity: kissing the bride at a Muslim marriage, calling a German Euro-MP a Nazi and commending his wife's sexual appetite to the Danish Prime Minister. This is the sort of thing for which he is known as il cavaliere, though the nickname was bestowed by his friend and godfather to one of his daughters, Bettino Craxi, Prime Minister from 1983 to 1987.</p>
    <p>When he was first elected in 1994, Berlusconi was already a familiar face in Italian life. He was, as they say, ben introdotto - 'well-introduced' - in political circles, but disconnected from political practice. His fiefdom was that of flimsily clad girls bouncing around on TV quiz shows, AC Milan football club and the media empire he had built.</p>
    <p>But suddenly, 'Berlusca' decided politics was for him and established a party out of nowhere opportunistically named after the football slogan 'Forza Italia'. Berlusconi stood, apparently, for nothing; he was the postmodern politician for the consumer age. But how wrong Italy was to think that Berlusconi stands for nothing. His genius was to get elected on dancing girls and then ensure both that the ancien régime remained intact and that he put himself above the law, which was closing in on him.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi was born in Milan, in 1936, the son of a bank official and a secretary at Pirelli tyres, and funded university studies by working as a pianist and crooner aboard cruise ships (he composed an album of love songs for singer Mariano Apicella).</p>
    <p>His first enterprise was the construction of a new town outside Milan, 'Milano 2'. No one knows where he procured the capital, but an encounter with a friend from Sicily is submitted as a possibility, alongside his admission to the P2 masonic lodge, a dark circle connected to the Mafia, right-wing and state terrorism With profits from Milano 2, Berlusconi founded the Publitalia advertising company and thence Mediaset, his chain of TV channels, one empire selling to the other.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi dabbled in politics only to advance his interests. During the 1970s, anti-monopolies law forbade private television to be national and in 1984 judges closed some of Berlusconi's local stations for showing identical material. Berlusconi called on Prime Minister Craxi - and was later charged with bribing him handsomely - who promptly re-opened them by decree and a year later made the decree into law abolishing the restrictions.</p>
    <p>Craxi later fled to Tunisia, from multiple corruption charges, and died. But by then, Berlusconi was off the legal leash and his empire, under an umbrella, Fininvest, comprised 50 magazines, two national newspapers, a galaxy of TV channels and studios, a film distribution network, publishing and advertising empires and glamorous AC Milan.</p>
    <p>In 1990, working as a correspondent in Italy, I found myself interviewing families who lived in houses built by Berlusconi, read papers and magazines published by Berlusconi, went to work for Berlusconi past advertisement hoardings owned by Berlusconi, after which they watched TV made by Berlusconi and on Sunday followed their team, owned by Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>In Italy, it's not what you know, it's who you know. The same happens everywhere, but in Italy, 'raccomandazione' is a formalised system. One of the fascinating people 'recommended' to the top by Berlusconi was Marcello Dell'Utri, whom he met playing football while students in Milan.</p>
    <p>They couldn't have been more different: the crooner and the Opus Dei Sicilian with childhood contacts to future Mafia superbosses. The two parted company until the 1970s, when Dell'Utri took a call from his old friend aboard his yacht anchored off Sicily.</p>
    <p>It is not certain whether, as a result of the ensuing reunion, Dell'Utri became Cosa Nostra's ambassador to Fininvest, vice-versa, or both. Either way, he fast-tracked through the ranks to become director of Publitalia. And in 1994, Berlusconi knew exactly whose vote he needed to inherit the Christian Democrat hold on Sicily and much of the south: the block vote mobilised by Cosa Nostra. In 2004, the state court in Palermo convicted Dell'Utri of securing and delivering that vote, sentencing him to nine years (against which he has appealed).</p>
    <p>The Dell'Utri scandal had a British spin-off when it emerged last year that Berlusconi's Mafia go-between had been a director of London-registered Publitalia International (later Publieurope), one of the firms in Berlusconi's labyrinthine offshore empire put together by Fininvest's international lawyer, David Mills, estranged husband of Tessa Jowell.</p>
    <p>The empire itself was subject to many judicial investigations, and Mills co-charged alongside Berlusconi with fraud, but the charges were dropped in 2007 after Berlusconi suffered a timely heart attack and the case expired. In 1996, though, Italian police and the Serious Fraud Office had raided Mills's offices in London, confiscating 15 boxes of documents, only for then Prime Minister Berlusconi to make history by personally petitioning the High Court to try and stop their return to Italy. But he was overruled by Lord Justice Brown, who said he found a case to answer. Mills has vehemently denied all charges and there is no suggestion he knew of Dell'Utri's Mafia connection.</p>
    <p>London was a rare legal rebuff: Berlusconi's self-insulation from Italian law has been spectacular, finally passing a law giving Italy's Prime Minister blanket immunity from prosecution.</p>
    <p>Britain's main memory of Berlusconi is the holiday he afforded Tony and Cherie Blair at his villa in Sardinia, sporting a bandana after a hair transplant and arranging a fireworks display reading 'VIVA TONY'. Blair was doing more than holiday with Berlusconi - they needed to discuss their mutual enthusiasm for war in Iraq.</p>
    <p>For Britons, the encounter said more about Blair than Berlusconi. But it also demonstrated Berlusconi's ability to dazzle and charm in equal measure. For Berlusconi can be all things to all men, master of making the illogic logical. After the accession of Pope Benedict XVI, Berlusconi, with his empire of semi-naked dancing girls, supported the Holy Father, insisting that lay institutions should enforce 'family values' and religious devotion.</p>
    <p>Out of power, Berlusconi carries the air of a premier-in-exile, but preparations to return are entwined with scandal, such as the recent leaking of wiretaps showing that his Mediaset executives had consulted regularly with counterparts at state-owned RAI channels to manage news favourable to Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>And in his bid to get re-elected, Berlusconi woos his two unlikely allies, ex-fascist Gianfranco Fini's National Alliance and the separatist Northern League under wayward Umberto Bossi, both wary of il cavaliere</p>
    <p>But Italy under Berlusconi the businessman did not do what it might have done. The assets of state were not privatised as much as they were in Britain; the Christian Democrat sense of responsibilities of state were, oddly, upheld. Hospitals are generally excellent, child literacy higher than in Britain and street crime lower. Even the big football clubs are not for sale. Berlusconi has no plans to sell Milan to Texan meat-packers or Russian oligarchs. Moreover, while England were too bad to qualify, Italy may win Euro 2008, probably why her really wants another stab at power.</p>
    <p>After winning the 2006 World Cup, some of the players chanted at Prodi, when he visited the dressing rooms to congratulate them: 'Siamo tutti di destra!' - we're all on the right. The leader of the opposition was reported 'well pleased' at the news.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The Berlusconi lowdown</hi>
    </p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Born</hi> 29 September 1936 in Milan, Italy. Married to Veronica Lario, with three children. He was previously married to Carla Elvira Dall'Oglio for 20 years, with two children.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Best of times</hi> Becoming Prime Minister twice - most recently between 2001 and 2006. Making 51st place last year on the world rich list 2007. Italy's richest person, Berlusconi is a self-made billionaire with personal assets estimated at $11bn last year.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Worst of times</hi> Criticised for suggesting laid-off Fiat workers take illegal, non-tax-paying jobs to recoup losses. His first, short-lived cabinet coalition, the first right-wing administration in 34 years, collapsed after just seven months following internal disputes.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">What he says</hi> 'Aside from the good weather, we have beautiful businesswomen and also beautiful secretaries.' Reasons why foreigners should invest in Italy.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">What others say</hi> 'I demand a public apology, since I haven't received any privately... I chose not to leave space for marital conflicts, even when his behaviour created reasons to do so.' Veronica, his first wife, in an open letter printed in a newspaper following a public flirtation with lawmaker Mara Carfagna.</p>
    <p>'A man known for planetary gaffes.' Massimo D'Alema, a former political colleague.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> This article was amended on February 11 2008. An error introduced at the editing stage led to our describing Veronica Lario as Silvio Berlusconi's first wife in the article above. He was married for 20 years to Carla Elvira Dall'Oglio before his marriage to Veronica. This has been corrected.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>