<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi sidesteps Murdoch in Serie A" author="John Hooper" date="2004-07-01" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2004/jul/01/business.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Rupert Murdoch's loss-making Italian satellite venture, Sky Italia, was last night facing the sobering prospect of a war with Silvio Berlusconi's Mediaset empire in the key area of Serie A football. By John Hooper." categories="Media" tags="Media,Business,Italy,Television industry,Rupert Murdoch,Media business,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="1cac839bb328de5d">
  <main>
    <p>Rupert Murdoch's loss-making Italian satellite venture, Sky Italia, was last night facing the sobering prospect of a war with Silvio Berlusconi's Mediaset empire in the key area of Serie A football.</p>
    <p>Mediaset has made a guerrilla raid deep into traditional Murdoch territory, scooping up non-exclusive rights to the home games of three of Italy's most glamorous sides. The €86m (£57.5m) deal will allow Mr Berlusconi's media empire to broadcast on its digital channels league matches played at the grounds of Juventus, Inter and his own side, AC Milan, for the next three seasons.</p>
    <p>The aim is to make them available through an innovative pre-paid card system. At present, fans must sign a contract if they want to watch the key Serie A games on Sky Italia's satellite channels.</p>
    <p>But under plans being developed by Mr Berlusconi's executives and reported in yesterday's Italian media, viewers would be able to go to their local newsagent or tobacconist and buy a card that would give them access to a specific fixture. The current estimate is that a single match could be bought for about €2.</p>
    <p>Mediaset executives believe the scheme is the first of its kind anywhere in the world.</p>
    <p>Even more worryingly for Sky Italia is that as part of the deal Mediaset has secured an option on the satellite rights to the three teams' home games after the end of the 2006-07 season. Exercising the option would enable Mr Berlusconi's executives to block Sky Italia's access to most of the key Italian league games.</p>
    <p>In a deal clinched on April 30, News Corp's Italian satellite subsidiary was reported to have paid the three clubs almost €500m for the 2005-07 rights. Its executives made light of Mediaset's coup.</p>
    <p>A spokesman said Mr Murdoch's group "has to deal with competition, including this sort of competition, throughout the world. We are not daunted."</p>
    <p>Serie A football is nevertheless at the core of News Corp's Italian operation. Sky Italia has signed up all the big name teams and they provide it with an estimated 40% of turnover.</p>
    <p>In the six months to the end of March, the company added 300,000 subscriptions and is on course to reach 3 million by the end of the year. But it is still bleeding money: in the fourth quarter of last year, its losses stripped $106m (£59m) from News Corp's operating profit of $760m.</p>
    <p>Mediaset's incursion again raised questions about Mr Berlusconi's dual roles as prime minister and TV mogul. As part of an attempt to popularise digital television, his government is investing more than €100m in subsidising the cost of decoders.</p>
    <p>So far, only 500,000 have been sold, but the total is planned to reach 2m by the end of 2005. And, under the terms of legislation passed earlier this year, analogue television is to be switched off altogether at the end of 2006.</p>
    <p>Less than a year after that, fans may have no option but to watch their teams on Mr Berlusconi's channels.</p>
    <p>Several opposition politicians yesterday asked why Italy's public broadcaster, which is answerable to the media tycoon in his role as prime minister, had apparently played no role in the manoeuvring that led to this important deal.</p>
    <p>The agreement also provoked howls of outrage from some of the clubs who have been shut out. Lazio's president, Ugo Longo, called for Italy's monopolies commission to intervene. Roma's Franco Baldini said: "We are moving towards a three-club championship."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>