<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Naples street battles erupt" author="Tom Kington" date="2008-05-24" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/may/25/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Berlusconi's vow to take tough line on rotting rubbish crisis sparks angry battles with police" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Waste,Recycling,Environment,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="9e0b19c32597869b">
  <main>
    <p>Street battles raged in Naples yesterday between police and protesters opposed to a new rubbish dump only days after <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> set down a new hard line on a garbage crisis that has left piles of rotting rubbish on many city street corners.</p>
    <p>The new Prime Minister convened his first cabinet meeting in Naples last week and announced a decree opening new dumps, which will be designated military zones, and new incinerators in and around Naples. But by Friday hundreds of people living close to one site, in a quarry in the suburb of Chiaiano, were turning out to hurl stones at police and overturn a bus in protest.</p>
    <p>Ignoring threats to impose stiffer sentences on protesters, Neapolitans even tried to set up road blocks around Naples's fortress-like police HQ, when arrested protesters were taken there. Yesterday, following further clashes, some protesters built a street barrier out of rubbish skips and barbed wire.</p>
    <p>Naples' latest garbage crisis has seen sacks of refuse piling up since December as dumps run out because of stumbling local government, protests against new dumps and suspected Mafia infiltration of the collection business.</p>
    <p>'The exasperation of the people in Chiaiano about being chosen for Naples' urban rubbish does not justify violence,' said Ermete Realacci, shadow environment minister for the centre-left opposition. 'And this is not dangerous waste.'</p>
    <p>Experts counter that protests are fuelled by the suspicion the Naples Mafia, known as the Camorra, is inserting toxic waste into municipal garbage. 'If the government can clamp down on that, it's on the right path,' said cancer specialist Antonio Marfella. But others suspect that the Camorra itself supports the protests to perpetuate a very profitable crisis for its collection firms.</p>
    <p>The battles marked a second bout of violence this month. In another poor suburb, Ponticelli, the heady cocktail of Mafia and trash was augmented by an influx of gypsies in the past two years from Romania, who set up camp amid abandoned factories and goods warehouses and were soon scavenging for metal in roadside rubbish, in competition with locals.</p>
    <p>'We wanted to be charitable, but could not find a way to help them,' said teacher Irma Battimo. 'Then one night they stole the entire aluminium door of our apartment building.'</p>
    <p>When a gypsy girl was accused of trying to steal a baby from a local mother, three camps were firebombed with Molotov cocktails, allegedly by youths following Mafia orders. 'The message from the Camorra was, "The state is not here to resolve your problems, but we are", said a local who refused to be named.</p>
    <p>Other reports have suggested that anti-gypsy locals were angry to discover that a local boss, nicknamed 'The Mayor', was charging gypsy families €50 (£40) a month to camp. Faced with a rebellion, he ordered the attack. By Friday, after hundreds of gypsies were moved out, council workers were erasing any trace of the camps.</p>
    <p>Poverty and crime in Ponticelli ensured that recent inflammatory, anti-immigrant rhetoric from Berlusconi's allies found an outlet here, rather than in the rich north it was scripted for. 'This is a classic guerra fra poveri, a war among the poor,' said Battimo.</p>
    <p>When Diego Maradona won the Serie A title for Napoli in 1990 and Bill Clinton jogged the seafront during the 1994 G7 summit, Naples was headed for the same rebirth as its Mediterranean cousin Barcelona. Maradona's downfall, after accepting one too many lines of cocaine, was an early warning. But the Camorra could be ignored as long as it remained in the suburbs, amid the garbage piles, far from the seafront villas of the city's rulers, who still trot out the mantra 'Naples really is the most beautiful city in the world'.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi said he would tackle the garbage crisis 'as if it were an emergency caused by a earthquake or volcano eruption'. Cynics pointed out the danger of moving from inaction to overreaction, recalling how state funding that poured in after the Naples earthquake in 1980 was often pocketed by the Camorra.</p>
    <p>For one police officer, the solution is simple. 'You stop the Camorra with better sentences, more guarantees of jail time, more police on the streets and less bureaucracy to keep them behind their desks,' said Cristiana Mandara, head of the Fugitive section at the Naples Flying Squad. Mandara, 38, hit the headlines in December with her capture of boss Edoardo Contini, and now has her sights on the Camorra's two most famous fugitives, Antonio Iovine and Michele Zagaria, bosses of the Casalesi clan active around Caserta outside Naples.</p>
    <p>Caserta is home to the region's real rubbish crisis, where clans have for years buried toxic waste taken off the hands of northern industrialists. It was fitting that the gypsies who fled the Molotovs in Ponticelli were last reported setting up camp under the same Caserta bridges.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>