<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Anna Masera: Arrivederci, George" author="Anna Masera" date="2008-06-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/jun/13/italy.georgebush" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Anna Masera: The US president's farewell tour of Rome took in protests, the Pope and some horseplay with Silvio Berlusconi" categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,George Bush,European Union,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="37c8413591c9ef25">
  <main>
    <p>"Bush on a Roman Holiday? We preferred Gregory Peck." The banner, referring – in strict Roman dialect – to the 1953 William Wyler movie starring Peck and Audrey Hepburn, stood out as an amusing note at the anti-Bush demonstration yesterday in Rome that accompanied the arrival of the American president in his last official <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/redazione/cmsSezioni/esteri/200806articoli/33640girata.asp">visit</ref> to Italy.</p>
    <p>A little more than two thousand protesters held a <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/indrasensi/2571191980/">colourful march</ref> in the centre of Italy's capital, animated by anti-war posters and slogans: "Bush and Berlusconi band of assassins, resistance has no boundaries"; "Bush, executioner"; "No more on the side of unjust wars"; "Italy leave Afghanistan and Lebanon". Some protesters wore striped inmate-like work clothes and cardboard masks representing Bush, Dick Cheney and Condoleezza Rice, many waved the rainbow peace flag, but also the Cuban one.</p>
    <p>But with all eyes fixed on the Obama-McCain race, the Italian goodbye to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/george-bush">George Bush</ref> as American president was not a hostile one: "Ciao, George" say most headlines in the media. Implying, "now, let's move on". And even the demonstration against this US administration and its Italian ally with its centre-right government was peaceful and uneventful. The real turmoil came from passersby and scooter or car drivers, angry about the increased traffic and difficulty in finding parking due to stricter security around town.</p>
    <p>Security will be even more strict today when Bush pays a visit to the <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7452166.stm">Pope</ref> at the Vatican ("Wouldn't it be eventful if he chose the occasion to convert to Catholicism?", whisper newspaper and TV news editors, desperately in search of a bigger audience).</p>
    <p>Yesterday, he visited first the Italian president Giorgio Napolitano, then premier <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. The topics of discussion were sanctions against Iran's nuclear programme (European allies have to decide whether to back Washington's request) and Italian participation in the so-called "five plus one" negotiating team.</p>
    <p>Italy is the European ally with the largest volume of business in Iran and wants to enter the group of six negotiating countries, composed of the five members of the UN security council (the US, Russia, China, Great Britain and France), plus Germany. The US always seemed open to including Italy, but the White House yesterday suggested that Italian ambitions are "not realistic". National security counsellor Stephen Hadley, however, said that on the subject Bush is "listening" and has made no decision.</p>
    <p>In fact yesterday in Rome, jumping from one appointment to the other, Bush seemed more interested in leisure than politics. At a photo opportunity before a sumptuous dinner, after a final press conference in which they pledged mutual friendship and a similar outlook, Bush and Berlusconi jokingly kissed each other on both cheeks. When the US president shook hands with him vigorously, the Italian premier pretended to faint in pain. Then, recovering, he showed off his biceps in Popeye-like style and asked Bush to verify their strength. Bush reassured him, tongue-in-cheek: "<ref target="http://www.asca.it/moddettnews.php?idnews=762115&amp;canale=ORA&amp;articolo=BUSH:%20BERLUSCONI,%20'TOUCH%20HERE'.%20PRESIDENTE%20USA,%20'YOU%20ARE%20STRONG'">You are very strong</ref>".</p>
    <p>No wonder the attention of the Italian media was drawn to the first lady, <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/redazione/cmsSezioni/esteri/200806articoli/33667girata.asp">Laura Bush</ref>, considered far more interesting than her husband. However, Italians couldn't help noticing that whoever fixed her busy schedule made the unforgivable mistake of having her show up at two different events on the same day - the international conference on Afghanistan in Paris and the world food programme event in Rome - wearing the exact same clothes. Fashion critics couldn't believe their eyes.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>