<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="'A grave state of intimidation'" author="John Hooper" date="2004-02-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/feb/05/worlddispatch.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The degree of influence wielded by Silvio Berlusconi over state-owned broadcaster RAI is coming under increasing scrutiny. John Hooper explains." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Television industry,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3bb241beb386c78b">
  <main>
    <p>The BBC is not the only public broadcasting service to find itself in the eye of a storm.</p>
    <p>In Italy, the chairwoman of the board of governors of RAI, the country's state-owned TV and radio network, is under pressure to step down in a row that goes to the heart of the continuing dispute over Silvio Berlusconi's dual role as media tycoon and political leader.</p>
    <p>It has long been clear that Mr Berlusconi, who owns all three of Italy's biggest commercial TV channels, also exercises an influence over what RAI transmits.</p>
    <p>But the same could be said of every prime minister since the corporation's foundation, and the presumption has always been that his influence, like theirs, was strictly passive.</p>
    <p>Like public broadcasters in many European countries, RAI's executives do not need to be told what is expected of them.</p>
    <p>They anticipate the sensibilities of their political masters and, since Mr Berlusconi came to office three years ago, have done so with such assiduousness that RAI frequently outstrips the prime minister's Mediaset network in its tact.</p>
    <p>When, for example, Mr Berlusconi caused uproar in the European parliament by likening a German MEP to a Nazi concentration camp guard last year, it was RAI's flagship evening news bulletin, and not Mediaset's, that decided viewers ought not to hear what he said.</p>
    <p>The most blatant pressure exerted by Mr Berlusconi on the public broadcasting service came when he said that revered veteran commentator Enzo Biagi and another RAI presenter, Michele Santoro, had made "criminal use" of airtime. Soon afterwards, they vanished from RAI, never to reappear.</p>
    <p>Earlier this week, RAI's chairwoman, Lucia Annunziata - who was criticised by Mr Santoro for not defending him - said that Mr Berlusconi did more than just hint.</p>
    <p>"I know for certain that Berlusconi picks up the telephone and rings the members of the board to suggest appointments and influence decisions on programmes," she told a group of foreign correspondents.</p>
    <p>"The prime minister contacts RAI executives directly to tell them what to do and what not to do. This is at least what is said to me to justify certain decision taken in the corporation."</p>
    <p>Her words unleashed a torrent of indignant denials from members of the board, which represents the parties that make up Mr Berlusconi's coalition.</p>
    <p>"I defy her to tell me that I have been put under pressure," said Marcello Veneziani, a philosopher and commentator. Sociologist Francesco Alberoni added: "Berlusconi has never telephoned me to ask anything about appointments or programmes."</p>
    <p>At a meeting on Wednesday, the governors asked Ms Annunziata to resign, saying that the relationship of trust on which the board depended had "deteriorated". But she refused, and there - for the moment - the matter rests.</p>
    <p>Members of Mr Berlusconi's majority suspect that the chairwoman may have been playing politics herself.</p>
    <p>A bill, which critics say would enhance Mediaset's already vast influence, is currently being debated in parliament. The bill was thrown back to the legislature by Italy's president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, who refused to sign it.</p>
    <p>What is quite clear is that Ms Annunziata is not alone in believing that RAI is under siege. This week, the deputy editor of the evening news on its premier channel, Rai Uno, quit her job.</p>
    <p>Among other things, she complained that reports offering different points of view ought not to always give the government the last word.</p>
    <p>After a meeting of the corporation's journalists, a statement was released by their union. It referred to a "grave state of tension and intimidation" within the corporation, and said that freedom of information was under attack from an "ever more pliable management".</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>