<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="So Signor Berlusconi, let's hear about your new film" author="Stuart Jeffries" date="2007-06-20" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/filmblog/2007/jun/20/theselfstyledjesuschristof" hostname="theguardian.com" description="In an exclusive interview Silvio Berlusconi thrashed out some potential ideas for his upcoming film - you better believe it." categories="Film" tags="Film,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="ccf7507fa7c6ff84">
  <main>
    <p>The self-styled Jesus Christ of politics, Silvio Berlusconi, <ref target="http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/international/news/e3ib6d2c95cdf6b2ef334bb0d0ba335da9d">is to write a screenplay</ref>. What, the world wants to know, will it be about? "Me, of course, numbnuts," the former Italian prime minister told me in an exclusive interview at one of his many palazzi yesterday. "No offence. You see, I am the richest man in Italy, the best political leader in Europe, I own all the super-sexy football clubs, I have had such great cosmetic surgery I will be hotter than July for the next 100 years. I am a tip-top entrepreneur with two leering eyes for Lady Business, I am like your <ref target="http://blogs.theguardian.com/tv/2007/06/the_apprentice_its_all_over_no.html">Alan Sugar</ref> but with much bigger coglioni. Much bigger. No offence, Sir Alan.</p>
    <p>"I am like Churchill, Napoleon, Jesus all rolled into one with a nice happy ending. Maybe a little Hugh Hefner too. Maybe a lot. What a life! What a story! What an excuse for a bazonga fest with all those lovely Italian ladies I will be spending the next six months casting for leading roles! Am I right?"</p>
    <p>I ignored his question. So it will be a vanity project then? "You better believe it, sonny. I bankroll, I direct, I star. Heavens yes. Monica Bellucci? She's a super-hot lady all right. She will play my now-estranged wife. Dream come true. What's the point of having money if you can't make dreams come true? Am I right?"</p>
    <p>I ignored his question. Have you got a title yet? "I can't decide. The Greatest Story Ever Told or Veni, Vidi, Vici: the Imperial Progess of a Latter-day Caesar. Probably go with the first. So many morons don't know Latin today. The world is filled with morons. Morons and me. No offence."</p>
    <p>Will the film detail your many gaffes? "Sure will, numbnuts, sure will. You say gaffe, I say slapstick, I say straight-talking, I say box-office comedy gold. Like that time I <ref target="http://www.martinfrost.ws/htmlfiles/berlusconi5.jpg">stood behind the Spanish foreign minister and made cuckold gesture</ref> for the official photo? Who didn't laugh? Hilarious." That scene might not play so well in Spanish cinemas, though. "Good point, numbnuts. Maybe we cut that scene."</p>
    <p>Won't the fact that you've alienated many billions of people with your off-colour remarks undermine the film's earning potential from foreign box-offices. "You're talking about China, yes? Well, let me tell you this. I may have said that the <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4857226.stm">Maoist China boiled their children and spread them on fields as fertiliser</ref>, but that remark was taken completely out of context." What was the context? "You don't remember?" No. "Me neither. Probably cut that scene too."</p>
    <p>Didn't you also call a German MEP a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/eu/story/0,7369,990294,00.html">concentration camp guard</ref>? "Again, that remark was taken completely out of context. But you should have seen his head. Square is not the word. Actually it is. It was very square indeed. I hope these remarks wouldn't affect the box-office of my film in Germany." Probably would. "Maybe cut that scene too. This is going to be one short film."</p>
    <p>And who will do the catering for the film? "The British. My joke. You Brits can't tell prosciutto from poo. No offence, but you can't. Toad in the hole? You're kidding, right? Everything's one big joke to you numbnut know-nothing Brit assholes, isn't it? No offence."</p>
    <p>None taken. So tell me the plot. "Star rises in the east. Kings, shepherds, whatever follow it to Milan. I'm born in Milan. A stable, but in Milan. My God I work so hard, I'm like a crazy German. I become tip-top multi-platform businessman with fingers in many pies. And lots of lovely ladies, too. I win the Battle Of Jena, lose the battle of Waterloo. Then I get into politics. So many inverted commas conflicts of interest, so many inverted commas links to the mafia. But I rise like a phoenix. Later, I make speech to parliament about fighting the Nazis in the beaches, while smoking a big cigar. I win the war single-handed. I am draped with lovely Italian ladies. Credits roll. Sounds great, am I right?"</p>
    <p>I ignored his question. "You know I once went to New York? Told the Americans to invest in Italy because we have the most beautiful secretaries in the world? Everybody got a good laugh. True story." But wasn't that sexist and racist? "Mmm. Maybe. Cut that scene too. Want to sell this film to America."</p>
    <p>Who will play you? James Gandolfini is quite possibly now free of his commitments to <ref target="http://blogs.theguardian.com/tv/2007/06/who_spoiled_the_sopranos.html">the Sopranos</ref>? "That American sociopath mobster? There's only one man who can play me. Me. Maybe me and a CGI baby." Who will direct? "Maybe Mel Gibson. But he has no dress sense and unresolved anger issues. So maybe me. In fact definitely me. It's a good idea, yes?"</p>
    <p>I ignored his question. But haven't there been several films about your life already, including one by award-winning director Nanni Moretti called <ref target="http://film.theguardian.com/Film_Page/0,,1765900,00.html">Il Caimano</ref> (a kind of crocodile) in which he depicted you as a man capable of seducing the Italian people with a straight-talking persona that made them forget his dodgy dealings and troublesome past? "He completely misrepresented me. He played me, that bearded freak. No offence, Nanni, but what am I, a sociology professor? I am an international playboy with a tip-top perma-tan and a business empire that funds a new Armani suit every day. Look at that smile. That's not a sociology professor smile. That's a money smile, numbnuts. Pure money."</p>
    <p>Thank you Mr Berlusconi, for this insight into your world. "Any time, numbnuts. No offence. More prosecco, baby? To my film. See you at the premiere, yeah?" I ignored his question.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>