<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Grumpy old men" author="James Richardson" date="2006-03-21" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2006/mar/21/europeanfootball.sport" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Serie A: Milan megalomaniac Silvio Berlusconi and his Fiorentina counterpart Diego Del Valle have been fighting again. James Richardson titters from the sidelines." categories="Football" tags="European club football,Football,Sport,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="2ef090d492615353">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi reckons Diego Della Valle is 'out of his mind'. For his part, Della Valle thinks Berlusconi is a 'cartoon character on the brink of a nervous breakdown'. Given that the former controls Milan (and pretty much everything else in Italy), the latter owns Fiorentina and the two sides are set to take each other on this Saturday, I'd say we're in for an interesting week.</p>
    <p>Relations between these two men have never been idyllic - Della Valle headed the recent revolt by the smaller clubs at the enormous TV deals Italy's big three were being awarded (in Milan's case to themselves, as Berlusconi also owns the TV people) - but last Saturday they hit a new low after Berlusconi made an unscheduled appearance at Italy's version of the CBI, the Confindustria. Italy's very-probably-outgoing prime minister grabbed the mike to harangue Italy's business leaders - and footwear magnate Della Valle in particular - for not supporting his right-wing coalition. "Either a man like this is out of his mind or he's hiding something," declared Long John Silvio.</p>
    <p>"I urge Berlusconi's family to make him take him some rest. He appears on the verge of collapse" came the reply from Fiorentina's owner. It certainly sets Saturday's game up nicely and so do last weekend's results. For while their <hi rend="#i">padroni</hi> were calling each other out at the business do, both teams also managed to record big league wins on the football field.</p>
    <p>Milan warmed up for Saturday's clash with a 4-0 demolition of Udinese, a result which featured a brace from Andriy Shevchenko, two assists and a goal from Alberto Gilardino, and prompted yet another managerial change at the Friulian side. Out goes former Udinese player Nestor Sensini and his frontman Loris Dominissini, who'd managed an impressive two draws and four defeats in six games in charge, and in comes local hero Giovanni Galeone. His task? To try and rescue a club that started the season facing Barcelona in the Champion's League, but now lies just one point above the trapdoor marked 'Serie B'.</p>
    <p>Fiorentina, meanwhile, set out their stall with a more measured 3-1 defeat of Ascoli. The win keeps them one point clear in the race for Italy's fourth Champion's League spot with a game in hand - the game in question being last week's suspended match at Cagliari, the remainder of which the league (proprietor: A. Galliani, vice-president of Milan) have scheduled to be played tomorrow night, three days before they visit the San Siro. Ta very much.</p>
    <p>Fiorentina can take comfort from the fact that their rivals Roma face a trip to the Stadio Delle Alpi to face Juventus. Their hosts may have already sewn up this year's title but there's been no let-up so far from the Turin giants. In fact, judging by the way they tore through Livorno this weekend, they've already launched their bid to win the next one.</p>
    <p>By contrast, Roma made heavy weather of their 2-1 home win over southern strugglers Messina. Having scored early through Simone Perrotta's header, they showed all the finishing skills of a toddler confronted with a plate of broccoli. Countless crosses went begging until, 35 minutes in, Daniele de Rossi helped a Mancini free-kick find its way past the Messina keeper.</p>
    <p>The referee gave the goal, but urged on by the Messina players, De Rossi quickly admitted to the official that it shouldn't stand. Confessing to touching the ball with his outstretched hand, he then pleaded "but please don't book me for it". The referee duly let him off with a shake of the guilty appendage. Italians are all too aware they're not known as a particularly sporting bunch, so De Rossi's gesture brought a chorus of post-game praise from everyone but Messina's manager: "I expect they'll be giving him a medal next," grumbled Bortolo Mutti, extracting the humbug from his mouth to point out that De Rossi should have received an automatic yellow card, and that the Roma midfielder probably owned up to avoid a two-match ban (new rules in Italy this season having already seen a Serie B player suspended for failing to come clean in a similar incident).</p>
    <p>No worries Bortolo, because de Rossi is now set to miss at least two matches anyway. Ten minutes from time he went down screaming and clutching his ankle in scenes reminiscent of Francesco Totti's recent injury. Roma's doctors - who've only just finished taking the screws out of Totti's ankle - reckon that, unlike his captain, De Rossi's ligaments aren't damaged but he's likely to miss both Saturday's game with Juventus and the following weekend's do at Fiorentina, their rivals for fourth place. Given that Roma's injury list was already making an NHS dental queue look short, it's the last thing the <hi rend="#i">giallorossi</hi> need.</p>
    <p>Like a Phil Collins tribute band, Roma are used to playing against all odds. But it looks like they'll need an even bigger miracle than usual this weekend to get anything from Juve. I'll be live from the San Siro this Saturday with Milan v Fiorentina, otherwise see you back here in a week for a full and complete disclosure.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Weekend results</hi><lb/> Treviso 1 - 2 Cagliari<lb/> Livorno 1 - 3 Juventus<lb/> Chievo 4 - 1 Siena<lb/> Fiorentina 3 - 1 Ascoli<lb/> Internazionale 3 - 1 Lazio<lb/> Lecce 1 - 2 Parma<lb/> Reggina 0 - 2 Empoli<lb/> Sampdoria 0 - 2 Palermo<lb/> Udinese 0 - 4 AC Milan<lb/> AS Roma 2 - 1 Messina</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>