<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Leader: Italy's only hope of recovery is to vote out Berlusconi" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2006-04-08" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/apr/09/leaders.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Leader: There are no quick cures for Italy's sickness, but purging Silvio Berlusconi from the body politic would signal the start of recovery." categories="Opinion" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2bb2c0269cf2cf6d">
  <main>
    <p>'The sick man of Europe' is a title that has been passed around the Continent. Coined for Turkey's imperial decline at the end of the 19th century, it passed in the 1970s to Britain. A few years ago, it was Germany. Now it is Italy.</p>
    <p>The EU's fourth largest economy stood still last year. Average growth over the past five years has been less than 1 per cent. The public finances are in an appalling state. Not surprisingly, when Italians go to the polls today, they might be minded to punish Prime Minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> for their collective malaise.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is not wholly responsible for leading <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> down a blind economic alley. Structural problems gestate over decades. But he did promise, when elected in 2001, to stop the rot. He promised 'an economic miracle', enriching his fellow Italians with the business expertise that made him the country's wealthiest man. The flaw in the plan was that the media empire that made Mr Berlusconi rich was founded not in the field of open competition but in the backrooms of Italy's cronyist political establishment. Since coming to office, he has spent more energy protecting himself from prosecution than on modernising the economy.</p>
    <p>Italian society has traditionally thrived despite the corruption of its national leaders, functioning, instead, on good local government and strong family ties that have reduced pressure on the state to provide social services. But there are signs this, too, is changing. The birth rate is among the lowest in the Western world, while one in five Italians is older than 65. This demographic imbalance points to a coming pensions crisis. No party in the election has policies to confront the problem.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's rival at the ballot box is Romano Prodi, former Prime Minister and European Commission president. His lack of charisma is the exact counterpoint to Mr Berlusconi's exuberant showmanship. Both head fractious coalitions that, if elected, would find it hard to co-operate on radical reforms.</p>
    <p>But there is a decisive factor. Mr Berlusconi has not only neglected Italy's economy, but he has warped its politics. He controls 90 per cent of broadcast media, a grotesque conflict of interest. He has diminished public life, deploying personal slurs instead of policy debate. He embodies a culture of corruption that devalues democracy in Italy and, by extension, the rest of the EU, which has been forced to do business with him.</p>
    <p>There are no quick cures for Italy's sickness, but purging Silvio Berlusconi from the body politic would signal the start of recovery.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>