<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Anti-corruption prosecutors in Spain target Berlusconi" author="Giles Tremlett; John Hooper" date="2006-05-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/may/31/spain.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Former Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi is being targeted by anti-corruption prosecutors in Spain just two weeks after losing his right to immunity from prosecution." categories="World news" tags="World news,Spain,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="383a430f9b979754">
  <main>
    <p>Former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is being targeted by anti-corruption prosecutors in Spain just two weeks after losing his right to immunity from prosecution.</p>
    <p>Spanish courts are considering whether to reopen an investigation into alleged tax fraud that was formally suspended five years ago. The case involves Mr Berlusconi's holdings in Spain's Telecinco TV channel during the early 90s which were alleged to surpass the 25% limit placed on ownership of a single television station by Spanish law.</p>
    <p>Anti-corruption prosecutors have suggested Mr Berlusconi's companies owned more than 50% of Telecinco, breaching anti-trust laws and committing tax fraud along the way. Offshore front companies were allegedly used to warehouse holdings in Telecinco, which allowed the former Italian prime minister to maintain a majority share in the channel. Mr Berlusconi has denied any wrongdoing.</p>
    <p>Eight of his business partners and employees in Telecinco will go on trial in Madrid on Monday; they face prison sentences of up to 14 years for alleged tax and document fraud.</p>
    <p>The case opens as Mr Berlusconi also looks set to sail once more into stormy legal waters in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. A Milan court is due to open a committal hearing on Monday in which he is accused of bribing David Mills, the estranged husband of the culture secretary, Tessa Jowell. Both men deny the allegation.</p>
    <p>Prosecutors in Milan claim the billionaire Italian politician paid Mr Mills, his former legal adviser, £320,000 for withholding evidence in two trials involving Mr Berlusconi in the 1990s. In April, the British lawyer laid before the court recently found documents which, he said, "totally exploded" the prosecution's case.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's fate in the Italian courts, where he faces other allegations of tax evasion, false accounting and fraud, may depend on the centre-left government, led by Romano Prodi. If changes introduced by Mr Berlusconi's government are allowed to stand, some of the offences of which he is accused will be "timed out" by a statute of limitations before the courts can reach a verdict.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>