<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Strike over Berlusconi bill closes Italian courts" author="John Hooper" date="2004-11-25" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/nov/25/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy's criminal justice system ground to a halt when judges, prosecutors and defending lawyers went on strike to protest at a legal reform bill being steered through parliament by Silvio Berlusconi." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="fda995b76534c6d6">
  <main>
    <p>Italy's criminal justice system ground to a halt yesterday when judges, prosecutors and defending lawyers went on strike to protest at a legal reform bill being steered through parliament by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and his allies.</p>
    <p>For the judges and prosecutors yesterday's one-day stoppage was a last-gasp bid to prevent legislation they fear will curb the independence of the judiciary and prevent it pursuing allegations against corrupt politicians. The proposed law faces a final vote in the lower house on Tuesday.</p>
    <p>The National Magistrates' Association, which called the strike, said more than 80% of judges and prosecutors had stayed away from work. Only urgent criminal and civil cases were being heard in Italy's 163 courts.</p>
    <p>A letter signed by 4,500 of Italy's 8,000 magistrates, which was delivered to the justice ministry, said the bill would make them "less free and independent". The justice minister, Roberto Castelli, said the letter contained "blatant falsehoods".</p>
    <p>The confrontation is taking place as Mr Berlusconi's personal struggle with the courts is about to reach its climax. Next month a verdict will be passed on a case in which he has been accused of bribing judges.</p>
    <p>His government's legal reform bill is a response to longstanding complaints by defence lawyers about the structure of the legal system, which they argue has an in-built bias against defendants. At present, judges and prosecutors - both known as magistrates - share a single career structure that allows them to switch to and fro between the two disciplines.</p>
    <p>The bill would force magistrates to choose within five years of entering the profession whether they wanted to pursue a career as a prosecutor or a judge. But defence lawyers argue the changes do not make a clear enough division.</p>
    <p>The prime minister has long contended he is the victim of a politically motivated campaign by leftwing prosecutors. The bill would ban magistrates from belonging to political parties and force them to submit to psychological tests.</p>
    <p>The bill extends the powers of the justice ministry and imposes a hierarchical structure on prosecutors, which critics say would make them more susceptible to government influence. Fears about how these provisions might be used intensified this week after it became known that the two prosecutors who have brought Mr Berlusconi to court faced a new round of disciplinary proceedings.</p>
    <p>The government says the reform will improve Italy's slow judicial process. But the magistrates' association has repeatedly accused the government of cutting funds to the justice system. It has complained of a lack of computers, insufficient funds for lavatory paper and even rat infestations in courthouses.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Italy's parliament passed a building law yesterday that critics say is tailormade to legalise alterations made at Mr Berlusconi's luxury villa on the highly protected island of Sardinia.</p>
    <p>The law, which was pushed through the lower house and attached to a motion of confidence, pardons property owners for some work done without planning permission, even on protected land.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>