<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Former Italy PM Silvio Berlusconi in hospital for heart problem" author="Daniella Nimcevic; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" date="2016-06-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/07/former-italy-pm-silvio-berlusconi-in-hospital-for-heart-problem" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Seventy-nine-year-old is taken to hospital in Milan, and spokesperson says his condition is not life-threatening" categories="World news" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" fingerprint="7690830db3668584">
  <main>
    <p>Italy’s former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has been taken to hospital for tests after suffering mild heart trouble. A spokesperson said his condition was not life-threatening. </p>
    <p>The 79-year-old centre-right leader and billionaire media mogul, who was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/15/silvio-berlusconi-community-service-sentence-tax-fraud">convicted of tax fraud in 2013</ref>, was admitted to Milan’s San Raffaele hospital on Tuesday morning suffering from a “cardiac deficiency”, the spokesperson said.</p>
    <p>Citing sources within Berlusconi’s Forza Italia party, the AGI news agency reported that the hospital visit had been scheduled after he suffered slight discomfort on Sunday night. Berlusconi, who turns 80 in September, will undergo tests in the next few days to determine the proper treatment, a hospital statement said.</p>
    <p>It is not the first time Berlusconi has had heart problems. The one-time cruise ship singer, renowned for a party lifestyle that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/18/silvio-berlusconi-cleared-underage-sex-charges-rubygate-bungabunga-abuse-office-coverup">continued even during his time in office</ref>, had a pacemaker fitted in 2006 in a hospital in the United States.</p>
    <p>Since his <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/12/silvio-berlusconi-resign-italy-eurozone">resignation as prime minister in 2011</ref> and his subsequent tax fraud conviction, Berlusconi has lost much of his political influence.</p>
    <p>His once powerful centre-right coalition has become increasingly fragmented, and his preferred candidate for Rome mayor, Alfio Marchini, a real estate mogul, lost out in the first round of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/02/corruption-gripes-help-five-star-movement-top-italy-local-election-polls">elections last weekend</ref>.</p>
    <p>News of Berlusconi’s hospital stay pushed shares in Mediaset, the TV company owned by his family holding, up 2%. His business empire also includes AC Milan, and he has been in talks with a Chinese consortium to sell a majority stake in the club.</p>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#i">Reuters and Agence France-Presse contributed to this report. </hi>
    </p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>