<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Football: Silvio Berlusconi claims Andriy Shevchenko wants to return to AC Milan" author="Staff; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" date="2007-06-15" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2007/jun/15/newsstory.acmilan" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Milan owner Silvio Berlusconi claims Andriy Shevchenko wants to return to the San Siro and that he is determined to re-sign him." categories="Football" tags="Football,Sport,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="eb6893393eea8427">
  <main>
    <p>AC Milan owner <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> today claimed Chelsea striker Andriy Shevchenko wants to return to the San Siro and that he is determined to re-sign him. The Ukraine forward has been repeatedly linked with a return to the <hi rend="#i">Rossoneri</hi> over the last six months following a difficult first season at Stamford Bridge and Berlusconi has now underlined his desire to be reunited.</p>
    <p>Vice-president Adriano Galliani admitted earlier this month that Shevchenko's return would only happen if Chelsea gave the all-clear to sell the player. The Blues paid £30m to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> last summer for the 30-year-old, but Berlusconi believes the deal is still possible.</p>
    <p>"I like [Samuel] Eto'o, he is young, but I am a romantic and I prefer Shevchenko," said Berlusconi. "The last time I spoke to Galliani, which was a couple of days ago, the probability of Shevchenko returning to Milan was 80%. Had that percentage gone down, I'm sure Galliani would have told me.</p>
    <p>"I consider Sheva as my son. I have experienced important moments with his family, such as his father's heart operation and the birth of his son, who I'm a godfather to. Andriy is still young, he's got so many years of his career ahead of him. Sheva has a great desire to return. There are no obstacles linked to his salary because he would be winning a similar fee as that of our top players. We will have to negotiate his transfer with Chelsea, each club looks at their own interests. I really believe Shevchenko would be an ideal player to complete our attacking line."</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Mario Melchiot</hi> has become Chris Hutchings's third signing at Wigan, joining on a free transfer from Rennes. Dutch defender Melchiot, formerly of Chelsea and Birmingham, passed a medical and agreed personal terms at the JJB Stadium yesterday but requested that his unveiling be delayed so he could inform Rennes.</p>
    <p>"Mario is someone we've been keen on for some time," said Hutchings. "He's an experienced and versatile player and he's another real quality addition to the squad."</p>
    <p>Despite playing 56 games in two seasons for Birmingham, Melchiot struggled to win over the supporters at St Andrew's and was among those blamed for the club's relegation from the Premiership in 2006. He was an ever-present for Rennes last season, however, helping them to fourth in the table and a Uefa Cup finish.</p>
    <p>He follows Titus Bramble and Antoine Sibierski, both of whom signed from Newcastle, in joining Wigan since Chris Hutchings took over on May 14. Major European sides including Lyon, Paris St Germain, Marseille, Roma, Lazio and Olympiakos had all been believed to also be tracking him.</p>
    <p>Sheffield United have agreed a deal with Turkish champions Fenerbahçe for striker <hi rend="#b">Colin Kazim-Richards</hi>. The Istanbul side, managed by Zico, will pay £1.275m, earning the Blades a healthy profit on the £150,000 they splashed out when signing the 20-year-old from Brighton last August.</p>
    <p>A number of Turkish clubs were reportedly interested in securing the services of Kazim-Richards, who made his senior debut for Fatih Terim's national team in a goalless draw against Brazil earlier this month. Despite being born in London he is eligible to play for Turkey through his Turkish Cypriot mother.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>