<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Emine Saner on women in politics" author="Emine Saner" date="2008-04-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2008/apr/18/women.spain" hostname="theguardian.com" description="This week, Spain got its first female-majority cabinet - a huge leap forward for equality. Then Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi derided them as 'too pink'. So who is winning the argument when it comes to women in world politics, asks Emine Saner" categories="Politics" tags="Women in politics,Spain,Italy,Politics,Gender,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="3e76c938b1bb86a5">
  <main>
    <p>An Italian politican preoccupied with fashion, hair and fake tan, and prone to emotional outbursts? I refer, of course, to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. This week it emerged, to no one's great surprise, that the newly re-elected Italian prime minister seems to have something of a problem with women in government. Referring to the fact that the Spanish prime minister, José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero, has just appointed Spain's first female-majority cabinet, Berlusconi said on Wednesday that "Zapatero has formed a government that is too pink, something that we cannot do in Italy because there is a prevalence of men in politics and it isn't easy to find women who are qualified ... He will have problems leading them. Now he's asked for it."</p>
    <p>Berlusconi isn't the only person who has been critical of Zapatero's decision to appoint nine women to his 17-strong cabinet (including 37-year-old defence minister, Carme Chacón, who just happens to be seven months pregnant). One conservative commentator in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/spain">Spain</ref> described Zapatero's female-majority cabinet as his "battalion of inexperienced seamstresses", as if the deputy prime minister María Teresa Fernández de la Vega (who has a doctorate in law, and a political career stretching back to the 1970s), and Magdalena Álvarez (a doctorate in economics, and a political career that dates from the 1980s) had just wandered in off the street.</p>
    <p>And the attacks on Zapatero's decision have underlined the ongoing antipathy to women in politics. There seems to be an increasingly wide gulf internationally between those who are supportive of women in government - and make great strides towards representative government as a result - and those who think that the very idea of women bothering their pretty little heads with such matters as foreign policy is completely beyond the pale.</p>
    <p>Zapatero, a self-proclaimed feminist, naturally represents the former attitude, being intent on equality. And he has shown that, given the right policies, it is possible to create a much more representative ruling class. When first elected four years ago, Zapatero appointed an equal number of men and women as ministers. Two years ago, he ruled that no more than 60% of candidates of any political party could be male, and that by 2010, the boards of any company pitching for public contracts should be made up of at least 40% women. "In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, as in Spain, there are enough women sufficiently qualified, intelligent and capable of being ministers or occupying other government posts," says Elena Valenciano, Spain's secretary for international relations. She adds pointedly that such an approach "would benefit politics and society in Italy".</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who has promised to include "at least four women" in his cabinet, embodies the less enlightened side of the equation. Campaigning in the recent elections, he referred to his female supporters as the "menopause section"; his women candidates are known as "the knight's ladies" (the knight being Berlusconi himself, of course, that noble 71-year-old ladies man). He has also referred to the appearance of the female candidates, in a bid to both publicise his party and undermine his women opponents. "The left has no taste, not even when it comes to women," rightwinger Berlusconi said recently. "As for our [women candidates] being more beautiful, I say that because in parliament they have no competition." Not to be outdone, Berlusconi's rival Walter Veltroni began amassing his own young good-looking female members for the cameras, prompting the media to brand them "Walter's angels".</p>
    <p>Of course, referencing how female politicians look - suggesting that they are either too good looking or too ugly to be taken seriously - is a classic tactic of those who fall into Berlusconi's camp, whether in the government or the media. When Labour came to power in 1997, the policy of selecting candidates from all-women shortlists for half of their winnable seats resulted in the doubling of women in Westminster from 62 to 121 - a hugely significant result, which should have marked a new political age. And yet a single unfortunate photograph of Blair surrounded by women MPs, spawned the lazy, misogynistic tag "Blair's babes", which was used against them for years and undermined that great leap forward.</p>
    <p>When Jacqui Smith, Britain's first female home secretary, gave her first statement to the Commons after the failed terrorist attacks last year, the focus of many of the news stories wasn't so much on what she said, but the amount of flesh she had on show (by most measures, not very much). The same fate befell Germany's chancellor, Angela Merkel, this week, when she wore a black evening dress with an admittedly plunging neckline to the opening of Oslo's new opera house. "Merkel's Weapons of Mass Distraction" was the Daily Mail's headline.</p>
    <p>In Britain the divide between the forward-looking and dinosaur elements was on show again last month, when David Cameron - who has just seven women in his 30-strong shadow cabinet - promised to give a third of senior jobs in his first government to women. This angered many male Tory MPs, with Philip Davies, the Tory MP for Shipley, saying that it was "completely unacceptable ... if you believe in true equality, which I do, then it should be irrelevant what somebody's gender should be".</p>
    <p>Which would be all very well if Britain wasn't failing so spectacularly to get women into government. The proportion of Labour MPs who are women increased to 27% in 2005 - considerably more than the Conservatives (8%) and the Liberal Democrats (16%) - but still not great. Overall, women make up just less than a fifth of British MPs. The right attitudes and policies - such as all-women shortlists - can change this. In Sweden, for instance, renowned for its progressive policies, women make up 47% of MPs, and in Norway, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gender">Gender</ref> Equality Act requires that all public bodies, including the cabinet, should be at least 40% women. In Germany, more than 30% of its elected representatives in the Bundestag are women.</p>
    <p>To see just how far some people's unease with women leaders extends, you only have to look at Hillary Clinton's campaign for the Democratic nomination in the US. Clinton's body, face and wardrobe have been pored over relentlessly, as if she was some kind of novelty specimen. The American media has been agonising over the question, "Are we ready for a woman president?" with Clinton being cast, variously, as a witch (her laugh has been described as a "cackle"), a bitch, and a ballbuster. Journalist Christopher Hitchens described her as "an ageing and resentful female". She has been too emotional or not emotional enough; too weak or too strong. She has been criticised for a perceived lack of warmth and the implication that she is not "motherly". There is that repeated accusation that she is only where she is because of her husband (accusations of nepotism against George W Bush were never quite so shrill). In a talk given last month, the American academic Barbara Pendleton said: "Many commentators appear to be unable to criticise her without dusting off their favourite sexist cliches, stereotypes and insults. Together they create an environment of hostility toward all women, not just Senator Clinton."</p>
    <p>"Being hostile to women in politics is easy," says Sarah Childs, senior lecturer in politics at Bristol University and author of a new study, Women and British Party Politics. "You can no longer say, 'Hillary Clinton shouldn't be president because she's a woman,' but what you can do is slag her off for what she looks like. A lot of the evaluation comes from a gender perspective and at the extreme, it is misogynistic. There are still men who don't think women should be in politics, and particularly in certain positions. It taps into everyday understandings of gender: can women really cope with security and terrorism threats? It's old-fashioned sexism."</p>
    <p>When it comes to the UK, she says that the quickest way to get more women into the House of Commons would be to use quotas. "If you want anything nearing 40 or 50%, you are going to have to use all-women shortlists and only the Labour party does that. I don't buy this argument that there are not enough women who want to be MPs - it's a house of 646. There are 300 women out there. It's about how you turn those who want to be MPs into MPs, and making sure political parties select women in their winnable seats. If you do that, you can get them in."</p>
    <p>As Zapatero has shown, with the right attitude, you can truly cause a revolution in politics.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">First among equals</hi> Who's who in the new Spanish cabinet</p>
    <p>When the Spanish prime minister named nine women for his 17-strong cabinet this week, his choice prompted international headlines. Most attention has been focused on <hi rend="#b">Carme Chacón</hi>, 37, from Esplugues de Llobregat, near Barcelona, who is the rising star inside the re-elected Socialist party, and the first female defence minister in Spain. She is also seven months pregnant. Images of her inspecting the troops with a baby bump turned up on the front pages of Spanish newspapers, along with widespread speculation about how much maternity leave she will take.</p>
    <p>Chacón began her political career nine years ago when she was elected to Esplugues council, later becoming mayor. She became a parliamentary deputy in 2000 and was named housing minister in 2006. Originally a lawyer, she is married to another socialist politician.</p>
    <p>As for the other new appointments, eyebrows were also raised at the naming of <hi rend="#b">Beatriz Corredor</hi>, 38, as the new housing minister, since her only experience in government has been serving alongside the failed socialist mayoral candidate in Madrid for less than a year. She takes over an important department at a time when Spain's decade-long housing bubble has just burst and banks are warning of record mortgage defaults. Trained in property registration, she is married with two children.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Cristina Garmendia</hi>, 46, from San Sebastián, is another new face. The science and investigation minister is a Socialist party stalwart, but has a background in industry, having founded her own biotechnology company, Genetrix, in 2000. For Zapatero, she is a key ally in the Basque Country.</p>
    <p>At 31, <hi rend="#b">Bibiana Aído Almagro</hi>, the new minister for equality, is the youngest person ever to occupy a cabinet post. Born in Cadiz, Andalucia, until her recent promotion she was head of the Flamenco Promotion Agency in the Andalusian regional government. Now her priorities will be to reduce domestic violence, which occupies a far higher position on the news agenda in Spain than in the UK.</p>
    <p>These are the new appointments, but Zapatero already had a sizeable number of women in his cabinet - when he won his first election in 2004, he named women to half of the 16 cabinet posts. So his "right-hand woman" was the veteran <hi rend="#b">María Teresa Fernández de la Vega</hi>, 59, who returns as vice-president, and is known as the enforcer in his government. After a distinguished law career, she became an MP in 1996 and rose through the ranks.</p>
    <p>Then there's the rural environment minister, <hi rend="#b">Elena Espinosa</hi>, 48, who has responsibility for climate change and the pressing water shortage in Spain.</p>
    <p>Public administration minister <hi rend="#b">Elena Salgado</hi>, 55, from Ourense, northern Spain, has worked in three difference ministries and is regarded as a safe pair of hands. An industrial engineer by training, as health minister she introduced Spain's partial ban on smoking in 2006.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Mercedes Cabrera</hi>, 56, who returns to the cabinet as education social affairs and sports minister, comes from a family steeped in politics - her uncle Leopoldo Calvo-Sotelo y Bustelo having briefly been prime minister in 1981-82, after Spain survived an attempted coup. Cabrera has long been a Socialist party stalwart and was named education minister in 2006. She is married with two children.</p>
    <p>Finally, the transport and development minister <hi rend="#b">Magdalena Álvarez</hi>, 56, returns to her post despite having become deeply unpopular last year over the failure of the government to deliver on its promise to have the high-speed AVE train link between Madrid and Barcelona run on time. Zapatero has weathered a storm of criticism for his cabinet of "ministras", not least from the likes of Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi. But the Spanish prime minister is clearly confident in his choices, insisting all the women in his cabinet were chosen on ability. In the next four years they plan to prove it.<hi rend="#b">Graham Keeley</hi></p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>