<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Germany shocked at Berlusconi 'Nazi' jibe" author="Ben Aris; Guardian staff reporter" date="2003-07-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jul/04/italy.germany" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italians may have a reputation for being the hot-blooded people of Europe, but the Germans were spitting with anger yesterday after Silvio Berlusconi's &quot;Nazi&quot; jibe." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Germany,European Union,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="2bb0987f90060495">
  <main>
    <p>The Italians may have a reputation for being the hot-blooded people of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, but the Germans were spitting with anger yesterday.</p>
    <p>"It was shameless, shocking and uncalled-for," said student Irina Losel, 22, of Mr Berlusconi's jibe.</p>
    <p>"I find it sad that someone like Berlusconi has so quickly forgotten what a terrible time this period in our history was. Even if it was a 'joke', it was the most tasteless possible."</p>
    <p>Germany's post-war generation suffered from war guilt, but after nearly 60 years young people appear to be getting fed up with all the references to what they increasingly regard as ancient history.</p>
    <p>"It is more of the same shit that comes up time and time again," said Frank Remschel, a 39-year old businessman. "We are always hearing these comparisons with Hitler and the Nazis. When will they leave off?"</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's rebuke was seen as doubly offensive, because most Germans agree with the MEP Martin Schulz's view that Mr Berlusconi used a new Italian immunity law to wriggle out of a bribery trial.</p>
    <p>"It is a bit rich for Berlusconi to say this," said Mr Remschel. "The Italian parliament has just passed a law making him immune from prosecution while we are pretty sure that he has stolen millions through corruption."</p>
    <p>With the anger, there also came a certain amount of bewildered disbelief that a senior statesman could say something so crass.</p>
    <p>"I was speechless," said Nadia Feldman, 70. "How can something like this be allowed?</p>
    <p>"How can someone like Berlusconi - Italy's prime minister, after all - become a statesman in the first place? I hope there are severe consequences for him."</p>
    <p>German politicians are in no mood to compromise, and they say nothing less than a full apology will do.</p>
    <p>"It was an awful thing to say, and a politician in his position should know better," said the CDU party MP Erika Reinhardt. "I hope there will be serious consequences for Berlusconi - but I don't think there is that much we can do."</p>
    <p>Most German MPs believe the slur calls for more than a few diplomatic phrases of contrition.</p>
    <p>"You can't treat your colleagues like this," said Ernst Burgbacher, a Free Liberal Party MP. "Berlusconi must apologise, and he must do it in public."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>