<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi vows to arrive for work as Italian PM" author="Barbara McMahon" date="2006-04-23" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/apr/24/italy.mainsection" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Still refusing to concede defeat in the Italian general election, Silvio Berlusconi put on another bravura performance at the weekend by serenading his supporters and then threatening to paralyse the incoming government." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="bfeac9679303cd04">
  <main>
    <p>Still refusing to concede defeat in the Italian general election, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> put on another bravura performance at the weekend by serenading his supporters and then threatening to paralyse the incoming government.</p>
    <p>The former cruise ship crooner took to the stage in a hotel restaurant in Trieste in northern <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, singing a medley of Neapolitan ballads. He also treated his audience, who applauded wildly, to a song he said he had composed in the wake of the election result, in which he talks about going to live on a tropical island.</p>
    <p>Afterwards he returned to attacking Romano Prodi, whose centre-left camp narrowly won the election two weeks ago and whose victory has been upheld by two Italian courts. Mr Berlusconi said the incoming coalition of nine parties would be unable to govern, adding that he would arrive for work as normal at the prime minister's office when the new parliamentary session opened on Friday.</p>
    <p>"The centre-left won't be able to govern, they are just passers-by. Without our accord in the senate, not even one provision will pass," he said.</p>
    <p>Tony Blair and the leaders of China, Russia, the US, Argentina, Japan and all of the major European countries have formally telephoned Mr Prodi to offer congratulations. Mr Berlusconi has shrugged off the calls, saying they reflect Italy's good standing on the world stage.</p>
    <p>At his home in Bologna yesterday Mr Prodi said Mr Berlusconi's refusal to acknowledge that the centre-left had won the election was "not my problem, it is his". He said his coalition would stay united and govern for the next five years. "We won the election and we have the right and the duty to govern. We will do so in the service and interests of all the country."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>