<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi allies to insist on choosing president" author="John Hooper" date="2006-04-30" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/may/01/italy.johnhooper" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi threatened at the weekend to resort to extra-parliamentary tactics to stop the centre-left from monopolising power in Italy following its hair's breadth victory in last month's election." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="bf2aba6f9102df6f">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi threatened at the weekend to resort to extra-parliamentary tactics to stop the centre-left from monopolising power in Italy following its hair's breadth victory in last month's election.</p>
    <p>After finally signalling he would step down as prime minister, Mr Berlusconi said he and his allies would insist on having one of their own number elected as head of state when a new president is chosen next week. He said his personal "Mr Fixit", a former employee of his business empire, would be among those proposed.</p>
    <p>Referring to the leaders of the centre-left, who narrowly won last month's general election, Mr Berlusconi added: "If they refuse our offer, we shall feel it our duty to [mount] hard, total opposition - not just in the chambers [of parliament]." He did not elaborate on what sort of tactics he was considering.</p>
    <p>The billionaire politician issued his threat after two votes in parliament on Saturday appeared to destroy his hopes of blocking the appointment of Romano Prodi as prime minister. By securing the election of its choices of speaker in both houses of parliament, the centre-left showed it could muster the majorities needed to pass legislation.</p>
    <p>But in the senate, where Mr Prodi and his alliance have a razor-thin edge, it took four rounds of voting - a clear indication of vulnerability. The contest, between the centre-left's candidate, Franco Marini, and the veteran politician Giulio Andreotti, descended into farce on Friday as the two sides argued furiously over whether votes cast for "Francesco Marini" were valid.</p>
    <p>It was widely suspected that members of one or more of the smaller parties on the centre-left deliberately spoiled their ballots to remind Mr Prodi of his dependence on their support and thereby boost their chances of a seat in the next government. Mr Prodi was yesterday racing against the clock to produce a list of names agreeable to all nine parties in a coalition that stretches from the Christian Democrat centre to the far-left.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>