<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian elections 2018 - full results" author="Jon Henley; Antonio Voce; Seán Clarke" date="2018-03-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/ng-interactive/2018/mar/05/italian-elections-2018-full-results-renzi-berlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italy yesterday went to the polls to choose over 900 members of its two houses of parliament. Former prime minsters Silvio Berlusconi and Matteo Renzi were the big losers as voters opted for anti-establishment parties" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Matteo Renzi,Five Star Movement,Beppe Grillo,The League" fingerprint="72d40a75d225d76d">
  <main>
    <head rend="h1">Italian elections 2018 - full results</head>
    <p>Italy yesterday went to the polls to choose over 900 members of its two houses of parliament. Former prime minsters Silvio Berlusconi and Matteo Renzi were the big losers as voters opted for anti-establishment parties</p>
    <head rend="h2">Provisional result</head>
    <head rend="h4">Chamber of Deputies 630 seats</head>
    <head rend="h4">Senate 320 seats</head>
    <head rend="h2">Party-by-party results</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Forza Italia</hi>, a fairly traditional centre-right party, was overtaken by</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Lega</hi>, former northern secessionists now more broadly nationalist, while</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">Fratelli d'Italia</hi>, a radical right party, also gained share. The strength of the elements within the alliance may affect what deals can be struck in forming a government.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Who are the winners and losers, and what happens next?</head>
    <head rend="h4">Matteo Renzi</head>
    <graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/4bc4db543307b5459a4586c44e6edd8a81582467/1738_24_882_882/140.jpg"/>
    <p>The Democratic party was expecting to do badly, but senior figures admit this is worse even than they feared. Renzi's career has taken another severe knock.</p>
    <head rend="h4">Silvio Berlusconi</head>
    <graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/efe70de723d26e80c7ca954d1953547e3410fdaa/325_45_1702_1702/140.jpg"/>
    <p>Although part of the biggest coalition, Berlusconi's Forza Italia is not the biggest party within the alliance. That leaves the former prime minister - who is barred from office - short of the electoral authority he needs if he is to act as an eminence grise in the formation of a new government.</p>
    <head rend="h4">Luigi di Maio</head>
    <graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/40295b93fc09ac997e7c3de1dd5ab2daa22774ed/1944_604_1519_1519/140.jpg"/>
    <p>Despite their protestations, the Five Star Movement did well even in the first-past-the-post seats which are new in this election. As the second force in parliament they could be instrumental in the formation of a government. But to do that they need to set aside their anti-politics stance and do some deals.</p>
    <head rend="h4">Matteo Salvini</head>
    <graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/a81cb852ac4c8905da04a5826f6debae46dbff98/1330_225_657_657/140.jpg"/>
    <p>Until recently, Lega was - by design - a strictly regional force. A strong nationwide vote has made it unexpectedly the senior partner in the right-wing coalition, strengthening Salvini's hand in government negotiations.</p>
    <head rend="h2">Regional and demographic trends</head>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://interactive.guim.co.uk/uploader/embed/2018/03/italian-election-map-zip/giv-3902iP9jzEUcoJzi/">map</ref>
    </p>
    <p>
      <ref target="https://interactive.guim.co.uk/uploader/embed/2018/03/scatters-zip/giv-39028SgjBWaRgSUN/">Scatterplots</ref>
    </p>
    <head rend="h2">Which parties could make up a coalition government?</head>
    <p>Several permutations are mathematically possible, but none appear politically easy. <hi rend="#b">Jon Henley</hi> explains</p>
    <p>Preliminary results from Italy’s general election show the country split three ways. None of the three factions – Silvio Berlusconi’s Forza Italia and the anti-immigration the League; a centre-left coalition headed by Matteo Renzi; and the anti-establishment <ref target="https://viewer.gutools.co.uk/world/five-star-movement">Five Star Movement</ref> (M5S) – look likely to have enough seats to govern alone, and no government is possible without the support of either the League or M5S.</p>
    <p>Some kind of coalition will therefore be necessary for a majority in Italy’s 630-seat parliament. Several permutations are mathematically possible, though none appear politically easy:</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>
        <hi rend="#b">Populist and far right: Five Star Movement and the League</hi>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>Projections have M5S as by far the largest single partywith 231 seats and the League on 123, giving this potential alliance – which would send shockwaves through the EU – a total of 354. Having long rejected all talk of any power sharing, M5S now says it is willing to at least talk about common policies. “We will discuss with all other parties,” its leader, Luigi di Maio, said, adding that the party has “a responsibility to govern”. Many analysts believe the leftwing of M5S would revolt were there a hookup with the League.</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>
        <hi rend="#b">Populist, rightwing, far right: M5S, Forza Italia, the League</hi>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>This combination would have a total of 453 seats, 99 of which would be occupied by from Berlusconi’s Forza Italia. All three parties initially ruled out alternative post-election pacts, but with Forza Italia on course to win fewer seats than the League, a senior official from the latter, Claudio Borghi, has suggested a rightwing alliance headed by his party’s leader, Matteo Salvini, could find an accord with M5S. Salvini appears to have ruled this out, saying he is “committed” to his alliance with Forza Italia, but has stressed the League has “a right and a duty” to govern.</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>
        <hi rend="#b">Rightwing and centre left: Forza Italia, the League, the Democratic party</hi>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>A grand coalition would have a projected 327 seats in parliament, 222 from the rightwing parties and 105 from the Democrats, but bring together some highly unlikely bedfellows in the pro-European centre left and the anti-immigration, EU-critical League. As such, it is seen as highly unlikely. A senior Democratic party official, Ettore Rosato, has said that if results stay as they are, “for us it is a clear defeat and we will move into opposition”.</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>
        <hi rend="#b">Populist and centre left: Five Star Movement and the Democratic party</hi>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>This option, with 336 parliamentary seats, also looks difficult to achieve politically. Matteo Ricci, a former Democratic party vice-president, has said there is “no chance” of it helping the M5S form a government. “The only ally with whom the M5S can form a government is Matteo Salvini , that’s the only option for them,” he said.</p>
    <list rend="ul">
      <item>
        <hi rend="#b">Fresh elections</hi>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>If there is no clear majority, the Italian president, Sergio Mattarella, could choose to leave the current centre-left government of Paolo Gentiloni in place, allowing time to set up a temporary government to organise new elections. That process could only start after parliament meets for the first time on 23 March.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>