<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi faces court on bribery charges" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2003-06-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jun/17/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, was today in court on bribery charges in what was expected to be his final trial appearance before parliament approves an immunity bill protecting him from prosecution." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="ba60c20cb5a2360e">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, was today in court on bribery charges in what was expected to be his final trial appearance before parliament approves an immunity bill protecting him from prosecution.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who is the first serving Italian prime minister to stand trial, told a packed Milan courtroom that there was no evidence against him.</p>
    <p>He is accused of bribing judges in 1985, before he was a politician, to block the agreed sale of SME, a state-owned foods conglomerate, to rival tycoon Carlo de Benedetti.</p>
    <p>It is alleged that Mr Berlusconi, wanting SME for himself, arranged for £85,000 to be paid to two judges, Filippo Verde and Renato Squillante, who overruled the sale to Mr de Benedetti.</p>
    <p>The prime minister denies the claim, saying that he is the victim of a political plot by Milan-based centre-left magistrates.</p>
    <p>"I wonder how the money of Italian citizens can be spent setting up a trial that is based exclusively on inventions," Mr Berlusconi told the court during his hour-long appearance.</p>
    <p>"There isn't - I repeat, I want to say this strongly - a piece of evidence, an accusation, a document. And there is no motive," he said.</p>
    <p>The prime minister said that, because of the trial, "tons of mud have been thrown at me for seven years by newspapers, television, in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and abroad".</p>
    <p>As the billionaire businessman turned politician left the courtroom, some booed him, while others starting chanting his name, shouting "up with Silvio" and clapping their hands.</p>
    <p>To the frustration of prosecutors and judges, today was only the third time that Mr Berusconi has attended court since the proceedings began three years ago.</p>
    <p>His appearance comes a day before the lower house of parliament is expected to pass an immunity bill, barring the country's top five officials from prosecution.</p>
    <p>The move would suspend his corruption trial indefinitely, just before Italy takes over the EU presidency on July 1.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, whose current term ends in 2006, insists that an immunity law would safeguard the democratic will of those who elected him from the unfounded charges of left-wing magistrates.</p>
    <p>However, opponents have called the bill a "monstrous, unconstitutional mistake", and accused him of using his power to protect himself and his private interests.</p>
    <p>The Milan prosecutor, Ilda Boccassini, has presented her case against Mr Berlusconi, but has not yet made a formal request for a prison term.</p>
    <p>In another trial dealing with the same case, Ms Boccassini has asked for a conviction and 11-year sentence against Mr Berlusconi's ally, the former defence minister Cesare Previti.</p>
    <p>The two trials were originally held together, but the court separated them because the premier's work schedule continually halted the proceedings.</p>
    <p>Mr Previti, who denies the charges, was convicted in a similar bribery trial last month, and sentenced to 11 years in prison. He has launched an appeal.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>