<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi sex scandal 'escort' says film is on the way" author="Andrew Pulver" date="2015-07-13" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2015/jul/13/berlusconi-sex-scandal-escort-says-film-is-on-the-way" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Patrizia d’Addario, who wrote a book about her alleged affair with the Italian prime minister, said in a court statement she was planning to make a film about it" categories="Film" tags="Film,Silvio Berlusconi,Culture,World news,Italy,Film adaptations,Books,Europe" fingerprint="bb12ce1d1aa74764">
  <main>
    <p>A woman who wrote a book about her alleged sexual relationship with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> says she is planning to make a film about the affair.</p>
    <p>Patrizia d’Addario made a statement to a court in Bari, <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/silvio-berlusconi/11732303/Silvio-Berlusconis-first-mistress-tells-Italian-court-she-wants-to-make-film-about-affair.html">according to a report in the Telegraph</ref>, at the trial of entrepreneur Gianpaolo Tarantini and six others who are accused of a string of crimes, including “aiding and abetting and inducing into prostitution”, in connection with allegations that they supplied Berlusconi with <ref target="http://www.ansa.it/english/news/2015/07/10/berlusconi-refuses-to-respond-at-bari-escorts-trial_2362cf6a-5e44-46c7-9628-e8cee7cecfea.html">women for sex parties in exchange for public contracts</ref>.</p>
    <p>D’Addario testified at the trial as a witness, and read out a six-page “letter” addressed to Berlusconi in which she said her “life has been ruined”. She also said: “I’m going to make a film about my experiences based on the truth of what happened. You destroyed my life, now you should apologise and tell the truth of our relationship.”</p>
    <p>D’Addario’s claims centre around an allegation that Berlusconi paid her for sex in 2008, after his marriage to former wife Veronica Lario broke down. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/02/patrizia-daddario-silvio-berlusconi">In 2009 she claimed on the TV programme Annozero that Berlusconi knew she was an escort</ref>, and that the parties she attended at Berlusconi’s residence “seemed like a harem”. In a subsequent book, whose title translates in English as Take Your Pleasure, Prime Minister, D’Addario wrote: “He told me he wanted contact with my skin, he held me tight, he took my breath away. I took him inside me, he suffocated me with kisses.” After its publication Berlusconi claimed he did not remember her and that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">he had never paid for sex</ref>.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi, who is not a defendant in the Bari trial, made a brief appearance shortly before D’Addario after being asked to take the stand as a witness for the defence. However, Berlusconi refused to respond to questions after announcing that he was following the advice of his lawyers as he is on trial for a linked case, <ref target="http://www.ansa.it/english/news/general_news/2014/11/14/berlusconi-lavitola-escorts-bribe-trial_f74b2c99-2211-4031-afc1-91eae7d971c0.html">in which he is accused of bribing Tarantini to lie about supplying the women</ref>.</p>
    <p>In a separate case, Berlusconi had <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/mar/11/berlusconi-vows-political-comeback-after-sex-case-acquittal-upheld">a conviction quashed</ref> for paying for sex with an underage prostitute and abusing his office. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jul/08/silvio-berlusconi-sentenced-to-3-years-for-bribing-italian-senator">Last week he was sentenced to three years imprisonment</ref> for bribing an Italian senator as part of a plot to destabilise Roman Prodi’s centre-left government, but is unlikely to serve the term as the statute of limitations on the case is to shortly expire.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>