<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi will undergo US surgery, says ally" author="Tom Kington" date="2006-12-18" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/dec/18/italy.mainsection" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi, the former Italian prime minister, is to undergo surgery in the United States, his political ally, Umberto Bossi, told a rally in Milan yesterday." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,Umberto Bossi" fingerprint="77ffd0adf867f7ad">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi, the former Italian prime minister, is to undergo surgery in the United States, his political ally, Umberto Bossi, told a rally in Milan yesterday.</p>
    <p>Mr Bossi, head of the Northern League, did not say what the operation would involve, but his statement follows reports that the conservative opposition leader is to have a pacemaker fitted.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, 70, collapsed while addressing supporters last month. Later he said he had fainted due to the heat in the room, but he was also found to have an irregular heartbeat.</p>
    <p>The newspaper Corriere della Sera said yesterday that Mr Berlusconi had telephoned President George Bush for advice about US heart clinics. The report said he had not made up his mind about a pacemaker, and might simply have a check-up, despite pressure from his children.</p>
    <p>Reports have named clinics in Cleveland, Connecticut and Texas as possible destinations for Mr Berlusconi, who has not confirmed any pending medical visit. When questioned, he joked that he would prefer to go to Las Vegas. He promised reporters that he would be back at work before Christmas.</p>
    <p>"He is in the US to undergo a few scheduled medical checks," Paolo Bonaiuti, a spokesman for Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party, said yesterday in response to questions about Mr Bossi's remarks. "He arrived in the US today."</p>
    <p>Il Messaggero newspaper reported that Mr Berlusconi had already visited the same Italian doctor who oversaw the recovery of Mr Bossi after he suffered a stroke in 2004.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>