<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi dismisses call to pull troops out of Iraq" author="Sophie Arie" date="2004-03-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/mar/29/italy.iraq" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi yesterday faced growing pressure from the Italian anti-war lobby after Romano Prodi, president of the European commission, said the Italian left would withdraw troops from Iraq if elected." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Iraq,Middle East and north Africa,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="4fc9d179baaedf07">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi yesterday faced growing pressure from the Italian anti-war lobby after Romano Prodi, president of the European commission, said the Italian left would withdraw troops from Iraq if elected.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi, who has controversially combined his EC role with leadership of Italy's opposition centre-left Olive Tree coalition, wrote a letter to the Corriere della Sera newspaper on Saturday describing the Iraq war as "illegitimate".</p>
    <p>Should Olive Tree come to power, "the problem would be to decide whether to continue or interrupt the participation in this war, [and] I have no hesitation in saying that the choice would be ending the intervention.</p>
    <p>"Because in its actual form, the occupation is the continuation of an unjustified and illegitimate war and not visibly capable of restoring peace and security to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/iraq">Iraq</ref>," he wrote.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi said the international community's intervention in Iraq was "indispensable" to protect the civilian population and provide humanitarian assistance. But such intervention would require military backing under the approval of the UN.</p>
    <p>At a political rally in Palermo Mr Berlusconi insisted there was no reason for Italian troops to withdraw before the June 30 deadline already set, and suggested that, if need be, they could remain beyond that date.</p>
    <p>Since Spain's new prime minister, José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero, pledged to withdraw Spanish troops from Iraq by June 30, Mr Berlusconi has reiterated that he has no intention of doing the same with almost 3,000 soldiers in the country.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's men chimed in with support. "Withdrawal today, just like that, of our troops from Iraq would be a catastrophic decision," said Pier Ferdinando Casini, the president of the chamber of deputies. "Shouting 'peace, peace', is nice, but it's not enough," Mr Casini said, denouncing what he called "unilateral pacifism" as damaging to the war on terrorism.</p>
    <p>The foreign minister, Franco Frattini, said an early withdrawal would be seen as "weakness in the face of terrorism" and accused Mr Prodi of making an illegitimate use of his position as European commission president.</p>
    <p>"Prodi is using the argument employed by part of the left, but he's doing it wearing the cap of the European president, a seriously illegitimate use of the post," Mr Frattini said in an interview with Corriere della Sera.</p>
    <p>But Mr Prodi's move, just weeks ahead of EU parliamentary elections, raises the heat on Mr Berlusconi, seen as isolated in Europe since the Madrid terrorist attacks helped bring down his close ally, José María Aznar, the other great European supporter of the US and Britain's stance on Iraq.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi, who founded the Olive Tree coalition in 1995 and defeated Mr Berlusconi in elections in 1996, is widely seen as the best contender to lead the opposition in 2006 general elections.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>