<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi dithers on Iraqi troops" author="Ewen MacAskill; Michael Howard" date="2005-03-17" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/mar/17/usa.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, appeared to soften his position on pulling troops out of Iraq in September yesterday, saying the date could be changed." categories="World news" tags="World news,US news,Italy,Iraq,Middle East and north Africa,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7fd252cf836677aa">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, appeared to soften his position on pulling troops out of Iraq in September yesterday, saying the date could be changed.</p>
    <p>"There's never been a fixed date," Mr Berlusconi said. "It was only my hope ... If it is not possible, it is not possible. The solution should be agreed with the allies."</p>
    <p>George Bush earlier denied that his "coalition of the willing" in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/iraq">Iraq</ref> was crumbling.</p>
    <p>"Countries will be willing, anxious, to get out when Iraqis have got the capacity to defend themselves," he said.</p>
    <p>"And that's the position of the US, our troops will come home when Iraq is capable of defending herself."</p>
    <p>Tony Blair, questioned in the Commons yesterday, said: "We should withdraw when the job is done, not before."</p>
    <p>Asked whether the MoD had drawn up contingency plans to "backfill" in the event of an Italian withdrawal, a defence official commented: "We are not at that point."</p>
    <p>The threat of an Italian withdrawal came as Iraq's new parliament was sworn in yesterday in Baghdad's heavily fortified green zone. The event was made largely symbolic by the lack of a new government to confer legitimacy on the 275-member body. Insurgents marked the occasion with a barrage of mortar bombs aimed at the green zone.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>