<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi resigns" author="Staff; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" date="2006-05-02" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/may/02/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3f1a0a2c9514e74d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi today resigned as Italian prime minister four weeks after losing the country's general election to a centre-left coalition.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi had contested the results of the poll and vowed to challenge the outcome in court.</p>
    <p>But he finally conceded the election this afternoon when he handed his resignation to Italy's president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, clearing the way for a new government led by Romano Prodi.</p>
    <p>The resignation was confirmed in a statement from the president's office after a half-hour meeting at the presidential palace.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi, who announced his decision to stand down at a cabinet meeting this morning, made no comment to reporters as he left Mr Ciampi's office.</p>
    <p>His resignation was the next formal step after the election of speakers for Italy's new parliament over the weekend.</p>
    <p>It will now be up to Mr Ciampi to decide whether to sanction the formation of a new government this week or wait until parliament elects a new head of state later this month.</p>
    <p>Mr Ciampi, whose mandate expires on May 18, has always said his successor should oversee the transition, but there has been speculation that he may do so himself.</p>
    <p>He is understood to be keen to end Italy's political limbo and to send a signal of stability to world financial markets.</p>
    <p>If Mr Ciampi does change his mind, Italy could have a new government by the end of this week.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi welcomed the move. "Democracy goes on, sometimes slowly, but it does," he said. "It is a very important step ... I hope the political vacuum doesn't go on for too long."</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is expected to continue as caretaker prime minister until the new government is installed.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi's coalition won the election on April 9 and 10 by the smallest margin in modern Italian political history.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi claimed there had been widespread irregularities during the poll but Italy's authorities upheld the vote, saying it was up to the new government to deal with any complaints.</p>
    <p>The conservative leader, elected in 2001, was the longest-serving leader of his country since the second world war.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>