<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Hadley Freeman on Berlusconi's new face" author="Hadley Freeman" date="2008-04-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2008/apr/16/fashion.italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Hadley Freeman: '[Plastic surgery] shows respect to those who expect you to represent them on an international and national stage,' Berlusconi said once. Joan Rivers couldn't have put it any better herself" categories="Fashion" tags="Fashion,Life and style,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" fingerprint="76c3004799227304">
  <main>
    <p>As <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the self-proclaimed Napoleon, Winston Churchill and Jesus Christ of Italian politics, assumes his usual role of prime minister this week, several questions spring effortlessly to mind: after 12 trials for corruption and bribery, two decidedly controversial terms in office and accusations that his closest associate, Marcello dell'Utri, works for the Family - capital F - is there nothing a man can do to put off Italian voters? And rather more overwhelmingly, what has that man done to his face? Happily, I light upon a contact who can answer this latter question in impressive detail. "It is common knowledge in Italy that Mr Berlusconi had cosmetic surgery done" says Dr Gennaro Selvaggi from Transform Cosmetic Surgery.</p>
    <p>Silvio himself has been uncharacteristically straight about this subject. In 2004 he went missing for a few weeks, before popping up, perkier, smoother, to say, yes, his "eyelids had been touched slightly." Looking at these before-and-after photos, we can see that these procedures have been done with the subtlety one would expect from a man whose idea of wit has in the past caused diplomatic rifts (it's astonishing how sensitive those German MEPs can be if you suggest that they should be cast in a movie about the Nazi regime).</p>
    <p>At least it's an improvement on Berlusconi's look of yore, consisting of a white bandana tied around his head, which he is said to have worn in the early days of his hair transplant. He most famously wore it in 2004 when Tony Blair visited him, and a comparison between the prime ministers is instructive. Sure, you might have qualms about the leader of your country going AWOL every few years to get his eyes sorted, but what's the alternative? Being led by a man who ages in dog years, seven years faster than usual? Judging from the mockery lobbed at Blair for just that at the end of his reign, this wasn't acceptable either. "[Plastic surgery] shows respect to those who expect you to represent them on an international and national stage," Berlusconi said once.</p>
    <p>Joan Rivers couldn't have put it any better herself.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>