<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Left celebrates after Berlusconi's coalition defeated in stronghold" author="Sophie Arie" date="2004-06-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jun/29/italy.sophiearie" hostname="theguardian.com" description="If, as Silvio Berlusconi likes to say, Italian politics is like a game of football, then his side has just taken a severe beating on its home ground." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7a88823bb431cf4f">
  <main>
    <p>If, as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> likes to say, Italian politics is like a game of football, then his side has just taken a severe beating on its home ground.</p>
    <p>His centre-right coalition could even be said to have scored an own goal.</p>
    <p>Results from weekend local elections showed Milan, Italy's wealthy industrial capital and the prime minister's home town and traditional stronghold, had swung dramatically to the left.</p>
    <p>Filippo Penati, of the Democrats of the Left, won 53.8%, kicking out the Forza Italia provincial president, Ombretta Colli. Overall, the centre-left won 14 of the 22 provinces up for grabs, turning the tables on the centre-right which had held 13 provinces to the left's nine.</p>
    <p>The defeat comes just a fortnight after the left won European elections in Rome. Forza Italia dropped four percentage points overall in the European election.</p>
    <p>Other provinces won by the opposition included Biella and Novara in Piedmont, and Brindisi in the south. The conservatives won Padua and Verona, provinces in the affluent north-eastern Veneto region.</p>
    <p>The Milan result was trumpeted by the left and left-leaning media as the stunning collapse of the "last fortress of Berlusconismo".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi made his first billions in the construction business around Milan and launched his media empire there. He owns AC Milan football club and often retreats to a luxury villa at Arcore, on the city outskirts.</p>
    <p>"How can one not read the Milan victory as a political sign for the entire country?" said Romano Prodi, the outgoing EU commission president and would-be opposition leader.</p>
    <p>"Il Cavaliere is paying the highest cost of three years of government [marked by] conflict and inefficiency," said La Repubblica daily. "Forza Italia has been defeated 'at home'."</p>
    <p>Commentators said the left's victory was not so much because it had played well but because the right had played badly. The Italian left remains fragmented, and its best potential leader is currently based in Brussels.</p>
    <p>The metaphorical "own goal" was scored by star player Silvio himself, analysts said. Voters, including loyal Forza supporters, were suffering from "Berlusconi fatigue".</p>
    <p>They had been drowned with too many images of their bronzed, smiling prime minister in the run-up to elections and were weary of the personal disputes detracting attention from Italy's real problems.</p>
    <p>The loss in Milan was also due to a rebellion within the ranks of Mr Berlusconi's coalition, known as the House of Liberty.</p>
    <p>In several run-offs, candidates from the reform minister Umberto Bossi's Northern League party campaigned against Forza Italia.</p>
    <p>'The Berlusconi product is not selling any more," said La Repubblica, calling for early elections.</p>
    <p>But Mr Berlusconi said he would not "lose sleep" over the defeat and would serve out his five-year term until 2006. "The commitments we took with our voters in 2001 don't change in any way," he told Apcom news agency in Istanbul, while attending a Nato summit.</p>
    <p>He is expected to announce a cabinet reshuffle sometime this week.</p>
    <p>"Berlusconi is still in the saddle," wrote Corriere della Sera newspaper. "But the horse is very, very unruly."</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>