<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi: Italian troops will stay in Iraq" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2005-05-05" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/may/05/italy.usa" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi today told MPs he would not pull Italian troops out of Iraq in response to disagreements with the US over the fatal shooting of an Italian agent." categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,US news,Iraq,Middle East and north Africa,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3fa6d1afb332cb43">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi today told MPs he would not pull Italian troops out of Iraq in response to disagreements with the US over the fatal shooting of an Italian agent.</p>
    <p>Addressing the Chamber of Deputies today, the Italian prime minister said he disagreed with some of the US military's conclusions into the March 4 shooting of Nicola Calipari in Baghdad.</p>
    <p>US troops who fired on the agent's car from a checkpoint may have been to blame even if they had shot mistakenly, Mr Berlusconi said.</p>
    <p>However, he added: "The outcome of the inquiry has nothing to do with the quality of our relations with the United States. Our friendship, the friendship between <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and the United States, has overcome more difficult problems than this."</p>
    <p>Italy issued its own report into the shooting three days ago, which concluded that the US soldiers' inexperience, stress and fatigue had played a role.</p>
    <p>Italy and the US began a joint investigation after US troops fired on Calipari's car as it approached a checkpoint, but issued differing reports after being unable to agree on what had happened.</p>
    <p>The US report into Calipari's death cleared the soldiers of any blame, saying the car had been speeding and did not heed warning lights and shots. It concluded that better coordination between the Italians and the US could have prevented the tragedy.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi contended that the temporary checkpoint, on the dangerous road to Baghdad airport, had not been properly marked. Calipari was escorting a freed hostage, the Italian journalist Giuliana Sgrena, to the airport after Italy had secured her release. Ms Sgrena and another intelligence agent in the vehicle were wounded in the shooting.</p>
    <p>Despite Calipari's death and the disagreement over the circumstances of the shooting, Mr Berlusconi said Italian troop deployment would continue.</p>
    <p>"We have no intention of establishing any connection between the assessment of the case in which our official lost his life and the role of our country in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/iraq">Iraq</ref>. We must insist in our commitment and assist the forces of a free and democratic new Iraq," he said.</p>
    <p>Italy sent around 3,000 troops into Iraq to help with reconstruction, despite widespread objections from Italians. The agent's death and the US conclusion that the soldiers bore no responsibility for it have angered the Italian public.</p>
    <p>Yesterday, the US president, George Bush, telephoned Mr Berlusconi to again express regret over Calipari's death. The Italian prime minister's office described their conversation as "long and cordial", and the White House spokesman Scott McClellan said the two leaders had agreed the episode would not harm "the strong friendship" between the two countries.</p>
    <p>The opposition leader, Romano Prodi - expected to run for prime minster in elections next year - said that while there was no direct link between a pullout and the Calipari case, it was time to discuss the end of the mission in Iraq.</p>
    <p>Earlier this week, cabinet minister Roberto Calderoli said the government must "reflect on the timetable for a return plan",</p>
    <p>Two months ago, Mr Berlusconi said that if security conditions allowed and the other allies agreed, some Italian troops could begin returning home as early as September. However, no timetable for the start of withdrawal has been set.</p>
    <p>Rome prosecutors are conducting their own investigation into the Calipari case. A leading Italian military prosecutor, Antonio Intelisano, yesterday told the Associated Press it was unlikely US soldiers would be prosecuted in Italy given legal restrictions and US protection of its troops in the past. The US has "without exception" stuck by a standard principle of international law under which soldiers "are judged by judicial authorities of their own country," Mr Intelisano said. He added that because the US report recommended no disciplinary action against the soldiers, there was little else to do.</p>
    <p>"This is the reason why this decision, all things considered, has not been accepted or shared in this country," he said.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>