<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi accused of rigging approval for Venice motorway" author="John Hooper" date="2003-08-04" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/aug/04/citynews.silvioberlusconi" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi's government has been accused of rigging a key committee to enable a motorway to be built through a world heritage site. By John Hooper." categories="Media" tags="Media business,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Television industry,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="7c0ff9e53e33176d">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi's government has been accused of rigging a key committee to enable a motorway to be built through a Unesco-nominated world heritage site.</p>
    <p>The charity Save Europe's Heritage said in a statement issued from London that the Rome government had removed officials who opposed its plans for the Valdastico Sud motorway in the area west of Venice.</p>
    <p>A decree authorising the road was signed by Mr Berlusconi in June. But a consortium of mainly Italian environmental and heritage groups is mounting a legal challenge to the measure which will have to be submitted by September.</p>
    <p>Save Europe's Heritage said the proposed motorway would run within a few hundred metres of historic villas built in the flat land south of Vicenza, many designed by the 16th-century architect Andrea Palladio.</p>
    <p>It said that, in some cases, the effect would be to deter prospective property buyers who would have been willing to restore them.</p>
    <p>The regional government has argued that the motorway will, on the contrary, protect such buildings. Giancarlo Galan, the head of the regional administration and a member of Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party, welcomed the approval of the project, saying: "All the cars which are blocking up this area will go on to the motorway, which for lengthy stretches will run in a trench and free all the villages from suffocating traffic jams."</p>
    <p>The Veneto - the region surrounding Venice - has long suffered from acute traffic congestion and the motorway would take vehicles off one of its most congested roads.</p>
    <p>Save Europe's Heritage said that the scheme had been given the go-ahead despite objections from the ministry of culture in Rome and the official local bodies responsible for archaeology and heritage.</p>
    <p>It added that "23 out of 36 members of the official environment commission were replaced after they rejected the proposals as being too damaging".</p>
    <p>The group said that the new members of the panel approved the proposed route with only minor changes.</p>
    <p>Marcus Binney, chairman of Save Europe's Heritage, said: "This is the most flagrant example of disregarding and discarding [environmental assessment] that we have ever come across. It is astounding."</p>
    <p>Among the houses affected by the scheme would the celebrated Villa dal Verme near Agugliaro. According to a report published by the group - Unforgivable Assault on a World Heritage Site, by Franziska Bollerey and Axel Fohl - the house would be within 300 metres of the new road.</p>
    <p>Mr Binney said that plans should be withdrawn pending an independent assessment.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>