<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="History dogs Berlusconi bid to transform Italy" author="Ed Vulliamy" date="2008-04-06" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/06/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italians are depressed as their country seems trapped in the doldrums. Ed Vulliamy reports on the malaise gripping a nation" categories="World news" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="3bd8d02593a187c5">
  <main>
    <p>As luck would have it for those enamoured of Silvio Berlusconi's charms, the year's first day of honeyed sunshine in Turin also brought to town the man who would be Italy's President of the Council of Ministers for a third time, and who leads the polls for next weekend's Italian parliamentary elections.</p>
    <p>Fittingly for the leader of his new party - the People of Liberty - which he calls 'monarchist' (he being the king), the rally was held outside the palace of Italy's once ruling House of Savoy. It was a while coming, though, with plenty of time to appreciate the girls, quintessential to any Berlusconi event, bouncing around the stage in baseball caps to a melodramatic campaign song, 'Thank Goodness for Silvio'.</p>
    <p>It was repeated 16 times before Berlusconi burst on stage, looking recovered from the heart complaint that allowed him to miss his most recent scheduled appearance in court.</p>
    <p>Used to accusations of corruption, Berlusconi's prescriptions for Italy are noteworthy: 'We need a new political morality... to abolish the privileges of the political class', and to mount 'an offensive against tax evasion'. The girls in white caps chant 'Silvio! Silvio!' and tearful women reach for his hand.</p>
    <p>This is how his campaign has gone: Berlusconi advising a woman worried about her financial future to marry his son and calling his opponent Walter Veltroni a 'recycled Stalinist' and his centre-left Democratic Party 'the bikini party, showing a lot, but covering up the communist essentials'.</p>
    <p>Though a former Communist, Veltroni epitomises their abandonment of the hammer and sickle to become first the Democratic Left (symbolised by an oak tree), and then the Democratic Party (symbolised by an olive tree and created by an alliance with 'The Daisy' party), which embraces the free market and admires Tony Blair.</p>
    <p>Whatever further vegetation Veltroni adopts, there is, as Massimo Cacciari, Mayor of Venice, says, 'no ideological difference between the programmes' of the candidates. Both promise capitalist modernity and, while Berlusconi parades a cult of personality, Veltroni last week came up with his best idea yet: to annul 500 laws throttling commercial life.</p>
    <p>Next weekend's vote falls in the context of what Italians call the malaise. When Italy lost a football match to Spain last week, the pain was compounded by Spain's economy recently surpassing that of Italy.</p>
    <p>A combination of labyrinthine bureaucracy, political patronage and a Byzantine system of nepotism has petrified the economy, so Italy now endures the lowest wages, growth rates and levels of foreign investment in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, as well as the lowest birth rate - an average of 1.27 children per couple. Unemployment is low at 6 per cent, but rises to 10 per cent for those aged 15 to 24. A recent survey found 53 per cent of Italians felt worse off than ever.</p>
    <p>Writing in La Stampa, the commentator Andrea Romano laments: 'Berlusconi appears to be heading for victory in what is, when all is counted, a referendum on his popular persona.' Berlusconi is first and foremost a man of television, not of politics, to whom a great deal has happened since he last won an election in 2001. Or, rather, has happened to those closest to him during his rise.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi's ascent to power began in construction, on the back of which he built a trash television empire which moulded consumerist Italy. When relationships with business and the political castes were decapitated by the 'Clean Hands' investigations into political corruption of 1990-94, Berlusconi faced examination by the judiciary. His response was a direct intervention into politics, filling a vacuum left by the rotten Christian Democrat-Socialist alliance. He won the 1994 election.</p>
    <p>All along, he kept his two closest associates. One was Cesare Previti, whom Berlsuconi met in 1974 when Previti was lawyer for an artisocratic family,whose 147-room villa near Milan he arranged for Berlusconi to buy for the price of an apartment - after which Previti became Berlusconi's lawyer and, later, Defence Minister. Last year Previti lost his final appeal against a conviction for bribing judges in a case involving Berlusconi's business interests.</p>
    <p>If Previti was Berlusconi's left hand, his right hand was Marcello Dell'Utri. They met as students in Milan. Berlusconi made Dell'Utri president of Publitalia, keystone of his media empire. Dell'Utri was the prime mover behind Berlusconi's decision to enter politics. And in 2004 judges in Palermo ruled that that had involved mobilising the Mafia vote behind Berlusconi, after some of the bloodiest years in Cosa Nostra's history, with the assassination of two anti-Mafia judges, Giovanni Falcone and Paolo Borsellino. He is currently appealing against the conviction, and until it is heard is eligible to take his position in the Senate.</p>
    <p>Berlusconi has been accused 11 times of criminal activity. He was convicted once, in 1990, for perjury over his membership of the secretive P2 Masonic lodge. Other cases ended in acquittal or by falling off the agenda due to a statute of limitations, a process he facilitated with his own legislation, which made his office immune from prosecution.</p>
    <p>Professor Paul Ginsborg of Florence University, whose latest book concerns the nature of Berlusconi's power, said: 'There are three problems with this man: one, his control of television; two, his attitude towards the law, shaping legislation to help his particular situation and to bring an autonomous judiciary under the heel of the executive and government. The third is the combination of these two - the fact that he happens also to be President of the Council of Ministers.</p>
    <p>'What is extraordinary is that the left is in denial of all this, despite it being a fundamental element in Italy's democratic emergency, and this will cost them dear in the long run.'</p>
    <p>The centre-left has always underestimated Berlusconi. This was evident when he launched attacks against the judiciary combating corruption. The judiciary is a pillar of democracy in Italy, and no one in the political class was happy with that.</p>
    <p>The hero of 'Clean Hands', Judge Antonio di Pietro, leads a small party allied to Veltroni. Berlusconi says: 'He fills me with horror, this judge, this champion of handcuffs, with his judicial culture,' despite having offered Di Pietro the post of Justice Minister in his first administration. Di Pietro has been tough on Berlusconi.</p>
    <p>'The time has come,' he says, 'for Berlusconi to cease his calumny towards my work and that of the judiciary. He fears me.' But Veltroni has vetoed the obvious appointment of Di Pietro as his Minister of Justice should he form a government; 'maybe they are all afraid,' muses Di Pietro, 'that I would finish the job I started.'</p>
    <p>A succession of indefatigable writers has produced a body of work detailing and naming the connections between the Mafia and the body politic and one of them, Paul Gomez, published an article last week naming candidates sponsored by a Cosa Nostra vote large enough in the south to swing elections.</p>
    <p>Another, Roberto Saviano, has become an international figure after writing a book naming the leaders and political connections of the Neapolitan Camorra crime syndicates. 'I am sick of politics that does not talk about the Mafia,' he says - a snipe not only at connections in Berlusconi's ranks, but also at Veltroni's failure to challenge them. Until, that is, he went south last week.</p>
    <p>The two Italian cities that exist in a volcano's shadow - Naples and Catania - live in fear of the Camorra and Mafia respectively. The market in Catania teems with colours, dialect, fruits and cheeses while - smoking and smouldering - looming Etna watches from above.</p>
    <p>Before Veltroni took the stage in Catania, one banner was hoisted: 'Mirabella is here, to stick it up the Mafia's arse.' After a long ramble, Veltroni got to business. 'Without legality', he said, 'there is no prospect for development or growth. But the killers are getting weaker. More and more people are refusing to pay extortion money. It is not the names but the entire culture we need to change.'</p>
    <p>Next day, in Calabria, Veltroni had a message for the criminal syndicates: 'Don't vote for us, because we will destroy the forces that prevent development in the South.' His comment was praised by columnist Corrado Augias: 'During five years in government, Berlusconi never, I repeat never, invoked any possible struggle against the Mafia.'</p>
    <p>While the campaign trail continued, Italy wrangled with a blizzard of bad news. Three people were executed by the Calabrian Mafia and judges in Turin opened an investigation into Cosa Nostra control over contracts to repair a motorway.</p>
    <p>The death of two youths from heroin overdoses on the same day in the Prati district of Rome caused Guglielmo Masci, director of the capital's anti-addiction agency, to talk about a 'river of white powder flowing into the capital'. Everyone knows the traffickers' name - Cosa Nostra - but no one makes the connection to politics.</p>
    <p>There was a flurry of deaths in the workplace, four from toxins, and another football fan murdered at a motorway service station, the authorities now considering a ban on all away travel.</p>
    <p>The continuing mountains of rubbish in Naples spawned in turn the scandal of dioxins in mozzarella. And as the cheese crisis passed, a police investigation began into allegations that a crop of Italy's prince of wines, the Tuscan Brunello di Montalcino, was diluted with southern wine.</p>
    <p>Disillusionment with politicians' failure to tackle these ills finds expression in the phenomenon of comedian Beppe Grillo and his anti-politicial movement, which began through popular websites but last September burst into the Piazza Maggiore of Bologna as a street uprising by 80,000 people for 'V-Day' (V for Vaffanculo - Fuck Off) during which Grillo read the names of, and charges against, the 24 convicted criminals sitting in parliament.</p>
    <p>'Dell'Utri... has already been elected, together with all the others,' says the ebullient Grillo. 'Parliament is the new brothel of the Italians. Your vote is of no use. The game has already been played.' Veltroni and Berlusconi both advocate privatisation and 'liberalisation' against the 'malaise' of a corrupt and ineffective state apparatus, but by doing so they also challenge fundamental Italian principles about the responsibilities of the state, like the ownership of utilities and railways and the defence of the industrial sector from foreign ownership or collapse. Italians pay low fares for excellent publicly owned railways and are opposed to selling off the family silver.</p>
    <p>For all the polemic about 'liberalisation' in Italy, Italians build cars and ships owned by Italian companies with state support. The very day Nicolas Sarkozy was showing off his wife to the British tabloids, his government was teaming up with Italy on joint ventures between subsidised French and Italian shipyards, of a kind long since vanished from Britain. Paul Ginsborg is among those concerned that market purism may not necessarily be in Italy's long-term interests. 'The Italian state,' he says, 'is not a malleable instrument. The Italians are ready to come to the defence of things if they think there is a principle at stake.</p>
    <p>'Veltroni's party is old before its time, advocating the privatisation of public services and what is actually a good public school and university system, a good health system and a good public railway system,' he said.</p>
    <p>The discourse over home ownership is best illustrated by football: Berlusconi has no plans to sell AC Milan - or Fiat to sell Juventus - to Russian oligarchs any time soon. And this is the language that has made the future of the national carrier Alitalia a permanent backdrop to the election's final stages. Whether or not Berlusconi's own family and interests are involved in his attempts to keep Alitalia a 'flagship company', his insistence that the airline should remain Italian does him no harm. 'How did it happen that our flagship company could be given to the French?' he asks. 'The biggest applause I get is when I defend our airline.'</p>
    <p>Eugenio Scalfari is the founder of La Repubblica and the most important figure in Italian journalism. 'There is a malaise,' he affirms. 'It is increased by certain politicians and by the media, in particular television which does not analyse what is happening, yet perpetuates the state of uncertainty. You will never see an analysis on television about how the recent inflation hike is something imported, only how it will affect people's spending power. If you ask Italians whether they feel better or worse off, some will say better, some will say worse, many will say the same. But if you ask them, "How's it going generally?", they will say "terrible".'</p>
    <p>'People who spend a lot are not able to spend as much as they want to. The Italian reality is that the surplus has become necessary. People have been persuaded that what is not necessary has become necessary. It is true that work is uncertain and wages are low. But unemployment is also low, and many of those precarious jobs were not there at all before. No politician in pursuit of a consensus is going to say to the public: "You are wrong." The result is that none of this addresses the malaise, of those earning 500 euros a month but they're too busy trying to get by and don't have time to voice opinions and their votes count for little.</p>
    <p>'Another important reality,' says Scalfari, 'is that the mass of Italians hate the institutions of state. They are anarchists for whom the state is something that collects your taxes and provides a police officer in the moment of need. And anarchism opens the door to dictatorship. The centre-left wants to liberalise the market in such a regulated way, while Berlusconi is seen as the anti-state par excellence</p>
    <p>'Although of course he is not in favour of liberalisation at all, he is a monopolist. All people want is to travel well, and pay a low fare.'</p>
    <head rend="h2">Profile of a republic</head>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> A <hi rend="#b">republic </hi>since 2 June, 1946. Italy's 'Parlamento' consists of the <hi rend="#b">Senate</hi> (326 seats, 315 elected by popular vote, of which 232 are directly elected and 83 are by regional proportional representation, 11 are appointed senators for life; members serve five-year terms). <hi rend="#b">Chamber of Deputies </hi>(630 seats; 475 are directly elected, 155 by regional proportional representation; members serve five-year terms).</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Italy is credited as being the the birthplace of the <hi rend="#b">piano </hi>and violin. Glasses, ice cream and the <hi rend="#b">thermometer</hi> were all Italian inventions.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> The average Italian consumes 25 kilograms of pasta a year.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> During the <hi rend="#b">First World War,</hi> Italy renounced its standing alliance with Germany and Austria-Hungary and in 1915 entered the war on the side of the Allies. In 1922 <hi rend="#b">Benito Mussolini</hi> came to power and eliminated political parties, curtailed liberties and installed a <hi rend="#b">Fascist dictatorship</hi>.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Berlusconi leads an alliance comprising his 'People for Liberty' party, the Northern League of Umberto Bossi, the 'post-fascist' National Alliance of Gianfranco Fini and other small rightwing parties. This is opposed by Walter Veltroni's Democratic Party, in alliance with former judge Antonio Di Pietro's Italy of Values party and the Radical Party. Other contenders are the Socialist Party, the Union of the Democratic Centre, plus the Rainbow Left, the Critical Left, The Right and a large number of even smaller parties.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> There have been more than <hi rend="#b">60 government turnovers</hi> since 1945.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Italy allied with Germany and <hi rend="#b">declared war on the UK</hi> in 1940. In 1941 Italy, Germany and Japan declared war on the US and the USSR. After the Allied invasion of Sicily in 1943, the King dismissed Mussolini and appointed <hi rend="#b">Marshal Pietro Badoglio</hi>, whose government declared war on Germany.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Italy has three<hi rend="#b"> active volcanoes</hi>: Vesuvius, Etna and Stromboli.</p>
    <p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> This article was amended on Thursday April 24 2008.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>