<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi to face confidence vote" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2005-04-19" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/19/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi will face a vote of confidence in the Italian parliament later this week, Senate officials said today, after he refused last night to resign and form a new government to appease disgruntled members of his ruling coalition." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="f7b8c0bd96a28747">
  <main>
    <p>Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> will face a vote of confidence in the Italian parliament later this week, Senate officials said today, after he refused last night to resign and form a new government to appease disgruntled members of his ruling coalition.</p>
    <p>If Mr Berlusconi loses the confidence vote, his centre-right coalition government will fall after serving four years of a five-year term, and a general election by late June is a distinct possibility.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is scheduled to deliver a speech tomorrow afternoon, first in the Senate and then at the lower house of parliament, unnamed officials in Italy's upper house were quoted as saying by both the Associated Press and Reuters news agency.</p>
    <p>He will face the confidence vote the next day. It is unclear who demanded the vote.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi is struggling to find a way out of the crisis, which started when his coalition suffered a crushing defeat at regional elections held across Italy this month.</p>
    <p>The speech is expected to explain Mr Berlusconi's shock decision last night to call for a confidence vote rather than resigning and forming a new government, as his foreign secretary had indicated he would. Italian prime ministers have in the past used the resign and reshuffle tactic to strengthen faltering coalitions, but Mr Berlusconi has rejected the move as harking back to Italy's messy political past.</p>
    <p>The reshuffle was demanded by the centrist Union of Christian Democrats (UDC), which had pulled its members out of the government on Friday. Cabinet minister Roberto Maroni said in an interview with Corriere della Sera today that Mr Berlusconi might appeal to the UDC during his parliament address and ask it to return to the government.</p>
    <p>The confusion yesterday outraged the opposition, which accused Mr Berlusconi of exposing Italy to ridicule. Piero Fassino, leader of the Democratic Party of the Left, spoke of "a crisis that is being transformed into an indecent farce", according to the ANSA news agency.</p>
    <p>Another centre-left politician, Gavino Angius, called the situation an "unacceptable shame".</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's coalition took power in 2001, and he had hoped the government would become the first in post-war Italy to serve a full five-year term.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>