<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Italian PM sues rival politician for slander" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2003-09-16" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/sep/16/italy" hostname="theguardian.com" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, filed a €15m (£10.6m) slander lawsuit yesterday against the head of the country's largest opposition party over comments he made about an alleged bribery scandal, news reports said." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="d20a4a8ed984bcec">
  <main>
    <p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, filed a €15m (£10.6m) slander lawsuit yesterday against the head of the country's largest opposition party over comments he made about an alleged bribery scandal, news reports said.</p>
    <p>The lawsuit centres on remarks last month by Piero Fassino, of the Democrats of the Left party, who denies taking kickbacks in connection with the 1997 partial sale of Telekom Serbia to an Italian telecommunications giant.</p>
    <p>Mr Fassino said "puppeteers" at Mr Berlusconi's office were behind the accusations.</p>
    <p>Neither side was available to comment yesterday.</p>
    <p>The Telekom Serbia case has been at the centre of political debate in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> ever since a financial consultant, Igor Marini - a witness before a parliamentary commission looking into the deal - accused Mr Fassino of taking kickbacks.</p>
    <p>The sale took place when power was held by a centre-left government, which included Mr Fassino as well as other politicians facing accusations, including the EU commission president, Romano Prodi.</p>
    <p>Mr Prodi was Italian prime minister when 29% of Telekom Serbia was sold to Stet, a holding company that controlled state-run Telecom Italia. He has described the accusations as an "infamy".</p>
    <p>Last year, Telecom Italia agreed to sell the stake back to the Serbian government for €195m - less than half the amount it originally paid.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>