<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="1992 box set review – A terrifying struggle for power in Italy" author="Kathy Sweeney" date="2016-01-07" url="http://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2016/jan/07/1992-italy-silvio-berlusconi-power-struggle" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Shadowy camerawork reflects the venal ambitions that seem to lurk beneath every elegant surface as the mafia, police, politicians – and Silvio Berlusconi – vie for control of a country teetering on the brink of disaster" categories="Television &amp; radio" tags="Drama,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Television,Television &amp; radio,Culture" fingerprint="3ae580681165ffc5">
  <main>
    <p>It was, in many ways, Italy’s year zero. Set chiefly in Rome and Milan, this gripping drama lays bare the corruption of political and civic life by big business in the early 1990s, as the mafia, the police and politicians of all parties – new and old – vied for control of Italy’s First Republic. As we watch the country teeter on the brink, with the entire political hierarchy imploding, we also see how the ambitious, the weary and the frightened can arrive at disastrous conclusions. Into this vacuum steps the colourful, controversial figure of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and Forza Italia, the political party named after a terrace chant.</p>
    <p>Although based on fact, events are entirely fictional – yet <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0OyUVliQAq8">1992</ref> still provides an astonishing insight into how Italy ended up in its current parlous state. Unfolding like a masterclass in long-form storytelling, the series follows multiple skilfully woven storylines centred on the attempts of Milan magistrate Antonio Di Pietro to sort this mess out through the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2002/feb/21/guardianweekly.guardianweekly11">Clean Hands</ref> investigation – Italy’s own Watergate. Early on, pharmaceutical entrepreneur Michele Mainaghi is reeled in. While fictional, Mainaghi represents the many industrialists who were arrested during the actual investigation. His firm sold tainted blood, leaving many citizens HIV postive – among them investigating cop Luca Pastore, who has an impressive energy for revenge. His plight becomes a metaphor for corruption in Italy: “A disease that can be fought, but cannot be cured.”</p>
    <p>Other characters include a veteran of the first Gulf war who, despite being a meathead, is elected to parliament for the far-right Northern League party; a wannabe TV starlet sleeping her way to the top; and a slick, Don Draper-esque marketing manager who works at Berlusconi’s advertising company, Publitalia, and is the first to spot his boss’s political potential. In an allusion to Berlusconi’s legendary proclivities, he also persuades an advertiser to back a new show featuring scantily clad young women dancing around, something that would become a staple of virtually all Italian commercial TV.</p>
    <p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Berlusconi</ref> appears fleetingly throughout, mainly via archive footage, although there is one memorable scene where he is played by an actor. We just see the back of his head as he tells a lewd joke to an audience of schoolgirls. Berlusconi’s real-life ally <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/12/berlusconi-ally-caught-in-lebanon-after-fleeing-italy">Marcello Dell’Utri</ref>, currently serving seven years for colluding with the mafia, is also depicted.</p>
    <p>Cinematically shot, 1992’s sombre, washed-out tones and shadowy camerawork reflect the venal ambitions that seem to lurk beneath every elegant surface. But there’s no moral compass: the viewer is never lectured to. Even the mafia is depicted as just another face of capitalism. With all this come commanding performances, a soundtrack that convincingly anchors the series in the early 1990s (Teenage Fanclub, Primal Scream, REM, Slint) and superbly-observed period detail (high-waisted trousers, comically clunky mobile phones and, of course, workers smoking at their desks).</p>
    <p>After 1992, Italian politics became increasingly unhinged and no less corrupt, and the economy went into a protracted coma that its leaders simply lied about – to Italy, to Europe and to themselves. A terrifying and cautionary tale of anti-politics, 1992 is essential viewing for anyone worried and mystified by the seemingly unstoppable rise of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/04/donald-trump-first-tv-ad-2016-president">Donald Trump</ref>. As this series reminds us, we have been here before, not long ago, and it was not pretty.</p>
    <p>There’s plenty of this story still to be told and there are, apparently, plans for a sequel. Bring on 1993.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>