<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi sues over book on crime" author="Guardian staff reporter" date="2005-07-28" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/jul/28/italy.books" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister, is suing a British author and the Italian publisher of a book exploring corruption and organised crime in Italy." categories="World news" tags="World news,Italy,Books,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,Organised crime,Europe" fingerprint="72e01005f390eb11">
  <main>
    <p>
      <hi rend="#b">The following correction was printed in the Guardian's Corrections and clarificatons column, Wednesday August 3 2005</hi>
    </p>
    <p>David Lane, author of Berlusconi's Shadow: Crime, Justice and the Pursuit of Power, said Mr Berlusconi was seeking more than €1m (£690,000) in "moral damages". The Italian publisher, Editori Laterza, which earlier this year published the Italian translation, L'Ombra del potere, is also being sued.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi's camp have not clarified the basis for the defamation suit. A court date has not yet been set.</p>
    <p>Penguin, which published the book in English, has promoted it as an "exploration of the dark underside of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> today".</p>
    <p>The book looks at Mafia, organised crime and corruption in Italy, "and it also looks at <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> ... the principal actor of the Italian political stage since the early 1990s," Mr Lane told the Associated Press.</p>
    <p>Mr Lane, who has lived in Italy for almost 20 years, said he was somewhat surprised that Mr Berlusconi was suing over the book. "People who buy it are probably already critical" of Berlusconi, the author said.</p>
    <p>The AGI news agency said the Italian publishing house "reckon the accusation to be groundless and will respond through legal ways".</p>
    <p>Mr Lane also writes for the Economist newspaper, against which Mr Berlusconi brought a libel suit after an article in 2001 that declared he was "unfit to lead Italy".</p>
    <p>The piece ran just before his election win.</p>
    <p>Two years later, Mr Berlusconi's lawyers accused The Economist of mounting a hostile and politicised campaign against him, after the Economist published a dossier accusing him of using his political power to avoid justice and enact laws favourable to his own media empire.</p>
    <p>Mr Berlusconi has faced numerous charges of corruption, but the most serious accusation - that he bribed a judge - was thrown out last December.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>