<doc sitename="The Guardian" title="Berlusconi's blame game" author="Simon Jeffery" date="2005-07-29" url="http://www.theguardian.com/news/blog/2005/jul/29/berlusconisbla" hostname="theguardian.com" description="Silvio Berlusconi is not a man known for reserved remarks, so it should not be too surprising that he told his Forza Italia party that the euro had 'screwed everybody'" categories="News" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" fingerprint="378a083e0841ce05">
  <main>
    <p>Silvio Berlusconi is not a man known for reserved remarks. He once told a German MEP he would make a "perfect" concentration guard in a film his friend was shooting, so it should not be too surprising that in remarks on the euro to his Forza Italia party he said the currency had "<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/italy/story/0,12576,1538925,00.html">screwed everybody</ref>".</p>
    <p>The target of the comments was not so much the euro as Romano Prodi, the former European Commission president who is expected to run against him in the Italian general election in the first half of next year. Mr Berlusconi's argument runs that Mr Prodi, PM from 1996-98, put Italy into the euro's fixed exchange rates at too high a level, which he says is the root cause of an economic outlook that stretches from recession to zero growth forecasts. He rather conveniently blames the problems on his watch on the man who hopes to succeed him.</p>
    <p>The author of the pro-EU British blog <hi rend="#b">Europhobia</hi> (who, incidentally, wants to see the Italian PM "out on his money-heavy, principle-light arse") points out it is just another case of <ref target="http://europhobia.blogspot.com/2005/07/berlusconi-disaster-rip-off-that.html">a politician scapegoating the EU</ref> over domestic difficulties. Since national leaders realised around the end of the 1990s the EU a) allowed them to implement reforms they could never get away with at home and b) then blame it all on "Brussels", this has been a growing trend.</p>
    <p>And it is such a multilayered blame game, Europhobia argues, that will most likely be the drive behind Mr Berlusconi's campaign.</p>
    <quote>
      <p>If he can keep blaming all his country's problems on outside forces, uniting the people against a common enemy, he knows he's got a chance. So blame the economy on the EU, blame the EU on his most likely opponent, and undermine the anti-war opposition by launching lawsuits against the CIA, thus proving that he's not another Blair-like lapdog of the Americans.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>From a position of pure opportunism (a charge not unfamiliar to Mr Berlusconi) it makes some sense. If the EU and the euro are less popular than imagined among European voters, as the French and Dutch rejections of the constitution would suggest, a politician can either challenge the sentiment and argue for Europe or ride the wave of disaffection. Since his likely challenger was the commission president who oversaw the introduction of euro notes and coins and the May 2004 eastern enlargement (common complaints among the disaffected) it will be interesting to see if Mr Berlusconi is prepared to push either line against Mr Prodi.</p>
    <p>But this is about more than Italian politics and comes down to some of the fundamental questions about the single currency and whether, after the constitution votes, it has the necessary political backing. Thomas Meyer, an economist at Deutsche Bank, argues Mr Berlusconi is playing a dangerous game that could haunt him. "Comments like these could well reinforce concerns about the long-term stability of European monetary union," he tells the <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/money/main.jhtml?xml=/money/2005/07/29/cnsilv29.xml&amp;menuId=242&amp;sSheet=/money/2005/07/29/ixcity.html">Daily Telegraph</ref>.</p>
    <p>The euro's weakness is that it is a child of Maastricht – a far reaching and radical treaty - but the political union that was supposed to follow stalled as integrationist ambitions faltered in the 1990s amid tight referendums and occasional rejections. The question now is how little political and fiscal union the common currency needs to work. A recent study by HSBC economists Robert Prior-Wandesforde and Gwyn Hacche said the euro was <ref target="http://politics.guardian.co.uk/eu/comment/0,9236,1530829,00.html">in danger of collapsing</ref> in a few years if the EU did not get serious about structural reforms to its economies and to its fiscal rules.</p>
    <p>The same report said Italy would do better outside the eurozone with a weaker currency. But while the euro may stop the Italian government from devaluing (which is what a weaker currency would mean) it does not follow that the euro is necessarily the cause of the economic malaise. Mr Prodi blames Italy's poor growth and competitiveness on Mr Berlusconi's economic policies. Moving west along the Mediterranean, neither the introduction of the virtual euro or later notes and coins halted Spain's 12 consecutive years of economic growth. Its jobless rate is still high by eurozone standards (9.3%) but today stands at a <ref target="http://www.forbes.com/business/feeds/ap/2005/07/29/ap2164087.html">25 year low</ref>.</p>
    <p>The problem with Mr Berlusconi's remarks on the euro screwing "everybody" is that while currencies are part of every economy they are not the totality. The US pressured China to make their currency stronger to make them less competetive, but the economic boom was not just a consequence of an undervalued yuan.</p>
    <p>The Iberian peninsular provides another interesting example here: a piece this week in the <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/26/business/26subsidy.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1122649223-zDatoHMYr6lQ8+UPGTCqjw">New York Times</ref> pitted Spain's economy against Portugal's and found that despite broadly similar external factors Spain had spent its proportionally smaller share of EU funds (1% of GDP against Lisbon's 3%) much better. It now enjoys improved per capita income, greater productivity and, unlike Portugal, is not stuggling to pull out of recession. The truth Mr Berlusconi seems intent to avoid is it is sometimes possible to screw yourself.</p>
  </main>
  <comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</doc>