<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Amy Lawrence" categories="Football" date="2009-07-17" description="Amy Lawrence: Milan and Juventus are preaching a tale of regeneration and rejuvenation but some fans are not buying it" fingerprint="ad6517eb1142071b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Serie A,Juventus,Milan,Football,Sport,José Mourinho,Silvio Berlusconi,Kaká,Real Madrid" title="Milan and Juventus put their faith in the young ones | Amy Lawrence" url="http://www.theguardian.com/sport/blog/2009/jul/17/milan-juventus-young-players">
<main>
<p>Considering Silvio Berlusconi's penchant for youthful things, how incongruous that he allowed his beloved Milan to grow so old. Now, on the back of a summer that has seen three club institutions in Carlo Ancelotti, Paolo Maldini and Kaka depart, the hierarchy is suddenly preaching a tale of regeneration and rejuvenation. Trouble is, the fans are a little bit too concerned to buy into it.</p>
<p>Some of those who made an appearance at Milanello, the club's training facility, for the first day of pre-season were not entirely complimentary about this new policy. A few choice phrases and hurled objects made their feelings known. Season-ticket sales are down. Berlusconi responded by idly claiming that his team were as good as Internazionale. Useful.</p>
<p>"Protesting is fair enough," assessed vice-president Adriano Galliani, "but none of us is falling apart. We have simply decided to keep an eye on the balance sheet and to look to our young players. We have [Alexandre] Pato, an undeniable talent, then [Giacomo] Beretta, [Gianmarco] Zigoni and [Davide] Di Gennaro who are the guarantee of our future."</p>
<p>The man employed to instruct them is also young. To the outside eye the promotion of the 39-year-old Leonardo, the urbane Brazilian who was a classy player at San Siro and has been working behind the scenes since his retirement, seems an extraordinary risk. He is a novice coach. This is his first experience of such a role at any level – in fact he spent part of the summer on a coaching course at Coverciano, the Italian Federation's technical centre, to gain the necessary qualifications. While the negotiations for Kaka were being completed between Milan and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/realmadrid">Real Madrid</ref>, he was sharing a room with a fellow student, knuckling down and tackling his exams. "It's a slog but it is a really useful course," Leonardo said. He was, by all accounts, a very keen student.</p>
<p>He was always popular with Milan fans, not only for his playing style but for having the acumen, as a scout for Milan, to bring Kaka and then Pato to the club from his homeland. But not everything from Brazil inspires confidence. Leonardo has received the dreaded vote of confidence from Pele, whose talent for predictions is notoriously off beam.</p>
<p>Interestingly, he is not the only coach from Italy's big three who is about to embark upon a big adventure in the pressure-cooker world of top-level coaching. Over at <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/juventus">Juventus</ref> the form er defender Ciro Ferrara, handed the reins for the final two games of last season after Claudio Ranieri was dismissed, has been installed to push Juve closer to the silverware that used to feel inevitable. Although Ferrara has gained invaluable know-how as a member of Marcello Lippi's staff with the Italian national team, this marks his debut as a numero uno. What a place to start.</p>
<p>Gambles they may be, but both clubs have a history of making such moves and seeing them develop into periods of triumph. Fabio Capello's first permanent job as a coach came at Milan, as successor to Arrigo Sacchi. The team of "Invincibles" which included Franco Baresi, Paolo Maldini, Ruud Gullit, Frank Rijkaard and Marco van Basten duly won four scudetti in five seasons and walloped Barcelona in the 1994 European Cup final.</p>
<p>Giovanni Trapattoni also began at Milan and was swiftly poached by Juventus to begin – at the age of only 37 – a roll call of honours in Turin that included all three European trophies and six <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/serieafootball">Serie A</ref> titles in a magnificent decade.</p>
<p>It is asking a considerable amount of both Leonardo and Ferrara to expect history even to half repeat itself. The shock of the new might be back in fashion – just ask Pep Guardiola what miracles can be achieved in one season flat – but both Milan and Juve are in the middle of some fairly serious restructuring of their squads.</p>
<p>At the moment Ferrara would appear to be better off. Juve have recruited international excellence down their spine – Fabio Cannavaro is back in his home environment at the heart of an Italian back four, Felipe Melo will add terrific bite to midfield, and Diego proved himself to be an tasty playmaker during an outstanding season in Germany. Milan, who are trying to buy Luis Fabiano from Sevilla, still look like they have work to do to make the necessary improvements.</p>
<p>Inter remain the team to beat in Italy, as they have been since the <hi rend="#i">Calciopoli</hi> scandal altered the dynamic between the top teams with a mighty lurch. Both Juventus and Milan need to make up the 10-point deficit by which both trailed Inter at the end of last season.</p>
<p>It may feel slightly strange for the Inter coach Jose Mourinho, who always appeared to relish his status as the young, brash kid on the coaching block, but this season on Italy's biggest stages he is the relative voice of experience.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>