<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff" categories="Football" date="2014-06-09" description="Clarence Seedorf has been dismissed by Milan coach after only five months in charge" fingerprint="a695ffe8485e617" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Serie A,Football,Sport" title="Clarence Seedorf sacked as Milan coach and replaced by Filippo Inzaghi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2014/jun/09/clarence-seedorf-sacked-milan-inzaghi">
<main>
<p>Clarence Seedorf has been sacked as the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> coach after five months in charge and replaced by the first-team coach Filippo Inzaghi.</p>
<p>The writing had been on the wall for the Dutchman over the weekend after Milan’s president <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> described him as being part of the club’s “past”.</p>
<p>The apparent delay in making the announcement was put down to negotiations over the parting of the ways with Seedorf, who was appointed in January, still having two more years of his contract to run.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.acmilan.com/en/news/breaking_news">The club released a short statement</ref> on Monday in which they said: “Clarence Seedorf has been dismissed. Filippo Inzaghi has been appointed as first-team coach, and is under contract until 30 June 2016.”</p>
<p>Berlusconi had said on Friday: “We’ll see at the next board meeting what solution we find for Clarence Seedorf but that’s enough talking about the past, we are looking to the future.</p>
<graphic alt="Filippo Inzaghi" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Sport/Pix/columnists/2014/6/9/1402321879525/Filippo-Inzaghi-012.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p>“I’ve seen that Inzaghi is very determined, hungry for victory and absolutely in line with everything we want Milan to be. We want a team which wins, plays convincingly and entertains the fans.</p>
<p>“I hope that next season we can field a team which can start a new cycle. We have to become among the top competitors again like we have been for the past 30 years, at the moment we are between one cycle and another.”</p>
<p>Milan won 11 out of 19 Serie A matches under Seedorf, who had spent 10 years at the club as one of their most distinguished players and a <ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefachampionsleague/news/newsid=2044392.html">four-times Champions League winner with three different clubs</ref>, on their way to finishing eighth in Serie A.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>