<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Michael White" categories="Politics" date="2009-10-29" description="Michael White: Two great literary titles share a birthday … two great literary titles that don't share a readership" fingerprint="7f75995739afbba5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,Media,Film,Magazines,Silvio Berlusconi,George Osborne,Russell Brand,Jimmy Carr" title="Michael White's Diary" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/oct/29/viz-russell-brand-jimmy-carr">
<main>
<p>It is a national disgrace. The week may pass with scarce acknowledgment that two of the nation's cherished literary magazines are celebrating their 30th birthday within days of each other – not even a joint service at St Paul's, despite their shared interests. The London Review of Books began as a supplement to its New York sister just as the Thatcher era was emerging. It now sells 44,000 copies among the progressive intelligentsia – the sort of people who so dislike Labour. Founded two days earlier in Chris Donald's bedroom at the parental home in Jesmond – the progressive quarter of Newcastle – was Viz, hand-stapled and sold in pubs for 20p. It mocks politicians too. At its peak Viz sold 1.2m, but still shifts about 80,000 at a yuppie £3 a pop. Karl Miller never edited Viz. Tariq Ali, Salman Rushdie or Eric Hobsbawm never contributed words or cartoons. Unlike Jeremy Clarkson, they may not even have read it regularly, or followed the careers of Buster Gonad, Johnny Fartpants, Sid the Sexist or the Fat Slags. Yet both magazines address the concerns of what the LRB calls "the common reader", and seek to entertain them with "complex, witty and surprising writing". Happy birthday, both.</p>
<p>Things must be tough, even for £100k-a-year doctors. The British Medical Journal's website now contains banner ads for Morrisons, the proudly low-cost supermarket chain, which declares this to be "Big Price Crunch Week". The highlighted specials are baking potatoes, satsumas and savoy cabbage. Don't they realise medics are as unhealthy as the rest of us?</p>
<p>What's going on? In Wednesday's FT <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/mar/24/in-the-loop-alastair-campbell">Alastair Campbell, the thinking man's Malcolm Tucker</ref>, warned that George Osborne should not be Tory election strategist and shadow chancellor. Ken Clarke can do better than that. The man whose name is linked with "gaffe" as closely as "Ant" is with "Dec" this week called attention-seeking <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/oct/28/vaclav-klaus-lisbon-treaty">Václav Klaus</ref> Europe's Mr No "the Boris Johnson of eastern Europe" – a two for one insult to both hooligans.</p>
<p>But is it Osborne who should worry? Ken (69) is telling friends that David Cameron should make him chancellor again for the first two years so he can soak up the blame for all those <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2009/oct/07/george-osborne-conservatives-spending-cuts">unpopular decisions Master George</ref> would have to take. Nice try, Ken, but don't wait by the phone.</p>
<graphic alt="Diary illustration" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2009/10/28/1256761156808/leslie_caron.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p>Panic at the London Gypsy and Traveller Unit the other day when the Sun rang, seeking to make a donation. "Are they trying to hack our bank acount?" gypsies asked travellers. But no, the cheque was from bearded narcissist <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/russell-brand">Russell Brand</ref>, payment for a BNP-bashing article in the Bun. LGTU is delighted: better an edgy comic on your side than an edgy gag from <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/stage/theatreblog/2009/oct/26/jimmy-carr-joke-apology">Jimmy Carr</ref> about "smelling female gypsy (moths) up to seven miles away". Carr, then as now, ended up apologising.</p>
<p>Italy is worried about the growing craze for binge drinking. Max magazine reminds its hip readers that "The beauty of Mediterranean culture is to try everything, but not to excess, and to enjoy the dinner right to the end" – advice Silvio Berlusconi has clearly taken to heart. But Max dispatched a team, horrified, to "the European <ref target="http://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/health/s/1019912_binge_drink_capital_of_britain">capital of alcoholism</ref>", there to watch girls in short skirts puking into cold gutters. Yes, Manchester, it's you. Yet, why should Italians be surprised? Complaints about the English being crop-haired, tattoed champions of bling "who drink till they are sick" date at least to William of Malmesbury (1090-1143). He probably blamed the Romans.</p>
<p>Not everyone can say they danced with Fred Astaire, Gene Kelly and (maybe) Rudy Nureyev. But <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Caron">Leslie Caron</ref> (78), who was promoting her autobiography, "Thank Heaven..." at the National Theatre this week, did it all, sang with Maurice Chevalier (a grumpy old man offstage) in Gigi, fought off booze and depression. When touring pre-Nasser Egypt in Roland Petit's company, she did not have to fight off lecherous King Farouk because Petit hid his female dancers in the loo for the king's visit. Farouk had to make do with the ballet boys.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>