<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Football" date="2003-06-09" description="Italian prime minister and AC Milan owner-president Silvio Berlusconi ruled out a move for David Beckham in emphatic terms today when questioned by reporters on his trip to the Middle East." fingerprint="1dcc0b2ff91a8105" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Football,Sport,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Berlusconi 'no' to Beckham" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2003/jun/09/newsstory.sport4">
<main>
<p>Italian prime minister and AC Milan owner-president <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> ruled out a move for David Beckham in emphatic terms today when questioned by reporters on his trip to the Middle East.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who still makes all the major decisions in the running of the club although he leaves his deputy Adriano Galliani in day-to-day control, could hardly have been more candid when asked about whether he would buy the Manchester United midfielder.</p>
<p>"There are many better ways of spending money, earned with such sacrifice, rather than signing Mr Beckham," said Berlusconi to Italian reporters in Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Earlier, the Italian club's vice president Adriano Galliani had been quoted as saying "Beckham is our primary target". But general director Ariedo Braida insisted the transfer rumours linking the Manchester United midfielder to the European champions were pure fabrication.</p>
<p>Braida today told PA International: "No, we are absolutely not interested, they are just fantasy rumours that have been reported by the press.</p>
<p>"He (Beckham) is a great player, but there is nothing in it."</p>
<p>United broke their silence on the speculation surrounding Beckham's future on Saturday when they issued a statement in which they revealed that Italian and Spanish clubs had "expressed a firm interest" in signing Beckham.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>