<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Julian Coman" categories="World news" date="2009-10-08" description="La Stampa attacks Berlusconi's claim that loss of legal immunity is part of a leftwing conspiracy to unseat him" fingerprint="bebb92083b7bc687" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Media,Newspapers,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Italian newspapers pass verdict on Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/08/la-repubblica-berlusconi-legal-immunity-case">
<main>
<p>The centre-left paper, La Repubblica, said that Berlusconi had treated the decision by Italy's constitutional court to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/08/sivlio-berlusconi-immunity-law-overturned">remove his legal immunity</ref> as if it amounted to a guilty verdict in advance.</p>
<p>"Terrorised by the judges and terrorised by his own past," it commented, "the premier seemed unaware that he reacted to the ruling as if he had been condemned already … In reality, it needs to be remembered that the prime minister has simply been restored to his normal status as an ordinary citizen … who must answer before the judges."</p>
<p>La Stampa attacked Berlusconi's claim that the constitutional court was part of a leftwing conspiracy to unseat him. In a comment piece headlined Beyond Every Limit the paper's former editor Marcello Sorgi wrote: "Berlusconi has every right to say that he will carry on in power despite the reopening of the cases … but what he has no right to say, as he did immediately after the decision yesterday, is that the court made its decision because it is "on the left". Incredibly, he even included the head of state, Giorgio Napolitano, in the plot against him."</p>
<p>But Il Foglio, edited by Berlusconi's rightwing ally Giuliano Ferarra, warned his opponents that it was too early to toast the prime minister's political demise.</p>
<p>"So Berlusconi returns to the courts," it wrote. "We're going to see some fun. [He] has fire in his belly, sustained by the goodwill of the majority of Italians. He won't have anything to do with futile early elections."</p>
<p>Il Sole 24 Ore, Italy's equivalent of the Financial Times, had less confidence in Berlusconi's ability to brazen out what it described as "the most difficult phase of his long political career".</p>
<p>In a editorial, the paper wrote: "The prime minister is severely weakened, limping like never before. The image of a leader who has now to present himself in various courts and respond to the questions of magistrates, with the fear of damning verdicts against him, will be devastating both at home and abroad".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>