<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Saviano; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2011-11-11" description="Current crisis may have been easily resolved if the embattled leader's promised reforms had been put into effect" fingerprint="3b88837f53b1c755" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi has always acted in his own – not Italy's – interests" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/11/silvio-berlusconi-own-interests-italy">
<main>
<p>There is a word which, more than any other, describes what characterises the Berlusconi government politically and economically, and what it has meant for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. That word is <hi rend="#i">immobilismo</hi>, an untranslatable term drawn from the vocabulary of Italian politics and which signifies inertia or opposition to progress.</p>
<p>In the past 20 years, nothing has happened for the good of the country. Not one of the reforms promised in 1994, and which would have helped to resolve the crisis that Italy was – and is – experiencing, has been put into effect.</p>
<p>It is clear that the markets have succeeded where the electorate, the opposition, the media and intellectuals have not. It is an irony of fate that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who always boasted of having created a business empire from nothing, of having embodied the American dream of the self-made man, and who always considered himself a champion when it came to numbers and money, should have been defeated in just the place where he always said he was in his element – in the market. He has been put into political receivership by an international financial establishment that could no longer trust his management of the economy.</p>
<p>A brilliant Italian writer, Ennio Flaiano, once said the shortest line between two points in Italy is a curlicue. The years of Berlusconi government have been a curlicue – the longest possible line between the old and the old dressed up as new.</p>
<p>In a short time, Berlusconi transformed politics into a football stadium in which the members of the public are the fans, supporting their sides regardless of how they perform. At most, for a bit, they boo. But they only and always want victory. Berlusconi introduced a new way of speaking so that deciding to devote yourself to politics became "taking to the field".</p>
<p>He himself said that his entry into politics took place so that he could look after his own interests – both his personal ones and those of his companies. And that is exactly what we have seen in the 20 years in which he has been unquestionably the central figure on the Italian political stage.</p>
<p>His official roles have coincided with his private business affairs. The foreign heads of state who have been closest to him in recent years are nothing but business partners.</p>
<p>There was Putin's gas. Russian energy represents 70% of exports to Italy and Hillary Clinton has expressed doubts about the business nature of the political convergence between Berlusconi and Putin. Then there was the embarrassing friendship with Muammar Gaddafi.</p>
<p>His government has not passed one law for the state; not one law that, over the years, might have given our economy the wherewithal to tackle the crisis on the horizon. There have been no laws for Italy – just laws for him.</p>
<p>It is not as if he lacked the numbers in parliament. He had, for a long time, an incredibly strong majority that would have allowed him to pass the promised reforms that, following the judicial earthquake that destroyed the old Italian parties in the 1990s, made him the new man, the new broom, the champion of that liberal reformism that he juxtaposed with the stagnation of a left that was incapable of changing.</p>
<p>There has been no reform of justice, nothing for the new generations, victims of a fateful deregulation of the labour market that has brought with it short-term contracts solely intended to favour companies that exploit the workers.</p>
<p>In Italy the public sector is in ruins. The health service has standards unworthy of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>. The schools, the universities and research are all crippled.</p>
<p>Parliament has for years been taken up with discussing, amending and voting on bills tailored to Berlusconi's personal needs and those of his companies, from the so-called Biondi decree of 1994, which tried to curb the powers of Italy's prosecutors, to the 2010 law of "legitimate impediment", which allowed Berlusconi to delay court proceedings against him.</p>
<p>Some favour him and his companies indirectly. Others have served in almost too blatant a way to legitimise, save or shield from collapse the prime minister's companies or, still more often, hinder the trials in which the prime minister was and is a defendant.</p>
<p>The new world Berlusconi promised has become an old world – older than the one that preceded it. And there is the risk that the politics that await us will be neither more nor less than the continuation of the power games that Berlusconi interrupted.</p>
<p>They will be the old dressed up as the new. It is not known yet whether the next government will be the result of an early election or a broad agreement between the parties. The debate is heated and the decisions are being taken right now, as I write and you read.</p>
<p>But the new government will have the arduous job of introducing the economic reforms that could have been implemented over the past 20 years, and which will instead strangle Italy in the months to come. Mario Monti, whom Europe has had the opportunity to get to know and appreciate in the 10 years in which he was a European commissioner, from 1995 to 2004, is now a life senator and the most likely candidate for this transitional government.</p>
<p>Europe trusts him and that could give the Italian economy a breathing space. But if it falls to him to take over the helm, he will have to make difficult choices which, Italian history shows, will not be rewarded.</p>
<p>What is more, even though Berlusconi the man seems to be finished, Berlusconi-ism is not yet dead. It is there, patiently waiting to re-emerge, ready to say "without me, it has been worse". Its standard-bearers are waiting to exploit the difficult moments through which Italy will be living.</p>
<p>So let's be careful about those who are slipping away. Let's be careful about those who, apparently in the cause of altruism, are saying that a cross-party coalition should include everyone, even this or that political faction. In this phase, altruism means dumping the responsibility on your political adversary.</p>
<p>And be careful too of those screaming for immediate elections. It is anything but a true battle for civil liberties, but rather an attempt to cash in on the votes that the crisis and the anger in society will make available.</p>
<p>The impression is that, once again, there is space for anything but talent and a will to reconstruct the country; a country bowed down not so much economically as in terms of its morale, its confidence, its people's belief in the possibility of future happiness, of being able to fulfil themselves without having to go abroad. In Italy, once again, the risk is that of wiping clean the slate so as to be able the more easily to go back.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i"> Roberto Saviano lives at a secret location to avoid reprisal attacks for his book about the mafia, Gomorrah</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>