<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2003-09-19" description="In common with many of his compatriots, Silvio Berlusconi sometimes seems unable to come to terms with Italy's fascist past, writes John Hooper." fingerprint="7830133ad0868e4c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Air-brushing history" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/sep/19/italy.worlddispatch">
<main>
<p>A pattern is beginning to be discernible in the aftermath of Silvio Berlusconi's renowned "gaffes", if that is indeed what they are.</p>
<p>First, he seems to apologise. Then he says he didn't. It is what happened after he told a German MEP in July that he reminded him of a concentration camp guard. And it is what has now happened over his claim that Mussolini "never killed anybody".</p>
<p>At the Rome synagogue on Wednesday those present heard what they thought was a "sorry". Amos Luzzato, head of the federation of Italian Jewish communities, said afterwards: "He apologised to us and specifically to me ..."</p>
<p>But then came a statement from the prime minister's office claiming he had merely "expressed his sorrow for the pain caused to the Jewish community by a manipulative interpretation of his words, not attributable to him".</p>
<p>In other words, Mr Berlusconi was sorry - not for what he had himself done - but for the effect of what had been done by other people: his enemies in the media who had, as usual, wilfully misinterpreted and misrepresented his words.</p>
<p>There are many who think it is deliberate: that the wily billionaire politician is trying to push back the bounds of the sayable, always taking two steps forward then one step back. Certainly, his recent assertion that Italy's judges were "mentally disturbed" could well have been part of a campaign to discredit them in the eyes of the public.</p>
<p>But it is hard to see what possible advantage Mr Berlusconi could derive from upsetting Jews by sticking up for a dictator who allowed some 7,000 to be deported to the Nazis' concentration camps.</p>
<p>As Augusto Minzolini, a columnist in La Stampa has noted, this is the same man who abandoned Italy's once pro-Arab stance; he who refused to see Yasser Arafat when he was in the Middle East earlier this year; he who said that "I experience every terrorist attack on Israel as if it were an attack on my own people" and was lauded in turn by Ariel Sharon as Israel's "super-friend".</p>
<p>"Either", Minzolini concluded, "Berlusconi is a friend of Israel and his comments were an accident, or the Jerusalem government, Sharon, the Mossad and the American Jewish community, which is preparing to welcome him with open arms [on a forthcoming visit to the US] ... have all blundered."</p>
<p>Maybe. Or maybe there is a third possibility: that there are unconscious contradictions in the views that Silvio Berlusconi holds; that, although he makes common cause with Ariel Sharon, a fellow rightwinger, Italy's prime minister nevertheless holds to the same indulgent view of the fascist past that is held by millions of his compatriots.</p>
<p>Unlike the Germans, the Italians as a whole have yet to come to terms with what Gianni Oliva, the author of a new book on Italy's role in the second world war called "our unspeakable past". Mr Oliva's point is that the activities of the partisans in the final phase of the war were used to create a myth of resistance to - rather than support of - Hitler and the Nazis.</p>
<p>But similar air-brushing techniques have been used on the period leading up to the outbreak of the war. Mr Berlusconi's remark is entirely consistent with the widespread view that Mussolini was simply a blustering clown and that the innate gentleness of the Italians softened the thrust of his crueller ideas.</p>
<p>In fact, Mussolini was the inventor of a perilous creed that inspired Nazism, but proved pretty popular to Italians at the time. He led his country, more or less willingly into a string of cruel and unnecessary wars.</p>
<p>Numerically, the deportation of the Italian Jews was a minor episode in the career of a dictator who, one recent biographer has estimated, caused the death of at least 1 million people, including Libyans, Ethiopians and the inhabitants of former Yugoslavia. Yet rarely do you hear or read a word about any of this in Italy.</p>
<p>The keeper of the nation's conscience, its head of state, President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, made his own contribution to the debate still raging over Mr Berlusconi's remarks in a ceremony at a village in the north west whose villagers took in fleeing Jews at the risk of their own lives.</p>
<p>It showed, he said, that "in the most tragic moment, the humanity of our nation glowed even more".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>