<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2006-04-11" description="Romano Prodi seemed assured of a majority in both houses of parliament, though the fate of Italy's next government could rest on a knife edge in the senate and its very formation by the centre-left was last night challenged by Silvio Berlusconi." fingerprint="16f0e2f3de248b04" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="A triumph of sorts as the professor beats the clown" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/apr/12/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>In the end, it turned out better than he must have feared at times during Italy's long, tense election night.</p>
<p>Yesterday, Romano Prodi seemed assured of a majority in both houses of parliament, though the fate of Italy's next government could rest on a knife edge in the senate and its very formation by the centre-left was last night challenged by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>The outcome was not the clear victory promised by opinion and exit polls, but it nevertheless represented a considerable triumph for a man whose genial manner and reasoned arguments were all but eclipsed during the campaign by the raucous, vulgar clowning of his opponent. Mr Prodi is an easy man to underrate. His nickname is "the Mortadella" because, like Italy's favourite pink sausage, he is agreeably bland and comes from Bologna.</p>
<p>But while "the Prof" - to give him his other nickname - may be regarded as having made a hash of his stint as president of the EU Commission, he has a 100% record of success in his homeland. He has twice taken on the intimidatingly populist Mr Berlusconi - first in 1996 - and twice emerged with the lion's share of votes and seats.</p>
<p>In the lower house of Italy's parliament, the Chamber of Deputies, he is guaranteed an ample majority of 50 seats because of a rule change made by Mr Berlusconi's government last year.</p>
<p>The centre-left Union won just 25,000 votes more than the rightwing House of Freedoms, but the new law provides the winning side with bonus seats to make sure it can legislate.</p>
<p>Mr Prodi's problems start in the upper house, which has the same powers as the Chamber of Deputies. There, different rules apply and the centre-left was looking at a tiny, two-seat majority of the elected senators.</p>
<p>But a further idiosyncrasy of Italy's political system is that not all its senators are elected. Seven are named for life. But most can be expected to vote for Mr Prodi if necessary, so his real majority in the upper house should be about six.</p>
<p>That Mr Prodi's majority should be so slim is evidence of the effectiveness of Mr Berlusconi's crassly populist tactics in the final stage of the campaign.</p>
<p>Whether it was his offensive language, his improbable claims to be a victim of an establishment plot, or his equally improbable promises of tax cuts, something worked. He succeeded in trimming a 3.5 to 5 percentage point advantage in the polls to virtually nothing by election day.</p>
<p>The fact that his party, Forza Italia, remains Italy's biggest should be enough to assure his survival, at least for the moment, as leader of the right. At 69, he does not have much time in which to wrest back power, but he should have plenty of opportunities.</p>
<p>If, as expected, Mr Prodi is appointed to head the next government, a narrow majority in the upper house will not be his only headache. On the one hand, the Union's programme commits it to "radical reforms" aimed at improving Italy's flagging competitiveness.</p>
<p>On the other, the election results showed the parties on the left which did best were those least keen on those "radical reforms".</p>
<p>Communist Refoundation - led by Fausto Bertinotti, a former trade unionist who dresses like an English country gentleman - wants to follow France by ditching a law that introduces short-term employment contracts.</p>
<p>But Mr Bertinotti can expect stiff resistance from the rightwing of the Union, who want to shape it into something like the US Democratic party.</p>
<p>In his latest film, The Cayman, the director Nanni Moretti compares Mr Berlusconi to the deadly reptile of that name.</p>
<p>If the centre-left does fall to squabbling, it will not be long before Italy's ruthless billionaire statesman eases himself off the mud and moves in for the kill.</p>
<p>That might just provide the winners of this contest the incentive they need to stick together.</p>
<p>The desire for survival is a great unifier.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Playing by the rules</hi>
</p>
<p>Some 3.5 million Italian citizens living abroad, who were given the right to vote in the election for the first time, helped Mr Prodi's government to victory. Four of the six overseas seats went to his Union coalition, one to Silvio Berlusconi's conservative allies and one to an independent party. The four seats gave Mr Prodi's forces 158 seats.</p>
<p>The balance of power in the Senate, however, may also depend on a group of aging Life Senators who are appointed "for outstanding merits in the social, scientific, artistic or literary field" and includes former presidents. Among them are Giulio Andreotti, 87, who was prime minister of Italy seven times and has been repeatedly accused of having ties to the Mafia, and who is likely to side with the right, and Nobel prize winner Rita Levi-Montalcini, who is likely to side with the left, and law professor and former president of Italy Francesco Cossiga, who is regarded as a "wild card" and may go to the left or right.</p>
<p>The turnout was extremely high, with 84% of those eligible to vote casting their ballots. Polls were also open for two days, instead of the usual one. Exit polls and surveys that failed to predict the outcome have been criticised by both sides.</p>
<p>Under Italian law, polls were not allowed to be published during the last two weeks of the campaign and many people relied on a poll before the blackout which gave the left a lead of 3.5% to 5%, a margin that was dramatically cut. Mr Berlusconi prompted laughter when he broke the rule a few days before polling, revealing he had called women working on sex chat lines and that seven out of nine he spoke to preferred him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Barbara McMahon</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>