<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-11-15" description="Berlusconi allies and bond markets appear to warm to PM designate's attempt to form a 'technocratic' government" fingerprint="5f8a6ab2dcabff6d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Mario Monti,Eurozone crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news,European banks,Business" title="Mario Monti's stock rises as Italy's 'moment of truth' arrives" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/15/mario-monti-italy-moment-truth">
<main>
<p>Mario Monti appeared to be making good progress towards the formation of a new government as the president of the European council, Herman Van Rompuy, warned Italy was facing its "moment of truth".</p>
<p>In early afternoon trading, the Milan bourse turned positive and the interest rate on Italian government bonds came down as encouraging signs mounted. They came after a sharp spike during the morning in the yields demanded for riskier eurozone debt pushed Italy's benchmark borrowing costs beyond the psychologically hazardous level of 7%.</p>
<p>Altero Matteoli, a minister in Silvio Berlusconi's outgoing government, who had been among those demanding that stiff conditions be attached to a new, "technocratic" administration, abruptly changed the tenor of his remarks. "It seems to me now that the government is born," he said.</p>
<p>His was the second positive comment to emerge from Berlusconi's party, the Freedom People (PdL). Its secretary, Angelino Alfano, had said that after meeting the prime minister designate, he thought: "Prof Monti's attempt to form a government can succeed."</p>
<p>What was unclear was whether the PdL had extracted any concessions from Monti who, on Monday night, said he would not go ahead if a time limit were put on his government. A general election does not have to be held in Italy until spring 2013.</p>
<p>The PdL originally floated two more demands. One was a narrow programme, restricted to the implementation of economic reforms and deficit-cutting measures agreed by Berlusconi with the European institutions. The other was the inclusion in the cabinet of the media tycoon's right-hand man, Gianni Letta, a former newspaper editor and Berlusconi executive.</p>
<p>Italy's biggest opposition group, the Democratic party (PD), strenuously denied a report it had agreed to Letta's inclusion on condition that Monti also brought in a politician from the centre-left, Giuliano Amato.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>