<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2009-10-27" description="Italy's prime minister has cancelled official engagements due to the illness, local media report" fingerprint="df6af02eb35bdc85" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,European Union,Europe" title="Scarlet fever may force Silvio Berlusconi to miss EU summit" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/27/berlusconi-scarlet-fever-italy-eu-summit">
<main>
<p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has contracted a mild form of scarlet fever, Italian media reported , leading him to cancel a public engagement and throwing into doubt his presence at a European Union summit this week.</p>
<p>The Italian daily Corriere della Sera said the 73-year-old prime minister may have contracted the illness from one of his five grandchildren. Symptoms including fever, rashes and a sore throat are treatable with antibiotics.</p>
<p>About 25,000 Italians catch scarlet fever each year.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's office did not comment on the report, but the financial daily Il Sole 24 Ore said political sources had confirmed the story and quoted the prime minister as saying: "How can I go on like this?"</p>
<p>Corriere reported that Berlusconi had pulled out of an event in earthquake struck Abruzzo today and might miss the EU summit in Brussels later this week.</p>
<p>Despite battling against prostate cancer in the 1990s and having a pacemaker fitted in 2006 after he collapsed on stage, Berlusconi has prided himself on his busy schedule since his reelection to a third term in 2008, despite suffering from acute neck pain.</p>
<p>During his three-day visit to Russia last week to celebrate Vladimir Putin's birthday, local media reported that Berlusconi briefly took the controls of a Russian aircraft and described "an enormous sense of power".</p>
<p>He returned to his villa near Milan at the weekend to hold talks with ministers in a bid to smooth out a row with his finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, over tax policy. On 16 November he will go back on trial accused of tax fraud, after Italy's constitutional court threw out a law granting him immunity.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's natural defences against illness are meanwhile undimmed, according to his personal physician Umberto Scapagnini, who has called his immune system "extraordinary".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>