<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-11-27" description="Despite pleas and threats from Berlusconi, Italian senators almost certain to vote in favour of expelling former PM after tax fraud conviction" fingerprint="7ffbd2357a27d7ed" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi set for Senate vote on expulsion" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/27/silvio-berlusconi-senate-vote-expulsion-italy">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi could suffer arguably the heaviest blow of his political career on Wednesday night when the upper house of parliament is expected to vote to oust him following a conviction for tax fraud.</p>
<p>A hostile front of the centre-left and anti-establishment Five Star Movement (M5S) is almost certain to vote against the former prime minister, who pulled his Forza Italia party from Enrico Letta's governing coalition and into opposition on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2011/nov/13/silvio-berlusconi-resigns-italy-in-pictures">resigned as PM in late 2011</ref> amid concerns over Italy's growing financial instability, received his first definitive conviction in 20 years of legal battles <ref target="http://www.economist.com/blogs/charlemagne/2013/08/silvio-berlusconi">on 1 August</ref>. He was sentenced to four years in prison, commuted to one year of community service.</p>
<p>The debate over the parliamentary ramifications of the conviction has dominated the national political scene for the past four months. The 77-year-old media magnate has issued <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/02/silvio-berlusconi-humiliating-climbdown-italian-parliament">alternate pleas and threats</ref> in an attempt to avoid being stripped of his seat under a law passed last year – with the support of his then party, the Freedom People – which stipulates that MPs convicted of serious criminal offences must be ineligible for parliament.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has kept up the battle until the last minute, claiming on Monday to have new evidence that he said would exonerate him, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/25/silvio-berlusconi-senate-vote-italy">begging his fellow senators</ref> to put off the vote until the documents had been examined.</p>
<p>He insists the conviction is another sign of his continuing persecution by leftwing judges. He has indicated that Giorgio Napolitano, the Italian president, should pardon him without him having to ask – an idea that drew a terse response from the former communist head of state.</p>
<p>Berlusconi is not expected to be present for the Senate vote. It is thought he will address supporters who are due to gather outside his residence in central Rome on Wednesday afternoon.</p>
<p>He is expected to begin serving his sentence next year for the tax fraud conviction, which related to a complex system of illegally inflated invoices at his Mediaset television empire. But this is not the end of his legal woes. Among other matters, he has been ordered to stand trial on charges of bribing a senator in an attempt to bring down Romano Prodi's government, and is appealing against a first-grade conviction handed down in June for having sex with an underage girl and abusing his office to cover it up. He denies the allegations in both cases.</p>
<p>Despite his expected expulsion, Berlusconi will by no means disappear from the political scene. His future role has been compared to that of Beppe Grillo, the M5S's figurehead who himself has not been elected.</p>
<p>"The Senate is voting the expulsion of a man who is since yesterday the reference point for a large opposition formation," wrote the analyst Stefano Folli in the business daily Il Sole 24 Ore. "After [centre-left hopeful and Florence mayor Matteo] Renzi and Grillo, we will have another extra-parliamentary leader."</p>
<p>The expulsion vote is expected to heighten the tensions that have plagued the Letta government from its inception this year, even if, with a breakaway centre-right group that remains loyal to the coalition, it has a reasonably secure if small majority.</p>
<p>With their leader kicked out of the senate, Forza Italia MPs could prove highly disruptive in opposition and could stymie the kind of institutional reforms Letta says he wants to pass, Folli wrote. "It's better not to delude ourselves: Berlusconi's collaborators have already explained that the right will be against almost everything."</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>