<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2012-10-26" description="John Hooper: Regional elections will test whether Italians have lost patience with the sleaze and corruption of Berlusconi and his party" fingerprint="1833c33d90b2c735" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Why Silvio Berlusconi's jail sentence matters, even though he won't serve it | John Hooper" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2012/oct/26/silvio-berlusconi-jail-sentence-matters">
<main>
<p>There is rich irony in what has happened in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> this week.</p>
<p>Ever since <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> decided to enter politics 19 long years ago, he and his supporters have clung to the argument that his legal problems were a result of that decision. Investigations into his financial affairs and private life, they insisted, were the work of leftwing prosecutors, who were trying to achieve in the courts a victory that leftwing parties were unable to achieve at the polls. It followed logically that, as soon as he retired from politics, the politically motivated jurists who were bent on putting him in jail would lose interest and turn the spotlight of their investigations on the media tycoon's successor as leader of the right.</p>
<p>His supporters would often say so: "Just you wait – the day he steps aside, his legal problems will just melt away."</p>
<p>On Wednesday, after months of dithering, Berlusconi announced that he was standing down, definitively and irrevocably, as his party's candidate for prime minister in the election that has to be held in Italy by the end of next April. Today, two days later, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/oct/26/silvio-berlusconi-sentenced-four-years">a court in Milan sentenced him to four years in jail</ref>.</p>
<p>So much for that theory.</p>
<p>Berlusconi will not, of course, go to jail. The Italian legal system is far too lenient for that. Or, to be more precise, it is a lot better at putting people in jail <hi rend="#i">before</hi> they are tried than after.</p>
<p>It soon emerged that three years were being knocked off Berlusconi's four-year sentence because of an amnesty introduced by the (centre-left) government in 2006. As for the remaining one year, well, Berlusconi gets two appeals and, since the courts move so slowly in Italy, he can assume that, before his appeals have been heard, a statute of limitations will have kicked in, timing out the charges against him.</p>
<p>So does what happened in Milan today actually matter? It does. But politically more than judicially.</p>
<p>Berlusconi regards as the crowning triumph of his political career the unification of the Italian right. Three years ago, he founded the Freedom People – a merger between his own Forza Italia! party and the rump of Italy's neo-fascist movement. Known by its Italian initials as the PdL, the Freedom People movement is not a monolithic conservative party comparable with the Tory party in Britain or the Partido Popular in Spain. The Northern League stayed out. So did the main conservative Christian Democrat party. But it was nevertheless a considerable achievement.</p>
<p>Today, the PdL is in stark disarray. Recent polls have suggested it now has less support than the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_Star_Movement">Five Star Movement</ref> created by the comedian and blogger, Beppe Grillo. On average, <ref target="http://www.termometropolitico.it/">in the five nationwide surveys conducted before 21 October</ref>, the PdL obtained less than 17% of the vote, compared with more than 27% for the centre-left Democratic party.</p>
<p>Robbed of Berlusconi's charismatic leadership (you can't deny the man knew how to grab the headlines) and lacking any cohesive ideology, the PdL had been floundering for months. But what really sent it into a tailspin was the cumulative effect of a string of corruption scandals in regional administrations dominated by the PdL. The governors of Lazio, the region around Rome, and of Lombardy, the region around Milan, have both stood down as a result.</p>
<p>In normal times, Italians are pretty fatalistic about the sleaze that oozes out of their institutions. But these are not normal times. After more than a decade of virtually no economic growth, rounded off by the crisis in the eurozone, they are beginning to feel real financial pain. And they are not at all amused to read of lawmakers with eight houses and governors taking Caribbean holidaymakers paid for by their businessmen chums, let alone regional ministers in thrall to organised criminals.</p>
<p>On Sunday, the PdL faces a crucial test when regional elections are held on Sicily. It will be the first real test of public opinion in the approach to the general election. The very last thing the PdL needed was for its founder – and the man who was Italy's prime minister for most of the years in which its economy languished – to be convicted two days before of dodging the taxes that most ordinary voters have no option but to pay.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>