<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Seán Clarke; Antonio Voce" categories="World news" date="2022-09-26" description="The rightwing coalition led by Giorgi Meloni’s Brothers of Italy party has won a clear majority and will form the next government" fingerprint="32f96efdd4245354" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Brothers of Italy,Giorgia Meloni,Enrico Letta,Silvio Berlusconi,Five Star Movement,Matteo Salvini" title="Italian election 2022: live official results" url="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ng-interactive/2022/sep/25/italian-election-2022-live-official-results">
<main>
<head rend="h3">Chamber of Deputies</head>
<head rend="h3">Senate</head>
<table>
<row>
<cell>Right</cell>
<cell>
<p>Chamb.</p>
<p>237</p>
</cell>
<cell>
<p>Sen.</p>
<p>115</p>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<table>
<row>
<cell>Left</cell>
<cell>
<p>Chamb.</p>
<p>85</p>
</cell>
<cell>
<p>Sen.</p>
<p>44</p>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<table>
<row>
<cell>Five Star</cell>
<cell>
<p>Chamb.</p>
<p>52</p>
</cell>
<cell>
<p>Sen.</p>
<p>28</p>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<table>
<row>
<cell>Centre</cell>
<cell>
<p>Chamb.</p>
<p>21</p>
</cell>
<cell>
<p>Sen.</p>
<p>9</p>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<table>
<row>
<cell>Others</cell>
<cell>
<p>Chamb.</p>
<p>5</p>
</cell>
<cell>
<p>Sen.</p>
<p>4</p>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/75e0d438f81f3b9697499e13270db99e95447de1/478_321_2100_2100/140.jpg"/>
<head rend="h3">Right alliance</head>
<p>Meloni's far-right party, Brothers of Italy, has overtaken Matteo Salvini's League as the ascendant force in the Italian right</p>
<graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/821d667db929487aea804fa1dd630d7fb3082d0c/1027_44_1021_1021/140.jpg"/>
<head rend="h3">Left alliance</head>
<p>The traditional centre-left force, the Democratic party, leads an electoral alliance comprised of smaller leftwing, green and centrist parties</p>
<graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/6defcc5f92b6be73018386c33d87c80146de8292/1388_521_1427_1428/500.jpg"/>
<head rend="h3">Five Star Movement</head>
<p>The populist party is running alone, having triggered the snap election by withdrawing support from Mario Draghi's technocratic government</p>
<graphic src="https://media.guim.co.uk/1f1e1c676507daae52e93489cf62176376552f25/1626_0_2863_2863/140.jpg"/>
<head rend="h3">Centre alliance</head>
<p>Alliance of two centrist parties which broke with the Democratic party, led by Carlo Calenda and former PM Matteo Renzi</p>
<head rend="h3">Others</head>
<p>A handful of small parties is expected to enter parliament. These could include the Eurosceptic Italexit and the traditional autonomist parties of South Tyrol and Valle d'Aosta</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">About the election</hi>
</head>
<p>The vote was triggered when the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/five-star-movement">Five Star Movement</ref> abruptly withdrew its support for Mario Draghi’s technocratic government, but an election was due next year in any event.</p>
<p>The last election, in 2018, brought the Five Star Movement to power, in coalition with Matteo Salvini’s rightwing populist League. Salvini later withdrew from the coalition, and Five Star formed a new government with the centre-left Democratic party. Then, in 2021, almost all parties supported the appointment of Mario Draghi as prime minister.</p>
<p>Italy has a truly bicameral parliament, in which the chamber of deputies and the senate have equal influence; any law must be approved by both, and any government must have the support of both. <lb/> Since 2018, the size of both chambers has been reduced, but electoral law is the same. Two thirds of seats are assigned proportionally, while the rest are assigned in first-past-the-post constituencies. This penalises smaller parties, and leads to the formation of strategic alliances aimed at winning in the single-member constituencies. Electoral alliances have no bearing on parties once members are elected, and won’t necessarily mirror the composition of the next government coalition.</p>
<p>Constituencies are broadly based on population, with exceptions to guarantee representation for two semi-autonomous regions, Val d’Aosta and Trentino-Alto Adige, and a small number of seats in each chamber representing Italians who live overseas.</p>
<p>These results are the official results as released by the interior ministry, not the projections which broadcasters and others make based on samples of results.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>