<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="Business" date="2011-10-24" description="The smirk shared by Angela Merkel and Nicolas Sarkozy when quizzed about Silvio Berlusconi on Sunday prompted even some of the Italian prime minister's fiercest enemies to close ranks behind him" fingerprint="f7abc47f9901ff1d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Business,Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Merkozy smirk at EU crisis summit boosts Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/oct/24/merkel-sarkozy-italy-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>The <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/oct/23/eu-europe-recession-silvio-berlusoni">smirk shared by Angela Merkel and Nicolas Sarkozy when quizzed about Silvio Berlusconi at their Brussels press conference on Sunday</ref> made headlines in Italy on Monday and prompted even some of the Italian prime minister's fiercest enemies to close ranks behind him.</p>
<p>Leading daily <ref target="http://www.corriere.it/">Corriere della Sera,</ref> which has criticised Berlusconi for delaying the economic stimulus package demanded by Europe, called the behaviour of Merkel and Sarkozy "excessive" in a front page editorial, adding: "For an Italian it was not great, and it matters little if you are pro- or anti-Berlusconi."</p>
<p>The <ref target="http://video.corriere.it/sarkozy-merkel-ridacchiano-berlusconi/c9d7baf0-fd9b-11e0-aa26-262e70cd401e">French and German leaders – now dubbed 'Merkozy' – exchanged glances and smiled</ref> when asked if they were confident Berlusconi would come up with reforms, prompting a gale of laughter from journalists.</p>
<p>"No one is authorised to ridicule <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, even after Berlusconi's obvious and embarrassing delays in tackling the crisis," said Pier Ferdinando Casini, the head of the opposition UDC party, adding: "I didn't like Sarkozy's sarcastic smile."</p>
<p>More predictably, <ref target="http://www.ilgiornale.it/">Il Giornale</ref>, the newspaper owned by the Berlusconi family, did not split hairs, likening Sarkozy's smile to the headbutt delivered to Italian footballer Marco Matterazzi by France's Zinedine Zidane in the 2006 World Cup final.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.repubblica.it/">La Repubblica</ref> summed up the general discomfort at seeing Italy put on par with Greece at the Brussels summit being held to thrash out a solution for the European debt crisis, calling any parallels with Italy's neighbour "ungenerous".</p>
<p>Berlusconi appeared to blame Sarkozy's behaviour on his unhappiness over Italy's overrepresentation on the board at the European Central Bank, now that Italian Mario Draghi has been appointed chairman and Italian board member <ref target="http://www.ecb.int/ecb/orga/decisions/html/cvbinismaghi.en.html">Lorenzo Bini Smaghi</ref> is refusing to step down to make way for a French appointee. "Sarkozy has started to get annoyed," said Berlusconi. "At a certain point I said to Sarkozy, 'But what am I supposed to do? Kill him?'"</p>
<p>Italian newspapers have suggested that Merkel's decision to share the joke with Sarkozy might have been payback after reports that Berlusconi made a vulgar joke about her looks.</p>
<p>With the EU wanting answers by midweek, Berlusconi was reportedly planning a rushed cabinet meeting on Monday to drum up stimulus measures including pension reform to complement the two austerity budgets Italy has passed this year to cut its deficit.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>