<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Michael White" categories="Politics" date="2011-11-09" description="By backing the government's line that Britain should not increase its IMF contribution, Labour is pandering to the unappeasable Eurosceptic faction" fingerprint="f3490157193393b4" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,Liberal-Conservative coalition,Conservatives,Economic policy,Foreign policy,Labour,David Cameron,George Osborne,Ed Miliband,Ed Balls,European Union,Eurozone crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Germany,France" title="The Little Englanders marginalising Britain to play to the gallery | Michael White" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/blog/2011/nov/09/little-englanders-marginalising-britain-europe">
<main>
<p>So Silvio Berlusconi's grubby fingers have <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-to-resign-italy">finally been prised off the levers of power in Rome</ref> – at least in theory. <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/09/timeline-silvio-berlusconi-italy-euro-elections">About time, too, for a rogue who shafted his country</ref>.</p>
<p>Who does that leave as the EU's most unreliable national leader? It's a hotly contested field but, for shortsighted tactical manoeuvres based largely on domestic party calculation, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/davidcameron">David Cameron</ref> must be be in with a chance. But is Ed Miliband's Labour party far behind?</p>
<p>First Berlusconi. Let's <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/08/italy-crisis-silvio-berlusconi">wait until he actually does resign</ref> – preferably with a garlic-soaked stake through his political heart – before celebrating this overdue event.</p>
<p>He may be plotting to bounce back via a surge of public support or the general election his rackety coalition is now seeking. He knows that the public prosecutor will be on his case as soon as he loses the protection of office – remember, the ailing <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-14782569">Jacques Chirac is on trial in Paris</ref>, albeit too ill to be in the dock in person.</p>
<p>As <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/economics-blog/2011/nov/08/euro-papandreou-berlusconi-bailout-debt">Larry Elliott complains here</ref>, there's a democratic deficit in much of the current turmoil. The eurozone's leaders – a shadowy, half-elected caucus that Larry calls the Frankfurt Group – have, in effect, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/08/greece-politicians-new-prime-minister">sacked the prime minister of Greece</ref>, and now Italy's too.</p>
<p>Portugal's and Ireland's governments have already fallen to election defeat, and Spain's is poised to be voted out too. That's always an important distinction: better the voters do it than Angela Merkel and Sarko.</p>
<p>Gordon Brown's defeat in 2010 is more complicated, but perceived economic failure was a crucial component of the story – not so much a democratic deficit as a financial one. That's true across the troubled eurozone belt, where voters enjoyed the boom (cheaper goods and credit) but turned on their elected leaders when it all went wrong.</p>
<p>The politically unaccountable nature of the eurozone project is not yet the decisive factor, but may become so as the logic of the present crisis forces greater central control over national budgets and deficits. Let's hope they are more successful than central banks and ratings agencies were in controlling the "too big to fail" banks.</p>
<p>Will the euro survive? The European commission president, José Manuel Barroso, said yesterday that all EU states, except Britain and Denmark with their opt-outs, have a legal responsibility to join eventually – no ifs or buts. It is the new norm.</p>
<p>Maybe, but that suggests to me that <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Manuel_Barroso">Barroso is just a Portuguese law professor turned technocrat</ref> who doesn't know much history. He left the Portuguese premiership for Brussels in 2004, just as Lisbon's own budget deficit was ballooning – he got out in time.</p>
<p>But what about Britain's role in the euro-drama which, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-to-resign-italy">so today's Guardian splash suggests</ref>, may almost halve next year's projected UK growth from 2.2% to 1.2%, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2011/nov/09/cbi-britain-to-avoid-double-dip-recession">according to the CBI</ref>, and what about the performance of the coalition's official opposition, Miliband-led Labour?</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/nov/08/eurosceptic-hero-maggie-gordon-brown">Jonathan Freedland's Guardian column</ref> pays generous tribute to Brown's role in preventing Tony Blair's woolly headed sentimentality towards the euro from taking sterling into the new currency and in making the 2009 G20 meeting in London more of a success (the claim is disputed by some economists) than this month's shambles in Cannes.</p>
<p>It's a fair point, though Johnny is kinder than he should be about Brown's persistent habit, as chancellor, of borrowing much more than was prudent as the boom ("no more boom and bust" was a very silly slogan) headed towards the cliff.</p>
<p>Over-leveraged banking caused the crisis, but the Treasury's over-reliance on taxes from financial services was part of the problem when it all crashed. It's not quite like the 1930s.</p>
<p>At fault, too, was Brown's tripartite division of responsibility for regulation, which took everyone's eyes off the ball. So was his refusal to admit in the election runup that his Britain had a deficit problem that was undermining the confidence of flighty markets – not a Greek problem, to be sure: that is a phoney coalition story line – but a potential problem, as France's tottering AAA status (yet another emergency budget looms) reminds even him today.</p>
<p>That said, with his vast experience and earnest internationalism, Brown would have done a better job of managing the international dimension of the crisis than Cameron and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/georgeosborne">George Osborne</ref> are doing.</p>
<p>In placating their own Eurosceptic backbenchers and party activists – not to mention the dark, sullen group of angry voters who vote Ukip, BNP or not at all – they have marginalised Britain in Europe in all sorts of ways in order to play to the gallery.</p>
<p>The issue that matters most to us all, because it's such an important part of the economy, is the EU's determination to load Europe's financial services industry – mostly located in London and other British cities – with new structures, regulation and taxes.</p>
<p>They are designed to prevent a repetition of recent excesses, a laudable goal, but getting highly technical models wrong may merely damage the industry or drive much of it to New York or Asia.</p>
<p>Good riddance? I don't think so. How do you think we are going to rebalance the economy, pay down the deficit and finance future growth? But most of the problems the UK economy faces are home-grown. Yes, exports have risen since the 20% devaluation of sterling, but imports have risen much faster. We can't blame foreigners for those choices, though plenty try.</p>
<p>The <ref target="http://www.openeurope.org.uk">Openeurope</ref> lobby <ref target="http://www.openeurope.org.uk/media-centre/pressrelease.aspx?pressreleaseid=181">has published a document</ref> that claims EU regulation and wider social law costs the UK economy £8.6bn a year – money that could otherwise generate 140,000 extra jobs.</p>
<p>I'm sure there's some truth in its claims just as there is (greater) force in Jonathan Sumption QC's (he's the new man on the supreme court) overnight speech saying the European convention on human rights is encroaching on what are rightly political decisions (just like the bankers).</p>
<p>Do they really think we would avoid all EU regulation from outside, or the outer circle? Does Norway? Would British manufacturing capacity be miraculously transformed? Would the £8.4bn be invested in productive capacity, or wasted on tax cuts, much of which would be spent on imports?</p>
<p>But the symbolic retreat that highlights the coalition's retreat (I do not count occasional bleats from Nick Clegg) into domestic insularity is the much-trumpeted failure both to contribute more directly to the eurozone bailout.</p>
<p>Even worse is its refusal of a British increase to the IMF's reserves, the global firefighting fund. In this, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/labour">Labour</ref> has joined the Tories in pandering to the unappeasable Eurosceptic faction.</p>
<p>Cameron and William Hague have a political problem.</p>
<p>The government recently passed the Sovereignty Act, a fatuous promise to grant a referendum if further powers are transferred to Brussels. It was meant to appease the sceptics, and failed. If the eurozone demands a treaty change to consolidate a fiscal union in which Britain would not be involved, the sceptics will demand their own renegotiation and referendum. Cameron will probably try to avoid it.</p>
<p>Is Labour doing better? Not really. The shadow chancellor, Ed Balls, the brains behind Miliband's economic policy, has a five-point plan for growth – <ref target="http://www.edballs4labour.org/blog/?p=2310">see here</ref> – which has some merits.</p>
<p>It, and the emerging reality of stalled growth, is already forcing Osborne towards an unacknowledged Plan B, where hair-shirted deficit-cutting targets slide.</p>
<p>But what about the government's refusal to contribute to an expansion of the IMF's funds (no one ever lost money lending to the IMF, by the way) to help restore confidence that demand can be sustained in the faltering global economy?</p>
<p>Cameron and Osborne say the eurozone has enough funds to resolve its own problems, prop up the indebted countries, recapitalise the banks and create its own backstop (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Financial_Stability_Facility">the European financial stability facility or EFSF</ref>) in sufficient "big bazooka" size to impress the markets: inadequate gestures that fail are always counterproductive, as the EU has repeatedly shown.</p>
<p>That's correct. Balls agrees. They have all refused to contribute further to the EU bailout fund, unlike Sweden and Poland, both also outside the zone. But it is quite another thing to say – and for Balls to echo – that Britain will not up its contribution to the IMF, one of the pillars of the postwar world, the greatest expansion of human prosperity (not just Europe and the US either) in history.</p>
<p>Why do they do it? On the specious grounds that IMF funds should not be used to prop up the eurozone, which – unlike many countries hit by liquidity problems and debt – has deep enough pockets to sort itself out. You can read Balls's many explanations on <ref target="http://www.edballs.co.uk">his website</ref>, which carries many of his speeches and radio interviews (he has a very assiduous press officer) <ref target="http://www.edballs.co.uk/blog/?p=2443">like this one</ref> and <ref target="http://www.edballs.co.uk/blog/?p=2449">this one</ref>.</p>
<p>I understand his argument, but don't accept the political judgment that underpins it. The spurious justification is that the IMF money might filter its way back into propping up the eurozone when the European central bank should really have the clout to be the EU's bank of last resort. True, but it smacks of appeasement to the Little Englanders in every party.</p>
<p>Foreigners won't care. They may shrug at a Little Englander Tory-led coalition donning its woad warpaint and hope it collapses soon (which it won't). But internationalists, champions of co-operation in a rules-based and ever more complex world, who look on Labour as their natural ally, won't read the small print.</p>
<p>They'll just see tactics, the sort of manoeuvre for which the late Harold Wilson – a great party manager, not much missed – was famous but not admired beyond the party. It all sits ill with the <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2011/nov/09/labour-uk-integrate-key-defence-europe">internationalist speech being made by Jim Murphy</ref>, Labour's defence spokesman, today.</p>
<p>Cameron's G20 report to MPs on Monday was not impressive, but he was tired and did manage a good joke about proposing a cheese tax to the French.</p>
<p>Miliband was worse, his brother David's intervention was better. All were drowned out by the wails of Eurosceptic Tory MPs who want to repatriate "sovereign" powers home from Brussels to Westminster, then hand the final decision over to a referendum.</p>
<p>If Britain ever needs friends and allies abroad again, perhaps in an unplanned financial crisis, I hope they've got a few in their back pockets. But who?</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>