<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-07-22" description="Italian prime minister issues first public comments on conversations alleged to have taken place with prostitute" fingerprint="af1ae1211476efac" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="I'm no saint, Silvio Berlusconi admits in wake of sex tape allegations" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/22/silvio-berlusconi-sex-tape">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister, joked today that he was "no saint" in his first public comments since a newspaper released alleged conversations between him and a prostitute.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has been entangled in scandal for months over his alleged encounters with young women. The controversy took on new life this week when the left-leaning weekly L'Espresso released tapes purportedly recorded at the leader's Rome residence. Berlusconi's lawyer has disputed the tapes' veracity.</p>
<p>"I'm no saint, by now you've figured that out," a smiling Berlusconi said at the inauguration of a new road project.</p>
<p>"Let's hope that those working at Repubblica understand that too," he added, taking a jab at the daily that has doggedly pursued the scandal story. The 72-year-old leader also noted that "there are a lot of nice-looking girls around".</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied paying for sex, and has called the allegations "trash". The scandal has done little to dent his popularity and has not threatened the stability of his cabinet. He said he expected to still be in power in 2012, when the new road will be completed. "We'll still be here," he said. "What would <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> do without us?"</p>
<p>On Monday and Tuesday, L'Espresso released recordings of what it said was the night Berlusconi spent with the escort. The recordings include intimate conversations between Patrizia D'Addario and a voice identified as Berlusconi's, both on 4 November and the morning after.</p>
<p>The tapes also feature alleged conversations between D'Addario and a businessman accused of recruiting and paying young women to attend Berlusconi's parties. D'Addario has said she recorded her encounters with the prime minister and turned the recordings over to prosecutors in Bari as part of an investigation into the businessman. She came forward because Berlusconi had reneged on a promise to help her out with a real estate problem she was having, she says.</p>
<p>While the voice on the tapes sounds like Berlusconi, it has not been independently verified that he is the speaker. Berlusconi's lawyer, Niccolo Ghedini, said after the first recordings were released that they were "without any merit, completely improbable and the fruit of invention". He warned that legal action would be taken against anyone who distributed them.</p>
<p>Also, Antonello Zappadu, a photographer who took pictures of topless women at the leader's home that were published by Spanish newspaper El País, said he had some 5,000 more photos. Berlusconi's lawyers have claimed invasion of privacy and the photos have been put under seal by prosecutors in Rome.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>