<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Giulia Laganà; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2008-06-24" description="Giulia Laganà: Democracy is in danger when a prime minister – himself involved in a corruption trial – embarks on a war against the judiciary" fingerprint="3ad2815e92b29e30" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Law,European Union,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Giulia Laganà: Berlusconi has declared war on the magistrates" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/jun/24/italy.law">
<main>
<p>The Italian Enlightenment philosopher <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cesare_Beccaria">Cesare Beccaria</ref>'s celebrated 18th-century treatise, "<ref target="http://www.constitution.org/cb/crim_pun.htm">On Crimes and Punishments</ref>", which laid the foundations of modern thought on detention, torture and the death penalty, is credited with first developing the notion that prison sentences should serve to further criminals' social inclusion, rather than merely meting out punishment as a form of social vengeance.</p>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's government, which swept to power two months ago in the wake of a <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article4021089.ece">media-fuelled popular frenzy</ref> about allegedly soaring crime rates, is currently rolling out legislation that will harshen sentences for a number of petty crimes and ensure that convicts' access to social service programmes as an alternative to serving time are severely curtailed. Italy's migrants – and undocumented migrants in particular – will bear the brunt of these measures, despite the fact that the overwhelming majority of criminals in the country are Italian citizens.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, however much the foreign media may delight in describing his antics, is not just a perma-tanned jester with an obsession for hair transplants and plastic surgery and a penchant for bad jokes about Germans, women, homosexuals and his wife. The former sea-cruise crooner proved how dangerous he is for democracy during his previous five years in power, when he rolled out changes in legislation to avoid trial or kill investigations into his shady busy interests, consolidated his media empire, exercised absolute control over state-owned TV, launched attacks on the judiciary, encouraged the secret services to spy and collect data on tens of thousands of allegedly left-leaning reporters, businessmen and intellectuals and presided over a G8 summit in 2001, where, according to <ref target="http://asiapacific.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGEUR300102001?open&amp;of=ENG-ITA">Amnesty International</ref>, the Italian authorities violated demonstrators' human rights on a massive scale.</p>
<p>This time around, Berlusconi's allies in parliament have already tabled <ref target="http://us.ft.com/ftgateway/superpage.ft?news_id=fto052320082126241427&amp;page=1">proposals</ref> to block an EU ruling that would turn one of the prime minister's terrestrial TV stations into a satellite channel. Last week, his lawyers-cum-MPs inserted a new, apparently contradictory amendment into the "security package", a set of bills which will toughen immigration and asylum legislation, crack down on petty crime and deploy the army in major cities. The "trial-killer" amendment, as it is now known, will block all trials currently underway for crimes that carry maximum prison sentences of 10 years and which were committed before June 30 2002 – an apparently arbitrary date, which will coincidentally ensure that Berlusconi's most recent corruption trial – <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/23/catholicism.italy">involving</ref> David Mills, Tessa Jowell's estranged husband – will grind to a halt.</p>
<p>In Brussels last Friday for an EU summit, an unusually sombre Berlusconi vented his rage against magistrates who, he claimed, wanted to "<ref target="http://www.ansa.it/site/notizie/awnplus/english/news/2008-06-20_120240487.html">subvert democracy</ref>". The Italian prime minister promised he would "denounce the initiatives of magistrates and judges who have infiltrated the judiciary [and] want to subvert the vote". Polls show that Italians, who have been subject to an intense, 14-year-long media campaign geared at proving that "red" magistrates bear a personal grudge against Silvio Berlusconi, back government proposals to curb the judiciary's independence. Italy's "phantom opposition", as <ref target="http://www.economist.com/world/europe/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11541286">The Economist</ref> recently labelled the Democratic party, have merely signalled that they may vote for yet another proposal to grant blanket immunity to the country's president, prime minister and to the presidents of the senate and chamber if the "trial-killer" amendment were to be withdrawn.</p>
<p>The Marquis of Beccaria famously quipped that "the greatest happiness of the greatest number is the foundation of morals and legislation". In Silvio Berlusconi's Italy, the greatest happiness of one particular individual appears to be shaping morals and driving legislation – subverting democracy in a founding EU member state.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>