<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Deborah Summers" categories="Politics" date="2009-02-17" description="Judges to rule on whether the husband of Olympics minister Tessa Jowell took a bribe from the Italian prime minister to give false evidence in corruption trials" fingerprint="aba080f90a3b6da" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Tessa Jowell,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Politics,UK news,World news,David Mills,Europe" title="Verdict expected in David Mills bribes trial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-tessa-jowell-silvio-berlusconi-trial">
<main>
<p>A verdict is expected today on whether David Mills, the estranged husband of the Olympics minister, Tessa Jowell, took a bribe from the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, to give false evidence in corruption trials.</p>
<p>Judges have begun the deliberations that bring to an end a three-year trial in which Mills, 64, faced charges of accepting a $600,000 (then £350,000) payment from the politician and tycoon.</p>
<p>Prosecutors are asking for a sentence of four years and eight months if he is convicted.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was originally accused of corruption, until his government passed a law giving him legal immunity.</p>
<p>Mills, a tax lawyer, is accused of taking the alleged bribe to give false testimony in a trial Berlusconi faced in relation to his business dealings. Mills was one of Berlusconi's consultants on offshore tax havens.</p>
<p>The charges stemmed from a letter which Mills sent to a British accountant in 2004 in which he said the $600,000 payment came from "Mr B".</p>
<p>He wrote: "I turned some very tricky corners, to put it mildly, and so kept Mr B out of a great deal of trouble that I would have landed him in had I said all I knew."</p>
<p>Mills has said the letter described a hypothetical situation as a way of soliciting tax advice for an unnamed client.</p>
<p>He has said the money came from an Italian businessman, Diego Attanasio, who had once been his client, a claim repeated by Berlusconi, but one which Attanasio denies.</p>
<p>Neither Mills nor Berlusconi was present for any of the hearings. Both deny any wrongdoing.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>