<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2007-07-06" description="Italy's judiciary has accused military intelligence of spying on those judges it considered hostile to Silvio Berlusconi, and of plotting to obstruct them." fingerprint="ffca326cc099a733" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Italy's military spooks 'spied on magistrates to help Berlusconi'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2007/jul/07/italy.international">
<main>
<p>Italy's judiciary has accused military intelligence of spying on those judges it considered hostile to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, and of plotting to obstruct them.</p>
<p>The spying allegedly took place from 2001 until 2006, when the media magnate was voted out and replaced as prime minister by Romano Prodi. Judges in Spain and the UK were also spied on, said the Superior Council of the Magistracy, which is chaired by Italy's president, the leftwing Giorgio Napolitano.</p>
<p>While making no specific accusations, the council said intelligence documents from 2001 seized in 2006 investigations were found to discuss "the neutralisation of initiatives" by magistrates and judges seen as opposing the centre-right government.</p>
<p>Justice minister Clemente Mastella said on Thursday that 250 judges had been spied on; those considered most dangerous were described by the documents as "the armed wing" of the judiciary. Mr Berlusconi was constantly at odds with the judiciary, once claiming that to be a judge one must be "mentally disturbed".</p>
<p>Nicolo Pollari, former chief of military intelligence service, denied that any "illegal dossiers" existed; what the council said were "files" was simply information collected from newspapers and other public sources. He is standing trial for allegedly helping the CIA kidnap a terror suspect in Milan in 2003.</p>
<p>The Prodi government said it had "full and total faith in the work of the magistracy", and called for "necessary clarity" in the affair. When details first emerged, the spying was attributed to a shadowy unit inside the service, but the council says it now thinks that it was top officials rather than "deviant sectors".</p>
<p>The council also said that a pan-European group, Magistrates for Democracy and Liberties, had also been spied on, and its internal emails intercepted.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>