<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2010-03-28" description="The Italian prime minister is likely to lose ground to his coalition partner in local polls this weekend" fingerprint="77a017359ba3c557" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,The League" title="Anti-immigrant Northern League bends Silvio Berlusconi to its will ahead of regional elections" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/mar/28/italy-elections-berlusconi-bossi">
<main>
<p>Rattled by sex and corruption scandals and looking foolish over the late registration of candidates, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has had a rough ride in the run-up to key regional elections this weekend. But any votes the Italian prime minister loses to his centre-left opponents may pale in significance to likely gains made by his coalition partner, the Northern League, as conservative voters scared by soaring immigration and job losses desert Berlusconi, 73.</p>
<p>Fresh from taking 10% of votes at national elections in 2008, the anti-immigrant league has already won its first scalp in the Veneto region, where it forced Berlusconi to dump governor Giancarlo Galan to make way for a league candidate in the election today and tomorrow. Guaranteed victory, the league will not only gain its first governorship but influence over two banking foundations that are key shareholders in UniCredit, Italy's biggest bank.</p>
<p>"Galan is better off at deep-sea fishing," sneered league founder Umberto Bossi (pictured), after he described Berlusconi's bungling of candidate registration in Lombardy and Lazio as "amateurish". The gruff Bossi now appears to treat Berlusconi the same way as the media mogul rants at magistrates and journalists.</p>
<p>From the days of describing immigrants as "Bingo Bongos" and promising to take pigs to urinate at planned mosques, league ministers have kept racial tub-thumping to a minimum, happy their programme is being put into action, from the criminalising of illegal immigration to the interdiction on the high seas of migrant vessels.</p>
<p>Sure of the top job in Veneto and neck and neck with the centre-left in Piedmont, the league is setting the stage to hand more fiscal power to Italy's regions, allowing the rich north to cut off the flow of tax euros to poorer regions, overriding Berlusconi's rule from Rome.</p>
<p>And if, warned the Turin daily La Stampa, Bossi overtakes Berlusconi in the north, "it will become nearly irrelevant to the league whether the centre-left or centre-right runs Rome. In the north there will be a kind of shadow government, something very similar to a declaration of independence."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>