<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2004-12-15" description="Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="3f9b126dda53879d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi" title="Pass notes: Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2004/dec/15/features11.g21">
<main>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Age:</hi>
</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Profession: </hi> Singer-songwriter.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Ah, it's that chap who won X-Factor is it?</hi> No, it's not him, though if Italy were to screen its own version, he'd probably stand a good chance of winning, what with him owning all the TV channels and everything. And, you know, being prime minister.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Another greying premier with long-lost dreams of rock 'n' roll stardom ... </hi> Actually, he might have a chance. Berlusconi is hot favourite to win the San Remo song competition with his natty little ditty Samba and Chocolate.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Sample lyrics, please: </hi> "You are coffee and chocolate / And you know I would die for you / Because I hold you inside me / Come and dance this samba with me, it speaks about you." It works better in Neapolitan.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Shouldn't he be paying more attention to his country's economic growth problems and the unrest over spending cuts that have prompted widespread strikes?</hi> Perhaps. But what better way to brighten the run-up to spring's regional elections than with a "high-calorie song which relates the passion of a male lover for a shapely Brazilian beauty"?</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Wonder what he'll come up with for the general election in 2006? </hi> Wonder no more. 2006 is the projected release date for the film of the life of Signor <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, based on his enthusiastically self-worshipping autobiography, An Italian Story. This was distributed to Italian households shortly before the last election, but only a cynic would consider it significant in returning Berlusconi with the largest majority in postwar Italian history.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Let's hope he doesn't give Tony Blair any ideas.</hi> I don't know - a PM supergroup might be just the thing to assuage voters' worries that Britain has lost friends over that Iraq business.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>