<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Media" date="2009-06-05" description="Italian prime minister's attack on Rupert Murdoch comes as state broadcaster RAI threatens to pull channels from Sky Italia. By John Hooper" fingerprint="76e9c9bf1245db5d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Rupert Murdoch,Sky,News Corporation,Television industry,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi dispute highlights battle with Murdoch over Italian broadcasting" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2009/jun/05/silvio-berlusconi-rupert-murdoch-rai-sky-italia">
<main>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2009/jun/04/silvio-berlusconi-the-times-rupert-murdoch">Silvio Berlusconi's account</ref> of why he thinks Rupert Murdoch's media outlets are out to get him came as a surprise to observers of the broadcasting scene in Italy. The VAT row he mentioned was resolved at the end of last year, to the detriment of Murdoch's Sky Italia.</p>
<p>The Australian-born media magnate now has another bone to pick with Berlusconi. But Italy's prime minister has good reason for not citing it.</p>
<p>Critics argue that the two media tycoons' latest dispute offers the most blatant example yet of something Berlusconi has always vigorously denied – that, when he is in power, Italy's public broadcaster RAI acts in his personal interests, providing him a virtual monopoly of what voters see on their screens.</p>
<p>RAI and Berlusconi's Mediaset together operate six of the country's seven terrestrial TV channels. The only serious competition facing this "duopolio", as Italians call it, is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/bskyb">Sky</ref> Italia, which has carved out an 11% share of the overall Italian TV market.</p>
<p>Some of Sky Italia's success is attributable to the fact that viewers can flick easily from Murdoch's own channels to the terrestrial and channels of RAI and Mediaset, which receive payment for their output being broadcast via the satellite broadcaster.</p>
<p>More than 13% of RAI's viewers now watch its programmes via Murdoch's service. The public network's satellite operation, RaiSat, which has five channels on Sky, and is among the few profitable divisions of a corporation which this year is expecting a net loss of ¤120m (£106m).</p>
<p>Yet last month RAI let it be known that it intended pulling all its services off Sky Italia when the current agreement runs out at the end of July. The logic of such a move has defeated more than one commentator.</p>
<p>Sky is offering RAI a seven-year deal worth ¤425m. The public broadcaster would also lose some ¤7m in advertising revenue from the RaiSat channels.</p>
<p>And a less easily calculable, but probably greater, sum from advertising lost from its terrestrial channels because of a drop in audience share, which an internal RAI study in April estimated at 3.5%.</p>
<p>In circumstances other than the anomalous ones created by Berlusconi's media interests, the public broadcaster would no doubt be seen as merely holding out for a better price.</p>
<p>But opposition politicians have called for Italy's anti-trust body to look into the possibility of connivance, and last month RAI's president, Paolo Garimberti, supplied grist to their mill when he declared that, before leaving Murdoch's service, his corporation would need the "absolute certainty that Mediaset will come off at exactly the same moment".</p>
<p>Paolo Gentiloni, broadcasting spokesman of the Democratic party, said the case "deserves serious examination".</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i"> To contact the MediaGuardian news desk email editor@mediatheguardian.com or phone 020 3353 3857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 3353 2000.</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>