<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-11-08" description="With the markets and key allies turning against him, it was only a matter of time before the three-time Italian PM was forced out" fingerprint="2e8de0b395a7d71d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe,Eurozone crisis,Business" title="Italy crisis: Silvio Berlusconi finds he's not too big to fail on day of drama" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/italy-crisis-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Just after the vote that sealed the fate of his government, a photographer from the Ansa news agency managed to get a shot of the sheet of paper on which <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> was writing. He had noted his tally of votes, and next to it, in brackets, "eight traitors".</p>
<p>Underneath were his options. One read: "I take note (offer my resignation)."</p>
<p>After all the lurid scandals, the high political drama of dwindling majorities, threatened rebellions and daring parliamentary escapes stretching back over months, the end - if such it was - came in unexpectedly muted fashion. Berlusconi did not fall, as he had planned to, in a nail-biting confidence vote that ended in cheering from the opposition and indignant protests from his supporters.</p>
<p>He lost a routine, though crucial, parliamentary ballot; went to consult his associates, and then - under a abruptly cleared sky and an almost full moon - he was driven from his residence in the Palazzo Grazioli up the Quirinal Hill for a meeting with the president at which he promised to go.</p>
<p>For weeks, he had remained defiant, brushing aside successive desertions by deputies and senators and turning a deaf ear to the discontent among those who remained loyal. As recently as Monday, he had quashed reports of his imminent resignation, describing them on Facebook as without foundation.</p>
<p>But in the night between Monday and Tuesday, things changed significantly. Shortly after 1.30am local time, a meeting ended between Berlusconi and leading figures in his party. Sources close to the prime minister admitted for the first time that he would assess his future on the basis of Tuesday's ballot in parliament.</p>
<p>"I'm not leaving," read the headline of Il Giornale, the Milan-based daily owned by Berlusconi's family. But, even as the first copies were reaching the newsstands, the message looked incongruous.</p>
<p>During the morning, the prime minister went through the motions, meeting two noted waverers at his home in the capital. But, as they were conferring, five more PDL lawmakers announced they were falling in with the plans of the opposition.</p>
<p>The vote that was to prompt Berlusconi's downfall was to approve last year's public accounts - a vital one for two reasons. The rejection of the accounts had sparked Italy's last political crisis in mid-October. And, unless the re-submitted accounts were to be endorsed this time, parliament would be unable to pass the economic austerity measures demanded by Italy's eurozone partners.</p>
<p>So, instead of voting against the government, the opposition agreed in the national interest to boycott the ballot instead: opposition deputies would take their places in the house, but would neither vote nor abstain when the moment came. That way, it would be clear how much support the government could really muster.</p>
<p>Characteristically, Umberto Bossi, the leader of the Northern League, the junior partner in Berlusconi's coalition, stole the opposition's thunder. Approached by reporters outside parliament shortly before lunch, he appeared at first not to have anything new to say.</p>
<p>The 70-year-old was asked about the long-awaited vote in the afternoon. Bossi replied: "Today, nothing will happen."</p>
<p>But then he immediately contradicted himself. "We asked the prime minister to step aside," he said, before going on to name as his choice of successor the secretary of Berlusconi's party, Angelino Alfano. After months of standing by the prime minister, he had doomed their rightwing government with a single, typically blunt sentence.</p>
<p>Seventeen years earlier on another winter's day, the League leader pulled the rug from under the TV magnate's first tumultuous and shortlived government. But whereas in 1994 Bossi was Berlusconi's executioner, switching his votes against the government in parliament, this time he and his followers stood by the coalition to the end and let others plunge in the knife.</p>
<p>On 14 October, when Italy's legendarily resilient prime minister had survived the last in a string of confidence votes, he mustered 316 of the 630 votes in the lower house, the chamber of deputies - a bare, one-seat outright majority. But yesterday when the vote on the public finances was held in mid-afternoon, as an apocalyptic downpour lashed the capital, he obtained only 308. Hence the "eight traitors".</p>
<p>On Monday, Berlusconi had said: "I want to look those who want to betray me in the face." That is possible in a confidence vote of the sort he planned to call.</p>
<p>But the ballot on last year's state accounts was a normal one, and so the votes were registered electronically and flashed up on a display behind the speaker. Soon afterwards, Berlusconi left the floor of the house looking grim-faced.</p>
<p>On the markets, the pressure on him to resign had been stepped up. The yield on Italy's 10-year benchmark bonds rose to 6.74%, taking the interest rate on Italy's debt to within sight of 7% , seen as the point of no return in the debt crisis.</p>
<p>But while Italy might not be too big to fail, it is probably too big to bail. Italy's debts amount to €1.9tn. Next year alone, it will need to ask the markets to lend it almost €300bn. Higher government bond yields are not just a problem for the treasury. Through the banks, they feed into the economy at large, raising the cost of borrowing for business.</p>
<p>As the spread between Italian and German bonds - a reflection of the extra risk of holding Italian bonds - approached five percentage points, the head of the Italian bosses' union, Emma Marcegaglia, said: "We can't go on like this for long."</p>
<p>It was a thought that many of her compatriots have been voicing for weeks, if not months.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>