<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-12-01" description="Gianfranco Fini says Italian leader 'confuses leadership with absolute monarchy'" fingerprint="97ac5a2c9734671d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Media,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi's ally Gianfranco Fini overheard criticising PM's 'regal' style" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/01/berlusconi-criticised-gianfranco-fini">
<main>
<p>The government of Silvio Berlusconi ‑ already beset by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">scandal over the prime minister's sex life</ref> ‑ was tonight rocked by comments from the man supposed to be the Italian prime minister's closest ally.</p>
<p>Gianfranco Fini, whose formerly neo-fascist party merged with Berlusconi's Freedom People movement in March, said that Berlusconi "confuses leadership with absolute monarchy" in remarks that were inadvertently recorded.</p>
<p>The daily <ref target="http://www.repubblica.it/2009/11/sezioni/politica/giustizia-19/fuorionda-fini/fuorionda-fini.html">La Repubblica posted to its website a recording of a conversation</ref> between Fini, the speaker of the lower house of parliament, and a prosecutor at a prizegiving ceremony on 6 November.</p>
<p>Unaware that the microphone in front of him was live, Fini said that Berlusconi "confuses leadership with absolute monarchy", and also remarked that his party leader was unable to distinguish between "popular consent, which he obviously has and which gives him a mandate to govern, and a sort of immunity from any other authority [such as] the magistracy, the audit court, the [top appeals court], the head of state or parliament".</p>
<p>While Berlusconi's supporters played down or laughed off the embarrassment, the leader of the main opposition party, Pierluigi Bersani, said it was "the confirmation of problems in the [governing] majority". Antonio Di Pietro, of the smaller <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Principles party, predicted that the scandals that have weakened Berlusconi had brought the country to "the eve of a new revolution".</p>
<p>As the prime minister's difficulties have mounted, Fini has become increasingly open in his criticism of the government's policies, and has astonished followers by voicing support for a tolerant, progressive and secular form of conservatism.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's travails are far from over. On Friday, a mafia informer is due to testify in court on an alleged deal between the prime minister and Cosa Nostra in the 1990s hotly denied by Berlusconi.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>