<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Business" date="2003-07-09" description="The Italian senate yesterday began debating a controversially amended bill that critics say would enable Silvio Berlusconi to extend his already formidable influence over the country's media. By John Hooper." fingerprint="68ec89ae9191cf49" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Business,Television industry,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media business,Italy,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi's boundless empire" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2003/jul/09/broadcasting.pressandpublishing">
<main>
<p>The Italian senate yesterday began debating a controversially amended bill that critics say would enable the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, to extend his already formidable influence over the country's media.</p>
<p>A wide-ranging communications bill would allow Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset television group to keep all three of its channels, enable it to increase substantially its advertising revenue and to buy into the newspaper market. Opponents of the bill have tabled more than 4,000 amendments.</p>
<p>Directly through Mediaset, in which Mr Berlusconi has a 48.6% stake, and indirectly by way of the state broadcaster, Rai, Italy's leader is in a position to influence more than 90% of the country's television output.</p>
<p>The dangers posed by his grip on the media were highlighted last week when the main Rai evening news bulletin failed to broadcast remarks by him that caused uproar across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>.</p>
<p>During an appearance before the European parliament, Mr Berlusconi told a German MEP he would be ideal for the part of a concentration camp guard in a film being produced in Italy.</p>
<p>Yesterday's debate began as Rai's parliamentary control board started questioning the news editors of all three state-owned channels about their coverage of the incident involving Mr Berlusconi.</p>
<p>The row has relegated to the background opposition protests over a vote last Wednesday that stripped from the communications bill a clause limiting any one owner to two terrestrial television channels.</p>
<p>The clause would have put on the statute book an existing decision by Italy's highest court and forced Mediaset to sell its Retequattro channel.</p>
<p>The Italian communications minister, Maurizio Gasparri, has argued that such limitations will soon be unnecessary because the bill also opens the way for the start of digital terrestrial transmissions in 2006 and thus a proliferation of channels in the marketplace.</p>
<p>Italy's monopolies commission said last month that the country's television market showed a higher degree of concentration than any other country in the European Union. It added that the two largest television companies in France had only a 74% market share, and the figures for Germany and Britain were 66% and 65% respectively.</p>
<p>Just as controversially, last week's vote in a senate committee changed two crucial limitations on advertising.</p>
<p>In the revised bill, a single company will be allowed up to 20% of the entire advertising market, estimated to be worth €25bn (£17bn).</p>
<p>The new legislation would also free Mediaset from a curb on the use of promotional spots, in which presenters interrupt programmes to exhort viewers to buy the sponsors' products.</p>
<p>Mediaset was ordered last year to count these so-called tele-promotions when calculating the time devoted to advertising, which is subject in Italy to a limit of 18 minutes per hour. The revised bill would enable them to be brought within a daily total.</p>
<p>Antonello Falomi, a spokesman for the left-wing opposition, said the new text "makes a gift of hundreds of billions to Mediaset". It also elicited a furious response from the Italian newspaper publishers' federation, whose president, Luca Cordero di Montezemolo, wrote last week to Mr Gasparri to complain that it risked making the distribution of advertising revenue in Italy even more unequal.</p>
<p>The only limitation imposed by the communications bill on the purchase of newspapers by other media groups is a 24-month moratorium from the point at which it comes into force.</p>
<p>Mediaset increased its first-quarter sales by 23% to €777m and reported an 11% rise in pre-tax profits to €191m.</p>
<p>The Milan-based company said in a statement that approval of the bill "would not change Mediaset's financial situation by one euro".</p>
<p>Berlusconi's media empire stretches from terrestrial television to magazine publishing. His TV assets are controlled by Mediaset, in which he has a 48% stake.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Terrestrial television</hi>
</p>
<p>Canale 5</p>
<p>Italia 1</p>
<p>Retequattro</p>
<p>La 7 (minority stake)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Advertising sales</hi>
</p>
<p>Publitalia</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Publishing</hi>
</p>
<p>Mondadori (controls 30% of the Italian book market and owns over 50 magazines)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Telecoms</hi>
</p>
<p>Albacom (19.5% stake)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Newspapers</hi>
</p>
<p>Berlusconi's brother Paolo owns leading national daily Il Giornale</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>