<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-05-04" description="Italian premier believes his wife fell into a trap organised by his political opponents" fingerprint="7e3a822ebb9f9e2f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi claims his divorce was 'incited' by the opposition" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/04/silvio-berlusconi-divorce">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's high-profile separation from his wife took a political twist as he and the leader of Italy's biggest opposition party clashed over who, if anyone, had encouraged her to file for divorce.</p>
<p>The row erupted after the prime minister told an interviewer that his second wife, Veronica Lario, should apologise to him for her behaviour – and not the other way round. In an interview with Italy's biggest-selling daily, Corriere della Sera, Berlusconi also implied that he was the victim of a plot hatched by his enemies.</p>
<p>"I am indignant," Berlusconi said. "Veronica has fallen into a trap. And I know who she is being advised by. Or rather, being incited by."</p>
<p>He added darkly: "The truth will come out, don't worry."</p>
<p>Dario Franceschini, the leader of the centre-left Democratic Party hit back, saying the prime minister's insinuation was "pathetic". He said: "We have acted like responsible people in this matter, leaving a personal matter out of politics."</p>
<p>The already distressed Berlusconi-Lario match headed for the rocks after the prime minister was reported to have attended the 18th birthday party of a girl from Naples who aspires to a career as a model and says that she calls him "Daddy". Writing angrily to a news agency afterwards, Lario concentrated her fire on her husband's selection of a string of pretty young women, including a Big Brother contestant, to be candidates for his party in next month's European parliamentary election. In an aside that was reported to have particularly riled the 72-year-old, his wife was later quoted as saying she could no longer remain married to "a man who frequents minors".</p>
<p>Asked if there was any chance of saving his marriage, the prime minister said: "I don't think so. I don't know if I want that this time. Veronica will have to apologise to me publicly. And I don't know if it would be enough ... It's the third time in an election campaign that she has pulled a stunt of this kind. It really is too much."</p>
<p>Yesterday's interview appeared to mark the launch of a vigorous counter-offensive by the Berlusconi camp, concerned that the shattering of the prime minister's marriage to the 52 year-old Lario could have widespread political fall-out. According to other reports yesterday, Berlusconi's aides fear his scorned wife might launch an all-out campaign against him, revealing embarrassing secrets and sensitive information, in interviews with magazines and TV chat shows.</p>
<p>A leading pollster, Renato Mannheimer, said: "I don't think that it will take votes away from the prime minister because there are other reasons why [his supporters] vote for him." But other commentators speculated that the matter could lose Berlusconi support among women and devout Catholics.</p>
<p>Corriere said the prime minister believed he was the victim of a plot to ruin him at the apex of his popularity.</p>
<p>The paper also quoted him as saying the affair was a result of "media criminality", and that he believed key details had been misrepresented.</p>
<p>Berlusconi said he had dropped in on the birthday party of young Noemi Letizia because her father, a lowly council messenger, was a "friend of many years". Asked why she called him <hi rend="#i">papi</hi>, he replied: "But it's a joke. They wanted to call me granddad. It's better they call me daddy, don't you think?"</p>
<p>One of several mysteries surrounding the row is how a billionaire television and property magnate came to be such a close associate of Letizia's father.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was originally quoted by news agencies as saying that Benedetto Letizia had been a chauffeur for his friend, Italy's disgraced former prime minister, the late Bettino Craxi. But after journalists established that Letizia had never worked for Craxi, the prime minister's office issued a statement denying he had ever made such an assertion.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>