<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-08-26" description="Veronica Lario decided to divorce Italian PM after he failed to tell her he would attend model's birthday party, says book" fingerprint="4fbc4a3f5a565367" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="'Lies' made me file for divorce, says Silvio Berlusconi's estranged wife" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/aug/26/silvio-berlusconi-veronica-lario">
<main>
<p>The estranged wife of the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has claimed his alleged lies pushed her to file for divorce as he became embroiled in a sex scandal.</p>
<p>In the book, Tendenza Veronica, (Veronica's Trend) – published today – Veronica Lario describes how she made the decision in April after Berlusconi failed to mention that he would attend a Naples birthday party for an 18-year-old model.</p>
<p>His attendance at Noemi Letizia's party was later reported in the media, sparking a series of allegations over his purported fondness for young women.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied having any improper relationship with Letizia or any other women.</p>
<p>The book published today is a revised edition of one first published in 2004 by the journalist Maria Latella.</p>
<p>In the new edition, she quotes 53-year-old Lario as saying the Naples incident was the latest problem in her relationship with her husband.</p>
<p>"It was the latest lie," Lario said. "Better, then, to try to seek a last way to respect myself – better to divorce. He put me in this situation."</p>
<p>Lario, a former actor with whom Berlusconi has three children, said his actions were embarrassing him on a global level.</p>
<p>"I cannot be his babysitter, and I cannot stop him any more from making himself ridiculous in front of the world," she said. "I'm done."</p>
<p>Lario's lawyer was not available for comment.</p>
<p>Lario caused a political storm when she announced her decision to divorce. Both the Italian and international media have since competed for new allegations linking the 72-year-old Berlusconi to models and even a prostitute.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied ever paying a woman for sex, and has dismissed the allegations as lies fabricated by the opposition and "left-leaning" media.</p>
<p>He has maintained his popularity in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> despite the scandal and the centre-right coalition which won elections last year has remained stable.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>