<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-09-10" description="But Italian prime minister continues to laugh off claims of paid sex in return for political favours" fingerprint="fea2802c97aea707" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi admits suspected pimp brought women to his home" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/10/silvio-berlusconi-admits-women-tarantini">
<main>
<p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has admitted for the first time that women were brought to his home by a businessman who is under investigation for aiding and abetting prostitution. But he repeated that he had not paid them for sex, and declared that he was "by far the best prime minister Italy has had in its 150 year history".</p>
<p>In extracts from a statement to police published yesterday, Giampaolo Tarantini, from the southern Italian city of Bari, said he had brought about 30 women to parties and dinners at Berlusconi's Rome <hi rend="#i">palazzo</hi> and at least six had spent the night there. The affair took on a new dimension today when it emerged that some of the alleged encounters took place on days when the prime minister cancelled official appointments.</p>
<p>At a press conference today with the visiting Spanish prime minister, José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero, Berlusconi said: "An entrepreneur from Bari, now well known, Tarantino or Tarantini, came to some dinners bringing with him beautiful women [and] introducing them as his friends, his acquaintances."</p>
<p>But he added that talk of a prostitution ring was "an utter lie, an utter slander". He had "never paid for a sexual service. For someone who loves to conquer, the joy is the conquest. If you pay, what joy can there be?"</p>
<p>Tarantini, who was seeking political introductions to further his business, told police he paid the women who stayed at the prime minister's residence €1,000 and reimbursed expenses to others. Three of the women – who included reality show contestants, a model, an actress and a self-acknowledged prostitute – have denied his claims.</p>
<p>Bari's chief prosecutor said today that the investigation had not so far uncovered any evidence of criminal activity by Berlusconi. But it has raised questions about whether the prime minister let his private life interfere with his official duties.</p>
<p>On 23 September last year he was scheduled to address the United Nations general assembly. His foreign minister, Franco Frattini, explained that the prime minister had been obliged to cancel by the crisis over the future of Italy's flag carrier airline, Alitalia. The situation, he told journalists in New York, "requires the prime minister's constant presence" in Rome.</p>
<p>According to Tarantini, that same evening he drew up at the entrance to Berlusconi's home in a vehicle with newly darkened rear windows and no fewer than five women in the back. They allegedly included the hostess in the VIP section of a well-known discotheque and a former Big Brother contestant – who denied Tarantini's full account, but not that she had been Berlusconi's guest. Tarantini alleges that a third woman had an "intimate encounter" with the prime minister that evening.</p>
<p>Three months later, on 23 December, Berlusconi failed to attend an event organised by the Italian Olympic committee and the head of state's Christmas party at which the president, Giorgio Napolitano, addressed his guests on the subject of legal reform.</p>
<p>The official explanation was that he had torn a muscle and, according to the daily La Repubblica, a statement issued that day said not even "the attention of a physiotherapist had succeeded in making it better".</p>
<p>Tarantini's statement, however, claims the ailing Berlusconi was visited during the evening by a Latin American showgirl and a former castaway in the Italian version of Love Island. Both have denied it.</p>
<p>The prime minister was in an apparently upbeat mood today, telling the press conference that he enjoyed "the admiration of 68% per cent of Italians" – though he did not cite a source. The previous evening he again joked about his reputation at a meeting of young members of his party. When a female follower got up to ask a question, he interrupted her, saying: "I'm letting off the boys, but the girls are having to give their phone numbers."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>