<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Michael Wolff" categories="Opinion" date="2013-03-04" description="Michael Wolff: Italy's Beppe Grillo and America's Al Franken are turning political farce into a political force, but why do they seek office?" fingerprint="81bb9435b6280e77" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Comedy,Beppe Grillo,Silvio Berlusconi,US politics,US Senate" title="No laughing matter: comedians from Italy to the US are reforming politics | Michael Wolff" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/mar/04/beppe-grillo-comedian-turned-political-reformer">
<main>
<p>Why do comedians like politics? I don't mean like in the sense of liking to make fun of politics and politicians, I mean why do they want to join the ranks of the dull, deliberate, bureaucratic, and, unfunny?</p>
<p>In Italy, comedian Beppe Grillo has formed an outsider party and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/26/italy-bersani-coalition-beppe-grillo">led it to singular success in his country's election last week</ref>. He holds not only the immediate future of Italy's governing coalition in his hands, but, with his opposition to the euro, perhaps the fate of the eurozone.</p>
<p>Comedians have been viable political voices – both as participants and commentators – for a quite a few years now in the US. Al Franken, the former Saturday Night Live writer and performer, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/michaeltomasky/2009/jun/30/senate-minnesota-al-franken">is in the US Senate</ref>. The most robust political commentary takes place on late-night comedy shows. Jon Stewart is practically a saint. Bill Maher is taken very seriously. The Grillo success will likely spawn more comedians eager to become the thing they abhor most.</p>
<p>Their appeal and political frisson has an obvious explanation. There hasn't been a politician, perhaps anyway in the world, for two or three generations (I might <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2012/nov/02/boris-johnson-political-gaffes">except London mayor Boris Johnson here</ref>) who's had a sense of humor, or at least been gutsy enough to use it. In a land in which all language has died, where the pieties of Barack Obama pass for eloquence, comedians have a distinct asset. Comedians seem alive and vital, politicians seem like the walking dead.</p>
<p>Political commentators too are pompous and phony, slavish rather than skeptical, and have helped cause the death of the news media. The left is particularly the province of the solemn and the self-important – at least on the right there are expressive oddballs. This has left only comedians to talk about politics – liberal politics, anyway – with any sense of what the audience is actually feeling about politics.</p>
<p>For a long time now, the phenomenon of the political outsider has been a keen force. But that outsider was really just someone who didn't yet have the job of the insider. Now practically all insiders try to cast themselves as outsiders. Of all the outsider professions – doctors and teachers and generals and politician's wives who try to heroically enter politics – comedian may be the most credible one. A comedian actually opposes politics – or, at least, a comedian makes fun of politicians. A comedian's meat is absurdity.</p>
<p>It is a hidden aspect of populism, that it may not primarily be about economic reaction and resentment, but about name calling. About the insults that the body politic is waiting for someone to express. It's about the right words. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, says Beppe Grillo, is "the psycho dwarf". In this, in fact, a comedian starts with a powerful and even unfair advantage. It is easy to make fun of politicians. The crowd is certainly with you on this one. Curiously, politicians make the job of a comedian much easier and now the comedian is taking the politician's job. But why would they want to, really?</p>
<p>Al Franken, once among the nation's leading political satirists, was elected to the United States Senate and promptly disappeared. Perhaps he entertains his friends and family. But to the rest of the world he seems as faceless and worn and as far from a funny remark as most of his colleagues.</p>
<p>This seems to be one of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/mar/02/beppe-grillo-dario-fo-italy">Grillo's worries</ref> and a key aspect of his current approach to the frantic efforts in Italy to form a new government: not to join. So far he seems to be refusing most of the entreaties to join with other parties to help create a coalition. His reasonable position is, you are what we are opposing, so why would we want to become part of you? Indeed, this is Italy, where politics is at a such a level of the sclerotic and corrupt that to join would be to lose your audience. You would become the punchline. And yet, of course, you will join. You will participate. You will become part of it.</p>
<p>You will trade in being a true outsider, whose job it is to say the unsayable, for being an insider, where everything, including the terms on which you try to remain at least in part an outsider, is negotiable. Negotiation is the death of language.</p>
<p>It is perhaps true that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/beppe-grillo">Beppe Grillo</ref> and, perhaps, Al Franken, are not in their heart of hearts comedians, but, actually, reformers – enlightened bureaucrats who ache to bring honesty and improvement to the system. In Italy, that possibility seems to be creating something of an Italian Spring. But it is as possible that Beppe Grillo is a product of that one thing that politicians and entertainers have in common: a vast need to be the center of attention.</p>
<p>So far, Grillo's party, Five Star Movement, is pretty much his singular expression, him sitting at home and making declarations, the opposite of a democratic expression. The potential comparisons between Grillo, the comedian-blogger, and Berlusconi, the crooner-TV mogul, are obvious ones. To be an outsider with a voice and a following, to be a comedian who has found his subject and whose jokes hit their target, is a position vastly rarer, more satisfying, and arguably much more influential than any you might get in politics.</p>
<p>So why, again, would you give it up?</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>