<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Jane Martinson" categories="Media" date="2004-12-14" description="Football fans in Italy will be able to take part in a groundbreaking venture by eight top clubs and Mediaset, the media group owned by Silvio Berlusconi, in which they will be able to buy prepaid cards over the internet or from local kiosks to watch games. By Jane Martinson." fingerprint="1ca883ab83a1cd55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Rupert Murdoch,Television industry,Business,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Berlusconi tries to block Murdoch in an Italian game of football rights" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2004/dec/14/rupertmurdoch.broadcasting">
<main>
<p>Tickets to watch the game being played out by television executives in the highly lucrative world of football rights are among the hottest in Europe.</p>
<p>From January 1, fans in Italy will be able to take part in a groundbreaking venture orchestrated by eight of the top Serie A clubs and Mediaset, the media group owned by Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. From New Year's day, as part of a soft launch of the pay-per-view offering, fans will be able to buy prepaid cards over the internet or from local kiosks to watch specific home games.</p>
<p>The innovative move is seen by analysts as a bid to enhance the take-up of digital terrestrial TV in Italy. The government has provided millions of digital set-top boxes free in an attempt to complete digital switchover by the end of 2006.</p>
<p>It is also regarded as a flagrant attempt by Mr Berlusconi - who owns AC Milan, one of the participating football teams, as well as Mediaset - to compete with Rupert Murdoch's local satellite group, Sky Italia.</p>
<p>One London-based analyst, who declined to be named, said: "From Mediaset's perspective, anything that slows the growth of Sky is good news."</p>
<p>For their part, executives at Sky Italia have downplayed the importance of the launch, which is to be fully rolled out next September. Speaking in New York last week, chief executive Tom Mockridge said: "We don't believe it fundamentally changes the business model ... we don't see it as a comprehensive threat to us."</p>
<p>The loss-making pay-TV group, which has 3 million subscribers, was prevented from buying football rights on the digital terrestrial platform in Italy. Yet analysts estimate that its games provide Sky with about 40% of annual turnover.</p>
<p>The popularity of the rival football offer could hamper Sky's ability to reach its target of 4 million subscribers by the end of next year. About 1 million Italian homes are expected to have received a free digital set-top box by the end of this year.</p>
<p>The separation of pay-TV rights is the fundamental difference between Italy and the UK, where Sky's deal with the Premier League works across all platforms. This contract, which came into effect in August, runs until 2007.</p>
<p>Until then, contenders such as Top-Up TV, or any other pay television group, will be unable to enter the football market in the UK.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>