<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-03-28" description="Freedom People includes Mussolini's spiritual heirs as coalition brings Italy closer to two-party state" fingerprint="3fa0402bfd24c735" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi realises dream with new rightwing party" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/28/freedom-people-silvio-berlusconi-italy">
<main>
<p>A unified party of the Italian right, bringing together followers of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the prime minister, and the spiritual heirs of Mussolini's fascist blackshirts will formally be created tomorrow by delegates at a congress convened to inaugurate the movement.</p>
<p>Speaking from a giant platform in an immense exhibition hall, Berlusconi last night declared the gathering open and moved closer to realising his most cherished dream - leading a single power-bloc of the right.</p>
<p>As soon as a 50ft high screen above the platform showed the prime minister was entering the hall, 6,000 delegates sprang to their feet to give him an ovation. A beaming Berlusconi strode to his place while loudspeakers blared out his party's election campaign song, whose title roughly translates as: "Thank goodness for Silvio".</p>
<p>By tomorrow, when the congress ends, the 6,000 delegates will have turned the Freedom People (PdL) - made up of Berlusconi's Forza Italia ("Come on Italy!") party and the post-fascist National Alliance - from an electoral coalition into a ostensibly monolithic movement representing the bulk of Italy's conservatives. Since most of the centre-left is already united in a rival Democratic Party (PD), the latest merger brings <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> significantly closer to a two-party system.</p>
<p>Berlusconi last night told the lines of delegates stretching out in front of him: "You cannot imagine how much joy this moment gives me."</p>
<p>He went on to declare "We are the party of the Italian people. We are the party of the Italians who love freedom and who want to remain free."</p>
<p>The National Alliance has been allied to Forza Italia since the mid-1990s, and ran under a single banner with him in last year's election, helping the media tycoon win a landslide victory and a third term in office.</p>
<p>Some commentators have argued that bringing them together as a single party is doomed to fail because of the lack of a coherent set of aspirations. But one of Berlusconi's ministers, Altero Matteoli, declared that the PdL would be "the post-ideological party of the future".</p>
<p>A last-minute spat between Berlusconi and the National Alliance's former leader, Gianfranco Fini, highlighted the difficulties that the two wings of the party could face in achieving smooth co-operation. After the prime minister remarked that some MPs were in parliament "to make up the numbers", Fini, who is speaker of the lower house, lashed out with unaccustomed vigour at his leader-to-be.</p>
<p>It was not the prime minister's job, he said, "to feed populism and a sense of mistrust of the institutions". Fini has warned that the new party could fall prey to "Caesarism". He is not alone in his concerns.</p>
<p>Some opposition leaders too have argued the politician, who has long mocked the judiciary, may be turning his fire on parliament. Berlusconi has said he wants to give Italy a presidential system like that of the United States, and that the PdL should give him unprecedented freedom to pursue his agenda.</p>
<p>Its foundation was welcomed by the PD's leader, Dario Franceschini, as "positive for democracy". But Antonio Di Pietro, who heads a rival opposition group, said: "It's not the birth of a new party that worries me. It's Berlusconi's aims, which are dictatorial".</p>
<p>Forza Italia was created by Berlusconi in 1993 as a response to the collapse of Italy's old political order and, in particular, the disintegration of the Christian Democrats, who had dominated government since the second world war. Berlusconi disbanded the party last November.</p>
<p>The National Alliance was another product of the early nineties. It began as little more than a re-christened version of the Italian Social Movement (MSI), founded to perpetuate the ideas of Italy's fascist dictator, Benito Mussolini, which it claimed was Italy's greatest statesman of the 20th century.</p>
<p>While Fini had initially seemed reluctant to dissolve the National Alliance, the merger caps his 15-year attempt to lose the post-fascist tag and transform his party into a mainstream conservative force.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>