<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="James Walston" categories="Opinion" date="2009-03-31" description="James Walston: Silvio Berlusconi seems intent on complete political domination of Italy – and he's just taken another step along that road" fingerprint="b73cd15db2248f4d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="James Walston: Berlusconi has taken another step along the path to political domination of Italy" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/mar/31/italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Somewhere in the recesses of one of his villas, Silvio Berlusconi must have a checklist of the various obstacles to his complete control over Italy. At the weekend, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/28/freedom-people-silvio-berlusconi-italy">he was able to make another big tick on the list</ref>.</p>
<p>In front of an adulating crowd, he was acclaimed leader of his new party, the <ref target="http://www.forzaitalia.it/">Popolo della Libertà</ref>, the "People of Freedom". The party had actually been in existence since November 2007 and won last year's general election with a substantial majority in both houses. But it was still a composite party of his own Forza Italia and the post-fascist <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/mar/30/silvio-berlusconi-fascism-italy-g20">Alleanza Nazionale</ref> until the latter officially dissolved itself last week. Now there is a single centre-right party in Italy with Berlusconi as its clear and undisputed leader.</p>
<p>In his first full term from 2001-06, Berlusconi dealt with his personal economic and criminal problems; in the second he is laying his claim to mark the era as "Berlusconian". Since being re-elected, he has given himself immunity from prosecution and is well on his way to reducing the judiciary's powers; there is a reform bill before parliament which would give powers of prosecution to a politically-controlled equivalent of the Crown Prosecution Service. The results in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> would be very predictable. Another bill will reduce investigators' powers to use phone taps.</p>
<p>He is using the recession to grapple with the very independent Bank of Italy and is trying to give the executive control over credit. The bank's governor, Mario Draghi, is tough and has shown that he can fight hard, so Berlusconi might not win this one.</p>
<p>The recession is also giving him the opportunity to undermine both regional and local government and the president. He has proposed a bill which would allow Italian householders, at least those who live in detached houses and who mostly vote centre-right, to increase their houses' volume by 20% in order to increase spending. There would be almost no control by local authorities.</p>
<p>Environmentalists and upmarket tourist operators are already cringing at the prospect as are the local authorities (even the centre-right ones) who see this an erosion of their power. Berlusconi wants to pass the bill as a decree, with instant effect, rather than "wasting time" with a normal parliamentary bill which would take months and be amended. This would have to be signed by the president and could lead to a stand-off.</p>
<p>He has already clashed with President Napolitano, who refused to sign a decree law last month. This would have overruled the verdict of the supreme court allowing Beppe Englaro to remove his daughter's artificial life-support system. Berlusconi used the highly emotive Englaro case to fight both the president's residual powers and the court by rushing a bill through parliament. The bill that is likely to pass will almost certainly actually reduce whatever rights Italians now have to a living will. Naturally Berlusconi had the wide support not only of the right but also many Catholics on the left and the church authorities if not all the clergy. Payback time for the church's electoral support will be in the form of financial support for Catholic schools under the slogan of "freedom of religion" trumpeted in Berlusconi's speech on Sunday.</p>
<p>Despite all this, Berlusconi complained on Sunday that "the prime minister has no power". This is chutzpah indeed, but there is clear and practical meaning to the remark. He wants the power to dissolve parliament (which at the moment is still the president's) so that he has a stick to threaten his coalition ally, Umberto Bossi and the <ref target="http://www.leganord.org/">Northern League</ref>, another item on his list. And the next item is to get 51% in the European elections. And it goes on.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>