<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2006-11-21" description="Amid fevered speculation over his political future, Italy's former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi went on trial today alongside David Mills, the estranged husband of the culture secretary, Tessa Jowell." fingerprint="37da9311d6e217f3" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Politics,Italy,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,David Mills,Europe" title="Berlusconi trial overshadowed by speculation about his future" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/nov/21/politics.italy">
<main>
<p>Amid fevered speculation over his political future, Italy's former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> went on trial today alongside David Mills, the estranged husband of the culture secretary, Tessa Jowell.</p>
<p>An article published by a newspaper close to the Italian right quoted Mr Berlusconi as saying he would never again return to lead <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. "I've done my bit. That's enough for me," he was said to have told friends. However, the billionaire politician's spokesman later quoted him as saying he had "no scheme for quitting" politics.</p>
<p>The confusion overshadowed the fact that Mr Berlusconi is again in court for alleged financial irregularities. In the trial that began - and was swiftly adjourned - today, he is charged with embezzlement, tax dodging and false accounting.</p>
<p>Mr Mills - who, like Mr Berlusconi, was not in court - is accused of helping him to dodge taxes and illegally set aside cash for his family. Another 12 people are on trial in a case that revolves around the allegedly illegal trading of TV film rights. All the defendants deny wrongdoing.</p>
<p>Today's proceedings were adjourned until next Monday because of objections from defence lawyers. In a petition to the court, they argued that the presiding judge, Edoardo DíAvossa, should not hear the case because he had ruled in an earlier trial involving a film production company that forms part of Mr Berlusconi business empire. Judge DíAvossa referred the question to an appeals court.</p>
<p>The trial is one of two in which Mr Mills is involved as a co-defendant alongside Italy's richest man. In the other, due to begin next year, the British lawyer is accused of taking a £340,000 bribe from Mr Berlusconi.</p>
<p>The political future of the man who is currently Italy's opposition leader has been a subject of growing conjecture. He turned 70 in September and if the present centre-left government led by Romano Prodi were to serve out its five-year term, he would be 74 when he next ran for prime minister.</p>
<p>His chances of returning to government depend on putting a swift end to the Prodi government, which has a notional majority of only one seat in the Senate, the upper house of parliament. However, the government can rely on a majority of Italy's life senators while some of Mr Berlusconi's own allies have been reluctant to fight the government in parliament.</p>
<p>This is particularly the case with the Union of Christian Democrats whose leader, Pier Ferdinando Casini, is seen as Mr Berlusconi’s most likely successor.</p>
<p>Having already clung to power for more than six months, the centre-left is set to burnish its credentials in the next few weeks by negotiating the passage of a budget for 2007.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>