<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Matt Williams" categories="World news" date="2013-02-23" description="Likelihood of weak government and rise of populist former comedian add to apprehension as Italian campaigning ceases" fingerprint="57a9f9b55125d64f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Mario Monti,World news,Euro,Europe" title="Italy awaits opening of general election polls amid uncertainty" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/23/italy-general-election-bersani-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Political parties in Italy were forced to cease campaigning on Saturday, as the country prepared for a general election <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/22/italians-options-election-looms">that is being closely watched across the eurozone amid fears of a damaging stalemate</ref>.</p>
<p>As candidates observed a mandatory 24-hour purdah ahead of polls opening, citizens were urged to vote. The polls are open on Sunday and Monday. A survey released in the run-up to the ballot suggested that the centre-left Democratic Party, led by Pier Luigi Bersani, held a five-point lead over a conservative coalition led by the former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. The outgoing premier, Mario Monti, heading a centrist coalition, is also running. But a lacklustre campaign has seen his chances fade in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Political analysts have suggested that the most likely outcome – which could ensure stability – is a governing alliance between Bersani and Monti. But Monti's faltering campaign has led to concern that he will not win enough senate seats to boost the centre-left bloc. A resulting weak government could lead to market fears over Italy's ability to implement measures to kick start its faltering economy.</p>
<p>Whoever takes power will face the arduous task of pulling Italy out of the longest recession it has faced in a generation. The election takes place amid deep public resentment at austerity measures brought in to curb national debt. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/23/beppe-grillo-italian-elections">Adding to the uncertainty has been the campaign of the comedian-turned-politician Beppe Grillo</ref>, an anti-establishment figure whose Five Star Movement is expected to poll strongly. Latest voter-intention surveys put him at around 16%, which would make his movement the third-largest electoral force.</p>
<p>As campaigning idrew to a close on Friday evening, Grillo stole the spotlight in Rome by attracting an estimated 500,000 people to hear his tirades against corrupt politicians and bankers. The success of the former comedian's "Tsunami Tour" has underlined the discontent felt by a large proportion of Italians regarding mainstream political parties.</p>
<p>"Grillo is saying the things that all ordinary Italians are thinking, he is giving us hope," said 41-year-old Luca Pennisi, a pastry chef at a café in Rome where several customers were still unsure who to vote for. "It's time to change the system, get rid of the old politicians and stop wasting public money," Pennisi said, adding that he had watched Grillo's final rally on the internet and would definitely vote for his grouping.</p>
<p>Others are less sure. A survey released on Tuesday found that 28% of Italians had yet to decide who to vote for, or were considering not voting at all. On Saturday, the Interior Ministry urged some 47 million eligible voters to vote, adding that it had made preparations for bad weather, including snow in some regions, to ensure that everyone could have the chance to cast their ballot.</p>
<p>"Elections are a fundamental moment for a democracy and we want all our citizens to experience them in the best way possible," interior minister Anna Maria Cancellieri said in a video posted on the ministry's website.</p>
<p>While Grillo's campaign ended on a high, others entered the mandatory 24-hour purdah on a quieter note. Berlusconi, who has promised tax refunds as a central plank of his platform, cancelled a planned appearance at a Naples rally, blaming an eye problem. Bersani rounded off at a theatre in Rome, while Monti held a similar event in Florence.</p>
<p>Despite fuelling anger among many Italians by introducing an austerity package while the country continues to struggle against rising unemployment, Monti – who replaced Berlusconi in November 2011 – is still supported by some who believe that the measures were necessary.</p>
<p>"My vote will go to Monti for a very simple reason, I think he is the only serious proposition," said one Rome resident, named Vito, who was on a stroll through the city on Saturday.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>