<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Patrick Wintour" categories="World news" date="2009-07-08" description="Patrick Wintour: Concern for the dispossessed at the summit of 25 nations sits oddly alongside Berlusconi's burlesque private life" fingerprint="7ef3832f0302d30c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="G8,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Gordon Brown,Politics,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi makes playboy's G8" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/08/g8-berlusconi-gordon-brown">
<main>
<p>It was a late start by Gordon Brown's standards. He burst onto his British Airways chartered plane bound for the G8 summit in L'Aquila, Italy, a little before 6.30am.</p>
<p>Sarah Brown, recently appointed as the prime minister's special envoy to Planet Normal, cheerfully wrote on her blog that she and her husband had been "up at the crack of dawn", though by the time she climbed out of bed her husband had almost certainly fired off several waves of emails across Whitehall.</p>
<p>Brown has never got up at the crack of dawn. He is always up before it, especially if a world summit on the economy is in prospect. Brown is in his element at the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref>.</p>
<p>He knows the detail of IMF structures backwards, the future trajectory of oil prices, the debt-GDP ratio of Papua New Guinea and the intricacies of climate change technology transfer funds. He has also been at this game for so long he hardly needs civil servants to come with him, and with admirable seriousness of purpose, he drives his G8 colleagues through with his commitment and knowledge.</p>
<p>But at this summit, he has come up against another irresistible force in the shape of the mercurial Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, a man who has organised a playboy summit of high comedy, chaos and emotion.</p>
<p>The summit, including a 25-nation guest list and 5,000 or so hangers-on, was shifted in April from a luxurious island off Sardinia to the dusty, earthquake-hit town of L'Aquila. Fifty thousand lost their homes in the capital city of Abruzzo.</p>
<p>The logo for the summit still depicts swimming Sardinian turtles, even though the event is taking place in some functional financial police barracks in the heart of the mountains – the kind of spartan quarters to which voters would like to see Britain's errant MPs consigned in future.</p>
<p>Italy's leader has eased the pain by providing some luxurious, silk bed linen – a Berlusconi speciality.</p>
<p>In the conference area, poignant pictures of the many Renaissance gems destroyed by the earthquake are displayed. Blue tents still pockmark the area, housing many residents who believe Berlusconi has not kept his promises to help them. One poster on a hilltop reads "Yes we camp". Aftershocks are still regularly hitting the town, according to the National Institute of Geophysics and Volcanology, but if there are emergency evacuation plans in place, Brown seems admirably oblivious to them.</p>
<p>This concern for the dispossessed sits oddly alongside Berlusconi's burlesque private life. Carla Bruni, wife of Nicolas Sarkozy, decided to arrive late as a semi-official protest at the way Berlusconi has partied with teenage girls, leading his wife to file for divorce.</p>
<p>Bruni is also keen to avoid a potentially embarrassing meeting with Mara Carfagna, the 33-year-old former topless model who is now minister for equal opportunities. For in the absence of his estranged wife, Berlusconi drafted in Carfagna and the education minister, Mariastella Gelmini, to escort the leaders' wives through the sites of Rome.</p>
<p>The demure Sarah Brown agreed to this outing, two hours from L'Aquila, partly since the visit included an audience with Pope Benedict XVI. She and Carfagna must have made a truly catholic group as they filed in for the audience along with wives of the Egyptian, Indian, Swedish and Mexican leaders.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's travails only got worse when he suffered a superstar battering by Bono at a U2 concert at the San Siro stadium in Milan to. Bono raged at him for cutting back Italian government aid to Africa. He told his audience: "Italians have many gifts to the world, modern physics, the Renaissance, the piano, the gift of singing from Pavarotti to Puccini. You have so many gifts.</p>
<p>"In the next few days your leader will have to decide where he stands on the gift of life that lives beyond these shores."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>