<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Football" date="2009-10-07" description="Albanian oil magnate Rezart Taci would have 'no problem' paying €700 million to buy AC Milan if Silvio Berlusconi decides to sell" fingerprint="efe992af92638f1f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Serie A,Football,Sport" title="Albanian oil magnate ready to pay Silvio Berlusconi €700m for AC Milan" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2009/oct/07/milan-rezart-taci-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Albanian oil magnate Rezart Taci says he would have "no problem" in paying €700million (£647m) to buy AC Milan if owner <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> decides to sell.</p>
<p>Speculation that Berlusconi will sell has increased since a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> administrative court ruled the Italian premier's holding company, Fininvest, must pay €750m to rival CIR for bribing a judge in a 1990s battle to buy Italy's biggest publisher Mondadori. Fininvest has repeatedly denied Berlusconi has any intention to sell</p>
<p>Talking to La Gazzetta dello Sport, Taci said: "My group is used to taking on big commitments and seeing them through to the end. I'm sure I can find the necessary financing."</p>
<p>The €700m figure matches analysts' valuation of seven-times European champions Milan, who are struggling to find form. Taci said he had already spoken to Berlusconi about buying the club.</p>
<p>"He told me that he does not intend to sell, but I know that if he decided to, he would take my proposal into consideration. I guarantee that I would do everything to keep Milan where they deserve to be – at the top of the world."</p>
<p>Taci admitted that his bid to buy <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/serieafootball">Serie A</ref> side Bologna in the close season fell through because his hopes were raised that he might be able to buy Milan instead.</p>
<p>"As a Milan fan I thought it was best to be patient for a little while," he said. "Why kid people of Bologna if there was the chance a bigger door would open in the meantime?"</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>