<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2010-10-31" description="Roberto Maroni defended Milan officers who released 17-year-old belly dancer into custody of Berlusconi's aide" fingerprint="fea988a911a1f61d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" title="Berlusconi's interior minister backs police who released girl to PM aide" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/31/italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Italy's interior minister has supported Milan police officers accused of breaking rules to free a 17-year-old Moroccan belly dancer from custody, under pressure from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>Citing police documents, Italian daily La Repubblica claimed today that orders by a magistrate to place the girl in a children's home were ignored by officers. They instead "blocked normal procedures" to release her into temporary custody of an aide of the prime minister.</p>
<p>Named by the Italian press as Karima Keyek, the daughter of Moroccan immigrants claimed she was entertained by Berlusconi in February at his Milan mansion, where he gave her cash and jewellery. She was arrested last May on suspicion of stealing €3,000 (£2,600) from a friend.</p>
<p>But Roberto Maroni, the interior minister, defended the police's actions. "The police applied all the rules and regulations, so there is nothing to object to," he said. Italian news agency ANSA reported that Berlusconi denied telling officers the girl was related to Egyptian president Hosni Mubarak, although police records reportedly state that he did.</p>
<p>Dario Franceschini, of the opposition Democratic party, demanded Berlusconi resign. "If it is confirmed that magistrates had decided to send the girl to a home, then we are looking at an intolerable mix of lies and crimes that are irreconcilable with the prime minister's role," he said.</p>
<p>Berlusconi claimed he "always tries to help people who need it", and sent an aide to help Keyek, who used the stage name Ruby, stay out of children's homes or prison. But following her release into the custody of Berlusconi's aide, she was immediately allowed to share a flat with a Brazilian model who she accused of working as a prostitute. Following a fight between the two, Ruby was treated for light wounds in hospital, arrested a second time and dispatched to a children's home.</p>
<p>La Repubblica suggested Berlusconi had not pushed for her release out of kindness, but through fear of "her memories, her big mouth and her volubility, which could really get him trouble".</p>
<p>Keyek has called Berlusconi a "gentleman" and denied having sex with him. But she has reportedly given prosecutors a detailed account of parties at his mansion and is now planning an autobiography.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's lawyer, Niccolò Ghedini, has in recent days been holding meetings with a number of other young women who attended events at the mansion, Corriere della Sera reported.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>