<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2023-05-06" description="The former Italian prime minister was speaking for the first time since he was hospitalised a month ago" fingerprint="7ea9d05d9326c74d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Giorgia Meloni" title="Silvio Berlusconi addresses Forza Italia members from hospital room" url="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/may/06/silvio-berlusconi-addresses-forza-italia-members-from-hospital-room">
<main>
<p>The former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has given his first address to the public since being hospitalised a month ago, delivering a video message to party members from his hospital room.</p>
<p>“Here I am, here for you, wearing a shirt and jacket for the first time in a month,” the 86-year-old billionaire media mogul said, in a pre-recorded address to a convention of his right-wing Forza Italia party.</p>
<p>Smartly dressed and sitting behind a desk with the party’s banner and the Italian flag behind him, he thanked members for their support, “which more than anything helped me overcome a very dangerous pneumonia”.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/apr/05/silvio-berlusconi-intensive-care-milan">admitted to Milan’s San Raffaele hospital</ref> on 5 April suffering from a lung infection, after which doctors revealed for the first time that he has leukaemia.</p>
<p>He spent the first week and a half in intensive care, before being moved to a normal ward.</p>
<p>He had hoped to be discharged in time for the two-day party convention, which began on Friday in Milan, a party source told AFP earlier this week.</p>
<p>But in the end, a film crew was brought to his hospital room on Friday to record his speech, media reports said.</p>
<p>Berlusconi’s doctors on Wednesday confirmed his condition was “stable” but did not mention when he might leave hospital.</p>
<p>Forza Italia is a junior partner in prime minister Giorgia Meloni’s coalition government, and Berlusconi, the party founder, remains its president.</p>
<p>Despite being in the Senate, Berlusconi is rarely seen in public.</p>
<p>He has been in and out of hospital over the past few years, notably after contracting Covid-19 in 2020.</p>
<p>Forza Italia has lost much of its support since its heyday, when Berlusconi was prime minister three times between 1994 and 2011.</p>
<p>
<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com#EmailSignup-skip-link-12">skip past newsletter promotion</ref>
</p>
<p>after newsletter promotion</p>
<p>The latest YouTrend survey put Forza Italia on 7% support, compared to almost 29% for Meloni’s far-right Brothers of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> party.</p>
<p>Their coalition allies, Matteo Salvini’s anti-immigration League, are polling at about 9%.</p>
<p>Berlusconi said on Saturday that his party was the “backbone of this government”, present “to ensure that its decisions are truly correct, fair, balanced”.</p>
<p>In his 20-minute video, which was peppered with applause from the audience, he said he was ready to get back to work.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>