<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Share" categories="World news" date="2012-10-27" description="From his early days as a cruise-ship entertainer to his 17-year domination of Italian politics, Silvio Berlusconi has never been scared of the limelight. We look at the changing faces of Italy's controversial former leader" fingerprint="1f22daff9154c18d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news;Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi in pictures" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2012/oct/26/silvio-berlusconi-italy">
<main>
<head rend="h1">Silvio Berlusconi in pictures</head>
<p> From his early days as a cruise-ship entertainer to his 17-year domination of Italian politics, Silvio Berlusconi has never been scared of the limelight. We look at the changing faces of Italy's controversial former leader </p>
<list rend="ul">
<item> The future prime minister began his career selling vacuum cleaners before going on to building a reputation as a singer in nightclubs and on cruise ships.<p>Photograph: Olycom SPA/Rex Features</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi the family man, with daughters Barbara and Eleonora – two of his five children from two marriages – in his villa near Milan in 1994. He married Carla Elvira Dall'Oglio in 1965, divorcing in 1985, and met second wife Veronica Lario after seeing her perform topless in a play.<p>Photograph: Franco Origlia/Corbis Sygma</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi's hospitality to Tony and Cherie Blair in Porto Cervo, Sardinia in August of 2004 caused problems for the UK prime minister later in his term of office.<p>Photograph: Davide Caglio/EPA</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi with his then wife Veronica in 1990.<p>Photograph: Susan Walsh/AP</p></item>
<item> Veronica Lario, Berlusconi's long-suffering wife,<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/aug/26/silvio-berlusconi-veronica-lario">filed for divorce in May 2009</ref>. "I cannot be his babysitter, and I cannot stop him any more from making himself ridiculous in front of the world," she said. "I'm done."<p>Photograph: Luca Turi/EPA</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi met Russian leader Vladimir Putin on a number of occasions while he was prime minister of Italy. Here the pair enjoy an informal outdoor dinner at the Zavidovo, Putin's residence northwest of Moscow, Russia. in February 2003.<p>Photograph: Itar-Tass/AP</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi's reputation for admiring women appears to be confirmed as he eyes up Argentina's president, Cristina Fernández de Kirchner, during the G20 Summit in Cannes in November 2011.<p>Photograph: Yves Herman/Reuters</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi attempts a high five with José Maria Aznar, then prime minister of Spain, at the beginning of a European Council meeting in Copenhagen in December 2002.<p>Photograph: Jens Noergaard Larsen/AP</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi with Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi during a meeting in Benghazi in August 2008.<p>Photograph: Reuters</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi whispers to Nicolas Sarkozy, at the time the French president, as German chancellor Angela Merkel smirks, during at a meeting at the Élysée Palace in October 2008.<p>Photograph: Philippe Wojazer/Reuters</p></item>
<item> Between the start of Berlusconi's third term as prime minister in 2008 and his<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/12/silvio-berlusconi-resign-italy-eurozone?intcmp=239">resignation in 2011</ref>, he endured 50 votes of confidence.<p>Photograph: .</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi lost two elections to his rival Romano Prodi, left, first in 1996 and<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/20/italy.johnhooper">later in 2006</ref>.<p>Photograph: Andreas Solaro/AFP/Getty Images</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi is supported at the podium by his personal doctor Umberto Scapagnini, far left, after collapsing during an emotional speech to political supporters in November 2006.<p>Photograph: Fabrizio Giovannozzi/AP</p></item>
<item> In May 2008 Berlusconi is<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/apr/15/italy1">elected as Italy's prime minister for a third time</ref>since he first stood for parliament in 1994.<p>Photograph: Alessandra Benedetti/Corbis</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi finally admitted he had undergone plastic surgery in January 2004. "I only had my eyelids retouched slightly," he told a press conference. But<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/mar/07/berlusconi-operation-face-cosmetic-surgery-italy?INTCMP=ILCNETTXT3487">by 2011 his appearance had undergone a dramatic transformation</ref>.<p>Photograph: .</p></item>
<item> It was also clear that something had happened to his hair, which had regrown over the bald spot on the back of his head.<p>Photograph: .</p></item>
<item> While signing autographs after a political rally in Milan in 2009, Berlusconi was attacked by a man who hurled a souvenir statue of Milan's cathedral at his face. The politician suffered a broken nose and two broken teeth and later needed surgery to repair the damage.<p>Photograph: .</p></item>
<item> In February 2011 Berlusconi's alleged use of prostitutes came to a head when an Italian judge ordered him to stand trial on charges of paying for sex with an underaged girl called<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/15/karima-el-mahroug-runaway-silvio-berlusconi">Karima el-Mahroug</ref>.<p>Photograph: Andreas Rentz/Getty Images</p></item>
<item> Berlusconi<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/12/silvio-berlusconi-resign-italy-eurozone">resigned for the last time</ref>on 12 November 2011 after losing his parliamentary majority.<p>Photograph: Christophe Karaba/EPA</p></item>
</list>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>