<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="James Sturcke" categories="World news" date="2005-03-09" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, said today the driver of the car in which an Italian agent was killed by US forces in Iraq last week had obeyed orders to stop." fingerprint="1d86903f97008b17" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Iraq,US news,Middle East and north Africa,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi contradicts US friendly-fire account" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/mar/09/italy.iraq1">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, said today the driver of the car in which an Italian agent was killed by US forces in Iraq last week had obeyed orders to stop.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi said the car, which was taking the freed Italian hostage Giuliana Sgrena to Baghdad airport, pulled up immediately when American soldiers flashed a warning light at it.</p>
<p>The prime minister told the Italian senate that the intelligence agent Nicola Calipari, who received a state funeral in Rome on Monday, had US military authorisation for his operation to secure the release of Ms Sgrena.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's version of events contradicts the initial statement from American forces, which said they fired on a speeding car, killing Mr Calipari and wounding Ms Sgrena and another agent, only after it failed to stop at a checkpoint.</p>
<p>In his first substantial address since Friday's shooting, Mr Berlusconi said the idea that Mr Calipari was killed by friendly fire was "painful" to accept. But he said he was assured the US was committed to getting to the bottom of the shooting.</p>
<p>"The US has no intention of evading the truth. I'm sure that in a very short time every aspect of this will be clarified," he said.</p>
<p>In his 10-minute address he made no mention of ransom payments to win Ms Sgrena's release. Some Italian officials have suggested a ransom was paid, but there has been no official confirmation.</p>
<p>"The case of friendly fire is certainly the most painful to bear," Mr Berlusconi said. "It feels like an injustice beyond any sentiment. It's something unreasonable.</p>
<p>"When Italian citizens have been victims of kidnappings, the government has always acted by following two directives: it has always rejected political blackmail, while at the same time activating all the political, diplomatic and intelligence channels to obtain the release of our nationals," he said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, it emerged today that the US president, George Bush, has promised <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> a "fast and thorough" joint investigation into the killing of Mr Calipari. In a letter to the Italian president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, Mr Bush lamented the "tragic incident", Mr Ciampi's office said in a statement.</p>
<p>The Italian government has also called the shooting an "accident" but disputes the US version of events and demands that Washington shed light on the incident and punish those responsible.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, a staunch supporter of the war in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/iraq">Iraq</ref>, sent 3,000 troops to the southern part of the country after the ousting of Saddam Hussein. Ms Sgrena, a journalist with the anti-war daily Il Manifesto, was taken hostage in Iraq on February 4.</p>
<p>The US military opened a separate inquiry today into the shooting of a Bulgarian soldier who Bulgarian officials believe may have been killed accidentally by coalition troops.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>