<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Politics" date="2008-04-19" description="Silvio Berlusconi, politician, 71" fingerprint="34ea7c79746c8661" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,Italy,Life and style,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi: Did I say that?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2008/apr/20/italy">
<main>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On women</hi>
</p>
<p>The women of the Right are certainly the most beautiful ... the Left has no taste, not even when it comes to women (2008)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On himself</hi>
</p>
<p>I am the Jesus Christ of politics. I am a patient victim, I sacrifice myself for everyone (2006)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On poltics</hi>
</p>
<p>Only Napoleon has done more than me. I am fighting communism just as Churchill fought the Nazis (2006)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On ageing</hi>
</p>
<p>It's the fate of the lion in winter: all his billions, all his television channels cannot rescue him from the mockery that rains down on the aged lecher, his powers visibly waning (2008)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On size</hi>
</p>
<p>They keep calling me a dwarf, but I'm taller than Sarkozy and Putin (2008)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On women</hi>
</p>
<p>People will vote for Daniela Santanchè because she is a beautiful babe (2008)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On his playboy image</hi>
</p>
<p>I'll try not to let you down and I promise you two and a half months of complete sexual abstinence until election day (2006)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On German MEP Martin Schulz</hi>
</p>
<p>I know a producer in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> is making a film on the Nazi concentration camps. I'll suggest you for the role of commandant. You'd be perfect (2003)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On hair loss</hi>
</p>
<p>I have little hair because my brain is so big it pushes the hair out (2001)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On women</hi>
</p>
<p>Ladies, I have a mission for you on election day: cook! Sweet and exquisite things, please. Bring them to the polling station to be examined. The boldest can try making a tart, the most skilful, profiteroles (2008)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On communism</hi>
</p>
<p>In the China of Mao, they did not eat children, but had them boiled to fertilise the fields (2006)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On Mussolini</hi>
</p>
<p>He never killed anyone, he sent people on holiday to confine them (2003)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On corruption </hi>
</p>
<p>We must fight against tax evasion but also defend the rights of tax evaders, or companies that make mistakes (2006)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On judges</hi>
</p>
<p>In order to make that job you must be mentally disturbed (2003)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">On his previous comments</hi>
</p>
<p>They're not gaffes. I've made no gaffes (2008)</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>