<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Luigi Zanda; Democratic party leader; Italian senate; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2013-12-29" description="29 September: Luigi Zanda, the Democratic party leader of the Italian senate recalls the end of Silvio Berlusconi's reign" fingerprint="dffed2bbcb23b32d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Berlusconi tries to bring down the Italian government – and is humiliated in parliament" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/29/2013-eyewitness-accounts-berlusconi-italy">
<main>
<p>There are days that can sum up a moment in the history of a country, and this was one of them. It embodied the break-up of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>'s political party – a group which had held together for 20 years and long been the dominant force in Italian politics – while also setting up the ousting of its leader from the Italian parliament a few weeks later.</p>
<p>It was late September when Silvio Berlusconi triggered a vote of no-confidence in the Italian government by ordering his ministers out of the ruling coalition – a move intended to bring down the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/profile/enrico-letta">Enrico Letta</ref>. On the day of the vote, Sandro Bondi, a stalwart supporter of Berlusconi's, stood up in the senate and said that his party would vote against the government.</p>
<p>By the time Berlusconi entered the chamber, however, he had begun to realise the extent of the rebellion in his own ranks. [He is pictured, above, surrounded by supporters during Prime Minister Letta's crucial speech to the senate.] And shortly after, Berlusconi himself made a short speech saying the opposite to Bondi – that he would back the current prime minister.</p>
<p>That speech summed up Berlusconi's decline as a political force. It was short and without ideas. It was clear he was just trying to quell the dissent in his party. But if he was hoping to keep his party together it didn't work. Two weeks later the party split anyway, and he took his party into opposition. He lost a gamble, and that is another sign of his decline.</p>
<p>That dramatic day in the Senate also launched a generational change in parliament, as Angelino Alfano [deputy prime minister and considered Berlusconi's heir] led the rebels in Berlusconi's ranks. Weeks later Matteo Renzi took over the centre-left Democratic party.</p>
<p>Will Berlusconi be back? His party is split and he has since been voted out of parliament because of a criminal conviction. He is older, his companies are not doing too well, and he faces more trials. It is hard to see him staging another comeback.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>