<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Naomi McAuliffe" categories="Opinion" date="2014-05-21" description="Naomi McAuliffe: He stunned the unstunnable Silvio Berlusconi. Clearly, nothing is now off limits for Newsnight's demob-happy grand inquisitor" fingerprint="79349135a6ba5699" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Gender,World news,Women in politics,Women,Jeremy Paxman,Silvio Berlusconi,Richard Scudamore,Women in the boardroom,BBC,Newsnight,Media,Politics,Business,Football,UK news" title="Jeremy Paxman's ultimate questions | Naomi McAuliffe" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/may/21/jeremy-paxman-questions-silvio-berlusconi-newsnight">
<main>
<p>In those last few days or weeks before leaving your job, most people just spend their time deleting incriminating emails and stealing stationery. If you don't think your future career will be harmed, or you're retiring, you might take the opportunity to tell everyone you work with exactly how much you hate them.</p>
<p>This is exactly where Jeremy Paxman seems to be since he announced his retirement from Newsnight. Unencumbered by the fear that the great and the good might refuse future interviews, he's asking the questions he has always wanted to ask. In doing so, he managed the stun the unembarrassable <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> by asking whether he really called Angela Merkel an "unfuckable lard-arse".</p>
<p>We need to harness the power of this deliriously demob-happy Paxo by seeking similarly probing questions for some of the recent hot sexism stories. Here are just a few suggestions for the next episode of Jeremy's everything-you-wanted-to- know-about-sexism-but-were-too-afraid-to-ask" series.</p>
<head rend="h2">To Richard Scudamore</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">What would you have say in order to be actually sacked from the Premier League?</hi>
</p>
<p>Scudamore, head of the Premier League, had his sexist emails come to light through a whistle-blowing PA. He was subsequently investigated by a Football Association committee, which found him profitable for the organisation, and didn't sack him. Which begs the question: if he brings in even more money, could he get away with calling women even worse things? Could this form the basis of a bonus scheme? Perhaps, here's a list of words you can use if you hit your targets. Also, given that <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/football/27481895 http://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/news/barclays-will-not-renew-premier-3579182">Barclays is withdrawing its sponsorship</ref>, will he be looking for more appropriate sources of income, such as Zoo Weekly magazine or the Dorchester?</p>
<head rend="h2">To the publishers of the New York Times</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Have you ever had a male editor who made decisions without consultation and had aggressive communication skills?</hi>
</p>
<p>Arthur Sulzberger Jr, publisher of the New York Times, responded to criticism that the sacking of Jill Abramson as executive editor was sexist with a bizarre and petty public statement listing her faults. These supposedly included "arbitrary decision-making, a failure to consult and bring colleagues with her, inadequate communication and the public mistreatment of colleagues". So, given this public mistreatment of a former colleague, will Sulzberger be sacking himself?</p>
<head rend="h2">To David Cameron</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Should you have promised to have a third of your cabinet made up of people called David rather than women?</hi>
</p>
<p>Cameron's pledge to have a third of his cabinet female at the last election has been an increasing embarrassment, as the number of women who attend cabinet meetings is just five. If he had committed to a third of Davids, even with the current number of attendees being four, it would have seemed a lot more achievable. It's also been almost impossible to find a minister for equality who has a decent commitment to equality, and can be representative. <ref target="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2014/04/nicky-morgan-david-cameron-has-just-appointed-minister-straight-women">The current minster for women has voted against gay marriage in the past</ref>, and the most senior minister in charge of women is a man – Sajid Javed – who holds the equalities brief.</p>
<head rend="h2">To Vladimir Putin</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Come, on admit it: you loved Conchita Wurst at Eurovision</hi>
</p>
<p>Putin has hardly been a pioneer for gay rights, bringing in "homosexual propaganda" legislation that bans the promotion of "non-traditional sexual relations" among children, but which effectively bans all gay rights campaign literature. Eurovision was the newest flashpoint after the Sochi Olympics, with petitions raised there as well as in Belarus and Ukraine demanding that Austria's entry, the bearded beauty Conchita Wurst, be banned from the contest or at least edited out of the broadcasts in their countries. Since Conchita won, a Russian MP has even called for an establishment of their own "straight" version of Eurovision, <ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/russia-must-leave-eurovision-immediately-following-conchita-wurst-victory--and-set-up-a-straight-equivalent-says-mp-9373940.html">but it seems that this would be conceptually and philosophically impossible</ref>. Despite the grandstanding, both Russia and Ukraine gave points to Austria in the contest, and there were plans for a bearded victory march, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/music/2014/may/16/eurovision-conchita-wurst-parade-russia-ban">before it was banned</ref>. So what we all want to know is: did Putin vote for her? Paxman could even throw down the gauntlet and challenge him to a beard-growing competition.</p>
<p>Of course, Paxman could also be set on leaders of Boko Haram in Nigeria; the Sudanese authorities, who are going to execute a pregnant woman for "adultery" and apostasy because she is married to a Christian: the Saudi royal family; or the Taliban, if only it were possible for them to be even slightly embarrassed by the rottweiler-in-chief.</p>
<p>At the very least, everyone will be watching these last few weeks of Jeremy's tenure at Newsnight for his <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rGIY5Vyj4Y">now-surely- inevitable Network moment</ref>.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>