<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2004-01-01" description="Italy's EU presidency will be remembered for Silvio Berlusconi's gaffes and the failure to draw up a constitution, writes Sophie Arie." fingerprint="3f02db2ab08fd286" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,European Union,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Jokes but no punchline" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jan/01/worlddispatch.italy">
<main>
<p>On July 1, Italy took the helm of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> amid high hopes that it could oversee the signing of a European constitution. That was meant to put Rome at the heart of Europe's history again, almost 50 years after the Treaty of Rome established the existence of a European Community. It didn't quite work out that way.</p>
<p>Six months and several memorable gaffes down the line, the draft constitution is in tatters and so, many feel, is Italy's reputation. At last month's summit in Brussels 25 members and future members failed to agree on a constitution in what Chris Patten, the European commissioner in charge of external affairs, described optimistically as "a fiasco but not a disaster".</p>
<p>But one man came out still smiling: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, Italy's prime minister, who yesterday completed his six-month stint as Europe's president. According to Mr Berlusconi, Italy's presidency was a "triumph". Its successes were just overshadowed by the much talked-about constitutional logjam.</p>
<p>Many will remember Mr Berlusconi's presidency, at a crucial and delicate time for the EU, above all as a series of unfortunate jokes.</p>
<p>The Italian presidency was characterised by Mr Berlusconi's disregard for political correctness. On his second day in the job, he compared a German MEP to a concentration camp guard. Months later he declared that Italy's fascist dictator Benito Mussolini, who sent thousands of Italian Jews to their deaths during the second world war, "never killed anyone". And last month, as European Union negotiations over a constitution were collapsing, the grinning president proposed that leaders should talk about other things, such as "women and football".</p>
<p>"I have behaviour ... that is not politically correct ... and I have no intention of changing," Mr Berlusconi explained amid the public outcry. He insisted he was just saying what other people thought.</p>
<p>The billionaire prime minister's provocative comments - always accompanied by a flashing smile - have created a perception that he is not a serious politician. Many Italians think his performance has severely dented the country's international reputation and there will be relief today as the presidency passes to the Irish and Italy fades out of the European limelight.</p>
<p>The past six months have served to acquaint the rest of the world with the day-to-day reality of Italian politics, and the European media have recorded their dismay at the Berlusconi government's habit of passing laws that work in the prime minister's personal favour. Only last week the cabinet passed an emergency decree to save one of the prime minister's private TV channels after a court ruled that it should transfer to satellite and thereby lose millions in advertising revenue.</p>
<p>Editorials this week in the Financial Times, Le Monde and the Economist excoriated the media tycoon turned politician.</p>
<p>Sergio Romano, writing in Corriere della Sera newspaper, acknowledged the serious allegations against Mr Berlusconi but said that the foreign press had made unfair accusations against the prime minister. Mr Berlusconi should not be blamed for the collapse of European constitution talks or the multibillion-euro hole in the accounts of the Italian milk giant Parmalat, Romano argued.</p>
<p>This stance could backfire, he added. "If you want to do Mr Berlusconi a favour, carry on down this path. You will guarantee him the support of what little nationalism there is left in our country."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>