<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2008-03-16" description="Berlusconi rides out the storm after his 'marry a millionaire' advice - but also recruits a fascist" fingerprint="b9224b6f1a03e74b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="King of the gaffe charms Italy again" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/mar/16/italy">
<main>
<p>When <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> told an attractive young voter questioning his economic policies that the way to deal with poverty was to marry a millionaire, it sparked outrage in Italy. But now the woman at the centre of the storm has said she was so impressed by the flirtatious former Prime Minister that she will vote for him in April's general election.</p>
<p>It is a typical incident in the colourful world of Berlusconi, whose ability to both flirt and put his foot in it livened up Italian politics when he was the country's leader. And now he is back on the campaign trail ahead of the elections on 13 April - a gaffe-prone 71-year-old with the hide of a dinosaur already in trouble for putting a fascist on his list of candidates, while supporters laud his charm.</p>
<p>In was on a TV news show last Thursday when a member of the audience, Perla Pavoncello, 24, asked the media mogul how she was supposed to start a family or get a mortgage without a job, only to be told: 'You should look to marry a millionaire, like my son, or someone who doesn't have such problems.' He then added: 'With that smile of yours, you could even get away with it.'</p>
<p>After a dull start, it was perhaps inevitable that the race between centre-left leader Walter Veltroni and Berlusconi required something outrageous from the two-time PM to get things started.</p>
<p>The episode recalled Berlusconi's advice to New York investors to move to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> because secretaries were prettier and his claims that he used his playboy charms to come out on top in talks with Finnish Prime Minister Tarja Halonen.</p>
<p>Opposition politicians slammed Berlusconi as Italy's answer to Marie Antoinette and forms quickly appeared on the internet to fill in and send off to Berlusconi's eldest son asking for his hand in marriage. Piersilvio Berlusconi, 38, declined to say if he was open to offers. A less flamboyant type than his father, he recently advised Silvio to stop being photographed so often with young women.</p>
<p>But instead of storming out of the studio, Pavoncello said she was 'neither offended of humiliated, but amused', by Berlusconi's career advice, adding she would vote for him next month. By Friday, she was even being approached to stand as a candidate for Berlusconi in local elections in Rome.</p>
<p>With the soft spoken Veltroni circling the country in his election bus seeking to make up a gap of around seven points in the polls, Berlusconi has been energetically working crowds in piazzas around the country dressed in an open-neck dark shirt and his trademark double breasted jacket, seeking to prove that he has rebounded from heart surgery.</p>
<p>After a public rebuke last year from his wife for flirting with showgirls, in which she claimed her 'dignity' had been undermined and that her husband's behaviour was 'unacceptable', Berlusconi appeared to suggest all was well at home, describing her in an interview last week as, 'intelligent, beautiful and indulgent', and adding that she was standing firmly behind his bid for office.</p>
<p>But critics looking for cracks in his armour pounced on Berlusconi's recruiting of Giuseppe Ciarrapico as a candidate, a lifelong fascist who hangs portraits of Mussolini in the newsrooms of the local newspapers he owns. In an unexpected bout of plain speaking, Berlusconi confessed that Ciarrapico was only useful to him for his newspapers, a surprising statement from a man who has long denied using his own newspapers and TV stations for electoral gain.</p>
<p>Suddenly pushed on to the defensive, Berlusconi's promises to conduct a balanced 'British-style' campaign appeared forgotten as he urged his candidates to liken Veltroni to Stalin on the campaign trail and called his opponent a Barack Obama wannabe.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>