<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Gina McCauley" categories="Opinion" date="2009-09-29" description="Gina McCauley: Silvio Berlusconi isn't the first to comment on Michelle Obama's skin: there's a branch of the media dedicated to ogling her" fingerprint="a62ed17f03f7032f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Michelle Obama,Silvio Berlusconi,Race,Beauty,Fashion,Women,US news,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Hands off Michelle Obama | Gina McCauley" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/cifamerica/2009/sep/29/michelle-obama-silvio-berlusconi-tan">
<main>
<p>I join the ranks irritated with Silvio Berlusconi for referring to Michelle Obama as "<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/28/obama-tan-berlusconi">suntanned</ref>" at a rally on Sunday – but for a different reason. I'm irritated because the Italian prime minister's gaffe will undoubtedly trigger another round of the media's public vivisection of Michelle Obama. Its hard to muster outrage at Berlusconi when there is an entire cottage industry of news organisations paying good money to talk about the first lady's body.</p>
<p>Salon commissioned an article about Michelle Obama's rear end called "<ref target="http://www.salon.com/mwt/feature/2008/11/18/michelles_booty/">First lady got back: an appreciation of Michelle Obama's beauty and booty</ref>". Time magazine recently joined the never-ending parade of articles about Obama's hair with "<ref target="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1919147,00.html?iid=tsmodule">Why Michelle Obama's hair matters</ref>". Did we really need 1,200 more words about her hair after hundreds of trees had already sacrificed their lives so that someone else could <ref target="http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2008-10-09/the-politics-of-michelle-obamas-hair/">compare Obama's hair to Scylla and Charybdis</ref>? I mean how can you top hair which symbolises monsters from Greek mythology? I'm not saying her hair doesn't matter. But is it all that matters?</p>
<p>Berlusconi also isn't the first to publicly comment on the first lady's skin tone – or the second or the third for that matter. The Washington Post's fashion critic Robin Givhan referred to the first lady's style as "<ref target="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/05/16/AR2008051601068.html">Camelot with a tan</ref>". Not to be left out, the Post's sister publication TheRoot.com commissioned an article called "<ref target="http://www.theroot.com/views/dark-and-lovely-michelle">Dark and lovely</ref>", in which the author, Vanessa Williams, called having dark skin "revolutionary" and declared that she would not apologise for objectifying Michelle Obama. Apparently, Williams felt the objectification was her due after a life-long battle with the beauty industry. Not to be outdone, Dayo Olopade produced <ref target="http://www.theroot.com/views/armed-and-not-dangerous">a dissertation on Michelle Obama's arms</ref>.</p>
<p>These articles all read the same: first-hand accounts that focus on the various appearance-obsessed neuroses visited upon black women that all require a public discussion of the first lady's body parts – something they would all rise up to condemn if a non-black person deigned to dissect our bodies in the same public manner (as Berlusconi did). Which raises the question: Are we creating a new <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/michelleobama">Michelle Obama</ref> body part sub-genre where black women writers are condemned to dwell for all eternity?</p>
<p>After all, there's lots we could write about the first lady. I'd be curious to know which of the crops in the White House garden failed to grow this spring, because my own indoor garden, which I planted at the same time as Obama, has died twice during the same period of time. I'd like to know what little girls around the world thought about watching Sasha and Malia travel the world with their parents this summer. I'd be curious to know how many children who attend school in our nation's capital have had a chance to be hugged by the first lady. In her first year in the White House, she's been on a breakneck pace visiting schools, soup kitchens and aquatic gardens in her new, adopted home town, hugging everyone in her path.</p>
<p>Instead, we'll get more articles about skin, arms and hair. Did I mention <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/sep/18/straighten-afro-tyra-banks">hair</ref>?</p>
<p>What next – a discussion of Michelle Obama's earlobes or perhaps her internal organs? Too late. We already discussed her uterus when we went through the <ref target="http://gawker.com/5141591/is-michelle-obama-pregnant">Michelle Obama pregnancy obsession</ref> at the beginning of the year. Clearly that speculation was inaccurate – otherwise these writers would be obsessing over the impending arrival of another baby Obama. At least <hi rend="#i">that</hi> would be a change of pace.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>