<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Martin Kettle" categories="Opinion" date="2006-03-15" description="Martin Kettle: Silvio Berlusconi is so unpopular in Britain that you might assume that a Labour government would be rooting for the centre-left to unseat him in Italy's general election. Blair doesn't see it that way." fingerprint="271dc0629aa05d0a" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Tony Blair,European Union,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="The professor or the knight?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/mar/15/theprofessorortheknight">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi is so unpopular in Britain that you might, even now, be forgiven for assuming that a Labour government would be rooting for the revived centre-left to unseat him in Italy's April 9 general election. After all, there are so few centre-left governments in power in Europe these days that you might assume Tony Blair would welcome an ally.</p>
<p>Blair, though, doesn't see it that way, and nor does Gordon Brown. In spite of all the aggravation that the Berlusconi connection continues to bring him at home, Blair would still rather see a right-wing populist government in power in Rome than the centre-left alternative under Romano Prodi. Why should this be?</p>
<p>Mainly because, in spite of everything else, Berlusconi is an ally of London over <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> market reform and can be relied on not to sign up to any federalist resuscitation of the EU constitution. The last thing that any British government wants is for Prodi, an ex president of the EU commission, to start reviving the European project.</p>
<p>So strong are these fears that Blair does not seem to have noticed how much more moderate and "New Labour" Prodi's programme has actually become this time. The left is still in the lead in the polls in Italy, and last night's first head-to-head TV debate between the "professor" (as Prodi is referred to in the Italian media) and the "knight" (Berlusconi) went Prodi's way, according to <ref target="http://www.corriere.it/Primo_Piano/Politica/2006/03_Marzo/14/sondaggioswg.shtml">initial surveys</ref>.</p>
<p>If Prodi knocks Berlusconi out of office in three weeks time, the whole European centre-left will be celebrating. But there will be no cheers in Downing Street.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>