<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Ian Black; Sophie Arie" categories="Politics" date="2004-03-05" description="Tony Blair flew to Rome for lunch with his Italian counterpart Silvio Berlusconi yesterday on an apparent bridge-building mission." fingerprint="6b6bd22db2835e09" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,UK news,European Union,Foreign policy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Blair and Berlusconi kiss and make up" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2004/mar/05/uk.eu">
<main>
<p>Tony Blair flew to Rome for lunch with his Italian counterpart <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> yesterday on an apparent bridge-building mission after Italy showed its discontent at being sidelined from last month's summit between France, Germany and Britain.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi had described the Berlin summit as "a mess" and said he and other EU countries saw it as attempt by the "big three" to dictate policy.</p>
<p>In their first meeting since then, Mr Berlusconi greeted Mr Blair in Rome's Palazzo Chigi with three warm kisses. After lunch, Mr Blair repeatedly described relations between the two countries as "strong".</p>
<p>Officials confirmed that Mr Blair had brought a bottle of whisky and a Scottish tie as gifts for Mr Berlusconi; the Italian press speculated that Mr Berlusconi would offer his new CD of love songs to Mr Blair in return.</p>
<p>The visit came as Denis MacShane, the Europe minister, lashed out at rightwing politicians for playing "cheap games" over the choice of a new president for the European commission.</p>
<p>He flatly rejected suggestions that left-of-centre candidates could not succeed Romano Prodi in Brussels if, as expected, the European parliament was dominated by the right after elections in June.</p>
<p>The right tends to favour candidates such as the Austrian chancellor, Wolfgang Schüssel, and the veteran prime minister of Luxembourg, Jean-Claude Junker. Tony Blair is thought to favour the highly-regarded Portuguese social democrat, Antonio Vitorino.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>