<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2019-10-28" description="Donatella Tesei, backed by Matteo Salvini’s League and Silvio Berlusconi, appears set to win in centre-left Italian stronghold" fingerprint="f32525d7a93153cb" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,Matteo Salvini,Silvio Berlusconi,The League,Brothers of Italy" title="Umbria election exit poll points to win for Salvini and Italy's right" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/28/umbria-election-salvini-and-italy-rightwing-berlusconi-donatella-tesei">
<main>
<p>Matteo Salvini’s political fortunes have been given a boost after an exit poll by Italy’s state broadcaster pointed to a win for a rightwing coalition backed by his League party in a regional election in Umbria.</p>
<p>Donatella Tesei, backed by the League, the far-right <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/brothers-of-italy">Brothers of Italy</ref> and former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi’s Forza Italia, will be elected governor with 56.5% to 60.5% of the vote, according to an exit poll for state broadcaster RAI.</p>
<p>The vote in the traditional centre-left stronghold, which has a population of less than 900,000, restores impetus to Salvini after his political blunder that saw the League lose power nationally this summer.</p>
<p>The hard-right leader walked out of government with the anti-establishment 5-Star Movement in August, expecting to trigger a national election that polls predicted he would win. Instead, 5-Star struck a deal with the centre-left Democratic party (PD), shunting Salvini into opposition.</p>
<p>However the initial indications from Umbria suggest the new 5-Star/PD alliance has failed its first electoral test.</p>
<p>The exit poll suggested Vincenzo Bianconi, leader of a civic alliance backed by 5-Star and the PD, would get 35.5% to 39.5%, while Claudio Ricci, a rightwing independent candidate, is seen at 1.5% to 4.5%.</p>
<p>The League chief had criss-crossed landlocked Umbria for weeks, promoting his national pledge to introduce a flat-tax rate many economists say Italy cannot afford, but which the League insists is needed to revive the sluggish economy.</p>
<p>His message found fertile ground in Umbria, where output slumped 15% in the decade after the 2007 financial crisis, compared with a 5% slide across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, according to Bank of Italy data.</p>
<p>Umbria marks the eighth straight victory for the centre-right in regional ballots since the last national election, in March 2018.</p>
<p>More important tests lie ahead that could potentially undermine the new national government.</p>
<p>In December, the poor southern region of Calabria goes to the polls and it will be the turn on 26 January of Emilia Romagna, a northern region with more than four times the population of Umbria and which is the historic heartland of Italy’s left.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show the League, with its anti-migrant, anti-tax message, has shed little support since it lost power nationally and remains easily Italy’s most popular party, with around 30% of the vote.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>