<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Stuart Heritage" categories="Opinion" date="2018-03-12" description="The Obamas are in talks to produce a high-profile series, but what would their peers come up with? Silvio’s First Dates, Putin’s King of the Woods – the possibilities are endless, says Guardian columnist Stuart Heritage" fingerprint="67fb807f8522d4ad" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Barack Obama,US news,Michelle Obama,Netflix,Media,Television,Culture,Television &amp; radio,Internet,Technology,Donald Trump,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Kim Jong-un,Vladimir Putin,Justin Trudeau,David Cameron,Politics" title="What if other world leaders followed the Obamas into TV? Just imagine … | Stuart Heritage" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/mar/12/world-leaders-obamas-tv-sivio-putin">
<main>
<p>As yet, nobody knows what Barack and Michelle Obama’s new Netflix shows will look like – they are reported to be in advanced <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2018/mar/09/barack-michelle-obama-in-talks-with-netflix-tv-series">talks to make programmes with the streaming service</ref>. While the smart money is on the Obamas highlighting inspirational stories from around the world, it might also end up as an interview show, or a dramatised memoir, or a full-volume down-the-barrel <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2018/feb/28/florida-shooting-conspiracy-theories-youtube-takedown">Infowars screech</ref>. Either way, to give a former world leader and first lady a platform like this is unprecedented.</p>
<p>And where the Obamas lead, others will follow. If any current or former world leaders are interested in joining the bandwagon, I have some ideas.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Donald Trump</hi>
</head>
<p><lb/> Given his CV, it only seems right that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump">Donald Trump</ref> should host another gameshow when he leaves office. And, given the state of things at the moment, it only seems right that he should host it from prison. In his show What’s In My Pillowcase?, Trump would stroll around the canteen of a low-security blue collar facility asking other inmates what he had stored in his pillowcase. Is it a ham? Is it a shoe? Is it a mouse? Guess right and contestants can win a full dump on Trump’s golden toilet. Guess wrong and it’s a quick shivving in the showers. Small hint: don’t guess that it’s a letter of support from Melania. It is never a letter of support from Melania.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Kim Jong-un</hi>
</head>
<p><lb/> Mythbusters is no longer the ratings juggernaut it once was, but arguably that’s only because it isn’t hosted by an unhinged hereditary dictator with designs on a global nuclear stranglehold. Let’s Find Out starring <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/kim-jong-un">Kim Jong-un</ref> would remedy this. Each week he’d try to solve a different pop-science query, such as “How many fingernails can you remove before an intellectual pleads for clemency?” and “What would happen to Seoul if hundreds of thousands of enemy troops suddenly appeared from a network of secret tunnels?” It’d be fun and educational, as well as genuinely terrifying.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">David Cameron</hi>
</head>
<p><lb/> Live from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/may/25/chipping-norton-set-cotswold-town-tv-review-community-spirit-complaints">Chipping Norton</ref> is a fun-filled entertainment series, filmed in the grounds surrounding David Cameron’s expensive shed. Imagine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TFI_Friday">TFI Friday</ref> if the only guest ever to appear was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2018/mar/09/jeremy-clarkson-hosting-who-wants-to-be-a-millionaire-ill-have-to-phone-a-friend">Jeremy Clarkson</ref>, the only musical guest was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/lostinshowbiz/2012/feb/16/alex-james-memoir-cheese">Alex James</ref> doing a long bass solo and the only words spoken by the host were a distant, regretful “I’m so sorry about Brexit,” repeated over and over again through a veil of tears and a cloud of cigarette smoke. That’d be Live from Chipping Norton.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>
</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">The former Italian prime minister</ref> is looking for love. Despite his fame – and despite already having a wife – all he wants is a little bit of companionship for the night. Silvio’s First Dates will address this. In a deserted, menacingly lit restaurant, Berlusconi will sit down with a succession of hand-picked women and try to woo them. Legally iffy and ethically reprehensible, Silvio’s First Dates will pretend that #MeToo never happened while asking the eternal question “Can a woman ever love an <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jul/08/silvio-berlusconi-sentenced-to-3-years-for-bribing-italian-senator">octogenarian criminal</ref> with a head like Jim Carrey from The Mask carved out of pickled conkers?”</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Vladimir Putin</hi>
</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/bear-grylls">Bear Grylls</ref>, watch your back. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/vladimir-putin">Vladimir Putin</ref> is here with a new outdoors-skills programme called King of the Woods, where he demonstrates all the skills the average person will need to survive in the Russian wilderness for a meaningful length of time. Want to carve a chair from a tree? Putin will show you. Want to punch a bear dead and use its carcass as a sleeping bag? Putin will show you. Want to poison a rival so that the rest of the world instantly becomes terrified of you anew? Guess what, Putin will show you.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Justin Trudeau</hi>
</head>
<p><lb/> This untitled programme doesn’t have a format or a structure. It’s just a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/tvandradioblog/2013/oct/04/slow-tv-norwegian-movement-nrk">slow TV-inspired</ref> close-up of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/justin-trudeau">Justin Trudeau’s</ref> face in a comfortingly black void, whispering words and phrases deliberately chosen to whip viewers into a state of glee. “Let me explain intersectional feminism,” he’ll coo. Or: “I’m about to rank every episode of Buffy the Vampire Slayer from worst to best.” Or: “Oops, I just nationalised all public services again.” Whatever you do, don’t watch this for too long. You’ll get lost in his eyes and then throw yourself off a building.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>