<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2010-02-25" description="Anna Masera: The Google ruling is a blow to the fundamental principle of freedom of expression upon which the internet was built" fingerprint="39be904ab3b4be45" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Censorship,Internet,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Google,Technology,Digital media,Facebook,Media,Privacy,Social media,Europe" title="Italy has taken a step closer to China | Anna Masera" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2010/feb/25/google-italy-internet-censorship">
<main>
<p>After an Italian court yesterday <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2010/feb/24/google-video-italy-privacy-convictions">convicted three Google executives</ref> for not censoring content on the web, Italy is closer to China than it might like. A court in Milan found the executives guilty of a violation of privacy in a case that involved an online video showing an autistic boy being bullied by classmates in Turin, posted in 2006 on Google Video (before Google acquired YouTube). This is a blow to the fundamental principle of freedom of expression upon which the internet was conceived. The whole world's eyes are on Italy: is it like China?</p>
<p>European law protects internet providers from responsibility if they remove illicit content as soon as they are informed of its existence – which is what Google did. This mechanism has thus far been successful in protecting the privacy of individuals while allowing creativity and freedom of expression to flourish online. If this principle is removed, and websites like YouTube or <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/facebook">Facebook</ref> are considered responsible for controlling each piece of content loaded on their platforms, the web as we know it will cease to exist and many of the economic, social, political and technological benefits connected to it might disappear.</p>
<p>Expecting <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/google">Google</ref> to adopt a censorship system that automatically filters videos published online is like expecting highways companies to be incriminated for lack of traffic control at the toll booth. Of course Google should adopt the best possible technology to avoid abuses. But if someone is to control driving licences, that someone should be the police, not the highway owner. And it's about time that authorities took into account the technological problems arising from certain measures.</p>
<p>Just two days ago the Italian media and politicians were debating on how to censor Facebook on similar grounds. In Italy, Google and Facebook are almost synonymous with the internet, so is Italy's anti-internet battle due to the fact that it is a free communication network, an alternative to Silvio Berlusconi's television empire? The question of a political conflict of interest for Italy's prime minister is in the back of the minds of foreign correspondents, but was quickly dismissed by the Oxford philosophy professor, Luciano Floridi, who holds a Unesco chair in information and computer ethics. "I don't believe in a concerted plot. But one thousand snow flakes can create a storm," he said</p>
<p>The Italian judge's decision arrives after many legal proposals to censor the web, and contributes to an illiberal and demagogical atmosphere that also influences the competitiveness of Italy in the global market: Italy is placed 78th in the World Bank Group ranking for ease of conducting business. Among European countries, only Greece, Albania and Croatia lag behind. Even if only for the reason that Italy is losing touch with the business community of the western world, today Italy is a little bit more Chinese.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>