<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Larry Elliott" categories="Global development" date="2011-05-16" description="Development charity One calls on G8 summit host President Sarkozy to deliver on promises made by his country at Gleneagles in 2005" fingerprint="7a4a43fcab96d3a1" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Aid,Society,France,Europe,World news,Germany,Italy,G8,Nicolas Sarkozy,Silvio Berlusconi,Global development" title="France 'failing to meet overseas aid target'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2011/may/16/france-failing-overseas-aid">
<main>
<p>The anti-poverty group set up by Bono and Bob Geldof on Monday put pressure on France to improve its aid record to Africa, when they said that backsliding by the hosts at next week's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/30/nicolas-sarkozy-g8-presidency-ratings-france">G8 meeting in Deauville </ref>had helped deprive the world's poorest countries of $7bn (£4.3bn) in aid.</p>
<p>In its annual analysis of progress towards meeting the promises made by the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> at the 2005 Gleneagles summit, the development charity One said that rich countries had delivered 61% of the extra financial assistance pledged to sub-Saharan Africa six years ago.</p>
<p>It praised the UK for making progress towards hitting its ambitious aid target and said that the US, Canada and Japan had delivered on relatively modest targets.</p>
<p>But it said that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref>, France and Italy had reneged on their pledges and were responsible for the $7bn shortfall.</p>
<p>Jamie Drummond, One's executive director, said: "Unfortunately it comes as no surprise that Prime Minister [Silvio] Berlusconi has yet again abjectly failed to deliver on his promises – and we continue to call for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to be at least temporarily removed from the G8 for this reason.</p>
<p>"But it is worrying that President Sarkozy and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref> are so far behind in a year when so much is expected of them as hosts of the G8 and G20, and at a time when African development, peace and democracy is at the top of the agenda."</p>
<p>At the Gleneagles summit, rich nations said that by 2010 they would increase development assistance by $50bn, with an extra $25bn going to sub-Saharan Africa. One said that France had so far provided only 44% of the money promised to sub-Saharan Africa, and raised suspicions that President Sarkozy's support for the so-called Robin Hood tax on financial transactions was a smokescreen.</p>
<p>"We welcome the momentum on innovative finance," Drummond said, "even though there are some questions over whether President Sarkozy's new focus on this area is in part an attempt to divert attention away from France's failure to meet its fair share of Europe's aid targets. That is why we are calling for real and measurable progress to be made before the end of 2011."</p>
<p>He added that it was hugely disappointing that Germany – which last week posted quarterly growth of 1.5% for the first three months of 2011 – had performed so badly on its development promises.</p>
<p>Calling on France, Germany and Italy to set out clear timetables to meet the promise made at Gleneagles to give 0.7% of their national incomes as overseas aid by 2015, he said: "At the same time, non-European G8 countries like the US, Canada and Japan should set new, ambitious commitments for aid to sub-Saharan Africa."</p>
<p>One said that the UK had provided 86% of the increased aid it had pledged to sub-Saharan Africa, with a jump of $1bn to $5.1bn during Gordon Brown's last year in office. "The UK has continued to provide global leadership of development issues during the last five years, most notably by maintaining its commitments to increase development assistance despite recent budgetary challenges."</p>
<p>The coalition government has ring-fenced the aid budget and promised to keep to Labour's target of 0.7% of national income by 2013. One said that to achieve this on current projections, development assistance would have to jump by £3bn in 2013 after being held at current levels for the next two years.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>