<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Graeme Wearden; Nick Fletcher; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Business" date="2013-02-26" description="Stock markets across Europe have fallen sharply after Italy’s general election leaves no party with control of the Senate" fingerprint="37ac00b791328d44" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Italy,Euro,Europe,World news,Mario Monti,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Eurozone crisis as it happened: Italian political deadlock sends markets tumbling" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/feb/26/eurozone-crisis-italian-election-deadlock-markets">
<main>
<p>European markets have closed for the evening, and after the day's bloodbath investors must be quite relieved. The uncertainty created by the Italian election result has sent them scurrying for the hills, as the eurozone crisis rises from the dead.</p>
<p>The FTSE 100 has finished down 84.93 points or 1.34% at 6270.44</p>
<p>Germany's Dax is down 2.27%</p>
<p>France's Cac has closed 2.67% lower</p>
<p>Italy's FTSE MIB has ended a volatile day 4.89% lower, its biggest daily fall for nearly a year</p>
<p>Spain's Ibex is off 3.2% on renewed contagion worries</p>
<p>In Athens the market is down 0.38%</p>
<p>But in the US the Dow Jones Industrial Average is currently 0.7% higher after Federal Reserve boss Ben Bernanke was dovish about the prospects of continuing bond buying to stimulate the world's largest economy.</p>
<p>Back with Italy, and the country's borrowing costs have climbed sharply, with 10 year yields rising from 4.37% last night to 4.91%. The two year is up 47 basis points to 2.17%.</p>
<p>The euro has fallen 0.1% against the dollar to $1.308 but rose 0.2% against the pound to 86.2p.</p>
<p>And with that, it's time to shut up shop for the evening. Thanks for all the comments, and we'll be back tomorrow for all the fallout from this latest develpement in the eurozone crisis.</p>
<p>And here's another scathing little quote about the Italian election.</p>
<p>Initially attributed to Dutch prime minister Mark Rutte, it was said by Hans van Baalen, leader of VVD party in the European Parliament ( Rutte’s party):</p>
<p>Italians must elect who they want to elect and must bear the consequences when they elect clowns.</p>
<p>Could Italy's centre left leader Pier Luigi Bersani form an alliance with the anti-establishment Beppo Grillo? Open Europe has punted the idea following Bersani's press conference:</p>
<p>[Bersani] said that, if asked to form the new government, he will put forward a "programme" - basically a to-do list for the next government, including changes to the electoral law, cuts to the cost of bureaucracy and politics in general and new policies for job creation to be discussed at the European level (whatever that means).</p>
<p>His line was that it's more important to "discuss what we want to do for this country" rather than wasting time in "diplomatic" exercises in an attempt to form a traditional coalition.</p>
<p>And that sounds very similar to what Grillo said earlier today, i.e. taking a policy-by-policy approach rather than going for a fixed coalition (in contrast to Berlusconi). So, could there be some sort of loose Bersani-Grillo alliance emerging?</p>
<p>EC president Barroso warns of giving in to populism</p>
<p>European Commission president Jose Manuel Barroso seems to be taking a swing at democracy, or "populism" as he called it.</p>
<p>Speaking at a Reuters summit he said - in the wake of Italian voters rejecting Mario Monti's austerity programme:</p>
<p>I hope we are not going to follow the temptation to give in to populism because of the results in one specific member state.</p>
<p>The question we have to ask ourselves is the following: should we determine our policy, our economic policy, by short-term electoral considerations or by what has to be done to put Europe back on the path to sustainable growth? For me the answer is clear.</p>
<p>Barroso said that just because Monti had been turfed out of office, it did not mean his policies were wrong. Clearly Barroso is not trying to be "populist".</p>
<p>Bersani says must react with humility to election result</p>
<p>Pier Luigi Bersani, head of Italy's centre left Democratic Party, has said the eurozone crisis and austerity policies were behind the election results.</p>
<p>He said: "We did not win, even though we came first," and added that they must react with humility to the the outcome of the election. "Our first responsibility to the country is to represent change, more so than in the election campaign," he said.</p>
<p>(Bersani had been accused of approaching the campaign too cautiously.)</p>
<p>He said the party would propose basic reforms for the political system, and support for those suffering in the crisis. But they could not get away from the gravity of the situation and the risks to the country.</p>
<p>As the largest coalition it should be allowed to have the first attempt at forming a government. He said he would appeal to parliament, and it was up to Silvio Berlusconi and Beppo Grillo to assume their responsibilities.</p>
<p>Asked if he would resign after the election result, he did not reply directly but said he would not abandon ship.</p>
<p>Grillo says any new Italian government will not last six months</p>
<p>The anti-establishment Five Star movement of comic Beppo Grillo, whose success in the Italian election has torpedoed the more mainstream parties, has helped bring about the current stalemate.</p>
<p>And Grillo reckons any attempts by the other parties to form a government are doomed to fail. According to Reuters, Grillo believes it would not last six months:</p>
<p>They won't be able to govern. Whether I'm there or not they won't be able to govern.</p>
<p>He said he would work with anyone who supported his policies but rejected entering a formal coalition:</p>
<p>It's not time to talk of alliances... the system has already fallen.</p>
<p>Beppe Grillo arriving at a polling station in Genoa on Monday. Photograph: EPA/Riccardo Arata Photograph: Riccardo Arata/EPA</p>
<p>It wasn't all bad news for Italy's technocrat prime minister Mario Monti, whose poor performance in the election is a bit of an embarrassment and a slapdown of his austerity reforms. It appears he didn't fail everywhere:</p>
<p>Monti can claim one victory in Italian elections - he came top among Italian expats living in Germany with 30.6% elezioni.interno.it/senato/scrutin…</p>
<p>Fed chairman Bernanke defends bond buying programme</p>
<p>US Federal Reserve chairman Ben Bernanke has strongly defended the central bank's bond buying programme in testimony to the Senate.</p>
<p>He said the benefits of the stimulus outweighed the possible costs. He said the Fed was aware of the public losing confidence it its ability to unwind its programme smoothly or the possible destabilising effects of low interest rates. But he said these risks did not seem material at the moment. He said:</p>
<p>To this point, we do not see the potential costs of the increased risk-taking in some financial markets as outweighing the benefits of promoting a stronger economic recovery and more rapid job creation.</p>
<p>But he urged politicians to avoid the spending cuts due to come into force at the end of the week, which he warned could combine with earlier tax rises to create a "significant headwind" for the economic recovery.</p>
<p>Markets have greeted his dovish tone on the quantitative easing programme positively, concluding it means the prospect of further easing.</p>
<p>The testimony followed some positive data, with positive new homes sales, growing consumer confidence and an unexpected jump in the Richmond Fed manufacturing survey.</p>
<p>US markets, which fell sharply on Monday after the impasse in Italy became clearer, are recovering ahead of a testimony before the Senate by Federal Reserve chairman Ben Bernanke.</p>
<p>The Dow Jones Industrial Average is up almost 100 points in early trading, but this has done little to help European markets, which are still firmly in the red.</p>
<p>The FTSE 100 is down 1.11% or 70.52 points</p>
<p>Italy's FTSE MIB is 3.84% lower</p>
<p>Germany's Dax is down 1.41% and France's Cac 1.63%</p>
<p>While Italy struggles to elect a government the Irish Coalition seems to be on the verge of saving €300m of its public pay bill as the Republic continues to be the 'poster child' for the EU, writes Henry McDonald in Dublin.</p>
<p>Agreement on a national wages and pension agreement in the public sector still hinges on unions accepting the deal. They are balloting their members over the weekend.</p>
<p>But the politician heading up the negotiations, the Labour Minister Brendan Howlin promised today that this will be the "last ask" from the government to the unions in terms of accepting austerity measures.</p>
<p>Speaking outside Government Buildings in central Dublin today, Howlin directly appealed to the unions to endorse the agreement: "I have said to public servants that this is the last ask. If you consider this, swallow hard as I know it's not easy and vote for this, we will not be coming back again and we can plan our recovery over the next three years."</p>
<p>Cuts to wages include a ten per cent reduction for any civil servant earning €185,000 or more. To demonstrate solidarity with public servants, the Cabinet are also taking pay cuts.</p>
<p>Taoiseach Enda Kenny will see his €200,000 salary reduced to €185,350, while Irish Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister Eamon Gilmore will see his €184,405 salary drop to €171,308.</p>
<p>Eurogroup head Dijsselbloem calls for Italy to stick to agreements</p>
<p>Jeroen Dijsselbloem, the Dutch finance minister and new head of the eurogroup, has added his voice to those calling for Italy to stick to its agreements with the rest of the eurozone. He told Dutch broadcaster RTL7:</p>
<p>I think and I hope there is a broad understanding that there is also a responsibility for the stability of the eurozone as a whole, and that agreements have to be met.</p>
<p>Pulling Europe from the economic doldrums requires a stable, political policy, also in Italy.</p>
<p>With the current political crisis in Italy, there are also disagreements elsewhere about the way forward.</p>
<p>In Portugal for instance, prime minister Passos Coelho has been playing down concerns about its bailout, as its creditors start another review. As reported by Reuters, he said:</p>
<p>We do not want more time under the adjustment programme, neither more time, nor more money. We intend to conclude the bailout programme by mid-2014 with the same financial package that has been envisaged.</p>
<p>But the leader of the main opposition party has said the package should be renegotiated. Socialist head Antonio Jose Seguro said:</p>
<p>We need more time and a delay of interest payments. There cannot be more austerity, there has to be a strategy of growth. I hope the government refuses proposals (by the troika of lenders) for more austerity.</p>
<p>Seguro also said the election result in Italy was "very worrying".</p>
<p>Open Europe, the thinktank, outlines the potential scenarios for Italy:</p>
<p>A national unity government, if Bersani, Berlusconi and Monti join forces – could be possible but may not be enough to avoid snap elections (maybe as early as next year, and after the electoral law is changed);</p>
<p>Grillo U-turns and agrees to form a coalition with Bersani’s centre-left alliance;</p>
<p>A re-run election (presumably within 3-4 months) (with a caretaker government taking temporary control).</p>
<p>But without a change to Italy's convoluted system of proportional representation, a new election might not help!</p>
<p>Under scenarios 1 and 3, there will be a lot of pressure to change the electoral law before new elections to avoid a similar stalemate. For that, however, there needs to be a majority in both houses, meaning that we’re looking at a potential Catch-22.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, of course, has already said he wouldn't want fresh elections - and other parties also appear opposed.</p>
<p>Here's the likely timescale:</p>
<p>15 March: First sitting of the Italian parliament (both chambers).</p>
<p>By 20 March: The speakers of both chambers should have been elected. After 20 March: Italian President Giorgio Napolitano starts official consultations on the formation of the new government.</p>
<p>However, there's another problem - Napolitano no longer has the power to dissolve parliament, because he is in the last six months of his mandate (his term finishes in May).</p>
<p>So if a new vote is needed, there could be months of paralysis while MPs elects a new president, so that parliament could be dissolved.</p>
<p>Pier Luigi Bersani, the centre-left leader who won control of the Italian lower house but not the Senate, is due to give a press conference in around three hours time (4pm GMT / 5pm CET)</p>
<p>Bersani press conference at 5pm. Rumours already flying round right, left and centre. #Italy</p>
<p>The European commission also warned that Italy must address its huge debt pile, in its first public comment on the election results.</p>
<p>Olivier Bailly, EC spokesman, told a regular press briefing in Brussels that Italy needs a government that will push for stronger economic growth and job creation.</p>
<p>Asked about today's tumbling stock markets, Bailly said:</p>
<p>Markets are free to react the way they want. As far as the Commission is concerned, we would like to underline our full confidence in the Italian authorities in their capacity to find and establish a political majority that will continue to deliver a growth and jobs agenda, which is what Italy needs to reduce the unsustainable level of its debt.</p>
<p>At around €2 trillion, Italy's public debt is expected to hit 128% of national output during 2013. But its annual deficit is relatively low, and could fall below 3% of GDP this year.</p>
<p>Bailly also insisted that the EC had heard the voice of Italians, and indicated some frustration with the way the election was fought (Bersani, in particular, approached the campaign rather cautiously)</p>
<p>European Commission says it's "heard the message of concern" by the Italian people #euro#Italy</p>
<p>Italy's financial regulator has responded to the heavy falls on the Milan stock market by banning people from short-selling shares in the country's biggest bank - Intesa San Paolo.</p>
<p>Intesa San Paolo's shares have already shed 10% in a volatile sell-off this morning.</p>
<p>Short-selling bans, which prevent speculators selling shares they don't own - are often rolled out at times of crisis. They won't stop investors selling out, though, and traders in Italy aren't impressed:</p>
<p>Europe's financial markets are still in retreat today, led by Italy where there's been little relief from its rout.</p>
<p>Spain's stock market has also seen a rush of sellers - reflecting concern that an escalating eurozone crisis could swamp Madrid's efforts to avoid a bailout.</p>
<p>Here's a round-up of the latest major indices:</p>
<p>Italy's FTSE MIB: down 745 points at 15606, -4.5%</p>
<p>FTSE 100: down 81 points at 6273. -1.29%</p>
<p>German DAX: down 149 points at 7623, - 1.9%</p>
<p>French CAC: down 85 points at 3636, - 2.29%</p>
<p>Spanish IBEX: down 227 points at 8017, -2.75%</p>
<p>Italian borrowing costs also remain sharply higher, after nervy bond traders drove down its bonds. 10-year Italian bonds are changing hands at a yield of 4.78% -- around 0.4 percentage points higher today.</p>
<p>Higher yields indicate that Italy is a riskier bet – a safe call, frankly. but something of a worry given tomorrow's big bond sale.</p>
<p>Robert O’Daly, Italy analyst at the Economist Intelligence Unit (EIU), comments:</p>
<p>With Italy looking ungovernable, the financial markets are responding as expected.</p>
<p>The Frankfurt stock exchange this morning. Photograph: Stringer/Germany/Reuters Photograph: STRINGER/GERMANY/REUTERS</p>
<p>Germany's foreign minister, Guido Westerwelle, has now weighed in, becoming the third German politician to argue that Italy must stick with Monti's reform plan.</p>
<p>Speaking in Berlin, Westerwelle said it was important that a stable Italian government is formed quickly - one that is committed to Monti's policies.</p>
<p>Given Monti's poor show, and the way Berlusconi won support by painting himself as the alternative to German oppression, this may not be the best approach from Westerwelle:</p>
<p>#italyvote fiscal consolidation and reforms must be continued consistently in italy - germany's westerwelle #perfecttiming</p>
<p>Italy has seen its borrowing costs jump at its auction of short-term debt this morning.</p>
<p>It sold €8.75bn of six-month bills, as planned, but at an interest rate of 1.237% – much higher than the 0.73% agreed at a similar sale last month.</p>
<p>Analysts blamed the post-election deadlock.</p>
<p>Italy is due to sell long-term debt tomorrow, and Christian Lenk of DZ Bank is warning that it will probably have to accept higher borrowing costs then too.</p>
<p>Our Southern Europe editor, John Hooper, flags up that we shouldn't simply see the Italian election result as a simple vote against austerity.</p>
<p>He explains that the surge in support for Beppe Grillo's Five Star movement reflects a deeper disenchantment with Italy's entire political system:</p>
<p>John writes:</p>
<p>Market analysts this morning are interpreting this as a vote against austerity. But that is not the whole story, and they will misunderstand (and underestimate) the result if they see if through an exclusively euro zone, macro-economic lens.</p>
<p>Many of Grillo's supporters are unquestionably fed up with their economic prospects. A recent study by the Demos think tank showed they were far more likely to be (a) pessimistic about Italy's (and Europe's) prospects and (b) unemployed.</p>
<p>But while Grillo did indeed lambast the current direction of the EU and the euro zone in his campaign (decrying Mario Monti as Angela Merkel's poodle), his Five Star Movement's main target is Italy's sleazy, complacent political establishment. A new government made up of pro-growth, anti-austerity ministers drawn from among the same old parties will not make the M5S go away.</p>
<p>What is more, the movement's attitude to the EU is profoundly ambiguous. When I spent well over an hour with him a few weeks ago he described himself as a "convinced European".</p>
<p>Guardian article from 11 February 2013 Photograph: /Guardian</p>
<p>But, Grillo says, the decision on the euro is such an important one that Italy's membership needs to be decided by the people in a referendum. The same is true of M5S's economic approach.</p>
<p>Grillo himself espouses an anti-capitalism that chimes with many of the ideas of the Occupy and anti-globalism movements. But his movement's programme actually talks about cutting the budget deficit, and with spending cuts.</p>
<p>Two German politicians have declared that Italy must stick with the reform programme which Mario Monti has put underway -- despite the surge of support for parties which oppose it.</p>
<p>Michael Grosse-Brömer, the parliamentary floor leader of Merkel's Christian Democrats (CDU), said this morning.</p>
<p>It is important that Italy has a functioning government. Monti's reform path must be continued.</p>
<p>(via Reuters).</p>
<p>German economy minister Philipp Rösler was putting a brace face on events, saying that he could imagine a better result for the pro-reform parties.</p>
<p>But in a statement, Rösler insisted there was no other way:</p>
<p>There is no alternative to the structural reforms that are already underway and which include consolidating the budget and boosting competitiveness.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the German tabloid newpaper, Bild, is horrified by Beppe Grillo's ascendancy, and the reappearance of Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Its headline asks: "Are they going to destroy our euro now?"</p>
<p>Italy's current prime minister, Mario Monti, is about to hold talks with the governor of the Bank of Italy, Ignazio Visco, and his own finance minister, Vittorio Grilli, about the situation following the election.</p>
<p>From Italy, our Rome correspondent Lizzy Davies reports that Italians have woken up to "utter confusion"</p>
<p>Last night the possibility of fresh elections was being mooted by some.</p>
<p>But the centre-left Democratic Party appeared to back away from that, and this morning Berlusconi had had his say too. Asked on Canale 5 television about another vote, the former prime minister replied in his inimitable style: "I don't think that would be helpful in this situation because there are no political programmes that have been discussed. The only one to have put forward programmes in this campaign was me."</p>
<p>As mentioned at 8.40am, Berlusconi said all parties must reflect on the result and make sacrificies "for the good of Italy".</p>
<p>Lizzy reports that, with the markets sliding, the former PM reminded us of his financial views, and criticised comparisons between Italy's borrowing costs and Germany's.</p>
<p>The spread between yields on Italian and German government bonds was "an invention of two years ago" without which Italians had lived very happily for years, he explained, adding that he was not worried about the effect the result was having on the markets.</p>
<p>"The markets are independent and also a bit reckless," he said. According to the Ansa news agency, he said: "Let's be done with the spread. Let leave it."</p>
<p>That spread has widened significantly today, following the fall in the value of Italian bonds (see 7.57am).</p>
<p>Why there is stalemate in Italy</p>
<p>The situation after yesterday's elections is that the centre-left has, as expected, secured a majority in the lower house of parliament, or chamber.</p>
<p>But in the upper house, or Senate, it has just two seats more than the centre-right bloc led by Silvio Berlusconi's Freedom People party.</p>
<p>Centre-left: 119 seats</p>
<p>Berlusconi's alliance: 117 seats</p>
<p>Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement: 54 seats</p>
<p>Mario Monti's centrist group: 18 seats</p>
<p>Thus total deadlock - as Grillo has previously said that Five Star will not work with other parties.</p>
<p>The Italian election results have knocked the wind right out of Europe's austerity drive, City analysts are suggesting today. Here's a round-up of early comment:</p>
<p>Kit Juckes of Société Générale:</p>
<p>The cognoscenti will be focusing on the fact that the Italian election was a clear anti-austerity protest by the people of the Euro Zone's third-largest economy.</p>
<p>Austerity delivers an even higher debt levels as it induces perma-recession, so what's the point?</p>
<p>Gary Jenkins of Swordfish Research</p>
<p>The election result is an embarrassment for Mario Monti, who managed to win around 10% of the vote in both houses, a triumphant return for Mr Berlusconi and a breakthrough for Beppe Grillo’s Five Star Movement. One can assume that Angela Merkel had to be served her dinner with plastic cutlery last night.</p>
<p>....the early indications are that Mr Grillo is still sticking to his pre-election promise that he would not enter into a coalition with either of the traditional parties. If he sticks to that line then it would appear to leave only some form of ‘Grand Coalition’ or new elections. One would imagine that the last thing that Mr Bersani would want is another set of elections because the momentum would appear to be with Mr Grillo.</p>
<p>Marc Ostwald of Monument Securities:</p>
<p>It would appear that another round of elections are inevitable [after] a victory for Mr Grillo, a resounding defeat for the establishment as represented by Berlusconi, Bersani and Monti.</p>
<p>Matt Basi, of CMC Markets:</p>
<p>Results from this weekend’s Italian election saw voters show firm opposition to austerity plans instigated by outgoing PM Mario Monti, in favour of a comedian and a tax evader with a scandal list that goes on longer than a Bunga Bunga party. Unsurprisingly, Italian treasuries are better offered this morning.</p>
<p>Trading in several Italian banks was suspended as soon as the market opened, because investors were so desperate to sell, trader @finansakrobat explains:</p>
<p>This is how bad it is in the Italian market today: Most Italian banks were halted automatically before they had a chance to open.</p>
<p>Political developments in Italy: Silvio Berlusconi has ruled out forming a coalition with Mario Monti, the technocratic PM who took power when Berlusconi was ousted in November 2011.</p>
<p>In a TV interview Berlusconi, whose centre-right coalition was narrowly defeated in the lower Italian parliament, said that all parties need to make sacrifices.</p>
<p>Asked if he'd be prepared to work with Pier Luigi's centre-left Democratic Party, Berlusconi said:</p>
<p>Italy cannot be left ungoverned, we have to reflect.</p>
<p>Berlusconi conceded that the centre-left had won the battle in the lower house (last night his party had argued that the race was too close to call). He also argued that Monti's weak performance showed that Italians would not accept his unpopular austerity measures.</p>
<p>in Milan the Italian stock market is plunging - by much more than feared.</p>
<p>The FTSE MIB, made up of the biggest companies on the market, has fallen by 5% -- shedding over 760 points (it took several nervous minutes before all shares were trading properly)</p>
<p>Yesterday afternoon the MIB actually spiked by 4% when the first exit polls emerged, suggesting a win for the centre-left coalition. The reality - a divided Senate with no clear way ahead - has sent investors fleeing.</p>
<p>Neither right nor left had an outright majority in the upper house, where the balance will be held by Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement (M5S). Grillo has ruled out supporting either side in his drive to sweep away Italy's existing political parties and the cronyistic culture they support – a sentiment he appeared to reiterate after the count by insisting the M5S was not planning on "any stitch-ups, big or small" and lambasting Berlusconi's voters for committing "a crime against the galaxy"</p>
<p>Alarming moves in the bond markets too, where Italian government debt is being sold off sharply, dragging Spain down too.</p>
<p>The yield (or interest rate) on 10-year Italian bonds has jumped dramatically to 4.82%, from just 4.37% last night. That's a truly dramatic move, and means traders are rushing to sell their Italian bonds.</p>
<p>Spanish 10-year bonds, another key benchmark, are now yielding more than 5.4%, from 5.1% last night.</p>
<p>It's a picture we've seen before in the eurozone crisis, when fear grows over a peripheral country's ability to repay their debts.</p>
<p>So #Italian and #Spanish 10-year bond yields jump sharply and everyone piles in to German bunds -- it's euro zone crisis redux #elezioni</p>
<p>The uncertainty in Italy has sent the euro reeling, now down by nearly 3 cents against the US dollar since the first predictions from Italy.</p>
<p>It just hit a low of $1.3034 - having received a thorough hoofing during Asian trading dominated by talk that the the eurozone's economic plans were in deep trouble.</p>
<p>As Paul Bloxham, HSBC's chief economist for Australia, told CNBC:</p>
<p>We're now left in limbo and we don't know what the election result means for the reform agenda and the policies Italy needs to implement. It's not a helpful outcome at all.</p>
<p>City traders are expecting big losses when trading begins.</p>
<p>IG is forecasting that the main Italian index, the FTSE MIB, will fall by over 400 points, or 2.5%. It also reckons the FTSE 100 will dive by 100 points in London.</p>
<p>Markets hate uncertainty, as Chris Weston, IG's chief market strategist, explains:</p>
<p>We simply don’t know the state of play with Italian politics, and markets find sellers in times of instability.</p>
<p>The President will take centre stage now and either form a ‘grand coalition’, although this seems unlikely. It has been speculated that Mr Bersani may look to team up with Beppe Grillo’s Five Star movement (again unlikely), or ultimately fresh elections will be called down the track.</p>
<p>This is a story of anti-austerity and one where most hadn’t expected the anti-austerity / anti-European parties to do anywhere near as well as they have. The Italian voter has spoken out and this has thrown up political instability as perhaps the number one issue facing Europe in 2013.</p>
<p>After a dramatic day in Italy, the centre-left group led by Pier Luigi Bersani has won a narrow victory in the lower house of parliament.</p>
<p>The Senate, though, appears to be deeply split with no party winning sufficient seats to control it.</p>
<p>And the really big shock for the European establishment is the success of the Five Star Movement, led by comedian Beppe Grillo. It has won more votes than any other party - a remarkable achievement, which shows deep anger in Italy against the political status quo.</p>
<p>Comic-turned-politician Beppe Grillo, center, arriving to cast his vote, in Genoa, yesterday. Photograph: Fabio Palli/AP Photograph: Fabio Palli/AP</p>
<p>But it was a bad night for Mario Monti, whose centrist pro-reform coalition was a distant fourth place - failing to win enough seats in the Senate to form a coalition with Bersani.</p>
<p>There is talk that a second election will be needed to break the deadlock, unless political leaders can somehow agree a workable coalition.</p>
<p>The euro has already fallen sharply in overnight trading, and traders are braced for a big sell-off when European stock markets open in one hour's time.</p>
<p>Just when when politicians and financial markets have grown confident (some might say complacent) that the worst was over, the eurozone debt crisis has flared back into life.</p>
<p>We'll be tracking all the developments through the day ...</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>