<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Michael White" categories="Politics" date="2009-10-08" description="Michael White: One way or another we have had a very bad political year, but, however imperfectly, the system still functions" fingerprint="b381d20f90020585" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Conservative conference 2009,Labour conference 2009,Liberal Democrat conference 2009,Politics,UK news,Conservatives,Conservative conference,Labour,Labour conference,Liberal Democrat conference,Liberal Democrats,Proportional representation,Constitutional reform,MPs expenses,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Nicolas Sarkozy,France,European Union,Tony Blair,Europe" title="Berlusconi and Sarkozy's woes should put our own politics in perspective | Michael White" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/blog/2009/oct/08/berlusconi-sarkozy-politics-michael-white">
<main>
<p>Good news from the Italian constitutional court, whose ruling against <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/oct/08/sivlio-berlusconi-immunity-law-overturned">Silvio Berlusconi's Animal Farm defence</ref> (that he is "first above equals") brings closer the moment when the old rogue will be driven from public life. The safety of the republic depends upon it.</p>
<p>But what comparative light does it shed on our own politics? A comforting one, I hope, and seek only to make this simple point. One way or another we have had a very bad political year, but, however imperfectly, the system still functions in troubled times.</p>
<p>From what I hear at the Tory conference one of our own – <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tonyblair">Tony Blair</ref> – may even emerge as the first full-time president of the European council of ministers, albeit with Italian and even French support.</p>
<p>The president of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref> and his nearest rival – Brown to his Blair – are, of course, currently slogging it out in a French court too, Sarkozy v De Villepin. We have been spared that sort of carnival. Fun though the French and Italian dramas are to watch, it is better to do so from afar. The damage done on these occasions is extensive.</p>
<p>What has been striking here in Manchester, as it was in Brighton last week, is how little the expenses scandal that rocked Westminster last spring has featured. I had half-expected MPs to be put in a corral and publicly condemned – as they used to be at Labour's conference in the heyday of Bennery.</p>
<p>The Lib Dems, whose USP is to feel virtuous about themselves whether that is warranted or not, made more of the scandal. But Labour and Tory politicians have been more perfunctory on the podium. So far as I can tell their activists have shown little appetite for recrimination either.</p>
<p>In Manchester only one serious offender is said to have dared show his face, though I did not see him. More interestingly, at the Guardian debate on the conference fringe (I chaired it) speakers were strikingly restrained in their proposals.</p>
<p>Only Nick Boles, a coming man in Team Cameron, suggested bold things such as a recall mechanism for errant MPs and electing police chiefs to ensure their priorities are our priorities. Boris Johnson's sacking of Sir Ian Blair as Metropolitan police chief and his replacement by the lovable Sir Paul Stephenson provides an encouraging precedent, he said.</p>
<p>That struck me as rather naive. But it was at least radical. Other panellists – Tim Montgomerie, the ConservativeHome blog king, Joanne Cash (both candidates in winnable seats, as Boles is) and Ben Wallace, a class of 2005 MP – were cautious.</p>
<p>Montgomerie banks a lot on MPs in the Virgin Parliament about to be elected being better people and providing better results; Cash, a lawyer and social activist, lays store on innate human goodness; Wallace, who put his expenses online a year before the scandal, thinks transparency and accountability will see us through.</p>
<p>All laudable, but not the sweeping reconstruction of the body politic that some people spoke of in the spring. As one of our panellists remarked, the crisis provided an opportunity for everyone to dust off their favourite panaceas, proportional representation for example. The Tories gave short shrift to that this week.</p>
<p>Myself, I think a new parliament full of new faces will help considerably to clear the air, though I am slightly scared at the prospect of the combustible mixture we may get: wholesome high-minded naifs who want to change the world mixed up with worldly eye-to-main-chance types. As has been reported, there are a lot of professional political-class types and lobbyists in the new crop.</p>
<p>But "new politics"? I don't think so. Just better corrective mechanisms for mistakes, a stronger Commons, ministers less ambitious to legislate for every problem that upsets the media, MPs with a sense of being on probation.</p>
<p>One instance of business as usual was borne down on me at a Manchester reception where a senior Cameroon said rather testily that, of course, the party leadership wouldn't press a referendum or anything else silly if the Lisbon treaty was in place by election day.</p>
<p>They were trying to reform the Tory image in so many ways that they had to throw the activists a bit of red meat to keep them happy. The meat was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>. Didn't I get that? Yes, I did, though I fear it is a tactic that jeopardises strategy – and will be regretted.</p>
<p>It was ever thus and foolish. But it is not to be confused with debauching the state as Berlusconi seems to have done or setting the security services on a party rival, which is alleged – alleged – in the Paris court.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>