<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2011-08-06" description="Editorial: Up to now, they have been woefully wanting. Now they must step up and get ahead of the markets" fingerprint="27fe10b218932d48" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Euro,George Osborne,Silvio Berlusconi,Angela Merkel,European Central Bank" title="We need strong leaders in the eurozone | Editorial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/aug/07/eurozone-economy-crisis-eu">
<main>
<p>There was always a theory that the eurozone leaders needed a full-blown markets crisis to focus their minds on the fundamental problems with the single currency. Last week they got it. Markets endured trading patterns not experienced since the dark days of the 2008 banking crisis, when the US government let the Wall Street bank <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/7615931.stm">Lehman Bros</ref> collapse onto to an unsuspecting market<hi rend="#b">.</hi></p>
<p>In the way that demise sent shock waves across the global financial markets, the mere suggestion that Italy, the third largest country in the eurozone, might need a bailout from its eurozone partners sent spasms through the financial system.</p>
<p>Nearly £150bn was wiped off the value of Britain's leading companies last week, while on Friday alone Wall Street suffered violent trading patterns that demonstrated the harsh reality that a eurozone debt crisis, colliding with a slowdown in the world's biggest economy, poses too many risks – even for the most experienced investors.</p>
<p>By the time European markets had closed, the first signs that European leaders were finally listening to the message they were being sent by the markets started to emerge. Italy's embattled prime minister <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-11981754">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> revealed that the G7 finance ministers – some of whom, such as George Osborne, are on their summer holidays – were ready to discuss the crisis.</p>
<p>Only a day earlier Berlusconi had been flippantly suggesting that the stockmarket falls were merely an opportunity for Italians to buy undervalued stock in his Mediaset media empire. Now he is promising to bring forward a €48bn package of austerity measures in the hope that the <ref target="http://www.ecb.int/home/html/index.en.html">European Central Bank</ref> will now agree to start vacuuming up the country's debt on the international financial<hi rend="#b"/>markets and ease the crippling borrowing costs that his country cannot afford. Full-blown buying by the ECB – until now focused on buying bonds from countries such as Portugal and Ireland that have already agreed bailouts – of Italian, and hopefully Spanish bonds, is exactly what the markets had been hoping for.</p>
<p>It is not straightforward, however. First there is the price; neither the ECB nor the European Financial Stability Fund, the vehicle set up in the wake of the Greek bailout, has the cash required. The EFSF will eventually have the capacity to spend €440bn under the terms thrashed out by eurozone leaders last month. Given its existing liabilities, it can probably only muster around €340bn to support Italy and Spain. That would enable it to buy only around 13% of existing Italian and Spanish government debt.</p>
<p>Last year the ECB purchased 15% of Greek debt but that had no impact on the rate of interest the Greek government had to pay to borrow or stop Greece hurtling towards a bailout. Put simply, it's no where near enough money.</p>
<p>Willem Buiter, the Citigroup economist and founder member of the <ref target="http://www.bankofengland.co.uk/">Bank of England</ref>'s monetary policy committee, reckons at least €2.5tn is needed if the EFSF is to be a credible weapon to defend the euro. Others are arguing that any rescue fund needs to be topped up to the tune of €4tn. A huge price tag.</p>
<p>Second, there are the practicalities. On Friday EU commissioner Olli Rehn insisted the EFSF would be ready in a matter of weeks. But the fact is each parliament across the eurozone needs to approve the new fighting fund. That will not be an easy sell in some north European countries, especially Germany, where <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/4572387.stm">Angela Merkel</ref>, facing election and behind in the polls, has to convince reluctant voters that it is in their long-term interest to send cash south. Aside from the political wrangling this will entail, parliamentarians across Europe are packing their bags for the summer holiday season.</p>
<p>Third, even if they do find a way to raise the cash and convince euro parliaments to pass the required rules, it may still only be a sticking plaster unless a way can be found to address the huge structural problems in both Italy and Spain, such as poor productivity and lack of competitiveness. Without reform, City economists expect it to be all but impossible for the Spanish and Italian governments to meet their deficit reduction goals – and find the economic growth vital to long-term economic recovery.</p>
<p>Britain, meanwhile, and despite George Osborne's protestations to the contrary, cannot stand on the sidelines while Rome burns and the single currency project goes up in flames. Nearly two-thirds of British exports go to Europe and the economic health of our biggest customers has major ramifications on British industry and banks. Our fragile economic growth would be dealt another harsh blow by further European turmoil.</p>
<p>This is not just an issue of financial stability. If Italy goes the same way as Greece, the protests witnessed in Athens could look like a little local difficulties compared with the demonstrations that are likely to hit the streets of Rome and Milan and exacerbate the already worrying north-south political divide in Italy. It is an issue of hard-core politics, of the post-war agenda of harnessing old enemies into an economic union that ensures they never turn on each other again.</p>
<p>So far leadership in the eurozone – from Merkel to Berlusconi and from <ref target="http://www.ecb.int/ecb/orga/decisions/html/cvtrichet.en.html">Jean-Claude Trichet</ref>, boss of the ECB, to <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3844973.stm">José Manuel Barroso</ref>, president of the <ref target="http://ec.europa.eu/index_en.htm">European Commission</ref> – has fallen woefully short. They have emerged as leaders who do not lead and are only ever forced to act at the 11th hour.</p>
<p>Now is the time. It is in no one's interest for a disorderly collapse of the euro. It is time for the leaders of Europe, the ECB and the EFSF to get ahead of the markets. But that will not be the endgame.</p>
<p>Once stability is achieved, and in order to ensure that the euro has a future that cannot be doubted, leaders will need to confront far bigger issues. Either a mechanism has to be found to allow a two-speed Europe where the countries of the periphery are not hobbled by an exchange rate that is totally inappropriate for their economic wellbeing, or the eurozone must consider political union where the more prosperous areas routinely help the less well-off. The United States of Europe is probably the only true long-term solution.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>