<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-03-26" description="Italian prime minister's remark follows last year's 'sun-tanned' comment" fingerprint="8ec6e21d152f8e65" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Barack Obama,World news,Europe" title="I'm paler than Barack Obama, says gaffe-happy Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/26/silvio-berlusconi-obama-gaffe">
<main>
<p>Not satisfied with having once referred to Barack Obama as "sun-tanned", <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> today returned to the subject, telling a reporter he was paler than the US president.</p>
<p>After a journalist commented that his response to the global economic crisis made him seem like Obama, Italy's prime minister, who is famed for his even, year-round tan, shot back: "I'm paler, also, because it's been so long since I've been in the sun." He quickly added: "He is more handsome, younger and taller."</p>
<p>His retort echoed the comment that got him into hot water last November when he joked in Moscow that Dmitri Medvedev would have no difficulty getting on with his new US counterpart because Obama, like the Russian president, was "handsome, young and sun-tanned". The 72-year-old media entrepreneur-turned-conservative politician brushed off censure of his comment, saying his critics had no sense of humour.</p>
<p>His latest gaffe came as he was already under fire in his own country for two other "jokes" that some of his compatriots found offensive. Opposition politicians, already indignant at his use of confidence votes to force through legislation without proper debate, expressed outrage when Berlusconi declared that MPs were in parliament "to make up the numbers". He was earlier criticised by trade unionists for saying people who lost their jobs because of the global economic crisis should "find something to do". Berlusconi added that, if he were fired, he certainly would not be "twiddling my thumbs".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>