<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2003-12-04" description="There has been growing speculation about the health of Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, ahead of one of the most challenging tasks of his political career - next week's crucial EU summit in Brussels to decide on the European constitution." fingerprint="77bec3efb203f106" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Concern over Berlusconi's health" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/dec/04/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>There has been growing speculation about the health of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, ahead of one of the most challenging tasks of his political career - next week's crucial EU summit in Brussels to decide on the European constitution.</p>
<p>For the second time in two weeks, it was announced on Tuesday that he had put off high-level official engagements.</p>
<p>Aides said he was suffering from a recurring gastro-intestinal ailment and was unable to attend two meetings which had been arranged to prepare for the summit.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi was meant to have had talks on Tuesday with the Cypriot president, Tassos Papadopoulos, and Denmark's prime minister, Anders Fogh Rasmussen. Last week, he put off a visit to India for the same reason.</p>
<p>His officials called it a "slight" indisposition. But in political circles in Rome there is a growing suspicion that it could be more serious.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who had an operation for prostate cancer six years ago, has been virtually absent from public life for almost a month.</p>
<p>His last significant public appearance was at a press conference on November 6 with President Vladimir Putin of Russia.</p>
<p>Italy holds the presidency of the EU and Mr Berlusconi and his ministers are keen to crown their stint with a deal on the constitution at the summit beginning on December 12.</p>
<p>The Italian leader is to fly to Paris today to meet his French and Spanish counterparts, Jean-Pierre Raffarin and José Maria Aznar.</p>
<p>It seemed last night that he would keep this appointment. His aides said he had been well enough to have a meeting with the Romanian prime minister, Adrian Nastase, yesterday.</p>
<p>Last month, Mr Berlusconi, 67, said he had received a clean bill of health during an annual check-up. He was operated on for cancer 1997, but did not reveal his illness until three years later.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>