<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-10-02" description="Enrico Letta asks parliament to save coalition government from collapse following withdrawal of ministers by Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="ffba8b2597a3b72f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" title="Italian PM appeals to MPs ahead of confidence vote" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/02/italy-vote-enrico-letta-silvio-berlusconi-coalition-government">
<main>
<p>The politics of the eurozone's third largest economy was in a state of uncertainty as the prime minister, Enrico Letta, urged MPs to search their consciences and support his government in a make-or-break confidence vote.</p>
<p>In a speech before the upper house of parliament, the head of Italy's five-month-old grand coalition said it was up to MPs from all sides of the spectrum to save the country from the "potentially fatal risk" of government collapse.</p>
<p>About 25 minutes into the speech, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the former prime minister whose decision to withdraw his centre-right ministers from the coalition sparked the crisis, entered the senate.</p>
<p>Facing what appeared to be an unprecedented rebellion within his own Freedom People (PdL) party, on Tuesday night Berlusconi had told loyalists to vote against the confidence vote.</p>
<p>But, on his way in to Palazzo Madama on Wednesday, he said the vote could yet go either way. "Let's see what happens," he told reporters. "We will listen to Letta's speech and then decide."</p>
<p>The Ansa news agency later reported that the PdL's official party line would be to vote against the confidence vote, paving the way for a dramatic but as yet unquantifiable split in the main centre-right party.</p>
<p>As the debates went ahead in the Senate, it was unclear how much support Letta could count on from PdL dissidents.</p>
<p>In the most important speech of his career, Letta urged senators to accept that Italy's government could not be held hostage by Berlusconi's increasingly pressing legal woes. The billionaire media magnate was convicted in August of tax fraud and faces imminent expulsion from the Senate.</p>
<p>In a direct rebuke to the 77-year-old, who has dominated Italian politics for two decades, Letta said the interests of one person and those of an entire nation "neither could nor can overlap". In a democratic state, he added, "sentences are respected and enforced".</p>
<p>Berlusconi has to choose by the middle of this month whether to serve his sentence under house arrest or in community services. Italians, he said, were sick and tired of "blood and theatrics" and of "politicians who butcher each other and then change nothing".</p>
<p>As Italy showed signs of emerging from its worst recession since the second world war, he said, the country needed a government that focused on its pressing socio-economic problems, which include record youth unemployment and a public debt of over €2tn.</p>
<p>Plunging it back into political limbo would delay efforts to help struggling businesses, embarrass Italy in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, and hit hardest ordinary families who have suffered the most during the economic downturn, he said.</p>
<p>"Italy is running a risk that is potentially fatal, without remedy," he said. "Thwarting this risk, to seize or not seize the moment, depends on the choices we will make in this chamber. It depends on a yes or a no."</p>
<p>In a final appeal that referred obliquely to Berlusconi, he asked senators for "courage and confidence" to avoid being hit by "shameful regret". He said it would be "a confidence [vote] that is not against anyone; a confidence [vote] that is for Italy".</p>
<p>If the government is able to continue, he said, it would exercise tight control over public finances and avoid the deficit running over 3%. If it was struck down and a new election had to be held, he said, Italy ran a risk of fresh ungovernability, with a deadlocked parliament likely due to an electoral law that Letta says is a reform priority.</p>
<p>The prime minister's speech began by quoting Luigi Einaudi, a former Italian president. "In the lives of nations, the mistake of not knowing how to seize the fleeting moment is irreparable," he said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>