<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-02-08" description="Prosecutors to request Italian prime minister face trial over allegations he had sex with an underage prostitute" fingerprint="7ffcc29d8247eed4" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Prosecutors seek Silvio Berlusconi trial over sex claims" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/08/silvio-berluscon-prosecutors-seek-trial">
<main>
<p>Prosecutors are to ask for Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, to be put on trial because of his relationship with a teenager alleged to have been an underage prostitute.</p>
<p>"Tomorrow morning, we shall submit our requests in relation to the position of Silvio Berlusconi and put out a statement," Edmondo Bruti Liberati, the chief prosecutor of Milan, told reporters.</p>
<p>Later today, he and the three members of his department involved in the investigation will hold what he called "a conclusive meeting" to discuss which charges should be laid and how.</p>
<p>Last month it emerged that Berlusconi had been formally placed under investigation in December, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/14/berlusconi-under-investigation-underage-prostitute?intcmp=239">suspected of paying an underage prostitute and then trying to cover up the fact by abusing his authority</ref>.</p>
<p>Together, the two offences carry a maximum sentence of 15 years. Berlusconi denies any wrongdoing, as does the girl at the centre of the affair – Karima el-Mahroug, a Moroccan immigrant runaway turned nightclub dancer.</p>
<p>Last May, while still aged 17, Mahroug was arrested on suspicion of theft and taken to a Milan police station. Instead of being returned to care, she was handed over to a friend of the prime minister after Berlusconi spoke by phone to a senior police official.</p>
<p>According to leaks from the subsequent investigation, the friend found her a home with a Brazilian woman alleged to be a prostitute.</p>
<p>The inquiry into the affair uncovered evidence, which Berlusconi's lawyers dispute, that Mahroug had several times visited the prime minister's home near Milan. Documents submitted to parliament last month contained witness statements and wiretap transcripts indicating dinners at the villa, attended by large numbers of women, led to "bunga bunga" sessions involving striptease and sex play.</p>
<p>Under Italian law, the age of consent is 14. But paying for the services of a prostitute aged under 18 is an offence, punishable by up to three years in prison. Juvenile prostitution is widely defined and, to secure a conviction, the prosecution does not have to prove full sexual intercourse took place.</p>
<p>Italy's prime minister risks being in the dock by Easter. The prosecutors who oversaw the police investigation have made clear they want him put on trial without committal proceedings.</p>
<p>It is unclear if they will ask the judge for a direct indictment on both charges. Normally, cases involving defendants accused of paying an underage prostitute require pre-trial hearings. The judge will have five days in which to decide for or against an indictment.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>