<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Andrew Anthony" categories="World news" date="2006-01-31" description="Andrew Anthony: At first sight, Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's promise to abstain from sex until after his country's general election on April 9 looks as if it could have been designed as an explanatory illustration of the phrase 'making a virtue out of a necessity'." fingerprint="7ea0712e97a78645" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Andrew Anthony on Silvio Berlusconi's promise of not having sex until the election" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jan/31/italy.andrewanthony">
<main>
<p>At first sight, Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's promise to abstain from sex until after his country's general election on April 9 looks as if it could have been designed as an explanatory illustration of the phrase "making a virtue out of a necessity".</p>
<p>After all, though he is a multibillionaire, and therefore not unattractive to certain avaricious tastes, Berlusconi is also a bald 69-year-old married man. For most men of his age, 10 weeks without sex qualifies as a typical interlude rather than heroic denial.</p>
<p>In fact his wife, the former actress Veronica Lario, wrote an autobiography a couple of years back in which she complained that she had "no one with whom to share a concert, or a book, or a walk, or even a shopping trip".</p>
<p>Now she can add "a bed" to that list of marital projects in which her husband is either unable or unwilling to participate. Except that Lario described a marriage of such physical, indeed geographical, detachment that it is unlikely that, even before the promise, she often had to wrestle Berlusconi for the duvet.</p>
<p>Yet given that Berlusconi made his pledge at a rally in support of family values, then with whom else but his wife could he practise his "complete sexual abstinence"? One answer, of course, is himself. He did not make it clear whether onanism is included in the remit of his physical sacrifice, but we do know that the Roman Catholic church has never been a keen proponent of the sin of self-pollution.</p>
<p>Still, however vain he may be, Berlusconi knows there are no votes to be won in refusing the pleasure of himself. As a self-described "playboy", and someone who was not long ago seen in intimate clinches with a 21-year-old assistant, he was surely referring to the superhuman self-control he will bring to the job of resisting nubile young women for a whole two and half months. The point is Berlusconi is a man, and not only that, he is an Italian man, and thus he sees himself as God's gift to women.</p>
<p>If that wasn't enough, he is also a politician. And as George Galloway demonstrated in Big Brother, politicians have their own particular reasons for gift-wrapping themselves as sex gods. Galloway told everyone in the house that his friends couldn't believe he would be able to go three weeks without sex. The message he wanted to convey was two-fold and exactly the same as Berlusconi's.</p>
<p>First he wanted to let the audience know that he is indeed Gorgeous George, devastatingly attractive to any woman with a heartbeat. Second, he wished to convey to the watching world that he possessed the self-discipline to rise above the curse of his seductive looks and ultra-masculine desire.</p>
<p>It's a canny manoeuvre that speaks to a variety of demographics as well as both genders. Yes, Galloway and Berlusconi, are saying, we have the sexual appetite of young men but the restraint of senior statesmen. Men, women, the youthful, the aged, the apolitical and the religious can find something of merit in that pitch.</p>
<p>However, though Berlusconi is seeking to identify with men, he is really aiming at the heart of women. And the question he is asking is this: Would you like me to be your cat? The risk with that strategy, as Galloway now knows, is that politicians can soon end up in the doghouse.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">It's not difficult to laugh at Naomi Wolf,</hi> the fragrant author of The Beauty Myth and sometime Great White Hope for a generation of feminists. She made her name by telling women to ignore the conventions of beauty imposed on women by the cosmetics industry, and for looking like the very embodiment of what women were supposed to reject. And many critics have ridiculed her habit of writing grand statement books about the world through the tiny prism of her own experience.</p>
<p>Then there was that tragicomic scene with Harold Bloom, the Shakespearean academic, in which, according her own account, she vomited after he attempted to woo her with the phrase: "You have the aura of election upon you". As one wit who tried to unpick the poetry of Bloom's words suggested, perhaps Wolf misheard "election".</p>
<p>Yes, it's not difficult to laugh at Wolf, so why does she go out of her way to make it even easier? In a recent interview, she admits that she now answers to "a higher authority". And she's not talking about transferring to a more prestigious publisher. "Higher authority", of course, is polite American for God.</p>
<p>Specifically, in fact, Jesus, whom she encountered in a vision in which Wolf herself appeared as a 13-year-old boy. It's a little bit confusing, I know, but then where is written that religious awakenings must follow a standard first-person narrative?</p>
<p>Anyway, Wolf describes the epiphany as "completely not the appropriate spiritual experience of someone of my background". Don't you just love that "appropriate"? What she means is that she underwent a politically incorrect spiritual experience because she is, like Jesus, a Jew. And, apparently, that's just not kosher.</p>
<p>So Wolf gives the man from Nazareth what can only be described as a make-over. "I so much want to distance this from Christianity," she says. '"It has nothing to do with religion whatsoever." She sees Jesus, not as '"this whole Christian construct but as a teacher and a social activist, as a rabbi and as a healer." If she were any more right-on, she'd be recruited by the Church of England.</p>
<p>But what I'd like to know is: if this has nothing to do with religion, the New Testament and 2000 years of devotional iconography, how did she know that the bloke in the vision was Jesus? Did he introduce himself, and if so, did he say "Forget all that Christian crap, I'm just a rabbi and a healer." Also, if he wasn't God, what was he doing in her vision? Why not another rabbi. And if he was God, doesn't that make her a Christian?</p>
<p>As an atheist, I can't say that I care. But I do thank God that Naomi Wolf continues to provide us all, regardless of faith, with so much first-rate entertainment.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Up until now, it's been hard to see the </hi>benefits of ethical shopping. But with the news that all right-thinking people should avoid buying flowers imported from abroad, because it's environmentally unsound, the movement has come of age, if not quite bloomed. I never buy flowers on Valentine's Day but this year I can look forward to not buying them without the guilt. It's not that I'm not buying them for my wife. I'm not buying them for the whole planet.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">This week </hi><lb/> Andrew saw <hi rend="#b">Hidden</hi>: "It's the kind of film that critics like because it's a 'profound comment on voyeurism'. But say it quietly, it's a bit slow and repetitive and exquisitely empty." Andrew read <hi rend="#b">Halfway through the Spring section of Anthony Powell's A Dance to the Music of Time</hi>: "A revelation. I hope to read the rest before I die."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>