<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2006-04-04" description="John Hooper: Silvio Berlusconi re-emerges as stealthily as an alligator - with similarly lethal effects." fingerprint="f69e822ab441dbfc" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="The 'cayman' bites" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/apr/04/thecaymanbites">
<main>
<p>"Silvio," said the former EU commissioner, <ref target="http://www.emmabonino.it/">Emma Bonino</ref>, "is a genius."</p>
<p>Ms Bonino may once have been an ally of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="http://www.governo.it/Presidente/Biografia/biografiaen.html">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, but she no longer has any incentive to praise him. In the current general election campaign, she is running for parliament as part of the centre-left opposition alliance, the <ref target="http://www.unioneweb.it/">Union</ref>.</p>
<p>But Ms Bonino is nothing if not forthright and she has the honesty to acknowledge political talent when she sees it. Mr Berlusconi had just stunned the opposition by letting it be known that he was going to see the pope a few days before the vote. The meeting came to nothing, but an impression was left that the Vatican, if not God himself, was on the prime minister's side. Ms Bonino's underlying message was that the centre-left needed to be constantly on its guard against a enemy it underestimated at its peril.</p>
<p>Until last night, not a lot had been seen of "Silvio the genius". He put up a disastrous performance in his first TV duel with Romano Prodi and his strategy of talking up his government's record while wishing away the country's problems had begun to grate on even his allies by the time the two men met on TV for their final debate.</p>
<p>But in the dying seconds of the encounter, he re-emerged. The film director, Nanni Moretti, called his newly-released movie about Italy's prime minister <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0429727/">The Cayman</ref>. And, indeed, Mr Berlusconi re-surfaced last night as stealthily as an alligator and with similarly lethal effect. He waited till the very end, when the affable professor Prodi no longer had a right of reply. Then, smiling into the camera and looking not at all unlike Elio De Capitani's portrayal of him in The Cayman, Mr Berlusconi told his audience that he intended to abolish at a stroke the municipal tax on first homes.</p>
<p>It doesn't really matter that only 12 million viewers - four million less than last time - watched his performance. The word will get around that by voting for the right you can rid yourself forever of what in Britain used to be called "rate"'. It would be hard to think of anything more likely to win over undecided voters.</p>
<p>Is it populist nonsense? Of course. Italy's local authority property tax brings in €2.3 billion. Either the government in Rome is going to have to make up the shortfall by raising taxes elsewhere or the councils are going to be forced to slash the services they offer to householders. Either way, the ordinary voter will suffer.</p>
<p>But whether, in the towns and villages, they will see it that way is quite another matter. In an instant comment on the debate, a <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/cmstp/rubriche/girata.asp?ID_blog=25&amp;ID_articolo=774&amp;tp=C">La Stampa columnist</ref> argued that it all came down to whether the voters would trust Mr Berlusconi to fulfil his promise. I am not so sure.</p>
<p>The promise is deliverable. In theory, the central government is going to have to find an extra €2.3 billion to give to local government. In theory, the last thing the Italian government should be doing is cutting back on revenue because it already has a budget deficit of 4.1% of GDP and the rules of membership of the euro say it should not be more than 3%.</p>
<p>But then Mr Berlusconi was never one for rules. And, bearing in mind that most of Italy's local authorities are run by the left, he might not anyway be in a hurry to make good the hole in their accounts. The issue is not so much whether Italy's floating voters believe he can deliver as whether they can see that once again - with apologies for another reptilian metaphor - he is offering them fiscal snake oil.</p>
<p>Can you fool enough of the people enough of the time? We shall find out after the polls close on Monday.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>