<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-11-07" description="Former neo-fascist leader and long-standing ally threatens to withdraw his FLI followers from the government" fingerprint="37a8db2d1081e729" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi under pressure after Gianfranco Fini's ultimatum" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/07/silvio-berlusconi-gianfranco-fini-ultimatum">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's longest standing ally presented him with an ultimatum that could herald the beginning of the end of the TV magnate's government.</p>
<p>Addressing supporters after a tumultuous week that saw Italy's prime minister on the receiving end of sex and drug allegations, Gianfranco Fini warned that he would withdraw his followers from the government unless Berlusconi resigned to form a new administration with new policies. Initial signs were that Berlusconi would refuse to do so, but would instead challenge Fini to bring down the government in parliament.</p>
<p>The man who for 15 years stood at Berlusconi's side delivered his ultimatum in the course of a wide-ranging speech in which he criticised, and even ridiculed, the administration's performance. Using language that appeared to leave an unbridgeable chasm between the two men, Fini, a former neo-fascist, accused Berlusconi of heading "the government of pretending everything is going well".</p>
<p>He made no direct reference to the latest controversies over the prime minister's private life. But in an unmistakable allusion Fini spoke of "moral decay" caused by a "loss of decorum and rigour in the behaviour of those who, as public figures, are required to set an example".</p>
<p>After Fini was denounced by the leadership of Berlusconi's Freedom People (PdL) party in July, his followers renounced the PdL whip and set up groups of their own in both chambers of parliament, robbing the prime minister of his majority in the lower house. But the Future and Freedom for Italy (FLI) movement, which met at the weekend near Perugia, is not expected to become a party until next year.</p>
<p>A key reason why Fini is apparently bent on prolonging the death throes of Berlusconi's wounded and all but inert administration is that the FLI is still not in a position to fight an election.</p>
<p>If Fini were to follow through on his threat to withdraw from government, it could fatally weaken the Berlusconi administration.</p>
<p>The government has made little significant progress for more than a year, paralysed by its leader's efforts to provide himself with immunity from the courts along with an unending succession of scandals over his sex life and the alleged financial misconduct of ministers and officials. Last week, a former prostitute came forward to say that she had twice been paid for sex by Berlusconi; that she had taken part with him in a sex session involving a teenager, and that cannabis was made available for guests at his holiday villa. He dismissed the claims as "made-up stories".</p>
<p>On Friday, Berlusconi tried to restore purpose to his administration when his cabinet approved a package of new security measures. Without referring to it directly, Fini told FLI delegates: "Nowhere in Europe is there a political movement as backward on civil liberties as the PdL."</p>
<p>He, by contrast, wanted to offer Italy a new, more tolerant and moderate brand of conservatism that would avoid "distinguishing between blacks and whites, between Christians, Muslims and Jews, between heterosexuals and homosexuals, [or] between Italians and foreigners".</p>
<p>Soon after the 2008 general election, Fini began a realignment of his position, the sincerity of which remains a subject of debate in the centre-left opposition.</p>
<p>In Italy, prime ministers have frequently resigned with the intention of forming a new, reshaped government. Berlusconi himself did so in 2005. But it involves a risk. The initiative then passes to the president, currently a former communist, Giorgio Napolitano.</p>
<p>As head of state, Napolitano could decide to ask someone other than Berlusconi to form a government, perhaps one with broad, cross-party support. Alternatively, the president could dissolve parliament and call a new election.</p>
<p>That would be unwelcome to the prime minister, whose poll ratings have fallen steadily as economic austerity measures introduced in May have started to bite.</p>
<p>According to Italian media reports, Berlusconi told aides he had no intention of resigning and that it was now up to the FLI to vote against him in parliament – a move that would lay Fini and his followers open to charges of betraying the right.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>