<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Patrick Wintour" categories="Politics" date="2005-05-28" description="Tony Blair began his marathon diplomatic effort to win support for his G8 agenda of Africa and climate change by winning the public support of the Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, yesterday." fingerprint="624b81efd5b6f904" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,UK news,G8,Italy,Guardian Hear Africa campaign 2005,World news,Foreign policy,Global development,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Blair gets Berlusconi's backing on Africa" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2005/may/28/uk.g8">
<main>
<p>Tony Blair began his marathon diplomatic effort to win support for his G8 agenda of Africa and climate change by winning the public support of the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, yesterday.</p>
<p>After his visit to Rome, he is due to hold talks in Moscow, Washington, Paris and Berlin before the Gleneagles <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit in July. Mr Berlusconi said after two hour of talks in Rome: "I have assured Mr Blair of my personal support and my country's support in favour of what I know is going to be a very reasonable, sound and viable set of proposals."</p>
<p>Mr Blair described the discussions as friendly and constructive.</p>
<p>He told an Italian seminar on Africa with Bob Geldof: "What's happening in Africa today is something that if it happened in any other continent in the world, there would be outrage ... and there would be immense, sustained pressure on world leaders to act."</p>
<p>Mr Blair went on: "Unfortunately, because it's in Africa this is not the case, and that's a very sad statement on the state of our politics."</p>
<p>"If we do not work with Africa to change its situation, I believe it would not only be morally wrong, it would be a very big mistake for our world in this century.</p>
<p>"If we allow one continent to exist in such a state, then the consequences ultimately will be felt by all of us."</p>
<p>The next big stage is a G7 finance ministers meeting next weekend and a world economic forum in Cape Town, starting on Wednesday, at which an action plan for Africa will be set out.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>