<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="UK news" date="2009-02-17" description="John Hooper details the corruption allegations faced by the estranged husband of the Olympics minister Tessa Jowell" fingerprint="29ba808d90a516d9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="David Mills,Tessa Jowell,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Politics,World news,Labour,UK news,Europe" title="Q&amp;A: The David Mills affair" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jun/07/qanda.italy">
<main>
<p><hi rend="#b">Why was the husband of a British minister on trial in Italy?</hi><lb/> David Mills is a lawyer. For several years, he advised Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. In particular, he helped Berlusconi create a network of offshore companies for his business empire. The uses of that network have been the subject of several court cases in Italy in which Berlusconi has been a defendant. Italian prosecutors initially took the view that Mills was simply a professional adviser who bore no responsibility for any alleged wrongdoing on the part of others. But, in 2003, two Milanese prosecutors began investigating him too.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">What was he accused of?</hi><lb/> There are two linked cases. In both, Mills has denied any wrongdoing. One involves the trading of film rights through offshore companies set up by him. He was accused of helping Berlusconi to evade tax and launder money, but that case was suspended after the Berlusconi government passed a law giving Italy's prime minister and other top officials immunity from prosecution. In the second case, which grew out of the first, Mills was the only defendant. He was accused of taking a bribe. The case against Berlusconi was suspended because of the immunity law.<lb/> What was the supposed bribe for?<lb/> Allegedly, to withhold evidence in two earlier trials in which Berlusconi was a defendant and Mills was a witness for the prosecution.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">How did this case grow out of the other?</hi><lb/> During their investigations, the prosecutors came into possession of a letter written by Mills to his accountant. In it, he said he had received $600,000 (£400,000 at the time) from a Berlusconi executive for having "turned some very tricky corners, to put it mildly", in his evidence to the Italian courts.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">What happened then?</hi><lb/> Mills was questioned by the prosecutors and confirmed the substance of the letter. However, he subsequently retracted his admission.<lb/> Where did he then say the money came from?<lb/> Another Italian client, a Neapolitan ship owner called Diego Attanasio. In 1997, a trust of which Attanasio was the beneficiary transferred just over $2m to Mills, who eventually kept $600,000. The prosecutors say the $600,000 was a bribe and that it was wrapped into the payment from Attanasio to disguise its origin. Mills says it was Attanasio's cash. This became the nub of the case.<lb/> What did Attanasio say?<lb/> He has not spoken to the press, but transcripts of his interrogation by prosecutors showed that he denied having authorised the $2m transfer. He said he had given Mills a free hand to manage some of his affairs offshore, including the setting up of the Bahamas-based trust from which the transfer was made. Attanasio said that, such was his confidence in Mills, he had even left him blank signed sheets of paper.<lb/> Are there links between Attanasio and Berlusconi?<lb/> None emerged at the trial.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">What evidence is there that the money came from Berlusconi?</hi><lb/> The only evidence prosecutors produced was the letter from Mills to his accountant, Bob Drennan. Auditors commissioned by the prosecutors to trace the flow of funds said: "Available documentation and analyses conducted do not allow [us] to identify the person who ordered the transaction".<lb/> What evidence has Mills produced that the money did not come from Berlusconi? <lb/> His lawyer laid several hundred documents before the court that Mills said provided a full explanation of how Attanasio obtained the money that he was later sent.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>