<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="James Richardson" categories="Football" date="2004-02-24" description="Serie A: AC Milan may have beaten hated rivals Inter to go five points clear, but owner Silvio Berlusconi is far from happy. James Richardson explains why." fingerprint="3c51126f9bf3f71f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European club football,Football,Sport,Silvio Berlusconi" title="James Richardson: Big mouth Berlusconi strikes again" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2004/feb/24/europeanfootball.sport">
<main>
<p>As any fool knows, Italian Prime Minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is both the owner of AC Milan and a man with far more pies than he has fingers to poke in them. He also has two enemies in life: communists and people who play football with only one striker up front.</p>
<p>Last Saturday night he took a break from battling the former to visit the San Siro for the Milan derby, only to come face to face with the latter, in the ample shape of his own Milan manager Carlo Ancelotti. And despite a 3-2 victory over neighbours Internazionale, Berlusconi was not best pleased.</p>
<p>"Tomorrow," Silvio icily revealed to the press post-game, "I'm going to write a letter to Ancelotti. It will not be a suggestion, but an order to him and all future managers of Milan. They must field two strikers, or resign."</p>
<p>And he's serious about it. A day later Berlusconi took to the airwaves of La Domenica Sportiva, a sexed-up Italian Match Of The Day, to claim: "The players agree with me. Permit me to point out that no club owner in the world has won as much as I have, so I know what I'm talking about. If Milan want to rival clubs like Real Madrid we must always take the field with the full might at our disposal. From now on, I want two strikers and Serginho in at left-back too. Otherwise Ancelotti will no longer be the manager of this club."</p>
<p>"I back Berlusconi 100%," chips in club vice-president Adriano Galliani who, in the family business that is Italy, also runs the Football League. "Let's add 'always two strikers' to the club crest."</p>
<p>Let's not. Milan had started Saturday's derby with Shevchenko as the lone striker, and by half-time were two goals down. Admittedly, the addition of Tomasson up front coincided with a remarkable turnaround - three second-half goals, including one from the Dane himself.</p>
<p>However, prior to the derby, Milan's amazing run of results had all been achieved with Shevchenko alone up front, backed by Rui Costa and Kakà. The line-up that sparked Saturday's controversy had in fact claimed seven straight wins - including a famous victory over Roma in Rome - and swept the Rossoneri to a five-point lead at the top of the table.</p>
<p>So Berlusconi's diktat now represents not just public humiliation but also a tactical nightmare for Ancelotti, the man who took Milan to the Champions League title just last May (not that Berlusconi hasn't taken credit for that win too - his office having recently leaked sketches of tactics and formations 'sent by the Premier to Ancelotti pre-game').</p>
<p>So far the manager's response has been typically measured: "I always listen to good advice," he told reporters. Still, he now faces a choice between sticking with his favoured formation or becoming the biggest yes-man since the man from Del Monte.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly the story is dominating talk in Italy, knocking events like Roma's 6-0 thrashing of Siena and Perugia's first win in 26 matches out of the headlines. "Berlusconi has made a serious mistake," says Bologna manager Carlo Mazzone, who added that "I've never met a club owner who knew anything about football."</p>
<p>A whopping 86% of Italians agree with him, according to the Gazzetta dello Sport's own survey. "It's his team, he can make them play with feathers in their bums if he likes," countered leading left-wing daily La Repubblica. "We wish he'd stop treating the rest of the country the same way." Ouch.</p>
<p>"Milan's biggest obstacle on the road to the title may yet be their president," was the ominous conclusion drawn by Mazzone, Serie A's longest-serving manager. Roma and Juventus certainly hope so. Meanwhile the next hurdle for the Rossoneri comes on Sunday, when Milan visit the decidedly in-form Lazio (a club whose manager, Roberto Mancini, is being linked with Inter again). Mercifully for Ancelotti, a return to the classic two-striker Milan formation is inevitable in this game as Kakà is suspended - but after that the Milan line-up is going to be very closely scrutinised indeed.</p>
<p>Particularly if that feathers-in-their-bums idea takes hold.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>