<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-04-27" description="Enrico Letta forms new administration, with Berlusconi ally Angelino Alfano as deputy prime minister" fingerprint="fcee5c1df5a3c76d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Italian elections 2013,World news,Enrico Letta" title="Italian coalition government unveiled after weeks of deadlock" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/apr/28/italy-coalition-berlusconi-letta-alfano">
<main>
<p>Two months after inconclusive parliamentary elections left the country paralysed, a new Italian government, including one of Silvio Berlusconi's closest allies as deputy prime minister, will be sworn in on Sunday.</p>
<p>Enrico Letta, the prime minister designate asked by President Giorgio Napolitano to form an administration last week, unveiled a list of ministers on Saturday who he said would form a grand coalition government. They will be voted on by parliament on Monday.</p>
<p>Angelino Alfano, the secretary of Berlusconi's centre-right Freedom People party (PdL), would be deputy prime minister and interior minister, said Letta – a victory for Berlusconi, the three-time former prime minister who just six months ago had been written off by many as being politically unsalvageable.</p>
<p>Alongside him in the new cabinet will be Fabrizio Saccomanni, the director-general of the Bank of Italy; Emma Bonino, a former European commissioner, as foreign minister; and Enrico Giovannini, the head of Italy's statistics agency Istat, as labour minister. The government, which brings together politicians from the centre-left, centre-right and centre, as well as technocrats, was described as the "only government possible" by Napolitano.</p>
<p>The elections in late February created a deadlock in the Italian parliament that had never been seen before, with a centre-left bloc of the Democratic party (PD) and its allies having a working majority in one house but not the other. Vying for control of the senate was a centre-right bloc led by the PdL, with Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement holding the balance of power. Pier Luigi Bersani, the then PD leader, refused to enter a grand coalition government with the centre-right. But he was forced to resign after weeks of wrangling and a disastrous presidential election. Letta, his deputy, took over the negotiations last week.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>