<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2007-04-17" description="John Hooper: Silvio Berlusconi has some powerful foreign chums, but why do so many of them have issues with civil liberties?" fingerprint="ff83041da182d6be" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Russia,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="A friend in need ..." url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2007/apr/17/silvioandmusculardemocracy">
<main>
<p>Vladimir Putin may be feeling a bit short of chums at the moment, what with the demonstrations in Moscow and St Petersburg, and Boris Berezovsky <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/frontpage/story/0,,2056322,00.html">telling the Guardian</ref> he is plotting to overthrow him.</p>
<p>So he will doubtless have been reassured to hear what his old friend Silvio Berlusconi has been <ref target="http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/04/15/europe/EU-GEN-Italy-Berlusconi-Putin.php">saying</ref> about recent events. The former Italian prime minister has been on a trip to Moscow where, among other things, he and Mr Putin visited a martial arts centre with Jean-Claude Van Damme (the "Muscles from Brussels" and star of such movies as Hard Target and Street Fighter).</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi subsequently assured reporters that freedom-loving Russians had nothing to worry about from their leader. Mr Putin, he said "believes in democracy", adding that "in him, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/russia">Russia</ref> has had a very positive guide". The leader of the Italian right dismissed the recent street demonstrations, claiming they had been "blown up a great deal".</p>
<p>But then Vladimir Putin is a key member of Silvio Berlusconi's circle of friends among foreign political leaders. The circle is small, but its members are extremely powerful.</p>
<p>Snubbed by many of his fellow-Europeans because of his conflicts of interest, his problems with the courts and his sometimes outrageous rhetoric, Mr Berlusconi has set about stitching together a network of personal friendships that allows him to claim he enjoys international respectability. Of a sort.</p>
<p>Mention the names of Vladimir Putin, George Bush and Ariel Sharon in the same breath as "human rights" and the response you get is likely to include such words and phrases as Chechnya, Guantanamo Bay, Abu Ghraib, Sabra and Chatila.</p>
<p>Another great Berlusconi chum is Turkey's prime minister, Recep Tayyip Erdogan. He may have burnished his credentials since coming into office, but just nine years ago Mr Erdogan was sufficiently convinced of the militant Islamist cause to have been reciting a poem that included the claim that the "mosques are our barracks".</p>
<p>It is one of the things his critics find most disconcerting about Silvio Berlusconi: the fact that so many of his soul mates either have an issue with civil liberties or represent a perceptibly authoritarian form of democracy.</p>
<p>He has another great pal among foreign leaders, who, like Mr Putin, has even brought the family for a holiday at the <ref target="http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/05/28/1085641716958.html">Berlusconi villa</ref> on Sardinia. Right now, though, I damned if I can remember his name.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>