<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roy Greenslade" categories="Media" date="2009-10-08" description="Scandals are good for newspaper sales, as Italian publishers are discovering in the continuing controversies involving the country's prime minister, and media mogul, Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="7aae408992cbf19c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Newspapers,Press freedom,Media,Europe" title="Roy Greenslade: Italian papers benefit from Berlusconi scandals" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2009/oct/08/silvio-berlusconi-italy">
<main>
<p>Scandals are good for newspaper sales, as Italian publishers are discovering during the continuing controversies swirling around the country's prime minister, and media mogul, <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>.</p>
<p>The paper making all the running, the Rome-based <hi rend="#b">La Repubblica</hi>, claims to be selling many more copies every day, as does the market leader, Milan-based <hi rend="#b">Corriere della Sera</hi>. The weekly news magazine,<hi rend="#b"> L'Espresso</hi>, has also enjoyed a sales boost.</p>
<p>"It's been a breath of fresh air for newspapers," said media analyst <hi rend="#b">Fabrizio Perretti</hi>, a professor at Bocconi University in Milan.</p>
<p>Alongside the circulation rises the publishers are celebrating unexpected share price increases. Despite the advertising slump, newspaper company shares are outperforming the the Italian stock exchange benchmark.</p>
<p>The downside is that papers are facing legal actions from Berlusconi, who claims they have libelled him. That, in turn, has prompted press freedom protests and petitions, again giving welcome publicity to the anti-Berlusconi papers.</p>
<p><hi rend="#i">Sources:</hi><ref target="http://www.followthemedia.com/index.php#tickle14">FollowTheMedia</ref>/<ref target="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601109&amp;sid=azk7siKA1cD4">Bloomberg</ref></p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>