<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-04-21" description="Tessa Jowell's estranged husband had been found guilty of taking bribe from Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="823f001d1f9b16d5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,David Mills,Tessa Jowell,World news" title="David Mills bribery case was thrown out on technicality, Italian court says" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/apr/21/david-mills-bribery-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Italy's highest appeals court today stated that when it quashed the conviction of Tessa Jowell's estranged husband David Mills earlier this year, on charges of taking a bribe from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, it did so because of a technicality and not because it believed him to be innocent.</p>
<p>The British lawyer had been rewarded for giving evidence that was crucial to the Italian prime minister's acquittal on a charge of bribing tax inspectors, the court said. But Mills could not be legitimately convicted because his offence had been "timed out" by a statute of limitations.</p>
<p>Mills was found guilty of taking a £390,000 bribe to perjure himself by omission in two trials in which Berlusconi was a defendant. Both his conviction and a jail sentence were upheld on a first appeal.</p>
<p>The court of cassation said the arguments used by the judges in the first appeal were "logical and coherent". Mills's counsel had failed to overturn the prosecution case, but had put forward a reading of the facts that was not "presentable" in a court of law, the judges said. Mills was hired by Berlusconi's Fininvest firm to create a network of offshore companies which it used for, among other things, the illegal funding of Italy's then-governing party.Mills has always maintained the use made of the companies was not his responsibility.</p>
<p>But the court of cassation said that, as an expert witness for the prosecution in the tax inspector bribery trial, he "had been reticent in answering questions concerning the ownership of Fininvest's offshore companies — with the result that the lack of conclusive evidence on [that] point had decided Silvio Berlusconi's acquittal".By distancing Berlusconi from personal involvement with the companies, Mills had enabled him to dodge tax and anti-trust legislation and hold on to "vast profits illicitly obtained abroad", some of which were passed to his children by his first marriage.</p>
<p>Jowell announced she was formally separating from her husband in March 2006, after accusations of bribery emerged against Mills.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>