<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Mark Tran" categories="World news" date="2004-12-30" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, today called for a special meeting of the world's eight leading industrialised countries to discuss their response to the Indian Ocean tsunami disaster." fingerprint="fdeec06e9c97f21c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Indian Ocean tsunami 2004,Italy,G8,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi calls for G8 tsunami talks" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/dec/30/tsunami2004.italy">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, today called for a special meeting of the world's eight leading industrialised countries to discuss their response to the Indian Ocean tsunami disaster.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's proposal for the emergency meeting came as the death toll from Sunday's tsunami climbed to more than 120,000. Aid agencies are struggling to carry out one of the biggest humanitarian exercises in history.</p>
<p>"I want to propose an extraordinary <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> meeting," Mr Berlusconi told reporters. "The meeting should discuss the organisation of aid and the possible reduction of debt."</p>
<p>The German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, yesterday said that the Paris Club of 19 creditor nations should consider letting Indonesia and Somalia delay debt repayments in order to help them recover.</p>
<p>"Before making the proposal, I want to talk to the other partners," Mr Berlusconi said, adding he would telephone Tony Blair later today. Britain takes over the presidency of the G8 this week.</p>
<p>Singapore's prime minister, Lee Hsien Loong, has called for an urgent meeting of leaders of Asean, the south-east Asian grouping, to coordinate relief efforts for victims of the tsunamis.</p>
<p>He said the meeting should also include other countries affected by the disaster and major aid donors - Japan, South Korea, China, the US and Australia - and international organisations such as the UN and the World Health Organisation.</p>
<p>Sixty nations have pledged more than $220m (£114.6m) in cash and hundreds of millions of dollars worth of emergency supplies. The International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies (IFRC) today launched an appeal for $59m.</p>
<p>"The scale of this disaster is growing by the hour. The devastation is unimaginable," the IFRC secretary general, Markku Niskala, said, adding that the money would provide emergency relief for two million people.</p>
<p>Oxfam said national aid groups were "rising to the challenge", but called on the UN to lead the way. "Given the scale and scope of this crisis, strong UN leadership is critical," Jasmine Whitbread, the international director of the charity, said.</p>
<p>The UN Secretary General, Kofi Annan, cut short a holiday to oversee the relief operation from New York. The UN will launch a major appeal on January 6.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>