<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2010-02-11" description="Roberto Mancini: Judges have been abused and threatened by the Italian premier for years – but now the judiciary is striking back" fingerprint="bee2d000b102d641" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi: a law unto himself | Roberto Mancini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/feb/11/berlusconi-judges-italian-premier">
<main>
<p>Last week, while Silvio Berlusconi and seven of his ministers were on a state visit to Israel and workers and trade unionists from Sardinia gathered noisily outside <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Chigi">Palazzo Chigi</ref> protesting against plans to close their factory, the House of Deputies debated and approved <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/03/italian-mps-berlusconi-trial-delay">yet another new law</ref> to protect the prime minister and his ministers from court appearances.</p>
<p>This came a few days after an unprecedented event in the history of the Italian republic. On 30 January, at the inauguration of the judicial year, hundreds of judges walked out of their courts in protest at the continual interference of the prime minister in the judicial system. Holding up copies of the Italian constitution – which contains the motto displayed on the walls of every Italian courtroom, "all are equal in the eyes of the law" – <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/8489253.stm">they filed out when a representative of the ministry of justice stood up to address them</ref>.</p>
<p>The protest was almost unanimous and was supported by the ANM (National Association of Magistrates). Even the independent magistrates joined in, although they disapproved of the method of protest, which they criticised as unnecessarily showy. But as regards the seriousness of the protest, the judges' solidarity was almost total.</p>
<p>Judges have been abused and threatened by Berlusconi for years. He has variously described them as <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metastasis">metastasis</ref>, mentally unstable, execution squads, red gowns and idlers. Finally, Italian judges wanted to express their dissent. They might not have all agreed on the strategy adopted to manifest their objections, but were united about the contents of the protest.</p>
<p>What is happening in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>? In short, the executive power is using its legislative power to obstruct the power of the judiciary.</p>
<p>The premier's judicial problems weigh heavily on the country; he is at the heart of various investigations which his government and its allies regularly define as "political persecutions", endorsing the ridiculous theory that Berlusconi is the victim of politically influenced judges.</p>
<p>As Massimo Gramellini, assistant editor of the Torino daily <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/redazione/default.asp">La Stampa</ref>, wrote:</p>
<quote>The idea that power goes hand in hand with responsibility is typical of Protestant nations. In Italy with its various 'mafie' and 'dignitaries' the opposite preconception is in force: power and wealth are safe-conduct passes allowing you to do whatever you like on a large scale and without any shame – doing what other poorer souls do on a smaller scale – stealing, lying, cheating.</quote>
<p>And as Marco Travaglio at <ref target="http://antefatto.ilcannocchiale.it/glamware/blogs/blog.aspx?id_blog=96578">Fatto Quotidiano</ref> opportunely reminded readers, "in other democracies, if a magistrate puts a politician on trial, the politician resigns. In Italy it's either the trial itself or the judge that disappears".</p>
<p>Since Berlusconi has just visited Israel, Travaglio recalled the <ref target="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1007094.html">farewell speech</ref> Olmert, the former Israeli prime minister, had made to the Knesset in August 2008:</p>
<quote>I am proud to belong to a state in which the premier can be investigated just like a common citizen. A premier cannot be above the law, nor can he be below it. If I have to choose between the awareness of being innocent and the fact that, if I stayed in office I could seriously embarrass the country I love and which I have the honour to represent, then I have no doubts: I will stand down because even the prime minister must be judged like others. I will show that the accusations against me are unfounded as an ordinary citizen.</quote>
<p>Sadly, Italian politicians rarely ask themselves if they are an embarrassment to their country. I'm certain that Berlusconi never does.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>