<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Mark Sweney; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Media" date="2007-08-22" description="Mondadori, the magazine publisher controlled by Silvio Berlusconi, is reported to have expressed interest in Emap's £700m consumer magazine division. By Mark Sweney." fingerprint="1907865e5732c1f4" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media business,Media,Business,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Berlusconi's Mondadori linked to Emap buy-up" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/aug/22/citynews.business">
<main>
<p>Mondadori, the Italian magazine publisher controlled by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has expressed interest in buying Emap's £700m consumer magazine division, according to a report today.</p>
<p>The Italian publisher and Lagardere-owned Hachette Filipacchi, whose British operations are run by former Emap chief executive Kevin Hand, have asked for a sales memorandum from UK radio and magazine business, according to today's Times.</p>
<p>Mondadori bought up Emap's struggling French publishing business for £380m in June last year.</p>
<p>Both companies had previously been <ref target="http://media.theguardian.com/city/story/0,,2137943,00.html">touted by analysts</ref> as prime candidates for Emap's consumer magazine division, which includes titles such as Heat, Closer, Grazia and FHM.</p>
<p>Emap is conducting a strategic review of its operation with suitors circling its three divisions - business-to-business publishing, consumer magazines and radio.</p>
<p>Reed Elsevier, United Business Media, and Informa have are reported to have requested information on the <ref target="http://media.theguardian.com/city/story/0,,2137943,00.html">£1.3bn business-to-business operation</ref>, as had been speculated by analysts.</p>
<p>UBM owns a division called CMP, whose management includes former Emap finance director Gary Hughes.</p>
<p>Venture capitalist group Chaterhouse has also reportedly asked for information on Emap's business unit.</p>
<p>GCap Media and Charles Allen's Global Radio have been named as firms that could be interested in Emap's radio operation.</p>
<p>However, analysts describe the radio division - valued conservatively as worth around £360m - as difficult due to a "hostile" regulatory environment for trade buyers such as GCap.</p>
<p>GCap, with the likes of Capital Radio and Xfm, and Global Radio with Heart FM, have geographical overlaps with Emap's radio station networks, which include Kiss and Magic.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 7278 2332.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>