<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Alexander Chancellor" categories="Opinion" date="2011-02-11" description="Alexander Chancellor: Despite everything, Silvio Berlusconi is still in office. His secret? He has 'the sun in his pocket'" fingerprint="3652802ef245d3cd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" title="Berlusconi – the master salesman | Alexander Chancellor" url="http://www.theguardian.com/global/2011/feb/11/berlusconi-master-salesman-alexander-chancellor">
<main>
<p>Whatever else <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> may be, he is unquestionably a master salesman. When he was building his media empire, long before he had even thought of going into politics, he had strict rules for the team selling advertising for his Italian television channels. They were, like him, to have "the sun in their pockets". They were to exude optimism and courtesy. They were forbidden to smoke, or have long hair, or beards, or even moustaches. Their breath was to be fresh, and their scalps free of dandruff. They were never to take off their jackets when with a client, or to put their briefcases on his table. Above all, there were to be no sweaty handshakes.</p>
<p>With these instructions, his salesmen went on to make him the richest man in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, with a fortune estimated 10 years ago at getting on for £8bn; and later to cap that already enormous achievement by selling him to the Italian people as their political leader, one who has since served longer in office than any other since Mussolini. One of the ways they achieved this was by portraying Berlusconi, in contrast to the sleazy, corrupt politicians who had preceded him, as a clean and honest man who, like Margaret Thatcher in Britain, would lift from the individual the deadweight of state regulation and bureaucracy and inaugurate a new era of open, efficient government. Remarkably, despite the allegations against him of bribery, corruption, tax evasion and mafia connections (not to mention those of "bunga bunga" sex games with teenagers), that reputation has not entirely evaporated.</p>
<p>Despite everything, Berlusconi still has the sun in his pocket. Addressing political rallies, he always looks hopeful, confident, and in charge. He dismisses all the accusations against him as petty politicking by embittered people of the left. And despite the mounds of evidence assembled by police and prosecutors, opinion polls show that 30% of Italians agree with him that he is a victim of unjust judicial persecution. The polls show that the sex scandals have caused his popularity to fall substantially, but at 28.6% he remains ahead of any other Italian party leader, and his ruling coalition is level-pegging at 39.5% with the opposition coalition of the left. Cameron and Clegg would be very happy with that.</p>
<p>A large majority thinks that Berlusconi should submit to questioning by the Milanese prosecutors (having so far refused on the grounds that they are biased against him and, anyway, don't have jurisdiction over the case), but despite this most Italians don't believe that his time as prime minister is up. Only 13% think that the claim that he illegally paid for sex with an underage prostitute will end his career, while 26% think the whole thing is a storm in a teacup and will be forgotten in a matter of days. A further 24% say they expect the allegation to boomerang against the currently cock-a-hoop opposition and actually boost Berlusconi's standing with the electorate.</p>
<p>On my visits to Italy, I have been surprised by how much Berlusconi is still admired. He may have fallen from grace among many women and Catholics, but most men, apart from those of the left, seem still to like him well enough. In Britain he would probably be resented for his wealth alone, but in Italy it works in his favour. He is lauded for giving work to thousands of people in his media empire, and his riches are seen as a guarantee that he will govern in the national interest rather than his own. If Blair and Reagan were Teflon leaders, Berlusconi is surely one in a class all his own.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Coming out of the kitchen</hi>
</head>
<p>A friend and neighbour of mine, who is an excellent cook, was telling me the other day that she hates cooking and believes that many other women feel the same. I find it hard to understand why anyone should hate something he or she is particularly good at, but it apparently can be the case.</p>
<p>My friend's reason for hating cooking is that it is hard work and, in the case of women, not greatly appreciated. Women, she says, are seen as nature's nurturers and assumed to be good at such domestic duties. It is expected that they will be good cooks; and if they are not, they are failures. For men, it is the opposite. A man who cooks well, or even cooks at all, is regarded as a rarity and even something of a marvel. I remember that my father once boiled an egg and received huge applause as a result.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">An ill wind</hi>
</head>
<p>I've had a bit of flak from some Guardian readers for objecting to a project for a wind farm on my doorstep in Northamptonshire. I may have made rather too much of the fact that it would be beside two Inigo Jones pavilions of which I am the custodian, for to some people this may have suggested privileged nimbyism and selfish indifference to the greater good. My point about the pavilions, which are open to the public, was that it would be inconsistent of the government to have subsidised the restoration of these previously derelict buildings and then to subsidise the ruination of their rural setting.</p>
<p>Be that as it may, the questions surrounding wind farms are far wider and deeper than their potential effect on any historic building, and one of them is whether it is a good idea to redistribute wealth to the rich from the poor. For it is the poor who must subsidise the huge profits of landowners and energy companies with their much-inflated electricity bills.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>