<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Andrew Sparrow" categories="Politics" date="2008-09-10" description="Andrew Sparrow: Silvio Berlusconi - hero of the left. That's not the way the bandana-wearing plutocrat is normally perceived, but that's the impression the Italian prime minister created at a slightly surreal press conference with Gordon Brown this afternoon" fingerprint="3fbe813f9ba2d50d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Gordon Brown,Energy bills,Italy,Politics,Tax and spending,UK news,World news,Economic policy,Trade unions,Business,Money,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi embarrasses Gordon Brown over windfall tax" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/blog/2008/sep/10/gordonbrown.energy">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi - hero of the left. That's not the way the bandana-wearing plutocrat is normally perceived, but that's the impression the Italian prime minister created at a slightly surreal press conference with Gordon Brown this afternoon.</p>
<p>Although Brown has all but ruled out a windfall tax on energy companies, it turns out that his rightwing Italian counterpart has had no qualms about introducing one of his own. It is known as the <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/a5a4518a-4150-11dd-9661-0000779fd2ac.html">Robin Hood tax</ref>, and, according to Berlusconi, it's gone down a storm.</p>
<p>"We resorted to this in order to do something about the balance sheets of those companies that have profited from rises in gas and oil prices in particular," Berlusconi said.</p>
<p>"We did so in order to create an aid fund for our citizens who were more exposed to increases in prices, particularly in food prices. We have a social card that uses funds from this particular tax, which is a temporary tax. It has been very well-received by the very companies concerned."</p>
<p>As Berlusconi boasted away, like a Mediterranean version of Derek Simpson, Brown had that smile on his face that suggests he's squirming underneath. On one of the key policy issues of the day, Berlusconi is adopting a stance that's more in tune with the desires of the TUC and Labour than the party's own prime minister.</p>
<p>Was Berlusconi doing it deliberately, just to have a bit of fun (because he could always have said something about how economic circumstances are different in the two countries etc)? Or was he just oblivious to Labour sensitivities on this issue? I don't know.</p>
<p>But Berlusconi was certainly in playful mood. When James Landale from the BBC asked him why Italy was 65th in a World Bank list of best places to do business, behind Jamaica, Peru and Turkey, he started rambling on about Italy having more TV sets and mobile phones than any other country in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, a high number of cars, 72% of Europe's stock of works of art, 100,000 churches, 3,500 museums, 2,500 archaeological sites and a world-class football team.</p>
<p>So there, Turkey.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>