<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-10" description="John Hooper: In the dullest election for years, Silvio Berlusconi looks set to return as Italy's prime minister" fingerprint="679082ad5a03478f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Sleepwalking to victory" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/10/sleepwalkingtovictory">
<main>
<p>It is not often a country like Italy - nearly as big as Britain or France - gets to within four days of a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy">general election</ref> having generated so little excitement.</p>
<p>The campaign leading to Sunday's ballot has been notably lacklustre. One reason is that the vote will be held under a <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Italy#New_electoral_system_.282005-.29">singularly dreadful form of proportional representation</ref> that leaves the decision as to who gets into parliament largely to the parties, rather than the electors. Another reason, though, is that the outcome is widely regarded as a foregone conclusion.</p>
<p>Nothing has emerged since the earliest stages of the campaign to overturn the view that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy.italy">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> will be the next prime minister. The latest polls gave him a 5%-9% lead.</p>
<p>This is a remarkable state of affairs. At 71, Berlusconi, like US presidential candidate John McCain, is labouring under a handicap because of his age. And, more to the point, he was voted from office just two years ago by an electorate disillusioned by his failure to deliver on his promises.</p>
<p>He is up against an opponent, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy1">Walter Veltroni</ref>, who is almost 20 years younger. Berlusconi's rival not only has experience of government (in the 1990s, as deputy prime minister to Romano Prodi) but, as mayor of Rome, made a credible fist of running the capital.</p>
<p>Why has he not been able to break through? The most obvious reason is that, as the new leader of the centre-left, he is saddled with the legacy of Prodi's last government. Its long-term plan was fair enough - to get the public finances in order by raising taxes and then cut them as part of a wider scheme to reanimate the economy. The problem was that Prodi only got through the first bit before his government fell on January 24.</p>
<p>Perhaps a more colourful figure might have been able to step out of the last prime minister's shadow. But, though unquestionably dynamic, Walter Veltroni gives an impression of being rather lugubrious. And while making reasoned, intelligent points in a reasoned, intelligent way, he is not exactly an electrifying speaker.</p>
<p>Just as importantly, he tends instinctively to hug the middle ground, always looking for points of balance and areas of compromise. That makes him an ideal leader of the new <ref target="http://www.partitodemocratico.it/">Democratic Party</ref>, a broad church that spans a range from Roman Catholic pro-lifers to barely repentant former Communists. But not perhaps the man to block Berlusconi.</p>
<p>The "perhaps" is still advisable, though. The latest polls are 10 days old. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> bans the publication of polling results in the final two weeks of a campaign. And what we know that this time there were unusually large numbers of undecided voters. There is still room for an upset on polling day. I just wouldn't put my money on it.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>