<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-09-29" description="The former prime minister declares he is 'ready to take up the battle' despite signs of rebellion in his own party" fingerprint="feb2489db6239365" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news,Italian elections 2013,Politics,Eurozone crisis,European Union,European monetary union,Economics,European banks,Euro,Five Star Movement" title="Silvio Berlusconi calls for fresh Italian elections 'as soon as possible'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/29/silvio-berlusconi-calls-italian-elections-soon-as-possible">
<main>
<p>An embattled but bellicose <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> called on Sunday for fresh Italian elections to be held as soon as possible, even as signs of rebellion in his own party grew and the country's president indicated that the country would only return to the polls as a last resort.</p>
<p>In a drastic and much-criticised move that reignited fears for the health of the eurozone's third-largest economy, the former prime minister and centre-right leader announced on Saturday he was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/28/italy-berlusconi-withdraws-ministers-coalition">pulling his ministers out of Enrico Letta's ever-fraught grand coalition government</ref>.</p>
<p>On Sunday in a telephone address to supporters of his Freedom People (PdL) party on his 77th birthday, Berlusconi declared he was "ready to take up the battle again". He said: "The only way is to proceed with conviction to elections as soon as possible. All the opinion polls tell us that we will win."</p>
<p>One of his keenest supporters, former topless model and former equal opportunities minister Mara Carfagna, lauded him with a phrase attributed to Albert Einstein: "Great spirits have always encountered violent opposition from mediocre minds."</p>
<p>Most of the media delivered scathing verdicts on the billionaire politician's gambit and, in a wry joke at a peace conference organised by the community of Sant'Egidio, Letta asked the audience to say "some prayers for Italy". The prime minister is expected to address parliament early this week.</p>
<p>Worryingly for Berlusconi, much of the criticism came from within his own party, which <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/18/silvio-berlusconi-politics">he recently relaunched as Forza Italia</ref>.</p>
<p>Four of the five ministers whose resignations were announced on Saturday voiced misgivings about the centre-right's direction, which Beatrice Lorenzin, outgoing health minister, described as tending towards "a radical right".</p>
<p>The most stinging blow came from Angelino Alfano, Berlusconi's right-hand man, who has been acting as deputy prime minister and interior minister in the Letta coalition. He said that if Forza Italia were to be dominated by "extreme positions", he would have to be "a Berlusconi-ite in a different way".</p>
<p>Perhaps in view of this highly unusual dissent, the three-time prime minister later issued a statement appearing to soften his stance and said the PdL would support a 2014 budget next month if it was "truly useful" to Italy.</p>
<p>Berlusconi blamed his decision to withdraw support from Letta's government on what he said was a failure to pass economic measures − notably a postponement of a sales tax hike due to take effect this week. Keen to point the finger at the centre-left Democratic Party (PD) for the crisis, the Berlusconi family newspaper Il Giornale headlined its website "Letta brings down the government".</p>
<p>The prime minister from the PD gave this suggestion short shrift, saying that Berlusconi was motivated "exclusively" by his own affairs.</p>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/14/silvio-berlusconi-conviction-respected">Berlusconi suffered his first definitive conviction</ref> in two decades of legal tussles on 1 August, and the ensuing sentence for tax fraud ratcheted up tension on the fragile coalition formed in late April.</p>
<p>A senate committee vote due on Friday is expected to strip him of his seat in the senate, and by mid-October he will have to decide whether he wants to serve his sentence under house arrest or in community service.</p>
<p>Some analysts saw the decision to pull the plug on the government as the last roll of the dice for a life-long gambler who felt the trap closing in. However, they said, it is a big gamble.</p>
<p>Returning to Rome from Naples (SUNday)on Sunday night before a crucial meeting with Letta, president Giorgio Napolitano reiterated his desire to find an alternative parliamentary majority for a Letta government. Engaged in frantic number-crunching and horse-trading, some senior PD figures said they were optimistic that such a solution could be found.</p>
<p>The February election that led to a prolonged period of political uncertainty gave the centre-left bloc a commanding majority in the lower house of parliament but a wafer thin lead in the senate, or upper house. To ensure Letta a workable majority, extra support would have to be secured from rebellious senators in, for instance, the anti-establishment <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/five-star-movement">Five Star Movement</ref> and PdL.</p>
<p>But, if this proves impossible, Italy might eventually have to return to the polls. "It is tradition for the president to dissolve parliament early when it isn't possible to create a majority and a government for the good of the country," acknowledged Napolitano.</p>
<p>The shockwaves sent through Italy's already fragile political landscape raised <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/26/us-debt-ceiling-fears-loom-over-markets-live">fears of a rise in Italy's borrowing costs</ref> at the opening of markets (MON)on Monday morning.</p>
<p>Fabrizio Saccomanni, the economy minister, sought to play down those fears, telling business daily Il Sole 24 Ore he had faith in the credibility which he said Italy had built up in recent months.</p>
<p>"And I also think the uncertainty connected to the government's instability has been largely already factored in during the last few weeks," he said.</p>
<p>But with unemployment at 12%- − nearly 40% among young people − and a public debt of €2tn (£1.75tn), Italy's recession-mired economy is in desperate need of decisive government.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>