<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2011-11-04" description="Prime minister insists Italy is in good health, with debts under control, and points to full restaurants as proof of strength" fingerprint="3fa4ca3fd031c751" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,International Monetary Fund (IMF),Europe,World news,G20,Economics,Global economy,Business,Eurozone crisis,European banks" title="Silvio Berlusconi shrugs off IMF's financial checks on Italy" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/04/silvio-berlusconi-imf-italy">
<main>
<p/>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi insisted Italy has no financial problems – even as its cost of borrowing rose to dangerously high levels and the president, Giorgio Napolitano, warned that the country is undergoing its worst crisis since the second world war.</p>
<p>As fears rose that the euro crisis is spreading to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and the embattled prime minister's majority continued to crumble, Berlusconi put on a typically upbeat performance in Cannes, defying reports of his political demise and denying that a planned IMF check-up on his reform programme was a humiliating limitation on his sovereignty.</p>
<p>Berlusconi insisted Italy was in rude financial health, with its debts under control, pointing to full restaurants as proof of its economic strength.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister said he had turned down an offer from the International Monetary Fund to extend Italy a line of credit. He also insisted he had asked inspectors from the IMF to monitor economic reforms demanded by the EU and which he promised will be voted through parliament by the end of the month.</p>
<p>The visits, to take place every three months, will start next week, said EU commission president José Manuel Barroso, who will be joining the IMF team to see for himself that Berlusconi carries out the measures he listed to EU leaders in Brussels last month to help to stave off Europe's worsening debt crisis.</p>
<p>Berlusconi likened the visits to a regular company audit which would prove he was on the right track. However, IMF managing director Christine Lagarde said the move was prompted by Italy's "lack of credibility" over reform, while the country's opposition Democratic party called the move "an abdication of sovereignty".</p>
<p>Francesco Rutelli, the head of the centrist Alliance for Italy party, said the country had been "put into administration" by the decision, and pointed out that Berlusconi has yet to fully reveal the reforms. "The government turned up in Cannes empty handed and the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g20">G20</ref> said: 'Enough, we're sending the inspectors.'"</p>
<p>News of the IMF visit appeared to do little to assuage the markets, however, as yields on 10-year Italian bonds hit a euro lifetime high of 6.43%.</p>
<p>Berlusconi admitted that changes to the labour market – a key plank in his reform programme – were missing from the measures he is seeking to put to a confidence vote in the Italian senate on 15 November.</p>
<p>Tough decisions on making hiring and firing easier will require talks with employers and unions first, he said. "I've dreamed all my life of making these reforms to the economy, but it hasn't been possible because of the socialists and communists," he reportedly said in a meeting at Cannes. Berlusconi will also face opposition from Italy's lawyers to moves to open up the country's professional guilds to greater competition.</p>
<p>Signs of Berlusconi's faltering authority at home were evident at his G20 press conference as his treasury minister, Giulio Tremonti, ducked questions over whether he had asked Berlusconi to resign.</p>
<p>As former loyalists confirmed their defections in Rome on Friday, leaving Berlusconi's majority uncertain, defence under-secretary Guido Crosetto said: "I don't know how many days or weeks the government has left. Certainly a majority relying on a few votes cannot continue for long."</p>
<p>Berlusconi, however, denied Italy is in financial dire straits, claiming restaurants were full and it was hard to find seats on planes. "Our budget deficit is half of France's and can be wiped out by 2013," he added.</p>
<p>"Berlusconi has no idea that his fairy tales will not save the country, but will leave Italy at the mercy of speculators," said Giorgio Conte, a backer of Berlusconi's former ally Gianfranco Fini.</p>
<p>"Berlusconi should try and stick his nose outside his villa at Arcore, between one party and another and maybe he would see the serious economic crisis afflicting the country," said Leoluca Orlando, spokesman for the opposition Italy of Values party.</p>
<p>The prime minister said he was confident of wooing back into the fold dissident MPs who have threatened to desert him this week.</p>
<p>He added: "I feel obliged to continue because I do not see in Italy a personality able to represent the interests of the country internationally."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>