<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Larry Elliott; Patrick Wintour" categories="World news" date="2009-07-09" description="Silvio Berlusconi calls personal chef to prepare six-course feast for G8 leaders in L'Aquila" fingerprint="2e1841c79fe7810d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="G8,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Food,Life and style,Europe" title="G8 summit: forget famine, here's the lamb" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/09/g8-leaders-menu">
<main>
<p>Forget climate change. Leave to one side what the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> says about nuclear proliferation or free trade. As usual, much of the talk tonight was not about what the leaders of the west were doing to help end global famine, but what they were shovelling down their throats.</p>
<p>While the dinner was not quite as lavish as the 25-course banquet put on by Japan last year, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> called in his personal chef, "il famoso" Michele Persechini, to prepare a sumptuous six-course feast washed down by half a dozen fine wines.</p>
<p>The meal got off to "il famoso's" take on the salad caprese beloved of Italian trattorias around the world. After the warm tomato salad with cheese, it was time for miniature macaroni with ragu before the centrepiece of the dinner – roasted lamb with beans and summer truffles from the Sangro hills accompanied by aubergines, green beans and roast potatoes.</p>
<p>Next there were cheeses, then a sweet pizza desert made with almonds, and for those still peckish a selection of local <hi rend="#i">celluci</hi> biscuits.</p>
<p>The sommelier favoured local wines in the spirit of solidarity after April's earthquake. Leaders sipped a Montepulciano d'Abruzzo before Berlusconi poured Barack Obama a glass of Cerasuolo Hedos Cantina Tollo 2008, the president's favourite wine. A Quindi Trebbiano d'Abruzzo, an Il Villa Gemma Montepulciano, a Plaisir bianco 2008 and a Montepulciano d'Abruzzo Colline finished off the list.</p>
<p>Adrian Lovett of Save the Children said: "More than one billion people are going hungry. Given the poor performance of the leaders at this summit, they don't deserve their dinner."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>