<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Alexander Chancellor" categories="Opinion" date="2010-06-04" description="Alexander Chancellor: A third of young Italians are jobless in the cash-strapped state" fingerprint="6f8f93d31583d71b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Media,News of the World" title="Alexander Chancellor: Italy's Republic Day celebrates a nation founded on work. Pity so many of its citizens don't have any" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/jun/04/alexander-chancellor-italy-unemployment-recession1">
<main>
<p>For reasons I have never understood, article one of the Italian constitution reads: "Italy is a republic founded on work." What kind of a principle is that on which to found a republic? Freedom? Equality? Justice? Maybe. But work? Work is just something people do, with varying degrees of enthusiasm; not an ideal for a society to pursue.</p>
<p>In any case, it was poignant that the national holiday celebrating the birth of this republic founded on work should have coincided this week with the country's worst unemployment figures in nearly a decade, showing that almost a third of young people in Italy now have no work at all (compared with nearly 18% in Britain).</p>
<p>Republic Day, held on the anniversary of the 1946 referendum that narrowly chose to abolish the monarchy, is Italy's main patriotic festival – which was why, annoyingly, everything turned out to be shut when I tried to go shopping in Tuscany on Wednesday. The holiday is marked on 2 June each year by a grand military parade in Rome that includes a fly-past of jet planes leaving trails of red, white and green, the colours of the Italian flag, over the eternal city. This year, because of the country's dismal economic state, the parade was more low-key than usual, and one newspaper carried a front-page cartoon featuring a march-past of "troops of the unemployed" under a headline reading: "Festival of the Republic founded on work."</p>
<p>To save money, the parade was shorter than it used to be, and did not include any tanks or other tracked vehicles, thus sparing the Colosseum the vibrations that had been thought to threaten its stability. Reviewing the parade were <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, seldom off his mobile phone, and the president of the Republic, 85-year-old former communist Giorgio Napolitano. His Republic Day message was a Cameronesque call for national unity in confronting an economic crisis, and for fairly apportioned sacrifices that would spare the weakest and most vulnerable. The Italian president, I should add, has gone even further than Cameron in setting an example of frugality at the top, by allowing his 75-year-old wife Clio to travel around Rome unescorted on crowded public buses.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">How can entrapment be in the public interest?</hi>
</p>
<p>Edward Terry, the father of the Chelsea and England footballer John Terry, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2010/jun/01/news-of-the-world-john-terry">has been let off with a suspended sentence</ref> after supplying cocaine to a News of the World reporter, because a judge concluded that "the offence has effectively been created by the actions of a newspaper". This is exactly what I felt about the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/law/2010/may/25/sarah-ferguson-public-interest-defence">Duchess of York's recent entrapment by the NoW's celebrated "fake sheikh", Mazher Mahmood</ref>. She asked him for £500,000 in exchange for access to her former husband, Prince Andrew, and was duly exposed for this shameful request. It is, though, inconceivable such a request would have been made at all had not Mahmood – this time posing as an Arab businessman – invited it.</p>
<p>Fergie may be greedy, stupid, disloyal or any of the other nasty things that are said about her, but it is impossible to imagine her taking the initiative in trying to sell access to Britain's decidedly unglamorous Special Representative for International Trade and Investment. Why would she have imagined that anybody would want to pay for such a thing? And whom would she have dared to approach with such a scandalous proposal?</p>
<p>As Judge Christopher Mitchell said of Edward Terry at his trial in Basildon, Fergie was a clear victim of entrapment, and her offence was also "effectively created by the actions of a newspaper". I not only disagree with the NoW's claims that it is in the public interest to expose offences that would never have taken place without its involvement; I think the newspaper should be stopped from creating any more of them. For one thing, it is scandalous that Mahmood's identity should be so studiously protected. On the contrary, his likeness should be displayed on posters throughout the land, as a warning to the gullible to be prepared.</p>
<p>In her interview with Oprah Winfrey on US television, Fergie said she had been "a huge, over-trusting, idiotic, stupid woman" for falling for Mahmood's scam. But I think I can now see why she might reasonably have done so. A clue lies in the explanation of Vinod Khosla, an Indian-born Californian computer billionaire, as to why he has just hired Tony Blair as an expensive consultant to his company: "Tony's going to help us in many areas that techie nerds like us in Silicon Valley don't understand."</p>
<p>That tells us what the consultancy business is all about. Experts in one field fear they don't know who's who and what's what in any other field, and this insecurity impels them to hire a supposed man-of-the-world like Blair to show them the ropes and tell them how to get on in unfamiliar company.</p>
<p>Mahmood's modus operandi is especially clever because it plays, I fear, on western prejudices about Arabs. Even so, did Fergie really think that anyone could be stupid enough to believe a relationship with Prince Andrew is worth paying money for?</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>