<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Politics" date="2009-02-17" description="Full text of the British lawyer's letter to Bob Drennan, describing a payment he received" fingerprint="3f0d915633a7b5db" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Tessa Jowell,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Law,World news,Politics,David Mills,Europe" title="David Mills's letter to his accountant" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-berlusconi-trial-letter">
<main>
<p>Dear Bob,</p>
<p>The brief relevant facts are these.</p>
<p>In 1996 I ended up with a dividend from Mr B's companies of around £1.5m after all the tax and fees had been paid.</p>
<p>This was all done on a personal basis: I took the risk, and kept my partners right out of it.</p>
<p>Wisely or otherwise, I informed my partners what I had done and, since it was a substantial windfall, offered to pay them (I think) around £50,000 or £100,000 each as what I though [sic] was a pretty generous gesture.</p>
<p>Which shows you how you can be, as they insisted the transaction should be treated as a partnership profit. To avoid litigation (we had just merged with Withers) I agreed to put the money on deposit in my bank until they were satisfied that there would be no third part claim.</p>
<p>By 2000 it was clear there would be no claim (I knew that all along) and the money was taken off deposit and paid out; I kept just under £500,000 out of what was then getting on for £2m.</p>
<p>So all that risk and cost for not very much. The greatest cost was leaving Withers. I was not asked to leave it, but felt so uncomfortable there, not least because my Mackenzie Mills partners had taken most of the benefit for none of the risk, that I really couldn't stay.</p>
<p>I spent 1998, 1999 and 2000 as a sole practitioner, and it was evident that the trials were going on, there would be lawyers to pay and there was always the risk of being charged with something – which is actually about to happen now as a result of the latest investigation, which you know about.</p>
<p>I kept in close touch with the B people, and they knew my circumstances.</p>
<p>They knew, in particular, how my partners had taken most of the dividend; they also knew quite how much the way in which I had been able to give my evidence (I told no lies, but I turned some very tricky corners, to put it mildly) had kept Mr B out of a great deal of trouble that I would have landed him in if I had said all I knew.</p>
<p>At around the end of 1999, I was told I would receive money, which I could treat as a long term loan or a gift. $600,000 was put in a hedge fund and I was told it would be there if I needed it. (It was put in the fund because the person connected to the B organisations was someone I had discussed this fund with on many occasions, and it was a round about way of making the money available.)</p>
<p>For obvious reasons of their own (I was at that stage still a prosecution witness, but my evidence had been given) it needed to be done discreetly. And this was a roundabout way.</p>
<p>At the end of 2000 I wanted to invest in another fund, and my bank made a loan of the amount, secured on my house etc., of around €650,000. I paid it off by liquidating the $600,000. I attach a copy of the dollar account.</p>
<p>I regarded the payment as a gift. What else could it be? I wasn't employed, I wasn't acting for them, I wasn't doing anything for them, I had already given my evidence, but there was certainly the risk of future legal costs (as there have been) and a great deal of anxiety (as there certainly have been).</p>
<p>This has been going on for more than eight years now. My contract was aware of how my income earning capacity had been damaged, and in 1998 and 1999 I was able to send bills from my practice to certain companies, which were paid and increased my income. But this was different.</p>
<p>Because I was pretty sure my CGT [capital gains tax] position was negative overall, I stupidly made no returns on my transactions. If they are closely looked at (ie, where did the money come from to buy the centurion shares?), I am obviously concerned about what to do and how this should best be handled.</p>
<p>I attach the key documents.</p>
<p>Yours sincerely</p>
<p>David Mills</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>