<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Fiona Winward; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-06-18" description="Italian prime minister denies women were paid to attend parties as prosecutors investigate claims" fingerprint="e6e00a2c3683c3e9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,G8,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi in fresh row over female escorts" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/18/silvio-berlusconi-female-escorts-row">
<main>
<p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, launched a desperate attempt today to fend off claims that female escorts were paid to attend parties at his official residence. It was the latest in a series of allegations regarding his private life,</p>
<p>Earlier this week, prosecutors shelved an investigation into the alleged misuse of state aircraft to ferry showgirls and musicians to parties at Berlusconi's Sardinian villa, but fresh allegations have broken out regarding the prime minister and alleged recruitment of women.</p>
<p>Yesterday Berlusconi said claims that women were hired to attend gatherings in Sardinia and at his official residence in Rome were "rubbish" and an attempt to smear his image before next month's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit that he will host.</p>
<p>The prime minister is already in the middle of a public divorce battle with his wife, Veronica Lario, who said she could not stay with a man who "frequents minors", after he attended the 18th birthday party of a Naples schoolgirl and aspiring model, Noemi Letizia, in April. Today, he attempted to defuse the latest row.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's lawyer, Niccolò Ghedini, rubbished the allegations peppered across the front pages of all Italian newspapers. "He does not need people to bring him women," he told the newspaper Corriere della Sera. "It seems a bit over the top to think that Berlusconi needs to pay €2,000 for a girl to go with him. He could have them in large numbers for free."</p>
<p>Public prosecutors in the southern city of Bari said they were investigating whether payments allegedly made to at least four women by a local entrepreneur, Giampaolo Tarantini, to attend parties "in exclusive locations in Rome and Sardinia" were an "induction into prostitution".</p>
<p>The case arose from wiretapped conversations collected during a separate business corruption inquiry in which Tarantini allegedly negotiated payments and travel arrangements with the women. Corriere della Sera on Wednesday published an interview with one of the women, a 42-year-old former model and television showgirl, Patrizia D'Addario, who claimed she had been asked to attend a party at Berlusconi's Rome residence, Palazzo Grazioli, in October last year.</p>
<p>"I said they would have to pay me and we agreed on €2,000," she said.</p>
<p>D'Addario said she was flown from Bari and put up in a luxury hotel ahead of the party at Palazzo Grazioli, where she and around 20 other women drank champagne until Berlusconi arrived.</p>
<p>"He showed us videos of his meeting with [President George] Bush and photos of his [Sardinian] villa. He sang and told jokes," she said, adding she "realised she had made an impression" on him. However, she said she returned to her hotel for the night and was paid only €1,000 "because I didn't stay". She claimed she was invited back with two other women several weeks later on the night of the US presidential election, on which occasion she claimed Berlusconi asked her to stay.</p>
<p>D'Addario said on both evenings she made secret audio recordings in which the prime minister's voice could be heard. Magistrates are examining these.</p>
<p>Denying the allegations in a terse statement, Berlusconi said: "Once again the newspapers are filled with rubbish and falsehoods. I will not allow this aggression to affect me and will continue to work, as always, for the good of the country". Ghedini told Corriere della Sera that even if the allegations were true, Berlusconi would be an "unwitting party" who "could not have known" that the women had been paid to attend the parties.</p>
<p>Asked what would happen if the women were found to have stayed after the party, Ghedini said: "If one of these people were to have relations with [Berlusconi], he would continue not to know [that she had been paid], and so there would be no legal or moral consequences."</p>
<p>Ghedini was criticised by female opposition MPs for saying Berlusconi would have been the blameless "end user" of the women.</p>
<p>D'Addario said she stopped agreeing to invitations to Palazzo Grazioli after Berlusconi failed to carry out an alleged promise to help her with a building project she had planned. She also claimed she had been told she would be put forward as a candidate in the European parliament elections, but that this was shelved after Berlusconi's wife publicly criticised as "shameless rubbish" her husband's reported plan to field showgirls.</p>
<p>D'Addario said it was clear relations with Berlusconi had turned frosty after she was barred by security from attending a Bari city council election rally, despite being a candidate affiliated to his Freedom People.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>