<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-01-19" description="Documents claim 'bunga bunga' parties involved Italian PM's female guests putting on – and then gradually taking off – uniforms" fingerprint="d7b912ad3dede70a" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Berlusconi criticised for 'use of policewomen's outfits in villa striptease shows'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/19/silvio-berlusconi-policewomens-outfits">
<main>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the Italian prime minister, today came under attack from a new and unexpected quarter when a police trade union objected to the reported use of policewomen's outfits for striptease shows at his home.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jan/17/berlusconi-paid-sex-women-milan-home">According to prosecution documents</ref> delivered to parliament, so-called "bunga bunga" sessions at Berlusconi's villa near Milan involved female guests putting on – and then gradually taking off – skimpy nurses' outfits and police uniforms.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who denies any wrongdoing, said yesterday he had no intention of resigning because of the latest disclosures, adding: "I'm enjoying myself."</p>
<p>Giorgio Innocenzi, the secretary general of the independent police trades union confederation, said that, if the accounts were borne out, "it would be a very serious development that impugns the high levels of professionalism guaranteed by women in the police".</p>
<p>He said the entire police force would feel deeply uncomfortable about wearing "a uniform that would have been held up to ridicule before public opinion, both national and international".</p>
<p>Innocenzi's remarks came as a special committee of the lower house of parliament began considering whether to allow a crucial part of the investigation to go ahead.</p>
<p>Prosecutors in Milan want to search the office of an accountant working for Berlusconi who is alleged to have rewarded showgirls, prostitutes and others hosted by the prime minister. Some are claimed to have received payments, while others got free accommodation.</p>
<p>The accountant, Giuseppe Spinelli, claims his office forms part of Berlusconi's parliamentary premises and is therefore covered by legislative immunity.</p>
<p>At the request of a deputy from the prime minister's Freedom People movement, discussion of the prosecutors' request was immediately postponed until Tuesday.</p>
<p>Last week, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jan/14/berlusconi-under-investigation-underage-prostitute">Berlusconi was formally placed under investigation</ref> on suspicion of paying for sex with an underage prostitute and trying to cover up the fact by abusing his position as prime minister.</p>
<p>It has been acknowledged that a then 17-year-old nightclub dancer, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jan/14/ruby-rubacuori-silvio-berlusconi">Karima al-Mahroug, also known as Ruby Rubacuori</ref>, was freed from a Milan police station after a call from his office.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>