<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-11-01" description="Gianfranco Fini says 'it would be time to step down' over allegations involving 17-year-old's release from custody" fingerprint="5796008d3ea3f77d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi told to resign by ally if latest scandal proven" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/01/silvio-berlusconi-must-resign-fini">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi had his back to the ropes today after his longest-standing ally said he should resign if the allegations levelled at him in the latest of several sex scandals were shown to be true.</p>
<p>Italy's prime minister was thrown onto the defensive last week by <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/29/silvio-berlusconi-office">claims he used his influence to secure the release of a teenage belly dancer accused of theft in May</ref>. The commander of the Milan police station from which she was released was today being questioned by a prosecutor about the incident, which may expose Berlusconi to a criminal charge of abusing his authority. The commander, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/29/silvio-berlusconi-office">Vincenzo Indolfi</ref>, has been quoted as saying the police were misled into believing the then 17-year-old girl – the daughter of a Moroccan immigrant – was a relative of the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak. Berlusconi has acknowledged he himself made the call.</p>
<p>Indolfi, who has since been promoted to a job in government, has insisted the correct procedures were followed. But reports at the weekend indicated the girl's release had not been authorised by the duty judge at the juvenile court, and that she was only formally made a suspect in the robbery case after the scandal broke.</p>
<p>Speaking on Sunday night, the speaker of the lower house of parliament, Gianfranco Fini said that if Berlusconi were shown to have intervened "it would be time to step down". Fini's rightist National Alliance was allied to Berlusconi's party for 15 years until the two merged to become the Freedom People (PdL) movement in 2009.</p>
<p>Since then, however, the formerly neo-fascist Fini has become an increasingly vociferous critic of the prime minister. In July, some of his followers renounced the PdL whip to form groups of their own in both houses of parliament.</p>
<p>Fini's role in the next few weeks will be crucial because he has the numbers to bring down the government. Opposition politicians have been openly pressing him to do so, and clear the way for either new elections or a cross-party, or non-party, transitional government.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has been in apparently desperate straits before, and survived. Last year, he was found to have a still-unexplained relationship with an 18-year-old aspiring showgirl and to have hosted parties for bevies of women, including prostitutes, at his residence in Rome.</p>
<p>His plight looks particularly serious this time with claims he committed a criminal offence. His popularity is at its lowest ebb since he returned to office in 2008. And he has shown – indeed, defiantly declared – that he has no intention of altering a lifestyle that is making him, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, vulnerable to international ridicule.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>