<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2011-03-03" description="Karima el-Mahroug, girl alleged to have been paid by Italian PM for sex while she was 17, attends high-profile Vienna gala" fingerprint="6720b277ca46d1cd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Austria,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Girl linked to Silvio Berlusconi shakes up Austrian high society ball" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/mar/03/silvio-berlusconi-karima-mahroug-austria">
<main>
<p>The TV cameras were told to ignore her, and Austria's rich and powerful sought to avoid her. But amid all the bling on display Thursday night at the Vienna Opera Ball, most eyes were still on one particular jewel – Ruby.</p>
<p>With Ruby Rubacuore (Ruby Heartstealer), whose real name is Karima el-Mahroug, at the centre of the scandal plaguing Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, her scheduled appearance at Austria's ball of balls was a sensation most of the guests present would have been happy to do without.</p>
<p>State TV was initially ordered to avoid covering her. But with the Berlusconi scandal big news, she was hard to keep out of sight – let alone out of mind.</p>
<p>Mahroug's comments on the eve of the ball added to Vienna high society's bad case of nerves.</p>
<p>"I can't waltz," she told reporters, before pausing for effect and adding with a smile: "I can only belly dance."</p>
<p>For centuries, Vienna's high society has waltzed blissfully through wars, recessions, and firebomb-throwing anarchists opposed to the moneyed decadence they think such events represent. But it has never had to deal with an 18-year-old dancer alleged to have been paid by Berlusconi for sex while she was still 17 – and the ripples caused by her presence relegated Libya's revolution and other top news from Austria's front pages.</p>
<p>Vienna's top priest was drawn into the fray, quoting scripture in favour of her attendance. The ball's organiser threatened to ban Richard Lugner, the 78-year-old millionaire who invited her, and former Dallas star Larry Hagman.</p>
<p>State television's head of programmes ordered cameras and commentators to make a wide detour around her. That in turn resulted in protests from TV employees who saw her as the biggest news of the event.</p>
<p>As guests started striding over the red carpet, the ban appeared to have been at least partially withdrawn, with hosts occasionally mentioning Mahroug's presence. A camera showed her arriving – although she was barely visible because of the paparazzi – and later panned over the box she shared with her entourage.</p>
<p>Ahead of the ball, this week's front cover of News, one of Austria's most widely read magazines, was dominated by a montage of Lugner in tails and top hat, his arm around Mahroug and the headline Scandal Surrounds the Opera Ball. Muammar Gaddafi and the uprising in Libya was relegated to a narrow strip running down the left side of the cover.</p>
<p>To underestimate the uproar is to ignore the place that the Vienna Opera Ball holds in the hearts of Austrians.</p>
<p>It is the climactic event of the annual ball season. Watched on TV by millions from home, champagne-sipping government leaders hobnob with captains of industry from boxes high above the main floor of the State Opera, while the less moneyed and influential crowd the tables below. Their hands perched on those of their male partners, debutantes – daughters of the rich and famous – celebrate their coming out into the privileged upper echelons by opening the festivities with a lilting waltz.</p>
<p>Some of Lugner's past guests – among them, a panoply of Hollywood actors and other lookers – had already raised carefully plucked eyebrows. He invited porn star Dolly Buster in 1999 and burlesque artist Dita von Teese three years ago.</p>
<p>But his choice of Mahroug – after actor Bo Derek backed out – was simply too much for some in Vienna, where parents of the moneyed class still send their children on manners courses.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was indicted last month on charges he paid for sex with Mahroug, when she was too young to legally work as a prostitute, and used his influence to cover it up. Both have denied having a sexual relationship.</p>
<p>Lugner – who is reported to have paid €40,000 ($55,500) for her appearance – doesn't understand the fuss. "If Berlusconi liked her, she's good enough for the Opera Ball," he told News.</p>
<p>But for ball organiser Desiree Treichl-Stuerkh, she is a "prostitute involved in ongoing legal proceedings against Berlusconi" – and, as such, <hi rend="#i">persona non grata</hi>. She said Lugner will not be given an opera box next year, adding that her office had fielded calls from prominent ballgoers asking how they can avoid being filmed or photographed with the Moroccan teen.</p>
<p>Her predecessor, Lotte Tobisch, said Mahroug's presence "is wrecking the Opera Ball", while Wolfgang Lorenz, the state broadcaster's head of programming who issued the coverage ban, warned against "turning the festivities into a hookers' ball."</p>
<p>Jumping into the fray, Toni Faber – head priest at Vienna's St Stephen's Cathedral – sided with Mahroug. Warning against hypocrisy, he used Jesusas an example, saying: "The tax collectors and the prostitutes will get into the kingdom of God ahead of you".</p>
<p>Cultural anthropologist Roland Girtler admitted he does not understand the excitement, noting that throughout history, courtesans were always welcome at balls. And despite the unease at the higher levels of Vienna's society, most Austrians seemed comfortable with Mahroug's presence.</p>
<p>A survey of 850 people prepared by Austria's Humaninstitut resulted in 70% of respondents saying that, now that Mahroug is in Vienna, "we should welcome her with Austrian charm".</p>
<p>As for Mahroug? She was just looking forward to the evening.</p>
<p>"It's certainly going to be a wonderful experience for me and I'm very grateful to get to go," she told reporters.</p>
<p>While she won't be among the first couples on the dance floor she says she intends to join the fun – despite her lack of waltzing skills.</p>
<p>"I'll dance along. You always learn new things."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>