<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-14" description="Anna Masera: When the ballots close Italy is faced with two undesirable outcomes: Berlusconi could prevail or there could be no clear winners at all" fingerprint="a7f8c21f9634c3cf" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Will Italy's nightmares come true?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/14/willitalysnightmarescometrue">
<main>
<p>Waiting for the first exit polls when ballots close at 3pm today, two nightmares are gripping Italy: the first is that once again, for the third time, <ref target="http://commentisfree.theguardian.com/john_hooper/2008/04/what_it_is_at_stake_in_italy_t.html">Silvio Berlusconi might win</ref>. The second is that there will be no winners and that the result of this vote will prove futile, leaving the country ungovernable.</p>
<p>If Berlusconi prevails, half of Italy will know how half of the United States felt when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/US_election_race/">George Bush was declared a winner</ref> over Al Gore. And a victory will be in spite of the many rightwingers who dislike him and vote for anybody but his Freedom People (Popolo delle Libertà or PDL). At these elections there are many lone-runners who decided against the coalition and prefer to measure their own appeal: <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniela_Santanch%C3%A8">Daniela Santanchè</ref>, head of La Destra (heir of the fascists), declared she'd rather lose than be "bought" by Berlusconi. So did the more moderate <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pier_Ferdinando_Casini">Pier Ferdinando Casini</ref>, head of the UDC (Unione di Centro, heir of the center-right ex-Christian Democratic party).</p>
<p>On the other side, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy1">Walter Veltroni</ref> - who founded the new Democratic party - convinced Radical party leaders (known for their liberal stance) <ref target="http://www.emmabonino.it/biography">Emma Bonino</ref> and <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Pannella">Marco Pannella</ref> to side with him in order to counter Berlusconi; but he asked communist leader <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fausto_Bertinotti">Fausto Bertinotti</ref> and socialist <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enrico_Boselli">Enrico Boselli</ref> to stay out and run alone.</p>
<p>Of course, in their last appeals to the voters both Berlusconi and Veltroni called for the <hi rend="#i">voto utile</hi> (useful vote): implying that voting for smaller parties is a waste and might mean giving a better chance for the opposite side to win.</p>
<p>Polls are forbidden, but all political parties commissioned them. Yet nobody dares to make predictions. This is due partly to the complicated electoral system that assigns seats at the senate; but it is also because everybody remembers the failure of all polls only two years ago at the last political elections when the centre-left leader Romano Prodi was given as a sure winner and ended up with a very narrow majority (which resulted in the failure to prevail at the senate and the fall of his government).</p>
<p>The outcome of these elections is in the hands of the high number of uncertain voters, because this time, many citizens are speaking up against Italian politics. Some are following the lead of the comedian and blogger <ref target="http://www.beppegrillo.it/">Beppe Grillo</ref>; some are simply discouraged by ballots in which representatives and senators aren't elected by the people but are nominated by the political parties. No wonder voter turnout is lower than usual, at least by Italian standards: yesterday by 10pm only 62.5% had voted - 4% less than in 2006.</p>
<p>This is the reason why Veltroni still hopes for a surprise victory, and why Berlusconi considers himself a winner already with his centre-right PDL. But it is also the reason why one can't dismiss a half-loss for Veltroni and a half-success for Berlusconi. No wonder PD leaders seemed optimistic at the end of the campaign, while Berlusconi was evidently so worried that he ended up anticipating a scam at the count of the votes. Veltroni hopes that the number elected at the senate will be higher for his party, Berlusconi hopes for a majority prize that will allow him to govern without having to depend on the Lega. And some leaders of the centre-right, aware of the impassed Prodi government with an opposed senate, even hope for a <hi rend="#i">super-partes</hi> technical government to face Italy's grave economic crisis and to reform this electoral system.</p>
<p>In a modern bipolar democracy, the worst result at an election is no clear winner (as La Stampa editorialist <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/_web/cmstp/tmplRubriche/editoriali/gEditoriali.asp?ID_blog=25&amp;ID_articolo=4382&amp;ID_sezione=&amp;sezione=">Luigi La Spina points out</ref>). That is why the undecided voters had better turn out and vote today before 3pm. However, if by late tonight the result is still unclear, with a different majority at the house of representatives and at the senate, whoever prevails in parliament, even just by one vote, will have to form an emergency government to correct the electoral law and bring the country back to vote. What a nightmare.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>