<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Football" date="2022-12-14" description="Silvio Berlusconi has been seen in a video telling Monza’s players he would bring sex workers into their dressing room if they won again against a top Serie A club" fingerprint="6ec8f6639063d7df" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Monza,Silvio Berlusconi,Serie A,European club football,Football,Sport" title="Berlusconi says he offered Monza squad sex workers in dressing room for big win" url="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2022/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-monza-sex-workers-in-dressing-room-serie-a">
<main>
<p>The former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> told Monza’s players he would bring sex workers into their dressing room if they managed to win again against a top Serie A club, a video published on social media showed on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who often uses colourful language, was accused in 2011 of having sex with an underage sex worker at one of his infamous “bunga bunga” parties. He was acquitted on appeal in 2015 after a judge ruled he had not known she was a minor.</p>
<p>“I told the guys ... now you will play Milan, Juventus. If you win against one of these top teams, I’ll bring a bus of whores into the locker room,” Berlusconi, 86, said in a video recorded at a Tuesday Christmas dinner with the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/monza">Monza</ref> players.</p>
<p>Daniela Sbrollini, a female senator from the centrist opposition Italia Viva party, called it the “usual misogynist language from Berlusconi: a joke in bad taste that leaves you speechless”.</p>
<p>Monza were promoted to Serie A for the first time last season and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/blog/2022/sep/19/monza-gamble-raffaele-palladino-unknown-manager-win-over-juventus">defeated Juventus</ref> in September. They will play Inter and Juventus again in January and will face Berlusconi’s old club Milan in February.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who owned Milan for three decades, bought Monza in 2018. They are 14th in the 20-team league.</p>
<p>
<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com#EmailSignup-skip-link-6">skip past newsletter promotion</ref>
</p>
<p>after newsletter promotion</p>
<p>Once the most dominant figure in Italian politics, Berlusconi is now less present, due to health problems and the dwindling popularity of his Forza Italia party, a junior member of prime minister Giorgia Meloni’s ruling right-wing coalition.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>