<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="Media" date="2003-05-08" description="Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi launched a media campaign urging the public to support him as he battles to avoid a corruption conviction by judges he accuses of plotting 'a constitutional coup'. By Sophie Arie." fingerprint="3bfc5308b00ff405" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Media,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi launches media counterattack" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/may/08/pressandpublishing.italy">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, launched a media campaign urging the public to support him as he battles to avoid a corruption conviction by judges he accuses of plotting "a constitutional coup".</p>
<p>The billionaire's possible conviction on bribery charges could come while <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> holds the EU presidency during the second half of this year. Yesterday the newspaper Corriere della Sera published an open letter from Mr Berlusconi, presenting the case for the defence.</p>
<p>Dismissing allegations that in the 1980s he bribed judges to help him take over the giant state food company SME, he called for his trial to be suspended and a parliamentary immunity law to be passed to avert a constitutional crisis.</p>
<p>"We must intervene. And not in order to help the premier 'pass the exam' in the [EU] semester, because I am capable of taking care of that myself," he wrote.</p>
<p>Parliamentary immunity was abolished in 1993, allowing judges in Milan to purge Italy's old political class in the Tangentopoli (Bribesville) trials.</p>
<p>The leftwing opposition sees reviving parliamentary immunity as a step backwards. "Italy is in danger. We risk becoming a regime without even realising it," the centre-left leader Francesco Rutelli told the newspaper La Repubblica.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who controls three television channels, told listeners to state radio yesterday that the Italian judiciary was using its power to "attack and eliminate" its political enemies.</p>
<p>Many Italians do not see the corruption allegations as a problem and Mr Berlusconi is convinced they would re-elect him. But only 8% of Italians trust their judiciary, he claimed in his letter yesterday.</p>
<p>The prime minister appeared in court on Monday to accuse Romano Prodi, the president of the European commission, of trying to sell off the SME at a cut price in 1985.</p>
<p>Last week Mr Berlusconi's ally Cesare Previti was sentenced to 11 years for bribery.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>