<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="Media" date="2003-06-28" description="Politician and tycoon takes over European presidency." fingerprint="7fbed02bb222cfa5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,European Union,Television industry,Media business,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="He built a Milanese utopia but can Silvio Berlusconi be trusted with the future of the EU?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jun/28/pressandpublishing.italy">
<main>
<p>On the edge of the bustling, grimy financial city of Milan, there is a quiet, green oasis. Arching footbridges, festooned with ivy, link blocks of Scandinavian-style flats to hair salons, cafes and tennis courts, saving residents the need to set foot on the road below.</p>
<p>Aeroplane flight paths that once crossed overhead have been rerouted, allowing the ducks to bob undisturbed on a glassy artificial lake. Lawns are neatly trimmed and private security guards linger under pine trees.</p>
<p>This is Milano 2, the ideal home for 10,000 Italians, built in the 1970s to offer an alternative to the grind of city life. The man behind the project was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, known as Il Cavaliere, Italy's prime minister and foremost tycoon - and, from next week, the European Union's president.</p>
<p>"This is not the real world. It's better than the real world," said Franco, a 19-year-old law student who has lived all his life at Milano 2. Other residents agree: they live "like the gods", "in a holiday camp" or "in a kind of utopia"'.</p>
<p>This upmarket estate has one bank, Mediolanum, one shopfront advertisement for Il Giornale, and Mediaset's first broadcasting studios - all owned by the Berlusconi family. When AC Milan, the football club owned by the prime minister, wins a match, the roars of satisfaction from television-watching families echo through the streets.</p>
<p>"Mr Berlusconi is very intelligent. If he can make a place like this, just think what great things he can do for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>," said Fabrizia, a fervent Berlusconi voter, in her late 50s, out feeding the ducks with her granddaughter Suzanna.</p>
<p>Milano 2 made 66-year-old Silvio Berlusconi his first millions and was his first step on the career ladder from singer on cruise liners to becoming Italy's most powerful businessman and politician. His construction company, Edilnord, subsequently thrived, building several more similar estates while Mr Berlusconi branched out into television, advertising, publishing, supermarkets, football and, finally, politics.</p>
<p>"Because of my personal history, my professional skills and my business achievements, I am a man nobody can expect to compare himself with," he once said.</p>
<p>Now, as he prepares to take over the EU presidency for six months from Tuesday, the Berlusconi phenomenon, for many, gives more cause for concern than confidence. European observers are worrying more than ever about the media tycoon's conflict of interests, his recently aborted corruption trial and his tendency to make what former prime minister Massimo d'Alema once called "planetary gaffes".</p>
<p>The run-up to the presidency has been a bumpy ride for the prime minister who, having won a landslide election two years ago, has watched a Milan court edge closer and closer to convicting him for corrupt business activities in the 1980s, before he went into politics.</p>
<p>Most recently, a growing surge of immigrants landing on Italy's southern shores has inspired his political ally, Umberto Bossi, the notoriously anti-foreigner leader of the Northern League, to threaten to walk out on the government coalition. Mr Berlusconi played this down this week, saying it was important to distinguish "between theatre and reality".</p>
<p>The corruption trial, in which Mr Berlusconi was accused of bribing judges to win the privatisation contract for the state food conglomerate SME in the 1980s, was the most serious of scores of investigations into the billionaire's allegedly backhanded business activities. Prosecutors have requested 11 years in jail for his private lawyer, Cesare Previti, in the case.</p>
<p>With rescue in sight, in the form of an immunity law rushed through parliament last week to protect the country's top five officials from prosecution, Mr Berlusconi told a Milan courtroom, sweat running down his sun-tanned face: "One citizen is equal to another [in the eyes of the law] but perhaps this one is slightly more equal than the rest, given that 50% of Italians have given him the responsibility of governing the country."</p>
<p>Although Mr Berlusconi argued that the immunity law brings Italian legislation in line with most European countries, Italy's opposition left is horrified.</p>
<p>"This is a serious threat to democracy in Italy and a deep shame for Italy in Europe," said Francesco Rutelli, leader of the leftwing Margherita [Daisy] party.</p>
<p>Graham Watson, leader of the European parliament's Liberal Democrats, added: "Europe is frankly astonished when a prime minister changes the law to stop a criminal trial against him."</p>
<p>With the handcuffs at bay for now - the law postpones his trial until the end of his mandate in 2006 - the majority of Italians, convinced that Mr Berlusconi is no more corrupt than their average politician, would still vote for him today, according to a poll in the country's biggest newspaper, Corriere della Sera, this week.</p>
<p>Commentators say that rather than suffer under the spotlight of the EU presidency, the eternal showman and would-be statesman will thrive on the international stage. But they also worry that at a crucial time in the history of the EU, with divisions over the Iraq crisis still smouldering, preparation afoot for EU expansion and pushing through a constitution, the Italian leader might not have been fully concentrating on the job.</p>
<p>"The fear among many is that Berlusconi might have his mind more on internal things than European [affairs]," Daniel Cohn Bendit, European parliament co-president of the Greens, told Italy's leftwing Unita newspaper. "I hope Berlusconi will know how to defend a certain idea of Europe as intelligently and as cunningly as he has defended his own affairs."</p>
<p>Italy has various priorities for Europe, to be presented next week when Greece hands over the presidency. They include boosting the continent's faltering economy, easing the entry of 10 new members, pushing for a common EU foreign policy and tackling Europe's immigration problem.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Il Cavaliere, who doubled up as foreign minister for most of last year, said Italy was "no longer the sick one in Europe" and promised an "ambitious" foreign policy for the EU presidency. Having forged closer ties with President George Bush and Tony Blair over the Iraq war, Mr Berlusconi has shown increasing desire to play a larger role on the international stage. But many fear that his comment that the west was superior to Islam caused irreversible diplomatic damage after September 11.</p>
<p>While offering warm support to Israel, even suggesting that it should be allowed to join the EU, Mr Berlusconi refused to meet Palestinian leader Yasser Arafat on a recent Middle East tour. In an apparent patch-up, he announced this week that the Palestinian prime minister, Mahmoud Abbas, also known as Abu Mazen, would visit Rome next month.</p>
<p>"People are suspicious because they don't exactly know where he [Mr Berlusconi] stands. He often gives the impression of wanting to merely go with the flow," said Daniel Keohane, a research fellow at the Centre for European Reform, a London-based thinktank.</p>
<p>Il Cavaliere, who has described himself as the "best political leader in Europe and in the world," is likely apply the same "think big" approach to European expansion as he has to Italian politics.</p>
<p>"Either we have a superpower with military capabilities far greater than the EU, or else the US can have another partner - the EU - which must eliminate its division and enlarge to countries like Russia, with its military capabilities, Ukraine, Moldova, Turkey and even Israel," he said in Brussels this year.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's relations with France and Germany have been strained over Iraq, and Germany's leading newspapers have published stinging editorials in recent days challenging Europe not to turn a blind eye to "the Berlusconi problem".</p>
<p>"Berlusconi is putting himself above the law," said Die Zeit, arguing that Europe should be taking developments in Italy as seriously as it took those in Austria three years ago, when extreme-right leader Jorg Haider joined the government, triggering EU sanctions.</p>
<p>In France an editorial in Le Monde this week said: "At this moment in its history, Europe might have hoped to be piloted by a man of undisputed moral and political leadership. That will not be the case."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Silvio's slips:</hi> Words that caused outrage</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">路</hi> In September 2001, soon after the terrorist attacks on the World Trade Centre, Mr Berlusconi told journalists during a state visit to Germany that western civilisation was superior to Islam because of its human rights record.</p>
<p>"We must be aware of the superiority of our civilisation, a system that has guaranteed well-being, respect for human rights and - in contrast to Islamic countries - respect for religious and political rights," he said.</p>
<p>"The west will continue to conquer peoples even if it means a confrontation with another civilisation, Islam, firmly entrenched where it was 1,400 years ago."</p>
<p>The comments caused international outrage. Mr Berlusconi said they had been taken out of context.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">路</hi> At a Nato-Russia conference last year, Mr Berlusconi called the Nato secretary-general Lord Robertson "Robinson", invented a new state "Estuaia", instead of Estonia, and referred to the founders of Rome, Romulus and Remus, as Romulus and Remulus. "From now on, they will always be Romulus and Remulus because it sounds good," he told journalists afterwards.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">路</hi> Mr Berlusconi has developed a reputation at international gatherings for flouting protocol. At a summit of EU foreign ministers in Spain last year, he held up two fingers behind a colleague's head, an Italian hand sign meaning "cuckold".</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">路</hi> Le Monde reported last year that Mr Berlusconi had proposed abolishing the European commission and sharing out its portfolios among member countries. He later said it was a joke. Romano Prodi, president of the commission and Mr Berlusconi's political rival said: "I would love to accept this proposition as a joke, but the shortest jokes are the best".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>