<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tony Bunyan" categories="Opinion" date="2009-06-24" description="Tony Bunyan: View from the EU: The results of the European elections look certain to cement the centre-right and far-right's sway over politics in Europe" fingerprint="c064bc15d5859c1c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European elections,European Union,European Commission,Race,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Europe's race to the right | Tony Bunyan" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/jun/24/europe-elections-right-wing">
<main>
<p>EU institutions and governments regularly repeat the mantra that we all "share common values", as if the project has unchanging standards and principles, but do we?</p>
<p>At the time of the 1999 <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/european-elections">European elections</ref>, when there were 15 EU member states, there were 12 social democratic governments and three on the centre right. Now there are 27 member states, with 20 governments on the centre right or far right and just seven on the so-called centre left (and that is including the UK government).</p>
<p>This has a direct effect on what happens in the most powerful body on EU decision-making, the Council of the European Union. When national interior ministries send officials, police and immigration officers and ministers to the plethora of justice and <ref target="http://www.statewatch.org/news/2009/mar/eu-council-preparatory-working-parties.pdf">home affairs working parties (pdf)</ref>, the article 36 committee, the strategic committee on immigration, frontiers and asylum and numerous sub-groups, the options they will support reflect national policies.</p>
<p>After 9/11, we have been told time and time again that terrorism could destroy our common values and democracies. But when Statewatch examined the proposed measures after the dreadful <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/news/gallery/2007/oct/30/spain.internationalnews1?picture=331114429">bombings in Madrid</ref> in March 2004, it produced a <ref target="http://www.statewatch.org/analyses/no-37-scoreboard-eu-plan.pdf">scoreboard (pdf)</ref> showing that 27 of the 57 measures put forward had little or nothing to do with tackling terrorism.</p>
<p>Terrible though the current threat of terrorist attacks are, they will not destroy "our common values and democracies". What is destroying them is the response of EU governments to terrorism. When the EU says it is balancing <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/may/05/security-liberty">security and liberty</ref> you know that the former will always win out over the latter. This is a reflection of the shift to the right at the core of the EU.</p>
<p>The <ref target="http://www.elections2009-results.eu/en/index_en.html">results</ref> of the European parliament elections look likely to give the centre right and far right a permanent majority. We are faced with the prospect of both the Council of the European Union and the European parliament being dominated by the right for the next five years.</p>
<p>The election gave the conservatives' group (PPE) 264 MEPs, the rightwing<ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8011001.stm#uen"> Europe of Nations</ref> (UEN) have 35 MEPs, the Independence-Democracy group have 18 MEPs (including Ukip, though the group may fail to meet the new minimum criteria to form a separate group – seven member states and 25 MEPs). To which can be added, on civil liberties issues, the UK Conservative party, with 29 MEPs, who have just cobbled together a new <ref target="http://www.euractiv.com/en/eu-elections/parliament-new-anti-federalist-group-fragile-coalition/article-183388">anti-federalist group</ref> (the European Conservatives and Reformists, ECR) with bed-fellows of <ref target="http://www.euractiv.com/en/eu-elections/parliament-new-anti-federalist-group-fragile-coalition/article-183388">highly dubious politics</ref>. This will give a total of over 346 MEPs out of 736. To this total can be added many of the remaining 43 "Other" MEPs who are <ref target="http://euobserver.com/843/28263">extreme-right</ref>, racist or fascist.</p>
<p>In the last parliament the racist/fascist MEPs formed the Tradition-Sovereignty group of 23, which then fell apart. This time around there are estimated to be between <ref target="http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/272316,far-right-gains-in-european-parliament-election-by--feature.html">30 and 35 MEPs</ref> who are ultra-nationalist, racist or fascist including – from France: three; Belgium: two; Hungary: three; UK: two; Netherlands: four; Austria: two; Bulgaria: two; Denmark:two; Finland: one; Slovakia: one; Romania: two: and Greece: two.</p>
<p>Some, such as the groups on the Italian far right, the National Alliance and Alessandra Mussolini's Social Alternative (who have eight MEPs) who merged with Silvio Berlusconi's new centre-right People of Freedom party in March are hidden in the PPE and the anti-migrant Northern League has eight MEPs in the UEN group.</p>
<p>The progressive groups, if they vote together, can muster the socialist group (PSE, which is to rename itself the Alliance of Socialists and Democrats for Europe, ASDE): 182 MEPs, the liberal group (ALDE): 80 MEPs; the Green group (Green/EFA): 53 MEPs; and the United Left (GUE): 32 MEPs, a total of 347. This coalition is by no means guaranteed. In the last parliamentary session the two big parties, the PPE and the PSE, joined forces to push through biometric passports and the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/feb/11/eu-liberty-central">mandatory retention</ref> of communications.</p>
<p>On these figures the balance of power on civil liberties issues would rest with the "Others" on the extreme right. In 1979 <ref target="http://www.elections2009-results.eu/en/turnout_en.html">61.99%</ref> of the electorate voted in the EU parliament elections and every election voter participation has fallen – now to its lowest-ever level, at just 43.24%. Disenchantment with the two mainstream political parties who have both moved to the right and the failure of the EU institutions to operate in an open and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/may/20/freedomofinformation-eu">transparent manner </ref>has contributed to this growing disengagement.</p>
<p>In the past two European elections, the main parties have attempted to "triangulate" the far right and racists by responding to their perceived appeal, especially on race and immigration. This tactic has failed, serving only to legitimate their extremist views and leaving us with racist and fascist MEPs from 12 EU member states. A frightening prospect for the future.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>