<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2005-04-18" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, today agreed to resign and form a new government to strengthen his struggling conservative coalition, a move that will avert fresh elections." fingerprint="7b8acb2fb4b7e76b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi resigns in bid to avert elections" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/18/italy">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, today agreed to resign and form a new government to strengthen his struggling conservative coalition, a move that will avert fresh elections.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's impending resignation, announced today by the foreign minister, Gianfranco Fini, would end the country's longest serving post-war government. But with one more year of his five-year term of office left, the move will allow Mr Berlusconi to escape without calling an immediate election, which polls show he would lose.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi had been under pressure to resign since his centre-right coalition suffered a crushing defeat in a regional vote held across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> earlier this month. His government neared collapse after the Union of Christian Democrats, a small centrist party headed by Marco Follini, quit the cabinet on Friday. Mr Follini demanded that Mr Berlusconi form a fresh government with a new platform.</p>
<p>Mr Fini made today's announcement after a meeting of coalition leaders in Rome. He said that at the meeting, Mr Follini "renewed (his) commitment to a new Berlusconi government" and Mr Berlusconi made the "ensuing decision to hand in his resignation to the head of state".</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi is set to meet with Italy's president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, later in the day.</p>
<p>The move will allow Mr Berlusconi to return to office with a parliamentary majority that may see him through another year. Resigning and immediately forming a new government is a tactic that has been used often by Italian prime ministers to strengthen faltering coalitions. Mr Berlusconi had resisted the move, dismissing it as a remnant of Italy's messy political past.</p>
<p>Once the prime minister hands in a resignation, it is up to the president to decide whether to ask Mr Berlusconi, or another candidate, to form a new government; or to dissolve parliament and call early elections. However, if a political agreement has been reached among majority forces, the president is expected to go along with it.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's coalition took power in 2001, and the prime minister hoped the government would become the first in post-war Italy to serve out the full five-year term. After the centre-right's collapse in the April 3-4 regional vote, Mr Berlusconi had proposed a cabinet reshuffle and a revised programme to relaunch the coalition ahead of the general election next year. The proposal was rejected by Mr Follini's party.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>