<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Politics" date="2006-10-31" description="David Mills, the estranged husband of culture secretary, Tessa Jowell, has been sent for trial in Italy - accused of accepting a £340,000 bribe from former prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi By John Hooper in Rome." fingerprint="a044088fb2e396d2" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,UK news,Italy,Media,World news,Labour,Television industry,Silvio Berlusconi,David Mills,Europe" title="Mills faces second trial over Berlusconi corruption charges" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2006/oct/31/italy.labour">
<main>
<p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the culture secretary, Tessa Jowell, was yesterday sent for a second trial in Italy - accused this time of accepting a £340,000 bribe from the former prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who was also indicted.</p>
<p>There were reportedly heated scenes before the decision was read out by a judge in Milan. Mr Berlusconi's lawyer was said to have accused the judge, Fabio Paparella, of defying the law by approving the indictments while defence lawyers were applying to have him taken off the case. Ignoring the lawyer's objections, Judge Paparella fixed the start of the trial for March 13.</p>
<p>The two defendants are already due to go on trial with 12 others in a related case which starts next month. Both men deny any wrongdoing.</p>
<p>Mr Mills told the Guardian last night: "This hasn't altered at all my confidence in the successful outcome of these proceedings. According to my lawyers, it is just the latest demonstration of [the judge's] evident bias in favour of the prosecution. Faced with his attitude, my lawyers decided it would be a waste of time to ask him to consider an expert's report which demolishes the prosecution case."</p>
<p>He said the prosecution was a waste of money. "The prosecution has known all along where this money came from, and I don't know why they are proceeding with this," he said. "I am innocent, and the documents we have will prove this."</p>
<p>Mr Mills, a lawyer, separated from his wife in March after extensive publicity given to the proceedings. The foreign secretary, Margaret Beckett, said yesterday Ms Jowell would not be "destabilised" by the announcement. "Despite the best efforts of many people to destabilise her, she has continued to do an excellent job, and I am sure she will continue to do an excellent job," Mrs Beckett said.</p>
<p>Mr Mills has been Mr Berlusconi's adviser on offshore legal matters for several years. Prosecutors claim that Mr Berlusconi paid him for withholding evidence in two earlier trials in which he was an expert witness. But, after initially concurring, Mr Mills changed his evidence and said the money came from another client, a Neapolitan ship owner. The ship owner has denied this, but the prosecutors have so far failed to produce evidence linking Mr Berlusconi to the payment.</p>
<p>The charges against both defendants - of corruption intended to pervert the course of justice - grew out of the first case, which comes to court on November 21. On that date, Mr Mills will face claims that he helped Italy's richest man to dodge taxes and launder cash.</p>
<p>Because of the slowness of the Italian courts and a law passed when Mr Berlusconi was in power, it is likely that most of the charges against him will be "timed out" before a final judgement can be given. However, there is no statute of limitations applicable to the money laundering allegation.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>