<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Agence France-Presse; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2023-05-20" description="Billionaire former prime minister, 86, had been suffering from a lung infection linked to leukaemia" fingerprint="3eb1d2698226c747" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,Giorgia Meloni" title="Italy: Silvio Berlusconi released from Milan hospital after six weeks" url="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/may/20/italy-silvio-berlusconi-released-from-milan-hospital-after-six-weeks">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has been discharged from hospital in Milan, declaring “the nightmare” is over, more than six weeks after the former Italian prime minister was admitted with leukaemia and a lung infection.</p>
<p>“Today, after 45 long days, I finally returned home,” the 86-year-old billionaire media mogul said in a statement after leaving the San Raffaele Hospital on Friday.</p>
<p>He described it as “an incredible emotion, a great relief”, adding: “It was a distressing and difficult period, but after the darkness, I won again.”</p>
<p>In a typically impassioned statement, Berlusconi thanked God and all those who had supported him. “I never felt alone,” he said, adding: “The nightmare is over ... Long live life, always!”</p>
<p>The senator, who has been plagued by health issues in recent years, was admitted to the San Raffaele on 5 April and spent the first week and a half in intensive care.</p>
<p>Doctors said he had been admitted for treatment for a lung infection, before <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/apr/06/silvio-berlusconi-diagnosed-with-leukaemia-italian-reports-say">revealing for the first time that he had leukaemia</ref>.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/giorgia-meloni">Giorgia Meloni</ref>, whose governing coalition includes Berlusconi’s rightwing Forza Italia party, led the congratulations for his return home.</p>
<p>“Go Silvio!” she tweeted, adding: “We are waiting for you in the field, to fight many battles together.”</p>
<p>Berlusconi led <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> three times between 1994 and 2011 but has dominated public life for far longer, as a businessman and media magnate and through his ownership of the AC Milan football club.</p>
<p>His career has also been dogged by scandal and legal woes, which for the past decade were focused on proceedings relating to his notorious “Bunga Bunga” sex parties.</p>
<p>Meloni had visited Berlusconi in hospital on Sunday, saying afterwards that he had been “in an excellent mood” and was still working “tirelessly”.</p>
<p>The former premier also received visits from his Forza Italia deputy, foreign minister Antonio Tajani, and coalition ally Matteo Salvini, leader of the anti-immigration League party.</p>
<p>“Welcome home, Great Silvio,” Salvini tweeted, while Tajani added: “We’re all happy you’ve returned home.”</p>
<p>Berlusconi had hoped to be discharged from hospital earlier this month in time for a Forza Italia convention in Milan but ended up <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/may/06/silvio-berlusconi-addresses-forza-italia-members-from-hospital-room">addressing delegates in a pre-recorded video address</ref> filmed in his hospital room.</p>
<p>Despite remaining president of Forza Italia, Berlusconi is rarely seen in public these days, and his health has long been a concern.</p>
<p>He was in hospital for 11 days for Covid-related pneumonia in September 2020, after contracting the virus while on holiday in Sardinia.</p>
<p>After being admitted again last month, doctors revealed he had “chronic myelomonocytic leukaemia”, a rare type of blood cancer.</p>
<p>The disease, which affects mainly the elderly, starts in blood-forming cells of the bone marrow and goes on to invade the blood.</p>
<p>Berlusconi’s cancer was in a “persistent chronic phase” and had not yet turned into “acute leukaemia”, the doctors said.</p>
<p>In March, Berlusconi was admitted to the same Milan hospital, where he spent four days.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>