<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Meltzer" categories="Life and style" date="2012-04-17" description="Soirees are in the news for all the wrong reasons this week. Should you find yourself at one of these awful dos, we have some advice" fingerprint="96f0d2dd8b950604" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Pippa Middleton,Life and style,Celebrity,Silvio Berlusconi,Barack Obama,World news" title="How to survive a party with Pippa Middleton or Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/apr/17/party-pippa-middleton-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>It has been a week of lurid parties. From the sisters of royals to the president's men, anyone with half a link to power has popped up at one salacious celebratory orgy or another. Pippa Middleton got us started, dressing up in <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/9208213/Pippa-Middleton-pictured-at-lavish-Paris-fancy-dress-party-hours-before-gun-incident.html">pink renaissance finery</ref> like Belle from Beauty and the Beast to celebrate her friend Arthur de Soultrait's lavish 30th in Paris with fellow socialites, hired dwarves and an impressive amount of bondage gear.</p>
<p>Then, of course, there were the 11 secret service agents – and half a dozen more military personnel – who brought a sizeable team of alleged prostitutes back to their hotel in Colombia just a few days before a scheduled visit from the US president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/15/us-secret-service-scandal-obama">prompting much embarrassed shuffling of feet (and staff)</ref> from an organisation known for its inscrutable professionalism.</p>
<p>And, on the topic of inscrutable professionals, even the normally strait-laced and chaste Silvio Berlusconi has been dipping his toe into the steamy waters of the sex soiree, although in his case this week has been less party time than the court case after the night before. Like a designated driver recounting the antics of her drunken mates over the morning's fry-up, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/16/silvio-berlusconi-trial-imane-fadil">27-year-old Moroccan model and soiree-attendee Imane Fadil has been regaling Italian judges</ref> with tales of girls stripping out of football shirts, cash-filled envelopes and much rubbing of old, tanned thighs.</p>
<p>These three are just the tip of the iceberg too; the ones that failed to keep a lid on things. For all we know, every world leader around – along with their bodyguards, buddies and siblings – spends half their nights in a dingy cellar somewhere decked out like Louis XIV watching women, dwarves or animals gyrating for a fistful of rolled banknotes. In fact, scratch that: for all we know, it's everyone except you and me. They're all meeting up in dirty seaside villas and dingy countryside bed and breakfasts to drag each other around on leads in period costume. Can you honestly tell yourself it's not possible?</p>
<p>Didn't think so. It's probably only a matter of time before an invite comes your way too, so you had best be prepared. Here's our six-point guide to surviving the wildest parties of the pervy and powerful.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Compliment the host</hi>
</head>
<p>This is easier at some parties than others, of course. If, like P-Middy, you're a guest of fashion entrepreneur the Vicomte de Soultrait – pictured in certain papers in the traditional Captain-Hook-on-a-dog-lead outfit of the French aristocracy – then the list of potential compliments is nearly endless. "Great choice of dwarves!", for example, or: "I loved you in Peter Pan at the Wycombe Swan."</p>
<p>If you're staying at the pleasure of Mr Berlusconi there are fewer options, but there's surely a positive spin to be put on Imane Fadil's revelation that – at one of the media mogul's wilder bashes – a Brazilian model stripped to her G-string dressed in an AC Milan shirt and a mask of the footballer Ronaldinho. You could try: "I like a man who knows exactly what he wants."</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Know the lingo</hi>
</head>
<p>If you're not sure what kind of party you're attending before you go, your best bet is to check the name. If it's "bunga bunga", odds are that's a Berlusconi do, and, unless you're a nubile young lass with a thing for leering older gentlemen, it's probably best to steer well clear.</p>
<p>The US secret service's bashes have equally evocative names: a "wheels-up" do is a chance for the team to let their hair down when a VIP has safely flown off and the mission is complete. A "pre-wheels-up" affair – as one congressman described this weekend's scandal – is almost the same, except it takes place days before the US president is due to arrive, and the focus is on bringing strange women into rooms containing the president's top secret itinerary for the visit.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Beware of power tools</hi>
</head>
<p>We've covered the biggest two power tools already, but this one's true in the literal sense as well. Pictures from Pippa's night out show sparks flying on the dancefloor as a gothic Lolita grinds buzzing DIY gear across the furniture. The same performer is later pictured posing with a dwarf in a miniature panama hat, a stuffed toy, and a young nun in a skimpy habit, suspenders and nipple-guards. Which brings us neatly to our next point …</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Ignore the nuns</hi>
</head>
<p>Better yet, ignore the women dressed as nuns, because they're anything but. Or at least they're an order of nuns I have not heard of who focus less on the modesty and penitence stuff and more on the lesser-known Catholic practice of ditching the wimple and getting naked. According, once again, to testimony from Berlusconi's trial, at one party a pair of young girls donned black habits and crucifixes, performed a pole-dance duet and stripped for Berlusconi himself. So, you know, avoid them. Especially if they're wearing Ronaldinho masks.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Have cash ready</hi>
</head>
<p>The secret service affair might never have made it to the papers had one man not taken it upon himself to refuse a $47 bill. According to reports, one of the women who had come back to the hotel with the group of agents demanded the sum as fair payment for her services, prompting a row so noisy that first hotel security and later the local police were called. After insisting for quite some time that – for reasons not yet divulged – he wasn't obliged to pay her anything, the agent eventually relented and handed over the money.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Leave quietly and avoid the cameras</hi>
</head>
<p>Probably the most important rule of all, and sadly the one that Pippa ignored: she was photographed the next morning riding through Paris with the Vicomte and fellow survivors with the roof down in a convertible sports car. Then, when the driver clocked the camera that was pointed at them, he whipped out a very real-looking handgun, turned to face the paparazzo and aimed the weapon directly down the lens. Pippa, meanwhile, grinned, resulting in a photo so scandalous it made the night before look like a particularly dull six-year-old's birthday. So as a general rule, when it comes time to leave, do exactly the opposite of that.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>