<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2008-05-21" description="Rightwing cabinet endorses a package of tough measures aimed at Gypsies and clandestine immigrants" fingerprint="7f49dbaff139fc09" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Roma, Gypsies and Travellers,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi clamps down on Gypsies" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/may/22/italy1">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's new rightwing cabinet, at its first meeting in Naples yesterday, endorsed a package of tough measures aimed at Gypsies and clandestine immigrants. In a move that appeared certain to cause controversy, the interior minister, Roberto Maroni, said local authorities would be empowered to check on the living conditions of citizens from other EU nations before granting them right of residence.</p>
<p>The measure appeared to be aimed at Roma living in encampments, and particularly at the estimated 50,000 Romanian Gypsies who have entered <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> in recent years and who are being blamed for much of the recent rise in crime rates.</p>
<p>The cabinet also decided to make unauthorised entry into Italy a crime.</p>
<p>The measures will make it easier to expel foreigners, including EU citizens, who are convicted of offences, a move that could bring the Berlusconi government into conflict with Brussels if it is judged to breach European law on freedom of movement within the EU.</p>
<p>In addition, the cabinet agreed to the confiscation of property let to illegal immigrants, a rule that could have instant and drastic effects on hundreds of thousands of foreigners known to be living in Italy without the right papers.</p>
<p>Adults who force children to beg will face imprisonment.</p>
<p>Introducing the package, Italy's prime minister said it was intended to assure "the right of Italians not to be afraid - a fundamental right that the state must guarantee".</p>
<p>Berlusconi's government also endorsed moves designed to tackle the piles of rubbish that have built up in Naples, the reason why yesterday's inaugural cabinet session was held in the city. The move includes the appointment of a junior minister to tackle the refuse collection crisis and the opening of eight new dumps.</p>
<p>As Berlusconi and his ministers deliberated, there were chaotic scenes across Naples as pressure groups seized a rare opportunity to publicise their grievances. Nine organisations, ranging from the Neapolitan Euro-Jobless, to Working Class Emancipation, held marches or sit-ins, gridlocking traffic in the city.</p>
<p>Several hundred immigrants and Roma joined a protest against the criminalisation of illegal entry. Until now, people from outside the EU found to be living in Italy without a residence permit has been served with an expulsion notice. But only in selected cases have clandestine immigrants been escorted to a frontier.</p>
<p>"The problem is that the authorities have let so much time go by since the last amnesty that now there are lots of us without the right papers," said one of the leaders of the protest, a Senegalese man who identified himself only as Osman. Officials are said to be wrestling with about 729,000 applications for legal residence.</p>
<p>Yesterday's cabinet meeting was held against an incendiary background of electoral rhetoric that Berlusconi's critics have linked to recent lapses into "mob justice". In Naples last week, a Roma camp was repeatedly attacked following the arrest of a young Gypsy woman accused of trying to abduct a child. After the inhabitants had been moved for their own protection, the buildings and caravans were burned to the ground, apparently by vigilantes acting on orders from the Neapolitan mafia, the Camorra.</p>
<p>The incident, together with a string of raids by police on Roma encampments, has shocked Gypsy communities.</p>
<p>"Everyone here is afraid," said 29-year-old Saltana Ahmetovic, who lives at the La Monarchina camp outside Rome. A neatly kept enclosure, the camp has been used since 1998. Some of the residents have built themselves wooden houses, while those still in caravans have long since removed the vehicles' wheels.</p>
<p>But though La Monarchina has a council-installed standpipe and is regularly visited by police, it appears to have no legal status. It still has no mains water and the electricity hails from a generator.</p>
<p>"They can't throw me out because I'm an Italian citizen," said Ahmetovic, whose mother arrived in Italy from Yugoslavia in the 1960s. "But if they take away my caravan I'll be forced to become a tramp." His mother and at least one of his sisters does not have citizenship.</p>
<p>Ahmetovic and some of his brothers, one of whom is engaged to an Italian, deal in scrap metal. "Our women sell bonsai trees in shops and restaurants," he said.</p>
<p>In Italian terms, he is a nomad but asked if he would like to live in a house, a dreamy look came over his face and he replied: "If only." Behind his caravan, on the edge of the camp, a small Italian flag flies from a pole.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>