<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="George Irvin" categories="Opinion" date="2011-11-07" description="George Irvin: Berlusconi's resignation would not save Italy. But this crisis could force the European Central Bank to face down the markets" fingerprint="6dcc416f18244c56" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European Central Bank,Italy,European Union,Silvio Berlusconi,Business,European monetary union,European banks,Financial crisis,Global recession,Greece,Euro,Economics,Euro,Europe,World news" title="Italy's crisis could be a blessing in disguise | George Irvin" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/07/italy-crisis-berlusconi-european-central-bank">
<main>
<p>Attention has suddenly switched from Greece to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/blog/2011/nov/07/greece-coalition-government-george-papandreou-crisis">Italy</ref>. As Italian 10-year bond yields reach 6.67%, eurozone finance ministers and IMF officials are braced for an emergency meeting. Although the European Central Bank (ECB) has recently lowered its benchmark interest rate and has been buying Italian bonds, the country's gross debt-to-GDP ratio is 118%, and the current sovereign bond yield is seen as little short of catastrophic.</p>
<p>By the time you read this, Silvio Berlusconi may well have resigned, according to his former minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/03/silvio-berlusconi-resignation-euro-crisis">Giuliano Ferrara</ref>. His parliamentary allies are split about budget cuts, the government's majority has been eroding and he faces a crucial vote on public finance on Tuesday. Since Berlusconi is widely considered by the markets to be an impediment to reform, his resignation could lead to a fall in the interest rate Italy pays on its debt (bond yields) and possibly to a brief period of respite.</p>
<p>But even if Berlusconi goes, Italy's troubles will continue. The government has some €1.6tn in gross liabilities outstanding, more than Greece, Portugal and Ireland combined and certainly far more that the €1tn-leveraged <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/nils-pratley-on-finance/2011/oct/11/does-efsf-have-design-fault">EFSF bailout programme</ref> announced at the end of October could deal with. Italy's growth record is poor, averaging <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-15429057">less than 1% per annum</ref> over the past 15 years. In 2009, GDP fell precipitously, and since then GDP growth has been barely positive; moreover, since 2009 inflation has been rising – currently it stands at just over 3% – and Italian competitiveness has been falling. As long as the country's growth rate remains below the interest rate paid on its sovereign debt, its debt-to-GDP ratio must rise by definition.</p>
<p>Italy has raised €277bn in debt so far this year, and it must sell €147bn more by the end of December. But every 1% in extra interest charged on sovereign debt means an extra €3bn in debt service <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> must pay. Most important, it is difficult to see how the country will finance the €260bn in debt that falls due next year – this is nearly twice the size of the comparable figure for Spain, another eurozone country deemed "too big to fail". So confidence on the part of fiscally conservative investors in Italy's public finances is vital.</p>
<p>What sort of reform does Italy need? The popular view – that Italy is highly indebted, profligate in its state spending and in need of a very strong dose of austerity – is disputed by many economists. For one thing, drastic austerity measures like those imposed on Greece could push the Italian economy back into recession (negative growth) making a reduction in the debt-to-GDP ratio impossible to achieve. For another, except in the immediate aftermath of the worldwide credit crunch and 2008 recession, Italy's budget deficit has not been particularly large. Currently, the <ref target="http://www.mt5.com/forex_news/quickview/1185397">overall deficit</ref> stands at 4% of GDP, and would fall to about 3% next year if economies announced in August by the finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, were implemented. Italy's "basic budget balance" – the overall deficit minus interest payment, which is the main measure used by the IMF – is reasonably healthy.</p>
<p>Finally, it is crucial to note that considerably more than half of Italy's debt is held domestically, mainly because the small family businesses that dominate the economy like to hold their pensions in the form of government bonds. Unlike <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/greece">Greece</ref>, where most sovereign debt must be sold to the foreign market, Italy sells much of its debt to its own private sector; this means that public sector debt is offset by private sector liabilities. Seen from the point of view of the nation as a whole, Italy is far less "indebted" than its public sovereign debt ratio suggests. Hence, the real problem is not so much the size of Italy's debt ratio or its deficit as the cost of financing it out of very low growth. The perceived solution is more about the incoherence of Italian politics than about the instability of its finances.</p>
<p>Since Italy is "too big to fail", if push comes to shove the recent €1tn "big bazooka" for the EFSF will be sorely tested. As the well-known economist <ref target="http://financialnewsnow.info/efsf-needs-bigger-bazooka-to-maximise-its-firepower-financial-times/">Willem Buiter</ref> recently suggested, of the €440bn nominally available, only €300bn remains to be used for bank recapitalisation plus bailouts. Although this can in principle be leveraged to €1tn to provide a 20-25% "first loss" guarantee, it is highly doubtful that such a guarantee would reduce Italian and Spanish borrowing costs to sustainable levels. Either the EFSF big bazooka will have to be trebled or else the ECB will need to step in, the latter being the only European organisation with the firepower to effectively stop contagion.</p>
<p>The irony is that had the Germans allowed the ECB to intervene decisively in the sovereign debt crisis by guaranteeing the eurozone countries' bonds unconditionally, the crisis <ref target="http://www.social-europe.eu/2011/06/greece-unecessary-crisis/">could have been contained</ref> in early 2010. Instead, ECB intervention has been conditional and temporary, while the EFSF is too slow and underpowered a vehicle to perform the task.</p>
<p>The world may be glad to see the back of Berlusconi, but his departure will do little to resolve the crisis. In the immediate future, this can only be done if the ECB faces down the markets. A proper central bank must act as lender-of-last-resort. We are rapidly approaching the day when, if the eurozone is to be saved, its politicians will need to face this simple fact. Italy's crisis might yet prove to be a blessing in disguise.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>