<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2009-04-09" description="Roberto Mancini: The Catholic church's intervention in the 'living will' debate is an attempt to turn religious conviction into state law" fingerprint="ac9226ed43a6fd60" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Pope Benedict XVI,Silvio Berlusconi,Catholicism,Religion,Europe,The papacy" title="Roberto Mancini: The Church should stay out of secular matters" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2009/apr/08/italy-pope-benedict-xvi">
<main>
<p>The secular state in Italy is under threat from Papal power in an ever more intolerant and triumphalist Church. If the chamber of deputies (the lower house of the Italian parliament) confirms the <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7967207.stm">living will law</ref>, which has already been approved by the Italian Senate (the upper house) it will reintroduce an oppressive climate of callous Papal <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obscurantism">obscurantism</ref>. Silvio Berlusconi's coalition, completely in the grip of the hysterical fundamentalists and <ref target="http://www.clonline.org/FirstPage.htm">Communione e Liberazione</ref>, fellow travellers of the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel_Lefebvre">Lefebvre</ref> traditionalists, has backed a shameful measure: that the patient and his/her family's will, despite being expressed before a notary, is not binding for the doctor. Under no circumstances can treatment be suspended.</p>
<p>The church continues to demand the right to control not only the life, but also the death of all Italians. <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mediaset">Mediaset</ref>, meanwhile, has taken on the role of persuader for its master Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Pope Benedict XVI and the very powerful <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conferenza_Episcopale_Italiana">Italian Episcopal Conference</ref> are using Italy as the fortified bunker in which to resist the secular state which came into being after the French revolution. They demand, come hell or high water, an act of faith on the part of non-believers.</p>
<p>An essential stage in this process of political restoration is the complete liquidation of the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Vatican_Council">Vatican II</ref> doctrines, loathed by the followers of Lefebvre and all ultra-conservatives. As many commentators have observed, transforming a religious conviction into a state law is a form of theocratic behaviour worthy of an Iranian ayatollah.</p>
<p>Within the clergy, conformity and self-interest reign, and only a few isolated voices of dissent have been heard. Among these is <ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Gallo">Don Andrea Gallo</ref>, the brave and hard-fighting founder of the San Benedetto community in Genova. "Democracy cannot be founded on Faith but must be founded on liberty, justice and the individual's rights. The Senate's and the Bishop's law is an act of violence...within the Church the supremacy of personal conscience is the basis of our doctrine and those who deny this are heretics. The ecclesiastical hierarchy is upholding a bigoted crusade." Amen to that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>