<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Pete Cashmore" categories="Life and style" date="2011-12-28" description="Plenty of people made their mark on 2011, but not in a good way – Pete Cashmore offers a selection" fingerprint="6b96da6e3373fc7f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Ricky Gervais,David Guetta" title="2011: The people who ruined it" url="http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2011/dec/28/the-people-who-ruined-2011">
<main>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/music/david-guetta">David Guetta</ref>. Please stop</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> The Haribo family. Ghastly</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■ </hi>TOWIE's Arg. A man so tragically stupid that he could walk into a room containing nothing but a basic office chair and a necktie and within 10 minutes he would still somehow have been overpowered, bound and gagged. And yet richer and more successful than us, and you</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> Bono. We're not sure why, we just know that he must have done SOMETHING</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> Aleksandr Orlov. Yeah, OK, we get it</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> The Krankies. Not just "too much information", so much as "information that should only ever be revealed in a sealed concrete bunker in which there is no oxygen to sustain any human life that might overhear it"</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> Whoever devised and commissioned 'OMG! With Peaches Geldof'. You know who you are. And we know that you're out there. And WE WILL FIND YOU</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. Could only comport himself with less sexual dignity in 2012 if he spends the entire year surfacing at random in major seaports in a transparent Perspex submarine, naked and waving with his bark-encrusted scrotum pressed up against the glass</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi> The Rupert Murdoch pie chucker.</p>
<p>Not because he made people feel a twinge of sympathy for Rupert Murdoch but because his stage name is "Jonnie Marbles". Deserved to go to prison just for that</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■</hi><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/culture/ricky-gervais">Ricky Gervais</ref>. Failed to pass our diversity awareness test (see also John Galliano, John Terry, Luis Suarez, #tramlady et al)</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■ </hi>Kirstie Allsopp. You still here?</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">■ </hi>David Cameron. Well, DUH</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>