<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Fiona Winward; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2010-05-09" description="Culture minister Sandro Bondi refuses to attend event over screening of Sabina Guzzanti's Draquila which mocks the PM" fingerprint="7eba0aad9100eb14" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Cannes film festival,Festivals,Documentary films,Film,Culture,World news,Cannes 2010" title="Silvio Berlusconi documentary row leads to Italian MP snubbing Cannes" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/may/09/silvio-berlusconi-cannes-sandro-bondi">
<main>
<p>The Italian government is refusing to take part in this year's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/cannesfilmfestival">Cannes film festival</ref> in protest at a documentary mocking prime minister Silvio Berlusconi's response to the L'Aquila earthquake, which devastated the central Italian town last year, killing more than 300 people.</p>
<p>Italy's culture minister, Sandro Bondi, snubbed an invitation to the festival, expressing his "regret and concern" over the screening of Draquila, which he described as "propaganda that offends the truth and the entire Italian population".</p>
<p>The work of Italian satirist Sabina Guzzanti, Draquila claims that Berlusconi systematically exploited victims of the quake to increase his popularity.</p>
<p>Coming at a time when Berlusconi's ratings had dropped to an all-time low and he was assailed by accusations over his private life, the earthquake "was as if God had stretched out his hand" to the prime minister, says Guzzanti. In one scene she impersonates Berlusconi strutting in front of cameras wearing a hard hat.</p>
<p>The daughter of a former MP in Berlusconi's People of Freedom party, Guzzanti has long been a thorn in the side of the Berlusconi government. In 2008, Italy's equal opportunities minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/oct/10/italy-comedy">Mara Carfagna threatened to sue her</ref> when she suggested Berlusconi had given the 32-year-old former topless model her job in return for sexual favours. Both Berlusconi and Carfagna have denied reports of an affair.</p>
<p>Italian authorities tried to prosecute her for saying<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/sep/12/italy.catholicism"> that Pope Benedict will "end up in hell, tormented by queer demons".</ref></p>
<p>Her film will infuriate Berlusconi, who moved the G8 summit to L'Aquila and has repeatedly cited the government's response as a major achievement.</p>
<p>Bondi's refusal to go to Cannes risked sparking a diplomatic row. Former French culture minister Jack Lang branded Bondi's decision "absurd", adding that he had "a strange concept of [artistic] freedom".</p>
<p>"His position is puerile, infantile and capricious. Incomprehensible from a minister of the republic," said Lang, currently special envoy of French president Nicolas Sarkozy.</p>
<p>In Italy, opposition politicians and film-makers called for Bondi's resignation . "It's not art that offends the truth and the Italian people, but the decision of a minister who, instead of acting like one, prefers to play the role of the prime minister's faithful servant," said Luigi De Magistris, an MP with the Italy of Values party.</p>
<p>Bondi also came under fire from within his own party. "Representing Italy is the minister's duty over and above polemics," said People of Freedom MP Fabio Granata. "It's a question of respect for Italian cinema."</p>
<p>However, Bondi received support from opera director and film-maker Franco Zeffirelli, who claimed the minister was right not to go. "I don't see why Bondi should endorse an unworthy film that offends Italy," he said, "The festival is famous for putting the world's rubbish on its bill."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>