<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="News" date="2006-03-14" description="Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, and his rival, Romano Prodi, face off tonight in the first of two television debates that could decide a general election in which any hint of a message is currently swamped by focus on the media, writes John Hooper in Rome." fingerprint="7ea6d76d1441c699" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Chicken and chips, chalk and cheese" url="http://www.theguardian.com/news/blog/2006/mar/14/chickenandchi">
<main>
<p><lb/> Silvio Berlusconi prepares for a television interview. Photograph: Plinio Lepri/AP<lb/> Italy's prime minister, <ref target="http://www.forza-italia.it/silvioberlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, and his rival, <ref target="http://www.romanoprodi.it">Romano Prodi</ref>, face off tonight in the first of two television debates that could decide a general election in which any hint of a message is currently swamped by focus on the media, <hi rend="#i">writes John Hooper in Rome</hi>.</p>
<p>The vote, on April 9 and 10, was meant to have been about the deplorable performance of the Italian economy since it fell into the hands of Italy's richest man. Other expected issues were education, taxation and the enduring conflict of interest between Mr Berlusconi's roles as a media proprietor and conservative politician.</p>
<p>But the main topic of discussion so far this week has been the prime minister walking out on an interviewer who <ref target="http://www.rai.it/news">dared to pitch</ref> him some tough questions. And by this morning reporting of the campaign was focused on such topics as what the moderator of <ref target="http://www.eventiraiuno.rai.it/HPprogramma/0,4520,41,00.html">tonight's debate</ref>, his wife and daughters ate for dinner last night after spending the evening in a bowling alley. It was roast chicken and chips.</p>
<p>The rigid rules of what looks like being a stilted, US-style debate have been pored over endlessly.</p>
<p>The absence of issues is partly because of Italy's decision to return to proportional representation. One of its many negative effects has been to sever the link between candidates and electors making it virtually unnecessary for the former to seek votes from the latter. The parties decide each candidate's ranking on a list from which the winners will be picked in turn as the votes are distributed.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, therefore, there has been little megaphone-and-soap box turns on the hustings, but even more concentration than in recent elections elsewhere in Europe on the two leading candidates and their TV appearances. Not that they have been anywhere like comparable.</p>
<p>Before equal air time rules came into force at the start of the campaign, Mr Berlusconi racked up hours of exposure on the commercial TV channels he owns and the state-run channels which, as prime minister, he can influence. Presenters, who would have been only too aware that their jobs could be on the line, rarely stopped him from launching into a monologue in which he lauded his government's purported achievements.</p>
<p>It is slightly ironic, therefore, that such care should now be invested in ensuring neither candidate overruns his time by more than a few seconds or gets an unfair advantage by having his good side nearest to the camera.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>