<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Heather Stewart" categories="Business" date="2009-07-04" description="Heather Stewart looks behind the G8 summit at the financial troubles faced by Italy" fingerprint="3ace817ed021c743" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Global recession,Global economy,Business,G8,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Italy's financial tremors rumble on for Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2009/jul/05/g8-summit-italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi will welcome world leaders to the earthquake-hit city of L'Aquila this week when he hosts the G8 gathering of western nations. But while these shindigs are traditionally an opportunity to show off the host nation's economy at its best, the credit crunch has left Italy with little to boast about.</p>
<p>Already hemmed in by hefty public debts - worth more than 100% of GDP - and an uncompetitive export sector, the country has been plunged into a severe recession by the collapse in world trade and analysts say it could take many years to recover. Industrial output fell so sharply in the first three months of this year that it is now back to the levels of two decades ago.</p>
<p>"Italy's quite reliant on manufacturing exports, and that's been hit particularly hard," says Zach Witton, of Moody's <ref target="http://www.economy.com">economy.com</ref>. He expects a sharp fall in GDP of more than 4% this year and predicts that the economy will continue shrinking in 2010, with pre-crisis rates of growth not returning until 2012 at the earliest.</p>
<p>Other governments, including Germany's, where Angela Merkel's finance minister, Peer Steinbrück, was initially scathing of "crass Keynesianism", have increased public spending to support their economies through the market turmoil. But Rome's coffers were already bare before the crisis began. "They've got one of the highest levels of public debt in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, and that is constraining the opportunity for fiscal stimulus," says Witton.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's antics with a string of young women have caught the headlines, but many voters have less titillating concerns on their minds. "The Italian economy, like its prime minister, is looking more and more debilitated: it may be capable of toughing it out, but at considerable and growing cost," says Maya Bhandari, of Lombard Street Research. She warns that a "lost decade" of sickly growth and declining market share is set to turn into another 10 years of lagging behind.</p>
<p>When the International Monetary Fund carried out its regular check-up on the Italian economy earlier this year, it reported bluntly that "the near-term outlook is bleak". At 7.4%, unemployment is lower than the European average, but productivity - the amount produced per worker, a fundamental key to economic success - has fallen by about 2% a year since 2000.</p>
<p>Italian banks avoided many of the worst excesses that led to the credit crunch, but Intesa and Unicredito, two of the largest, have considerable exposures in vulnerable eastern Europe. Unicredito has already received financial support from the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development, to prevent it pulling the plug on loans to struggling economies such as Hungary.</p>
<p>Even before the credit crunch, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> was singled out as one of the "Pigs" (Portugal, Italy, Greece and Spain) that were lagging behind their northern cousins, making it almost impossible for the European Central Bank to set an appropriate interest rate for everyone.</p>
<p>When the euro was launched, one of its purported benefits was that the discipline of being forced to stick to the rules of the stability and growth pact, without the safety valve of a depreciation, would force governments to implement reforms. In fact, many observers now argue that the shelter of a common currency - which prevents financial markets picking off the currencies of weaker members and sending them into freefall - has masked the policy weaknesses of the Pigs.</p>
<p>Italy still has thousands of tiny family firms valiantly struggling to compete in low-value manufacturing with much cheaper Asian rivals, while a forest of regulation makes it difficult for new enterprises to establish themselves. It has consistently lost export market share to other countries for years.</p>
<p>It takes a brave government to wrestle with many of these challenges. Jonathan Ashworth, an economist at Barclays Wealth, says: "I've always thought Italy is the best example of a failure of good governance."</p>
<p>When Berlusconi's predecessor Romano Prodi's administration tried to reform the regulation of taxis in 2006, in a bid to cut fares and allow more operators into the market, thousands of drivers blockaded the streets of Rome in protests that lasted for months.</p>
<p>Berlusconi himself has shown little appetite for forcing through unpopular change. He plans to focus on natural-disaster recovery and re-regulation of the financial sector with his international rivals this week; but he also faces a much tougher struggle to clear the rubble from Italy's battered economy.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>