<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roy Greenslade" categories="Media" date="2007-11-23" description="Leaked phone taps suggesting that Italian state television RAI and its private rival Mediaset colluded to favour Silvio Berlusconi when he was prime minister have thrown the spotlight on political interference in Italy's media." fingerprint="276a878c90a3c745" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="So Berlusconi DID control TV output" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2007/nov/23/soberlusconididcontroltvo">
<main>
<p>Leaked phone taps suggesting that Italian state television <hi rend="#b">RAI</hi> and its private rival <hi rend="#b">Mediaset</hi> colluded to favour <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi> when he was prime minister have thrown the spotlight on political interference in Italy's media.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">La Repubblica</hi> has published transcripts of phone conversations in 2004 and 2005 between executives at RAI and at Mediaset, owned by Berlusconi, during which executives discuss how to present his defeat at local elections in a more favourable light in news programmes and talk shows.</p>
<p>During his five years in power, the media tycoon turned political leader was widely accused by opponents of controlling 90% of Italy's broadcasters, because RAI is traditionally subject to government influence. The report has sparked an outcry among Berlusconi's critics and prompted an internal investigation at RAI, which has now moved closer to the government of prime minister <hi rend="#b">Romano Prodi</hi>.</p>
<p>RAI is at the heart of Italy's patronage system. Successive governments hand out top jobs there to reward loyal proteges. Its board members, appointed by parliament and the government, are picked depending on their party affiliation. (Via <ref target="http://investing.reuters.co.uk/news/articleinvesting.aspx?type=media&amp;storyID=nL21184462">Reuters</ref>)</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>