<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Giulia Lagana" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-17" description="Giulia Lagana: Italy has fewer women in parliament than Afghanistan. But no wonder, when it seems that to get into government, only the gorgeous qualify" fingerprint="bef2522fb2a2f68d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Gender,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi's beauty pageant" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/17/berlusconisbeautypageant">
<main>
<p>Identifying the political winners of Italy's recent election may be relatively easy, but one particular category appears to have lost out once again - women, who make up over half the electorate, look set to scoop less than a quarter of the seats available in the new parliament. Female MPs in Italy, according to the <ref target="http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm">Inter-Parliamentary Union</ref>, made up just over 15% of the total in 2006, against a European average of 21% and 36% in similarly devoutly <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2008/04/17/witaly117.xml">Catholic Spain</ref>. Given current trends, Rwanda's 49% of female parliamentarians, or even Afghanistan's 28%, seem hard to attain.</p>
<p>A rather lacklustre election campaign was livened up by Silvio Berlusconi's jokes, many of which are about the beautiful women he seems to privilege as political partners. "Rightwing women are definitely more beautiful than leftwing ones", he told journalists a few days before the vote. During his previous stint as prime minister, the tycoon turned political leader <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/feb/01/pressandpublishing.italy">told delegates</ref> from his coalition partners the National Alliance: "I notice some extraordinary pretty legs around here." Back in 2002, Berlusconi began a joint press conference with Danish prime minister Anders Fogh Rasmusson by remarking that "Rasmussen is the most <ref target="http://observer.theguardian.com/magazine/story/0,11913,1123962,00.html">attractive prime minister</ref> in Europe".</p>
<p>Berlusconi has promised that four of the 12 ministers in his government will be women, against Romano Prodi's six out of 25. Like Prodi, though, the new prime minister looks set to only allocate low-level ministries without a budget, like the ministry for the family, to women. Top candidates include <ref target="http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/people,870,can-berlusconis-women-save-italy,25058">Mara Carfagna</ref>, a former TV starlet and Miss Italy finalist whose recent two-year stint in parliament went virtually unnoticed and who will probably head the equal opportunities ministry, and Stefania Prestigiacomo, a striking former minister in Berlusconi's 2001-2006 government whose stance on gay rights and IVF treatment set her out from the yes-men (and women) Berlusconi usually favours.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article3750505.ece">Giulia Bongiorno</ref>, who is mooted as the next justice minister, first registered on the media radar when, as veteran prime minister Giulio Andreotti's lawyer, she screamed with joy as judges in Palermo assessing Andreotti's links with the mafia delivered a guilty verdict for her client which was tempered by the statute of limitations, making it void. Bongiorno has since gone on to forge a career as a top lawyer for the rich and famous.</p>
<p>Rising stars in Berlusconi's coalition include the flamboyant Angela Maraventano, a restaurant owner who hails from the tiny Sicilian island of Lampedusa, where most of Italy's boat people land every year, and who will represent the deeply anti-south and xenophobic <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7350691.stm">Northern League</ref> after a stint as the island's deputy mayor.</p>
<p>Chauvinism and a lack of gender equality, however, are not confined to the right. The leftist Rainbow alliance's leaders are all middle-aged men. Walter Veltroni, the head of the Democratic party, walked out to face the cameras <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_pictures/7347658.stm">on Monday night</ref> and to congratulate Berlusconi on his victory surrounded by the party's top brass, all of whom, except for three token women, were men.</p>
<p>Maybe Italian women will be better represented next time - though, if Berlusconi is right about voters privileging "aesthetics", they will have to ensure female candidates are "beautiful chicks" to stand a chance.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>