<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-08-02" description="Italy's lower house to decide whether to demand ousting of Giacomo Caliendo, in test of prime minister's majority" fingerprint="7fb9983d1c838fef" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Berlusconi minister faces parliamentary vote over corruption claims" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/aug/02/silvio-berlusconi-giacomo-caliendo-vote">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi learned tonight that he faces a crucial parliamentary ballot on Wednesday that will test the strength of his majority – and the credibility of the rebels challenging him.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister's former ally and now leading critic, Gianfranco Fini, the speaker of the lower house, agreed that the chamber of deputies should vote on an affair that goes to the heart of divisions in the country's politics.</p>
<p>In what is likely to be its last act before the summer recess, the lower house will decide whether to demand that the government relieve of his duties a junior minister involved in a corruption inquiry.</p>
<p>The vote, which could trigger a full-blown government crisis, is scheduled to be held two hours before David Cameron arrives in Rome for talks with Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Giacomo Caliendo, a junior justice minister, was told last month he was formally under investigation on suspicion of belonging to a secret cabal that is claimed to have acted as the prime minister's dirty tricks unit. It allegedly tried to influence judges involved in cases vital to Berlusconi, and dug the dirt on his opponents.</p>
<p>Caliendo has refused to resign, and his stance has been backed by the prime minister. Fini has repeatedly challenged Berlusconi's easy-going attitude to graft allegations and said last month that any member of the government who was put under investigation should resign immediately.</p>
<p>His decision, at a meeting of parliamentary managers, is bound to anger Berlusconi, whose representative at the meeting described it afterwards as "unacceptable". Last week, 33 deputies loyal to Fini broke away to form their own group in the lower house and today it emerged that 10 members of the senate were forming a parallel group in the upper house.</p>
<p>On paper at least, the defections have robbed Berlusconi of his majority in the chamber of deputies. A defeat on Wednesday would not force the government from office, but it would be a humiliating setback and might prompt Berlusconi to seek a snap election.</p>
<p>Remarks by some of Fini's followers, however, suggested they could seek refuge in abstention. That would deal a severe blow to Fini's credibility and that of his cause. He is already under pressure after a report last week in a newspaper owned by the Berlusconi family, claiming that the brother of Fini's partner was living in a flat in Monte Carlo that had been bequeathed to the speaker's former party.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Fini described the allegations in Il Giornale as "false and defamatory" and said he had instructed his lawyer to sue for libel.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>