<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Xan Brooks" categories="Film" date="2010-05-13" description="It's the morning after the official opening of the Cannes film festival, and the competition films have started unspooling. Xan Brooks gets stuck in" fingerprint="aa3696d5b140ff7d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Xan Brooks Cannes diary,Cannes film festival,Film,Culture,Festivals,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World cinema,Cannes 2010" title="Cannes 2010 diary: those homesick Chongqing Blues" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2010/may/13/cannes-2010-diary-mathieu-amalric">
<main>
<p>The sun is out, the sky is blue, but <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2009/may/18/cannes-film-festival-antichrist-lars-von-trier">chaos reigns</ref> at the heart of the Palais. I can't see the sky and the sun is a dream because I'm forever inside, pinballing between the darkened screening rooms. This Cannes has opened in a rumble-tumble rush, the same as it always does. In the scramble to get through the cordons I see a man go down, spread-eagled on the carpet, and the surge of the crowd whisks me past before I can reach out to haul him up. Perhaps he is lying there still.</p>
<p>I watch Chongqing Blues, which is measured and engrossing; a kind of emotional post-mortem that charts an ageing ship captain's search for the truth behind his estranged son's death. I see Tournée, directed by Mathieu Amalric, who also stars as the harassed promoter cajoling an American burlesque troupe down the west coast of France. If Amalric's film is finally too transient – too light on luggage – to be fully successful, it's still sharply observed and nicely played by an ensemble cast. The dancers keep likening Amalric to a frog, but he's actually more rodent-like, with his darting movements, whiskery grin and bright black eyes. His voluptuous co-stars loom effortlessly over him. Each time there's an argument I fear for his safety.</p>
<p>Should we also be worried about Sabina Guzzanti? The evidence suggests we should, because her Michael Moore-ish documentary Draquila: L'Italie Qui Tremble has already sparked <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/may/09/silvio-berlusconi-cannes-sandro-bondi">a diplomatic incident on the Croisette</ref>, with the Italian culture minister boycotting the festival in protest. The problem, it seems, is that Guzzanti has had the temerity to lambast Silvio Berlusconi's handling of the L'Aquila earthquake, claiming that he used it as an excuse to draft draconian new laws (ostensibly "emergency" measures) while shoving the survivors into tent cities where the gates are locked and the roads are prowled by soldiers. Anyone who protests (mostly old men and women, from the looks of the footage) now faces up to five years in prison. Anyone, that is, except the Italian culture minister, who seems to have hit upon a nifty legal loophole. Malcontents take note: you may protest in favour of Silvio Berlusconi, but not against him.</p>
<p>At the back of the Palais, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/video/2009/may/21/cannes-film-festival-marche">the Marché du Film</ref> has opened its doors and set up its stalls. I vow to pay it a visit, to see what exotic goods are on offer this year. But before that, I have another screening to attend and this one is in the Salle Buñuel, on the fifth floor, right at the top. In my panic I mispronounce the name: "Je cherche Sally Buñuel!", which makes it sound as though I'm late for a meeting with Luis's demented little sister. I'd quite like to see a film by Sally Buñuel, but sadly it is not to be, because she does not actually exist. Salle Buñuel, on the other hand, does – and incredibly it boasts acres more legroom than the fancy Salle Debussy and Grand Théâtre Lumière. I kick back, stretch out and wait for the lights to go down. Five minutes in, it already feels like home.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>