<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2011-11-09" description="Letters: The power of the cabal will be broken when we learn to trust the citizen and involve them in the decision-making process" fingerprint="7bc85b47737ce696" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European Union,Europe,Nicolas Sarkozy,George Papandreou,Silvio Berlusconi,Greece,Italy,Angela Merkel,World news,International Monetary Fund (IMF),Economics,Global economy,European Central Bank,Financial crisis,Global recession,Banking,Eurozone crisis,European banks,Business" title="Letters: Europe's shameful democratic deficit" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/europe-shameful-democratic-deficit">
<main>
<p>Larry Elliott is right: the anti-democracy movement is gathering pace (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/economics-blog/2011/nov/08/euro-papandreou-berlusconi-bailout-debt">This is no democracy – Europe is being run by a cabal</ref>, 9 November). More sinister still, not only is democracy under threat but politics too. Wherever people gather together in public to make political demands they are derided and dissuaded, sometimes stealthily – as in David Cameron calling on the St Paul's protesters to disperse (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2011/nov/08/occupy-london-protesters-issue-demands">Report</ref>, 9 November).</p>
<p>The prime minister's assertion that people have the right to protest rings hollow when advance warning is given of the possible use of baton rounds. So the students that demonstrated yesterday were not only defending the welfare state (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/07/students-fighting-education-welfare-state">It's not just education: we're defending the welfare state</ref>, 8 November), they are defending politics itself by occupying public spaces and making political demands. The same goes for the various Occupy movements around the world, and David Cameron can't pick and choose which ones to support – vocally in support of the Egyptian demonstrators in Tahrir Square earlier this year, yet sanctioning the violent removal of the Trafalgar Square protesters. Wherever they are, the Occupiers have one thing in common: the demand for regime change, a change from a social life dictated by the market to one determined by the people.<hi rend="#b">Professor Andrew Dobson</hi><hi rend="#i">Keele University</hi></p>
<p>Larry Elliot's article on Europe's democratic deficit may have been stating the obvious, but we do need to debate it.</p>
<p>The EU has always had a problematic relationship with democracy. Ireland said no to the Nice treaty in a referendum and was ordered to hold a second ballot to ensure victory.</p>
<p>Yes, a cabal runs Europe, it would be worrying if their policies were working, but they are not. The trouble for the average citizen is that governments come and go, but policies remain. The question "why bother?" is then asked, leaving a vacuum for a cabal to survive. Turnout across Europe at the last EU elections was 43%, hardly a ringing endorsement.</p>
<p>The power of the cabal will be broken when we learn to trust the citizen and involve them in the decision-making process. We must debate directly electing commissioners and make the council transparent. And first to go must be the closed list system for electing MEPs.</p>
<p>The EU is an ongoing experiment, with 60 years of achievements and failures. The only way it can be a successful experiment is to never stop striving for improvement.<hi rend="#b">Sajjad Karim MEP</hi><hi rend="#i">Conservative, North West England</hi></p>
<p> Caroline Lucas rather misses the point when she portrays the Green party as an alternative to the current political class (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/07/greens-support-the-occupy-movement">Letters</ref> , 8 November). Her party is as much a part of the pro-EU consensus as the Lib-Lab-Con, and virtually all of her policy ideas come straight from the European commission.</p>
<p>Ukip totally opposes this new form of unelected government and is picking up significant support as a result.<hi rend="#b">Nigel Farage MEP</hi><hi rend="#i">Ukip, South East England</hi></p>
<p> First George Papandreou, now Silvio Berlusconi – when it comes to deciding who's in power, it's the markets that ultimately decide (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-to-resign-italy?newsfeed=true">Report</ref>, 9 November). I am not a fan of these politicians, but I naively thought it is electorates that choose who's in power, rather than stockbrokers, bankers and credit-rating agencies.</p>
<p>In Papandreou's case, it seems his mistake was suggesting that he dare consult the electorate. Now we hear that markets are "demanding" the establishment of non-political leaderships in both countries. Perhaps it would be easier for them if we all gave up on elections and installed administrators instead?<hi rend="#b">Stephen Tibbett</hi><hi rend="#i">London</hi></p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>