<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2009-10-25" description="Roberto Mancini: The Italian leader's obsession with being in sole command may damage the fragile democratic scaffolding of the constitution" fingerprint="7aa44228050b7f90" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi's videocracy | Roberto Mancini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/oct/25/berlusconi-italy-critics">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi recently declared war against the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/08/silvio-berlusconi-immunity-television">president of Italy</ref>, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/08/sivlio-berlusconi-immunity-law-overturned">constitutional court</ref>, judges and the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/libertycentral/2009/oct/13/silvio-berlusconi-propaganda-unit">foreign press</ref>: "I, personally, will take care of freedom and democracy," he announced.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's lastest outburst took place at the headquarters of the Industrial Association of Monza, in the vicinity of Milan. As usual, the prime minister's language was theatrical, but above all it revealed his peculiar concept of democracy, which coincides perfectly with that of his friend, Vladimir Putin: "You look after the feel-good factor, I'll look after freedom and democracy."</p>
<p>He used a typical Milanese dialectal expression "<ref target="http://www.corriere.it/politica/09_ottobre_12/marcegaglia_napolitano_berlusconi_a28496b6-b74e-11de-b239-00144f02aabc.shtml"> ghe pensi mi</ref>" (I'll take care of it myself) to express how zealous he is. Although he lives in a permanently hectic whirl, he'll find time (like Superman?) to personally look after everything.</p>
<p>He's an autocrat, a monarch.</p>
<p>In his usual impromptu style he offered a place in his government to <ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emma_Marcegaglia">Emma Marcegaglia</ref>, the president of the Italian Industrialists (the Italian CBI) who was present at the meeting, before going on to describe as "anti-Italian" anyone who dares criticise him – identifying himself, modestly, with the state.</p>
<p>So what's new? Mussolini too defined those anti-fascists who were forced by the regime to go into exile as enemies not of his government, but of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
<p>Being in sole command is Berlusconi's real obsession. During the past 10 years, even when he was the leader of the opposition, he has relentlessly delegitimised every institution – the judiciary, the constitutional court, the National Audit Office or the head of state. First it was <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscar_Luigi_Scalfaro">Scalfaro</ref>'s turn, then <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_Azeglio_Ciampi">Ciampi</ref>'s and now it's <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Napolitano">Napolitano</ref>'s.</p>
<p>More serious is that his attitude has not changed as prime minister. The idea that holding this office entails any particular obligations never seems to occur to him. Electoral success is an absolute – and superior to any state institution. Whoever has the voters' approval should be entitled to immunity from criminal and civil liability.</p>
<p>The candidate chosen by the people is thus above the law; he is anointed by the Lord, like the Sun King – motto: "<hi rend="#i">L'état c'est moi</hi>". He seems unable to distinguish the fundamental and constitutional differences between an autocracy and a liberal democracy, or to understand the balance of powers, or the distinction between the state and the government. He lashes out at a new adversary every day.</p>
<p>In his inimitable way, he brands as "communist" those who dare to maintain that "we are all equal in the eyes of the law" (the motto displayed in every Italian courtroom). As the proprietor and shareholder of many media companies he considers journalists his serfs, and he now routinely describes the New York Times and other foreign newspapers as dangerous Bolshevik publications, claiming that the foreign press bad-mouths him, Italian democracy and Italian products.</p>
<p>Italian democracy is still young and fragile. The risk is that, sustained by his powerful media lineup, Berlusconi's actions damage the fragile democratic scaffolding of the constitution, which has held the country up since 1948. The rules of a liberal democratic state are in danger of being subverted by a conceited and ignorant videocracy, which measures the performance of government ministers in terms of their TV performances.</p>
<p>So we Italians are subjected to a never-ending political theatre, which panders to the lowest populist instinct of an audience of vulnerable consumers of silly television game shows, invented by delinquent spin-doctors.</p>
<p>To illustrate my point I'd like to recommend <ref target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120086/">Joe Dante's The Second Civil War</ref> (1997), a prophetic vision of the current situation in Italy. Representative democracy, in Italy as all over Europe, must be defended.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian.</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>