<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Annalisa Piras" categories="World news" date="2011-01-14" description="There is a long list of cases pending against the scandal-prone Italian prime minister but it seems unlikely they will proceed" fingerprint="b3e6510eac36df55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" title="Silvio Berlusconi scandals set to rumble on" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/14/silvio-berlusconi-scandals">
<main>
<p>Paying for sex with a minor in Italy carries a maximum sentence of three years, but in all likelihood <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has nothing to fear from what he describes as his "platonic" friendship with Ruby Rubacuori.</p>
<p>The 17-year-old belly dancer denies any "active" participation in the erotic rituals allegedly favoured by the prime minister, and the other attendees are unlikely to testify to the contrary. Even if they did, Italy's constitutional court has only partially dismantled the immunity shield Berlusconi's lawyers have devised to protect him.</p>
<p>There is a long list of cases pending against the 75-year-old prime minister, but it seems unlikely they will proceed either. The Italian justice system is shamefully slow and renowned for its inefficiency. For those with money and political influence, there are infinite delaying tactics to reach the statute of limitations.</p>
<p>Some magistrates, and a small number of politicians in the opposition, demand that Berlusconi answers the accusations in court. But the truth is that trying to defeat him legally has, in the past, fed his "victimisation" propaganda, and made him stronger in elections. It may do so again. The prime minister plans early elections, for which, according to Italian reports, he would present a new party, simply called Italia. "If you vote against Italia, goes the slogan, "you are voting against your country".</p>
<p>Pollsters say that in 2011, the year of the 150th anniversary of the unity of Italy, the name may inspire voters. Ironically his new Patriotic party, predicted to win 25% of the vote, would only be able to govern in a coalition with the Northern League, the secessionist, xenophobic party whose leaders love to loathe the national flag.</p>
<p>If the party wins, the palace of the President of the Republic, and the end of any legal threat, would be the next step for Berlusconi. His enormous wealth, his grip on the economy and the various systems of power seem often to make him invincible.</p>
<p>The centre-left opposition, increasingly divided and confused, appears incapable of offering any credible alternative, even though, if united, it could gain the numbers to govern. Italy, in dire need of a competent government, seems condemned to be held hostage for many months by the personal scandals besieging its discredited prime minister.</p>
<p>All Italian leaders, including the Catholic church, playing an increasingly open role in politics, share a responsibility in the country's mess.</p>
<p>A famous quote from the founders of the united Italy is "now we have created Italia, we need to work on creating the Italians". It is meant to stress the importance of building a sense of the common purpose and civic duty in a culture which has been so often cursed by individual selfishness and egoism.Now that Berlusconi is creating "Italia", how long before Italians demand he serve the common interest?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Annalisa Piras is the London correspondent of L'Espresso, Italy's leading news magazine </hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>