<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2009-12-15" description="Anna Masera: Many of Silvio Berlusconi's fiercest opponents are uneasy cheering violence – reminded of dark times in Italy's history" fingerprint="7a0e10f7df2dded5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Italians wrestle with Berlusconi attack | Anna Masera" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/dec/15/silvio-berlusconi-attack-opponents-italy">
<main>
<p>"This is truly a bad day for Italy, and it's the duty of all the political forces to ensure that Italy does not go back to the years of violence," commented Gianfranco Fini after Sunday's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-milan-statue-attack">attack on Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister</ref>. Fini talked as the head of the Italian house of representatives, but his comment reflects the thoughts of many Italians, on both sides of the political spectrum: Berlusconi's wounded face full of blood left most astonished and in deep shock.</p>
<p>Their memory goes back to two dramatic times in Italian history: <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/28/newsid_3564000/3564529.stm">Mussolini's corpse being hung on display</ref> in Milan's Piazzale Loreto in 1945 after the defeat of fascism, and the so-called <hi rend="#i">anni di piombo</hi> (leaden years, literally) in the 1970s, when leftwing and rightwing extremists put the country under fire and the government was accused of pursuing a <hi rend="#i">strategia della tensione</hi> (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strategy_of_tension">strategy of tension</ref>). There is an awareness today of the risk of a polarised tense political climate in which terrorism may flourish once again.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/_web/cmstp/tmplRubriche/editoriali/gEditoriali.asp?ID_blog=25&amp;ID_articolo=6734&amp;ID_sezione=&amp;sezione=">Mario Calabresi</ref>, editor-in-chief of La Stampa and son of police commissioner Luigi Calabresi, one of the first victims of that terrorism in the 70s, wrote in the newspaper:</p>
<quote>There is never justification for violence. The day Italian politics understands this, it will have reached maturity. The wounded bloodied face of Silvio Berlusconi cannot but leave us flabbergasted. I can't imagine a serious person with a desire to be seen as good and democratic having a different reaction to what happened. If the first reaction is that he asked for it or deserved it, that means that we entered a space in which the political dialectic has degenerated.</quote>
<p>On the internet there is a reflection of the argument raging among Italian citizens. Many assert that what happened to Berlusconi was a reaction to an anti-democratic, xenophobic government: "he asked for it" is the main message that comes across on a Facebook page of Massimo Tartaglia, the aggressor, which has 50,000 fans. It was an act of a psychologically disturbed person with no political affiliation, yet for them he is a hero because he managed to hit the premier in the face. But there are at least just as many who say that such thoughts are despicable.</p>
<p>And while some politicians are already worrying about too much freedom of expression online and invoking censorship, it helps to realise that what comes across in the online world is what crosses the minds of people in the real world: even well-known politicians such as Rosy Bindi. In an <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/redazione/cmsSezioni/politica/200912articoli/50349girata.asp">interview with La Stampa</ref>, the president of the Democratic party – known for her deep personal animosity for Berlusconi, especially since he said on public television that she was "more good-looking than intelligent" – couldn't withhold a thought that crosses the minds of many Italians who dislike Berlusconi: violence should be condemned, but the premier is not a victim, he is responsible for the creation of a violent climate.</p>
<p>As Calabresi concludes in his article, the atmosphere in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> is similar to that of a stadium in which one hears only the voices of the ultras shouting. And where everybody seems more interested in the destiny of the premier than the country.</p>
<p>Yet maybe this event will help restore the basic values and premises necessary in a democracy. Ezio Mauro, editor-in-chief of La Repubblica, the newspaper at the vanguard of fierce opposition to Berlusconi, yesterday wrote an <ref target="http://www.repubblica.it/2009/12/sezioni/politica/giustizia-21/aggressione-mauro/aggressione-mauro.html">opinion piece</ref> entitled: "Against violence, for freedom", in which he expressed solidarity towards the wounded premier, because he is "a man hit by violence", in an "insane gesture that reminds us of the kind of tragic period we experienced during the worst years of our lives". Mauro, underlining the fact that the pictures of the premier's bloodied face circulating all over the world testify to the degradation of Italian politics, calls on friends and adversaries to unite against violence:</p>
<quote>It's the only way to save politics […] Even if the gesture of Piazza Duomo is an isolated incident and the fruit of insanity, at stake is nothing less than freedom. Berlusconi's freedom to display his politics and ideas coincides with our freedom to criticise him. This 'freedom space' is called democracy. Let's defend it.</quote>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>