<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2004-02-18" description='The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, suggested yesterday it was "morally acceptable" to avoid paying taxes if they were too high, as he launched his European parliamentary election campaign.' fingerprint="5f5ae227b043fe2c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="It's OK to dodge taxes, says Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/feb/18/italy.sophiearie">
<main>
<p>As election pledges go, it was almost certainly a winner: don't pay tax.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, suggested yesterday it was "morally acceptable" to avoid paying taxes if they were too high, as he launched his European parliamentary election campaign.</p>
<p>"If we ask citizens to pay 33% tax they will all convince themselves that it is right and a duty, that it is correct to pay for the services they receive," Ansa news agency quoted him as saying.</p>
<p>But the billionaire media tycoon also told a press conference that if taxes amounted to more than 50% of people's income, it seemed "morally acceptable" to avoid paying.</p>
<p>He pledged to bring down taxes next year ahead of Italy's 2006 general elections.</p>
<p>Opposition politicians howled with disapproval. "This is clearly an instigation to break the law," said a Left Democrat, Fabio Mussi. "It is a crime not to pay taxes. It would be good if Berlusconi remembered that."</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi confirmed he would stand for European elections this June, dismissing the possibility of losing as an "impossible hypothesis", despite recent polls indicating his popularity is sliding.</p>
<p>His candidacy comes days after his arch rival, the European commission president and former prime minister Romano Prodi, launched a campaign to unite the Italian left against Mr Berlusconi's centre-right coalition.</p>
<p>Observers say the prime minister is likely to decline taking up a seat in the European parliament should he win, passing it to another candidate from his party.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>