<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-10-26" description="Government pledges to bring in a plan for sales of public assets that will bring in an extra €15bn" fingerprint="6f8c81bf91399649" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe,European Commission,European Union,The League" title="Berlusconi hopes letter to Brussels will improve Italy's financial standing" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/26/berlusconi-hopes-letter-europe-improve-financial-markets">
<main>
<p>The letter that Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, was putting before his fellow European leaders on Wednesday night contained plans for early sales of public assets and a change in employment law to make it easier for workers to be made redundant, according to a version leaked to the Italian news agency Adnkronos.</p>
<p>The document was drawn up by Berlusconi's rightwing administration in an effort to bolster the financial markets' faith in Italy's ability to pay off its huge borrowings and isolate it from the debt crisis sweeping the euro zone. The centrepiece of the document was a modest scheme of pension reform.</p>
<p>Pierluigi Bersani, the leader of Italy's main opposition group, the Democratic party, swiftly dismissed the government's letter as containing "nothing serious".</p>
<p>Adnkronos said the government had pledged to bring in by 30 November a plan for sales of public assets that would yield the treasury an extra €5bn (£4.4bn) over each of the next three years. It also committed itself to a relaxation of the law that prevents employers from dismissing workers in an economic downturn.</p>
<p>The tense atmosphere was highlighted when two deputies – one from the government benches and another in opposition – had to be separated by attendants in parliament. They almost came to blows over a remark by the speaker, Gianfranco Fini, on TV on Tuesday night. In a discussion of the Northern League's reluctance to agree to wider pension reform, Fini reminded viewers that the wife of Umberto Bossi, leader of the League, had retired at the age of 39. A League representative angrily accused the speaker of failing to act impartially and "offending those who took advantage of pension regulations that were in effect at the time".</p>
<p>As Berlusconi arrived in Brussels for the European summit, he was given new warning of the risks facing Italy.</p>
<p>Alessandro Settepani of the ratings agency Fitch said its sovereign bonds could be downgraded again because of Italy's failing economic growth prospects.</p>
<p>"The Italian growth rates forecast even for next year are very low," he told the Ansa news agency. Settepani said Fitch could take "a new rating action" in 12-24 months, but might act sooner if "something negative happens".</p>
<p>A spokesperson in Brussels said earlier that the European commission was expecting from Rome "a list of very detailed, concrete measures with a clear timetable that must be followed by the speedy application of new measures".</p>
<p>The prime minister had hoped to convince the Northern League, the junior partners in his rightwing coalition, of the need for a radical change in the pension system. The reform would have improved the long-term prospects for paying off Italy's mountainous, €1.8trillion public debt.</p>
<p>But the most Bossi would agree to was a slight modification to existing plans to raise the normal retirement age by 2026. The government is committed to changing the pension age from 65 to 67, according to the letter.</p>
<p>Bossi refused to endorse a plan to abolish Italy's time-in-work pension entitlement which allows for retirement before the standard pensionable age.</p>
<p>According to some accounts, denied by the League, its consent to even a limited reform was made conditional on the prime minister standing down in January to force a snap election. It had been widely speculated in Italy that the government might in any case step aside in the new year.</p>
<p>But in the version offered by La Repubblica, Berlusconi, 75, would again stand as the candidate of the right. Such a move would dash the hopes of many in the markets who have been assuming the prime minister would be replaced by a politically neutral government, headed by a technocrat, that could introduce painful but necessary reforms.</p>
<p>Chief among these are measures to promote growth by modernising Italy's economy. The government has for weeks been discussing a bill to stimulate growth, but without agreeing on a draft.</p>
<p>But according to the leaked version of the letter to Brussels, the government said it would have its plans ready by 15 November and would introduce four new measures in the next eight months.</p>
<p>The president-designate of the European Central Bank, Mario Draghi, called it a programme for "courageous reforms". His remark was among the few positive signs on a day that also saw a sharp rise in Italy's short-term borrowing rate. The treasury auctioned some €8.5bn of six-month bills known as BoTs at an interest rate of 3.535%, almost 0.5 percentage points higher than at the last comparable auction in September.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>