<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2014-02-14" description="Critics say Democratic party star Matteo Renzi has reverted to old Italian tactics as he looks set to take power without election" fingerprint="b782db7b8629973f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Enrico Letta,David Miliband,Politics" title="Italy's new prime minister: is Renzi a young Blair, Berlusconi – or the Fonz?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/feb/14/italy-new-prime-minister-matteo-renzi-profile">
<main>
<p>In 1994, the year that Silvio Berlusconi won his first general election, a bespectacled 19-year-old with luxuriant hair and an earnest expression appeared on one of the billionaire's television channels as a contestant on Wheel of Fortune, or, as it is known in Italy, <hi rend="#i">La Ruota della Fortuna</hi>. In his brown suit and carefully fixed tie, the teenager is not immediately recognisable, but his voice is. At a certain point during <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LKbYpboK5eE">the show</ref>, he is heard to declare: "I would like to give the answer." Twenty years on, Matteo Renzi is still saying the same thing – only now the problem isn't a word game, but Italy itself.</p>
<p>On Friday, as Enrico Letta, the prime minister who had struggled for nine-and-a-half months to hold together a fractious coalition government, handed in his "irrevocable" resignation, Renzi, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/feb/13/italian-pm-enrico-letta-to-resign">man who had in effect ousted him</ref>, appeared on the verge of becoming the youngest leader in the history of the republic.</p>
<p>It is expected that Giorgio Napolitano, the 88-year-old president who has already begun consultations for a new executive, will now ask the 39-year-old mayor of Florence to try to form a government capable of mustering a majority. Whether the self-avowedly ambitious centre-left leader will fare any better than his party colleague in a bitterly divided parliament is, for the moment, unclear.</p>
<p>He was showing no outward sign of being cowed. At a Valentine's Day gathering in Florence on Friday, he said that, although it was "quite delicate" of him to say so: "This is one of the most beautiful moments for me in five years."</p>
<p>Many, however, do not share his enthusiasm – including some who have backed him for years as the brightest and best hope for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. After calling on the Democratic Party (PD) to rebel against the prime minister and orchestrating what Letta indirectly branded a "palace coup", he now looks likely to enter Palazzo Chigi – the prime minister's official residence – without having been voted in by the public and, some say, with blood on his hands.</p>
<p>Many observers have said that a politician who built his persona on a rejection of the old political guard appears to have manoeuvred himself into pole position with skills that could have come straight from the rulebook of his fellow Florentine Niccolò Machiavelli.</p>
<p>And, while most supporters understand why holding an election now under the old system is not advisable, many would have preferred to see him continue his work to push through a replacement electoral law from outside parliament, and keep his golden-boy image untarnished by the trouble that almost certainly lies ahead.</p>
<p>In his speech to the PD's national committee on Thursday, Renzi made it clear he was taking what he saw as a necessary gamble to save Italy "from the quagmire" and set it, finally, on a path of radical reform. Such was the urgency, he said, that he needed to take the risk.</p>
<p>"He who is in politics has the duty of taking a risk sometimes," he said. "If I had not taken risks at certain points in my life I would still be in my second term as president of Florence province."</p>
<p>Frank, bold and with a touch of arrogance, the comments were Renzi down to a T. Moreover they referred to what is considered one of his defining moments: the point in September 2008 when he decided that, having become Italy's youngest provincial president at 29, he wanted more: namely, the mayorship of Florence.</p>
<p>To do so, however, he had to enter the PD primaries – something he was given to understand in no uncertain terms was not on his party bosses' agenda. In his 2011 book, <hi rend="#i">Fuori!</hi> (Out!), the man who came to be known as <hi rend="#i">Il Rottamatore</hi> – The Scrapper – for his disregard for the old political machine recalled being told to "wait in line" for his turn to come.</p>
<p>"I didn't want the others, them, to decide the timings," he wrote. "I didn't want to submit to their rules, the rules of a generation that has already given all it had to give." Renzi stood in the primaries, and won.</p>
<p>Soon, he was not only mayor of Florence but the politician with the most consistently high approval ratings in Italy. His blend of chutzpah and dynamism seduced many voters who felt he articulated their own exasperation with an ageing, sclerotic political class. His position as a moderate within the PD – an eclectic mixture of former communists and Christian Democrats, among others – allowed him to appeal to centre-right voters tired of Berlusconi and centre-left voters who had lost hope for their own party. He <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/apr/24/matteo-renzi-tipped-italy-pm">told the Guardian last year</ref> that Tony Blair was a role model for him - an admission that is still considered controversial among many on the Italian left.</p>
<p>As mayor – ensconced in his splendid office in the historic Palazzo Vecchio, where a fresco of the 16th-century siege of Florence covers the wall behind his desk – Renzi could have permitted himself a bit of breathing space. But, in a hurry as ever, his eye had wandered beyond the Arno to an altogether different place: the headquarters of the PD.</p>
<p>At the end of a long and vigorous battle for the party leadership in 2012, Renzi, despite crisscrossing the country in a camper van, lost out to Pier Luigi Bersani, the candidate of the PD's old guard. It was his first real defeat. Months later, he met <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/davidmiliband">David Miliband</ref>, the former UK foreign secretary, who had had his own well-publicised defeat in a party leadership election.</p>
<p>The Guardian understands that the British politician advised Renzi to learn the right lessons from his loss, encouraging him to stick to a "forward agenda" for Italy and try to be part of a progressive politics proposed by figures such as Hillary Clinton. As it turned out, the effects of defeat did not last long: under Bersani, the party ran a lacklustre general election campaign and squandered its chances of a commanding majority in parliament. He resigned last year.</p>
<p>Renzi, meanwhile, was continuing his celebrity-like political career. He was photographed, Fonz-like, in a leather jacket and dark glasses and appeared – but, this time, did not compete – in a television talent show. For those who were concerned that he was simply too charismatic, telegenic and image-conscious to be reliable, these actions were all the confirmation they needed: Renzi, they cried, was a kindred spirit of Berlusconi, and too slick to be serious.</p>
<p>Among the other criticisms were that his policies were not always clear, and that he lacked experience, having never held a seat in parliament and spent almost all his career at a local level.</p>
<p>Despite these reservations, however, Renzi finally won over his party in December, winning his second leadership contest by a landslide. The victory set up a peculiar dynamic in the country in which the PD leader, never one to hold back, unleashed an almost daily barrage of criticism on a government which, though a coalition, was led by a member of his party.</p>
<p>He struck a controversial deal with Berlusconi to push through electoral reform, but, for weeks, it seemed he had calculated that it would be better to operate from the sidelines than enter the fray.</p>
<p>His mind appeared to have changed, to dramatic effect, this week. Will his ousting of Letta – his biggest risk to date – pay off? After his appearance on <hi rend="#i">La Ruota della Fortuna</hi>, Renzi went home with 48m lire (about £20,000) in his pocket.</p>
<p>He – and many others – will be hoping that fortune smiles on him now.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>