<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="Media" date="2003-02-28" description="Italy's media mogul prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, faced a storm of political protest yesterday for trying to directly nominate the bosses of the state television service. By Sophie Arie." fingerprint="3ea813289337d753" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Television industry,Media business,Italy,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Furore over 'junk TV' puts heat on Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/feb/28/broadcasting.silvioberlusconi">
<main>
<p>Italy's media mogul prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, faced a storm of political protest yesterday for trying to directly nominate the bosses of the state television service.</p>
<p>Politicians from across the political spectrum said the prime minister was trying to reduce the country's state television to junk broadcasting after reports said he wanted a fast-food boss to head the service.</p>
<p>After a week-long crisis forced board members to resign, Mr Berlusconi reportedly tipped Mario Resca, the head of McDonald's in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, to be the new president of Radio Televisione Italiana (Rai). The suggestion provoked uproar since, by law, the board members of what is Italy's equivalent of the BBC should be nominated by the speakers of the country's upper and lower parliamentary houses.</p>
<p>The left-of-centre daily, La Repubblica, declared that "Rai with Ketchup has been born", and said bypassing the system for nominating board members would be "obscene from a democratic point of view".</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi has faced the greatest threat yet to his government, as members of his coalition compete for control of Rai.</p>
<p>Rai has always been the target of power-hungry politicians in Italy, and the Northern League leader Umberto Bossi has threatened to break ranks with the government coalition if Rai 2's headquarters are not moved north to Italy's financial capital Milan.</p>
<p>But as Mr Berlusconi battles to hold his coalition together, his own position as a billionaire controlling three national television channels has raised new fears that he is riding roughshod over democracy.</p>
<p>"We have hit the bottom," said Willer Bordon, the chief whip for the opposition centre-left Margherita party.</p>
<p>"Reality has surpassed fantasy now," he said. "No one could have imagined such a conflict of interest. Now there is not even a conflict, there are just the interests of the head of the government."</p>
<p>Massimo D'Alema, a former prime minister and a senior figure in the Democrats of the Left opposition party, said: "It is hard to think of anything as indecent as this indecency."</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's media empire, Mediaset, has continued to grow since he won a landslide election victory in May 2001. The public is apparently unconcerned, and the law does not stand in his way. He has avoided the one restriction on those in public office holding broadcasting licences by putting family members in charge of his media interests.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi brushed off Thursday's outcry, insisting he did intend to let the speakers make the decision about who should run Rai.</p>
<p>He has consistently denied trying to influence the Rai management. But the two outgoing board members issued a damning report after they stood down on Wednesday, confirming growing complaints by staff that programmes, particularly in the field of current affairs, were being "manipulated" daily in the government's favour.</p>
<p>Last year two popular news presenters were forced out of their jobs after they were critical of Mr Berlusconi. He said they had been making "criminal use" of state television.</p>
<p>There was also an outcry when Rai decided not to broadcast the February 15 peace march, saying it would "put undue pressure on politicians".</p>
<p>As they left Rai, Antonio Baldassare and Ettore Albertoni wrote that there was "a constantly growing instrumental use of various programmes for propaganda and not, as they should be used, for exploration and discussion for an adequate knowledge of the facts".</p>
<p>Michele Santoro, one of the ousted presenters, said: "Berlusconi has been systematically trying to put Rai to sleep."</p>
<p>Mr Resca, who was previously unheard of on the Italian political scene, is also an unpaid "adviser" on the board of Mondadori, Italy's largest publishing house, which Mr Berlusconi control, and is the president of the American Chamber of Commerce in Italy.</p>
<p>"I am surprised and honoured," Mr Resca reportedly said on hearing the news of his possible nomination. "I am a businessman."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Mobbing the media</hi><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Berlusconi combines running Italy with controlling much of the media. He is Italy's richest man. Through his holding company, Fininvest, he owns 48% of Mediaset, which includes three television channels. His brother edits a national daily newspaper, Il Giornale. Mediaset controls a leading advertising company and Italy's biggest book and magazine publishers</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Although he indirectly controls Rai, the state television corporation, via his parliamentary majority, he is accused of trying to ruin it so as to win more viewers for his own channels. Mediaset has thrived at the expense of Rai. Its three channels, Canale 5, Italia 1 and Retequattro (Rete 4), won 46% of primetime viewing in January, beating Rai for the first time</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> The average Italian watches four hours of television a day and more than 80% depend entirely on television for news</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Mr Berlusconi, known in Italy as the 'Grand Seducer', began his career as a crooner on a cruise boat and launched his first cable television station in 1974. He founded Fininvest in 1975, started three channels in the 1980s and bought AC Milan football club. His personal wealth is estimated at £9bn.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>