<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Jonathan Glancey" categories="Art and design" date="2011-10-14" description="Jonathan Glancey: Big Ben is becoming the leaning tower of London, but architects the world over have begun deliberately tilting towers, from the Capital Gate in Abu Dhabi to Anish Kapoor's Olympic Orbit" fingerprint="3f1979ea5eb05f7a" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Architecture,Art and design,Anish Kapoor,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,Venice Biennale" title="Constructive criticism: the week in architecture" url="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2011/oct/14/constructive-criticism-modern-architecture">
<main>
<p>News that <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/oct/11/in-praise-of-leaning-towers">Big Ben or, more properly, St Stephen's Tower, is leaning</ref> is not exactly surprising. Battered by the elements and undermined by human intervention – the digging of sewers, railways, roads and underground car parks all around them, as well as the effects of war and earthquakes – it seems remarkable that so many towers around the world stand ramrod straight. Some, like the famous <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaning_Tower_of_Pisa">campanile at Pisa Cathedral</ref> have leaned since they were new. Others, like the <ref target="http://www.slowtrav.com/blog/annienc/2008/04/leaning_tower_of_san_pietro_di.html">church towers of Venice</ref>, have leant gradually over the centuries, as the artificial structure of the islands they rise from rots and buckles.</p>
<p>What has changed in the past few years is the fact that architects are designing towers that lean deliberately. <ref target="http://www.rmjm.com/">RMJM</ref> – a long established British practice – has just completed a 35-storey tower, the <ref target="http://www.capitalgate.ae/">Capital Gate</ref> in Abu Dhabi, that, said the architects when it was commissioned, "is intended to lean 18 degrees westwards, more than four times that of the world famous leaning tower of Pisa". And it does. This angle of lean has secured the eyecatching tower a place in the <ref target="http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/">Guinness Book of Records</ref> as the "World's Furthest Leaning Manmade Tower."</p>
<p>The root of this leaning architecture can be found in the <ref target="http://arkinetblog.wordpress.com/2010/03/11/monument-to-the-third-international-vladimir-tatlin/">mesmerising, although unbuilt, 400-metre high Monument to the Third International</ref> designed by <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir_Tatlin">Vladimir Tatlin</ref> shortly after the Bolshevik revolution. It was to have leant over Petrograd (later Leningrad and now St Petersburg) at the same angle as the Earth's tilt: 23.5 degrees. Inside its double-helix steel frame, three great chambers – a cube, a pyramid and a cylinder – would have revolved, in turn, yearly, monthly and daily. Appropriately, the "daily" cylinder was to have housed a newspaper. The tower has haunted dreams of architects and engineers ever since: a <ref target="http://www.architectsjournal.co.uk/ra-unveils-tatlins-tower/8620939.article">10-metre replica</ref> has just been completed by the team at <ref target="http://www.dixonjones.co.uk">Dixon Jones</ref> in the courtyard of the <ref target="http://www.royalacademy.org.uk/exhibitions/building-the-revolution/">Royal Academy of Arts as part of the exhibition, Building the Revolution: Soviet Art and Architecture 1915-35</ref> that opens on 29 October.</p>
<p>"It's been a huge challenge, but what a pleasure creating an interpretation of something you so admire", designer Jeremy Dixon tells me. "It's been rather like interpreting a piece of music where you have to fill in the gaps with imagination and whatever skill you have."</p>
<graphic alt="Tatlin's tower" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Admin/BkFill/Default_image_group/2011/10/14/1318602123530/Tatlins-tower-007.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p>Meanwhile, the leaning, looping structure of the <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/mar/31/anish-kapoor-artwork-tower-london">ArcelorMittall Orbit</ref> at the London Olympics Games 2012 site is very nearly finished, but the big day of completion turns on the weather: high winds have prevented engineers from putting the last piece in place. What is clear is that this extraordinary 115m red tower, designed by <ref target="http://www.anishkapoor.com">Anish Kapoor</ref> and <ref target="http://balmondstudio.com/main/">Cecil Balmond</ref>, and realised in co-operation with <ref target="http://www.arup.com/">Arup</ref> and <ref target="http://www.ushida-findlay.com">Kathryn Findlay Architects</ref>, owes much to Tatlin's tower.</p>
<p>Britain will be home in years to come to thousands of almost invisible new towers if the winning entry of the competition for the design of a new national standard electricity pylon is put into production. This is the <ref target="http://www.bystrup.dk/">T-Pylon by the Copenhagen firm Bystrup Arkitekter og Designere</ref>.</p>
<p>The judges of the competition held by the National Grid, the Department of Energy and Climate Change and <ref target="http://www.architecture.com/">RIBA</ref> agreed unanimously that T-Pylon would work best and make the least impact on the landscape. It would be <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2011/may/22/national-grid-pylons-design">two-thirds the height of current standard British pylons</ref>, although National Grid engineers will work closely with the architects before a new version is allowed to march across the country.</p>
<graphic alt="T-Pylon" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Admin/BkFill/Default_image_group/2011/10/14/1318602458913/T-Pylon-007.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p>In Scotland, a tower that disappeared 18 years ago might just rise again. This was the <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/gsalib/sets/72157619480243726/">90-ft campanile of St Bride's, East Kilbride</ref> in the diocese of Motherwell, one of a large number of Catholic churches built from the late 1950s in new towns and areas of new mass housing. A daunting design – its power station-like exterior houses a magnificent daylit interior – St Bride's was designed by <ref target="http://www.gillespiekiddandcoia.com/major.html">Gillespie Kidd &amp; Coia</ref> (architects of the internationally famous modern ruin, <ref target="http://www.glasgowarchitecture.co.uk/cardross_seminary.htm">Cardross Seminary</ref>), and consecrated in 1964. The campanile neither leaned nor swayed, but was demolished to keep maintenance costs of this vast church to a minimum. Now the <ref target="http://www.rmjm.com/people/paul-stallan">Paul Stallan Studio</ref>, part of RMJM, has been asked to restore St Bride's. We can only pray that the campanile will be rebuilt. Without it, the church has been like a headless statue of a saint vandalised by passing iconoclasts.</p>
<p>Back to Earth, or Venice, with a bump. Silvio Berlusconi is trying to replace <ref target="http://www.telecomitalia.com/dam/telecomitalia/documents/Governance/en/Biographies/cv_paolo_baratta_eng.html">Paolo Baratta</ref>, head of the <ref target="http://www.labiennale.org/en/Home.html">Venice Biennale</ref>, with his friend <ref target="http://www.theartnewspaper.com/articles/Venice+Biennale+head+ousted/24815">Giulio Malgara</ref>, a 73-year-old businessman whose greatest cultural achievement to date is bringing <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gatorade">Gatorade</ref> to Italy. The Italian government is expected to approve the appointment.</p>
<p>Baratta has done much to raise the profile of the Architecture Biennale. According to <ref target="http://www2.lse.ac.uk/researchAndExpertise/Experts/r.burdett@lse.ac.uk">Ricky Burdett</ref>, director of the 2006 Architecture Biennale, speaking to <ref target="http://www.bdonline.co.uk/">Building Design </ref>magazine, "In the Italian system, individuals make a big difference, and this will be a serious loss. It is sad and depressing to see that local politics has once again won the day in a country that has so much to offer. The Italian government should reconsider this flawed appointment. But with teenage sex scandals and a banking crisis occupying politicians' minds, I doubt anybody is listening."</p>
<p>Writing in the <ref target="http://www.architectmagazine.com/">Architect</ref>, the journal of the American Institute of Architects, Aaron Betsky, director of the 2008 Architecture Biennale, says: "My contacts tell me that the outrage this move by Berlusconi has produced is so intense that what is usually a routine procedure validating the prime minister's choice might offer chances for reversal." Mind you, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2008/sep/16/architecture">Betsky's Biennale</ref> offered the very kind of spectacle that might well have triggered Mr Berlusconi's sudden interest in the Biennale. Ding Dong, as Big Ben might say.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>