<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2003-12-03" description="Protesters have taken to the streets to condemn a new law that opens the way for Silvio Berlusconi to expand his media empire. Sophie Arie reports." fingerprint="36ddc1181023fe57" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="'Attacking our democratic lifeblood'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/dec/03/worlddispatch.italy">
<main>
<p>For many Italians, the impression that the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, not only runs, but also owns, most of their country has just edged a significant step closer to becoming reality.</p>
<p>Opposition leaders, journalists and academics were today leading street protests after a controversial new law opened the way for Mr Berlusconi's media empire - which already dominates television, publishing and advertising sales - to branch out into newspapers and radio.</p>
<p>The new law also clears the path for Radioitelevisione Italiana (RAI) - Italy's equivalent of the BBC - to be part-privatised, and increases the permitted amount of advertising time per programme.</p>
<p>At the same time, the law reverses a court ruling that had obliged Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset broadcasting company to cut the number of private terrestrial TV channels it runs from three to two before the end of this year.</p>
<p>Criticis, who complain that Mr Berlusconi's combination of wealth and power is already stealthily gagging the country's media, say that the new bill is unconstitutional, and tailor-made to meet the prime minister's business needs.</p>
<p>They claim that Mr Berlusconi already controls 90% of Italy's television viewing through Mediaset and his parliamentary majority which, they say, gives him indirect control over RAI. His family controls one newspaper, Il Giornale, and the Panorama current affairs magazine.</p>
<p>"If freedom of information is the basis for a democracy, then we need to say, without mincing our words, that this attacks the democratic lifeblood of our country," left-leaning daily La Republica said.</p>
<p>"Something has to be done. Before we know it, Silvio will be privatising the country's prisons," said Dario Fo, the Nobel Literature prize winner who is currently starring as Mr Berlusconi in his new satirical play about the billionaire businessman turned leader.</p>
<p>"Then he will be able to buy them all," added Fo. He'll be living in luxury in his own prison the day the lawyers finally get him."</p>
<p>The government argues that the new law will help to increase competition, keep pace with technology and provide greater choice. Supporters of the bill say the new measures are in line with those that exist in Britain, the US, and Spain.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's daughter Marina, the vice-president of the family holding company, Fininvest, heaved huge sighs of relief that the bill had finally been passed.</p>
<p>"I must confess to being very emotional," she said, weeping with delight. "It will be an important thing for the whole system in Italy."</p>
<p>Under the bill, multi-channel digital broadcasting will be introduced in Italy, with a ban on simultaneous ownership of broadcast and print media being lifted in 2009.</p>
<p>For Fininvest, the ruling means potential new business worth up to €750m (£525m).</p>
<p>On Wednesday reports said that, despite opposition objections, the European commission had received no formal complaints about the law, and had no plans to open an investigation.</p>
<p>The new law has been brewing for months, delayed by opposition attempts to modify certain clauses. Protesters - including well-known journalists who, in recent years, have lost their jobs at RAI after criticising the prime minister - organised street demonstrations across the country.</p>
<p>The chief of RAI, Lucia Annunziata, has already threatened to resign, and said: "The law favours Mediaset over the public service, and it is therefore my duty, as head of the public service, to make my position explicit."</p>
<p>Italy's president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, can refuse to sign the bill into law.</p>
<p>"The president is a man of sufficient authority, wisdom and fairness to know on his own what he should do," said the opposition leader, Piero Fassino.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>