<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tim Williams" categories="Opinion" date="2010-11-22" description="Tim Williams: It is the controversy surrounding Berlusconi's decision to restore Mars's penis to an ancient Roman statue that is misplaced" fingerprint="76a995849bc303da" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Sculpture,Art,Art and design,Heritage,Culture" title="Silvio Berlusconi's restoration work is no cock-up | Tim Williams" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/22/silvio-berlusconi-penis-statue">
<main>
<p>I can picture the scene. Berlusconi checks his email. "Ever wanted a larger member...?" He pauses, thinks about it for a while. "Well, I've had the hair done, and it might impress the young ladies at the forthcoming orgy." He looks up at Mars, the statue of the heroic god of ancient Rome painstakingly chiselled from the finest Carrara 1,835 years previous. Venus is draped over his shoulder adoringly. However Mars, far from appearing as the revered übermensch warrior of antiquity, resembles <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_and_Lorena_Bobbitt">John Wayne Bobbitt</ref> after a fight with his ex-wife. Then it hits him: "<hi rend="#i">Che buon' idea!</hi> I shall restore his manhood!"</p>
<p>The recent restoration of the ancient Roman sculpture owned by the Baths of Diocletian Museum in Rome and currently adorning Berlusconi's office, has proved ideal cannon fodder for the international press. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/18/fake-penis-statue-silvio-berlusconi-residence">Mars's missing penis has been meticulously re-carved</ref> and attached by magnets, allegedly on the orders of Berlusconi himself and causing many to jokingly speculate as to why Venus merely had her hand replaced – rather than a breast enlargement.</p>
<p>One "horrified" <ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1330944/Berlusconi-builds-Mars-Venus-statue-penis-fake-hands.html">art historian is quoted</ref> as saying "It's horrific. You just can't add on bits ad hoc to these works of art – the penis and hands may well have been there originally and then removed but you can't add something on like a plastic model."</p>
<p>This all sounds rather melodramatic to me. Sure, opponents of Berlusconi have a right to bemoan the costs involved which may or may not have been better spent elsewhere (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/11/the-second-fall-pompeii">Pompeii perhaps</ref>). But this unidentified art historian sounds panic-stricken. Being an art historian myself, and possessor of at least a little common sense, I definitely know that this "restoration" is anything but horrific, and wasn't "ad hoc" either. The fact that there are two almost identical sculptures in the collection of the Louvre and the Capitoline museum (the three are reproduced side by side on page 181 in <ref target="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Sculpture-Antiquity-Present-Georges-Duby/dp/3822816620">Sculpture from Antiquity to the Present Day</ref>) for which to establish precedent is conveniently overlooked. But with this kind of alarmist rhetoric one might be mistaken for believing someone merely wandered in off the street and superglued on a Ron Jeremy replica dildo (which reminds me of a sculpture I saw last year in Brighton, which involved the aforementioned object and a taxidermic Armadillo – you can <ref target="http://www.jamiemccartney.com/armadildo.html">guess the title</ref>).</p>
<p>The issues concerning restoration and conservation of important historical artworks and artefacts are entirely subjective and, what's more, in this case it's reversible. Sure, when meandering around the Sainsbury wing of the <ref target="http://www.nationalgallery.org.uk/visiting/floorplans/sainsbury-wing/">National Gallery</ref> I sometimes wish the altar pieces and rood screens showed the scars of their years, but we generally view these objects in alien contexts anyway: whitewashed walls, artificial lights, armed with audio guides and with our view partially obscured by swathes of tourists. All the same, it is nice to see the vibrancy of the pigments as intended: give it another few hundred years and the dirt and grime will be back; swings and roundabouts.</p>
<p>It would seem that the hype surrounding this story can primarily be attributed to the fact that it was a male sexual organ that was restored in connection with the propagated myth of Berlusconi's apparently superlative testosterone. But no one, especially in the press, has taken Berlusconi out of the equation and proposed the view that Venus and Mars might actually look better with the new additions.</p>
<p>We far too often credit authors of works of art with an untouchable deity status – it's no longer "authentic" once "tampered" with. Such a view would render Michelangelo's celebrated Pietà, restored on a number of occasions – most notably after being attacked with a geologist's hammer by mentally ill <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laszlo_Toth">Laszlo Toth</ref> in 1972 – to a considered weakened mongrel or hybrid-like status. The point of the work has not diminished, and the restoration for me, merely adds another interesting facet to its social history. Indeed, perhaps the greatest positive to come out of the Berlusconi story is that a worldwide audience has been exposed (unintentional double entendre) to an ancient Roman sculpture they've probably never seen, thought or cared about previously.</p>
<p>By the way, Mars is not the only archaeological male to have gained a penis this year. In April, the <ref target="http://www.metro.co.uk/weird/832374-long-man-of-wilmington-given-20ft-penis">Long Man of Wilmington</ref> gained a temporary appendage more in keeping with his name and rivalling that of the <ref target="http://www.mysteriousbritain.co.uk/england/dorset/featured-sites/the-cerne-abbas-giant.html">Cerne Abbas Giant</ref>. Intriguingly, I don't recall it being international headline news.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>