<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="David Hills" categories="Football" date="2011-04-09" description="Silvio on style; president of the week; sacking news; plus the ref who smelled too good" fingerprint="3c218f6d98605db1" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Fifa" title="Said &amp; Done | David Hills" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2011/apr/10/said-done-berlusconi-sepp-zamparini">
<main>
<head rend="h2">Big week for</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi> - attacking "communists" for putting him through three "ridiculous and groundless" trials for alleged fraud plus one for alleged underage prostitute bunga-bunga issues – and ruling out a Milan bid for Mario Balotelli due to the striker's negative moral image. "There is a Milan code of behaviour that I don't think is very close to that of Balotelli. He suffers distractions. I just don't like his style."</p>
<p>(February, the Sun: "Balotelli's Busty Beauty Badgered by Berlusconi at Bunga Bonkathon ... A model dating Mario Balotelli yesterday told how she was collared by Silvio Berlusconi at one of his parties. Stunning Sara Tommasi, 29, said: 'He told me I had beauty and intelligence, I should go into politics. I told him I just wanted to be an actress.'")</p>
<head rend="h2">Election news</head>
<p>Last week's best endorsement: former <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/fifa">Fifa</ref> executive <hi rend="#b">Chung Mong-joon</hi> backing Sepp's rival Mohamed Bin Hammam, despite having called Hammam "mentally ill" and "like a mafia leader" in 2009. "I can't say he's perfect – but he is the right man to bring change and revolution. A president should be admired, beloved and respected! Blatter is not."</p>
<head rend="h2">Plus: credibility lost</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Quote of the week</hi>: Fifa acting "robustly" to ban Indonesia's FA head Nurdin Halid after he failed to stop a breakaway league. Fifa said Halid had become undemocratic and had now "lost all credibility". <hi rend="#b">2</hi>: number of times since taking over in 2004 that Halid has run the FA from inside prison while serving time for fraud.</p>
<head rend="h2">President of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">February</hi>: Palermo owner Maurizio Zamparini says he sacked coach Delio Rossi for "having no balls". "Rossi has ruined my Palermo, destroyed my club. I should have done this at Christmas." New manager Serse Cosmi is "a real man, a man of grit". <hi rend="#b">April</hi>: Sacks Cosmi for "fundamental weakness"; reappoints Rossi. "I was emotional last time. Rossi's a good coach."</p>
<p> Zamparini's previous best man-management moment: <hi rend="#b">2003</hi> – telling the press he'd "personally kill" his players for being "shit": "I will cut off their balls and eat them in my salad." Zamparini says he knows he can be "impulsive": "I'm not an easy president."</p>
<head rend="h2">Also gone last week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Paul Ince</hi> – sacked by Notts County after five months. Ince told the press last year: "One of the assurances I wanted before agreeing to come was that I'd be given time. Alex Ferguson always said to me to make sure I have a good relationship with the chairman before taking a job. I think I've got that here."</p>
<p> Plus <hi rend="#b">Neil Tolson</hi> – Hyde FC, sacked four days after the Blue Square North club's chief executive Ted Davies said the speculation must stop. "Neil's our manager and we have to stand by him. It's a building process, not a knocking-down process."</p>
<head rend="h2">Poaching news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Germany</hi>: Hertha Berlin say Hoffenheim have been "aggressively poaching" teenage boys from their youth side. Hertha complained after a senior Hoffenheim scout told a Hertha official his club should stop trying to retain its youth team players like some sort of "Stasi association". Hoffenheim: "These were verbal gaffes. We apologise."</p>
<head rend="h2">Harry news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Last week</hi>: Harry Redknapp says Wayne Rooney was wrong to swear at a camera: "Why do these young players have to be so angry with the world? He's a silly boy." <hi rend="#b">Last year</hi>: Harry tells a Sky interviewer: "I'm not a wheeler fucking dealer – fuck off. I'm a fucking football manager."</p>
<head rend="h2">Love news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">2009</hi>: Emmanuel Adebayor says the love from Man City fans has made him feel special after Arsenal fans turned cold. "I am at a club now where the fans love you. I just try to give them something back in return."<hi rend="#b">Last week</hi>: Says he's at Real for love after City fans turned cold. "At Arsenal the fans really loved me and when I come to Madrid I feel it too, I feel that the fans love me. There's nothing more important than to feel loved. That's all you want to feel."</p>
<p>(<hi rend="#b">Oct 2008</hi> – Manu's guiding principle: "Money is killing football: people are making their decisions based on money. If I made my decisions because of money, I would not be at Arsenal. I'm at Arsenal for love.")</p>
<head rend="h2">Fine of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">£750</hi>: Fine for Rapid Bucharest manager Marius Sumudica after he reacted to being sent off for over-celebrating a goal against Gaz Matan by giving the referee a "tender kiss". "I lost it for a moment. But he smelled so good. I know it wasn't normal."</p>
<head rend="h2">And finally</head>
<p>Also at Rapid: Sumudica says defender <hi rend="#b">Marius Constantin</hi> is "nothing to me" after Constantin tried to choke him during training. "He won't play here again. Sure, I made a joke about his wife, but he's a punk. He stinks of beer and smokes. If you go in his room the smoke is so dense you could leave a bike standing upright unsupported. He likes the minibar and uses gum to clean his breath. You know, I don't care for him."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>