<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-10-15" description="Box office success of the film Benvenuti al Sud suggests Italians can overcome Northern League-style separatist prejudice" fingerprint="b64449cde1a4cf41" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Film,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,North-south divide,The League" title="Hit film gives Italy chance to close north-south divide" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/15/film-italy-north-south-divide">
<main>
<p>It is shamelessly unoriginal. None of the actors is a front-rank star. And it was the director's first solo feature movie.</p>
<p>Yet a new Italian comedy, Benvenuti al Sud (Welcome to the South), has achieved box office success by getting Italians to laugh at one of their most deeply held convictions: that an unbridgeable divide separates the rich north of their country from the poor south.</p>
<p>Released on 1 October, Benvenuti al Sud grossed €3.8 million (£3.3m) in its first weekend, pushing the US sci-fi blockbuster Inception into second place at the box office. Cinema managers reported the sale of tickets per screen was at levels usually only seen at Christmas.</p>
<p>The film is an acknowledged remake of a French movie, Bienvenue chez les Ch'tis, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2008/mar/04/news.france">which told the story of a southern postal employee unhappily transferred to the north</ref>. But in an Italian context, and with a self-pitying northern hero dispatched to the Mezzogiorno, the plot acquires more political bite.</p>
<p>Italians are flocking to see the movie as their country prepares for the 150th anniversary of unification next year, at a time when the notionally separatist Northern League has never been stronger.</p>
<p>The League already has enough parliamentary clout to bring down Silvio Berlusconi's government and polls suggest that, in the event of a snap election, it would increase its share of the vote by half. Days before the release of Benvenuti al Sud, the Northern League leader, Umberto Bossi, described the Romans as "pigs".</p>
<p>That is a view that would no doubt be endorsed by the wife of the film's hero. She is the leader of a thinly disguised Northern League vigilante patrol with a sense of civic duty so strong she will not let her son accept a balloon from a street trader unless it is accompanied by a valid tax receipt. When her husband, played by Claudio Bisio, is posted south of Naples, she buys him a flak jacket.</p>
<p>What he finds is something at odds with his prejudices. The people of the hilltop town of Castellabate are admittedly incomprehensible. And they eat disgusting things (he is served <hi rend="#i">sanguinaccio</hi>, a blend of pig's blood and chocolate, for breakfast).</p>
<p>But they are friendly, honest and live in a place of heart-stopping natural beauty. Even the rubbish gets sorted (although it is disposed of by being hurled through a window into a passing handcart).</p>
<p>Bisio called the movie "my way of celebrating the unity of Italy". Its director, Luca Miniero, said its success "shows there's a desire to make peace, to overcome the confrontation".</p>
<p>That would seem to be true. But his film also succeeds by offering an entrancing vision of a Mezzogiorno wiped clean of its blemishes. Towards the end, when the camera tracks along the coast, it takes in the port of Acciaroli, the birthplace of a brave mayor, Angelo Vassallo, who refused to bow to the demands of property developers in league with organised crime. On 5 September, Vassallo was shot dead.</p>
<p>As one of the characters in Benvenuti al Sud remarks, in the film's most memorable line (also lifted from the French original): "When an outsider comes to the south, he cries twice – when he arrives and when he leaves."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>