<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper; Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-02-25" description="First reports indicate strong support for alliance led by Pier Luigi Bersani's Democratic party and bloody nose for Mario Monti" fingerprint="b399706507a2074b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Mario Monti,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Italy election exit polls point to win for Bersani's centre-left coalition" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/25/italy-election-exit-polls-bersani">
<main>
<p>Italy's centre-left coalition appears to be heading for victory in the country's general election, but it remains unclear whether it will win the outright majority in both houses needed to govern the country.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2013/feb/25/italian-election-results-live-coverage">Exit polls indicated a strong showing</ref> for the alliance led by Pier Luigi Bersani's Democratic party (PD) and a slump in support for the centrist bloc of Mario Monti, the outgoing technocratic premier.</p>
<p>Minutes after polling stations closed in one of the most important and <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2013/feb/24/italy-heads-polls-political-stalemate">unpredictable Italian elections</ref> in decades, a telephone poll for Rai, the state broadcaster, put the centre-left bloc of the PD and its allies on 35%-37% of the vote in the lower house of parliament and 36%-38% in the upper house, or Senate.</p>
<p>A centre-right bloc led by Silvio Berlusconi's Freedom People party was in second position, with 29%-31% in the lower house and 30%-32% in the Senate. The same poll put former comedian <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2013/feb/23/beppe-grillo-italian-elections">Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement</ref> in third, and Monti's centrist grouping significantly behind in fourth. The results were roughly echoed by a separate exit poll for Sky television.</p>
<p>Observers cautioned against making predictions based on the initial indications, which have proved unreliable in the past. However, the numbers are stark enough to reinforce the pre-electoral prediction that Bersani's party would win the most seats in the Chamber of Deputies.</p>
<p>The fate of the Senate is less clear. The result will rest on key regions such as Lombardy, where the centre-right – in alliance with the Northern League – could win and deprive the centre-left of seats it would need for a majority. Sky's exit poll said the Lombardy result was tied.</p>
<p>Another crucial factor will be whether Monti's centrist bloc manages to gain enough Senate seats to be of use to the PD as a potential governing ally.</p>
<p>The markets, which have been watching the results of the election closely, reacted positively to the indications. The spread between Italy's benchmark 10-year bonds and the German equivalent narrowed to 260 basis points.</p>
<p>Turnout, according to exit polls, was significantly down on the last election in 2008. The parliamentary elections will mark the end of Monti's technocratic government, brought in at the end of 2011.</p>
<p>The fractured nature of the political landscape and complexities of the electoral system have raised fears that recession-mired Italy, which has had a decade of near-economic stagnation and more than a year of punishing austerity, could end up with a deadlock in which no strong government is possible.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>