<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Annalisa Piras" categories="World news" date="2011-02-08" description="Half the country believes premier should face justice, while the other believes the theory he is a victim of political persecution" fingerprint="9f2dc808d5b79347" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Italy divided over Silvio Berlusconi's trial on sex-related offences" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/08/italy-divided-berlusconi-trial-bunga-bunga">
<main>
<p>Italy is in the midst of a kind of civil war; experiencing a split personality. Half of the country thinks that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> must stand trial and put an end to what many think is his flight from justice. The other half believes, or pretends to believe, the prime minister's theory that he is the victim of a "political persecution of ex-communists and ex-fascists allied with the red judges to overthrow his democratically elected government".</p>
<p>These two Italys read different newspapers, watch different television news bulletins, and profoundly despise each other.</p>
<p>The world can only wonder whether judgment day could finally be approaching for Berlusconi. Does the news that prosecutors are seeking to put him on trial for sex-related charges mark the beginning of the end of the confusing chess game between Italy's magistrates and the PM's lawyers? It's hard to know. We are in unprecedented territory and the legal complexities of the case are difficult to grasp even for eminent legal minds. In what appears as a constantly changing surreal saga, the perspective of what is going to happen next seems now to be dictated more by one's hopes than by reality.</p>
<p>One interesting idea circulating is that the magistrates are working around the clock to expedite the start of the sex-charges trial, before Berlusconi lawyers manage to stop it. If so, national television audiences would be subjected to the spectacle of a "bunga-bunga" trial featuring an infinite series of young wannabe showgirls, lowlifes, drug dealers, prostitutes and pimps as witnesses — an extremely awkward situation for Berlusconi.</p>
<p>But the prime minister's lawyers and most of his followers seem to believe that no one will ever manage to bring him to court. They now claim to have found documents that prove that Ruby, the woman he is accused of paying for sex when she was 17, was in fact born a year earlier than previously thought. Paying for sex with an 18-year-old is not a crime. If they can move back time, what is it that they cannot do ?</p>
<p>In the meantime, street protests are intensifying. On Sunday a large nationwide bipartisan women's protest will be held to demand a country which respects all women. Conveniently, Berlusconi has called his supporters to a counter-demo on the same day to protest against the "politicised judges who are assaulting him".</p>
<p>The astonishing truth though is that none of the bunga-bunga scandal seems to affect the political situation. The Northern League, Berlusconi's key ally in the ruling coalition, is determined that he should be persuaded to introduce a hurried reform of Italian federalism which will allow, among other devolved powers, the rich north to keep its tax revenues – thus dropping the constitutional and fundamental principle of solidarity between the north and south of the country. In exchange Berlusconi will get a justice reform which should keep the judges at bay for some time. Together they have the majority of MPs. They have the numbers to pass these laws. Bunga-bunga or not, there is therefore nothing that the other half of the country can really do.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Annalisa Piras is the London correspondent of L'Espresso, Italy's leading news magazine</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>