<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-09-18" description="Another blow for embattled Italian PM as Giampaolo Tarantini detained on suspicion of drug trafficking" fingerprint="43028ebc3a2ff4f4" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Drugs trade,Italy,World news,Sex work,Society,Europe" title="Businessman who says he supplied women for Silvio Berlusconi's parties arrested" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/18/silvio-berlusconi-tarantini-italy-prostitutes">
<main>
<p>The man who claims to have supplied <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the Italian prime minister, with a stream of women for parties was arrested today on suspicion of drug trafficking.</p>
<p>Giampaolo Tarantini, a businessman from the southern city of Bari, was already under investigation after being accused of supplying narcotics and aiding and abetting prostitution. He was detained by revenue guard officers on his arrival in Bari from Rome.</p>
<p>"It was felt that … because of the things that have happened in the last few hours, the last few days, there was serious tampering with evidence, so [the arrest] was a precautionary requirement," said Antonio Luadati, Bari's chief prosecutor. "[It was also felt that,] because of indications from the police concerning movements and plans, there existed the danger of escape."</p>
<p>Tarantini said that he feared for his life following the publication of a statement to police earlier this month, which contained the admission that he had procured some 30 women for parties at Berlusconi's Rome residence over a period of five months last winter.</p>
<p>He said that at least six of the women stayed the night, and were rewarded with payments of €1,000 (£900) each. Tarantini said that the prime minister was unaware of the payments. His statement contained several references to the supply of drugs for parties unconnected with Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Today's arrest is yet another blow to Italy's embattled prime minister, linking him even more closely to a world of cocaine-fuelled partying and dubious contacts.</p>
<p>However, given Berlusconi's resilience so far – and the lack of any evident plan for his replacement – it is not thought likely in Italy that he will resign.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>