<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Chris Tryhorn" categories="Media" date="2007-05-14" description="A consortium including Silvio Berlusconi is poised to buy Big Brother producer Endemol this week in a £2bn deal. By Chris Tryhorn." fingerprint="7e038cf6db010088" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Independent production companies,Business,Media business,Media,Television industry,Silvio Berlusconi,Endemol" title="Berlusconi group 'to buy Big Brother producer Endemol'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2007/may/14/independentproductioncompanies.broadcasting">
<main>
<p>The £2bn sale of Big Brother producer Endemol is set to be completed this week amid reports that the company will be snapped up by a consortium including former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and the group's co-founder John de Mol.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's media group, Mediaset, and Mr de Mol, who co-founded <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/endemol">Endemol</ref> in 1994 before selling it to Spanish telecoms group Telefonica six years later, are being backed by Goldman Sachs.</p>
<p>The Berlusconi/de Mol consortium's £2bn bid has beaten off rival offers fronted by Endemol's former chief operating officer, Tom Barnicoat, and the managing director of Endemol France, Stephane Courbit, according to today's Financial Times.</p>
<p>Endemol was put up for sale by Telefonica in March, more than a year after the Spanish group had floated a 25% stake on the Dutch stock exchange.</p>
<p>The company's range of hit formats, which include Big Brother and Deal or No Deal, also attracted the interest of private equity companies.</p>
<p>Mr Barnicoat's bid was reportedly backed by Apax Partners and US group Thomas H Lee, while a French private equity player, PAI, supported Mr Courbit.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 7278 2332.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>