<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Annalisa Piras" categories="Opinion" date="2010-12-15" description="Annalisa Piras: Berlusconi could stay put for another 10 years. Is there any way of rescuing Italian politics from this sickness?" fingerprint="7bb85326f635465f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" title="In this gory zombie movie, Silvio Berlusconi is back from the dead again | Annalisa Piras" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/dec/15/silvio-berlusconi-back-from-dead-italy">
<main>
<p>While <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/14/riots-rome-silvio-berlusconi-confidence-votes">Rome was burning in the worst riots in three decades</ref>, and Silvio Berlusconi was, yet again, coming back from the dead, it was difficult not to marvel at the spectacle unfolding. Politics is always theatre. But, in Italy, on December 14, it became a gory zombie movie.</p>
<p>The prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-survives-confidence-vote1?intcmp=239">survived two motions of no confidence</ref> and came back from the brink. He scraped it by three unexpected new votes, 314 against 311. One party leader has asked prosecutors in Rome to investigate claims of corruption.</p>
<p>The centre-right coalition that gave Berlusconi one of the widest parliamentary majorities ever has disintegrated only two and a half years into the legislature. And there is nothing there to replace it. Zilch.</p>
<p>Early elections, probably in spring, are looming. It is obvious that no government can effectively lead a nation, let alone a country with the third biggest public debt in the world, with a three-votes majority. Italy's public debt rose to a record €1.87tn in October, or to almost 120% of gross domestic product, <ref target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704694004576019491578119686.html?mod=googlenews_wsj">the Bank of Italy said</ref> yesterday. The government's handling of Italy's stumbling economy, besides sex and corruption scandals, is among the key issues that prompted opposition politicians to try and oust it from office. Now, the Lega Nord, the remaining ally of Berlusconi in the conservative coalition, is eager to cash in on the fatigue towards the elderly leader. A possible new majority could be based on a deal between Berlusconi and the Catholic moderate Pier Ferdinando Casini of the Christian Democrat Union of the Centre (UDC). According to one nightmarish scenario, the Catholic leader, very close to the Vatican, could get the role of PM in exchange for supporting the election of <hi rend="#i">il Cavaliere</hi> as president of the republic in 2013. The head of state has a seven-year mandate. Which means Berlusconi going on for another 10 years. That is some dead man walking.</p>
<p>What can be done? Is there any hope to be found, anywhere?</p>
<p>There are a few glimmers. The <ref target="http://www.euronews.net/nocomment/2010/12/15/italian-students-demonstrate-against-berlusconi/">students marching all over Italy</ref> show that new creative energies are re-assembling. Nichi Vendola, the gay, Catholic ex-communist governor of Puglia, is increasingly popular, and has been nicknamed "the Italian Obama". It is not completely unthinkable that he could challenge Berlusconi at the next election as leader of the opposition. Vendola is charismatic, wears an earring, writes poetry, but, even more disconcertingly for an Italian politician, appears authentically honest. If the banalisation of corruption is the poison with which Berlusconi has intoxicated Italy for so long, honesty and integrity are, for many, the urgent antidote that the country need to resuscitate it from its sickness.</p>
<p>If it seems too early for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to embrace a gay, Catholic leftwinger, there is always the possibility of a "technical government", which Italy had before Berlusconi, in the 90s. There have been renewed calls for presenting a bipartisan/politically neutral national unity list to the next elections. Supported by all the opposition parties to Berlusconi, it would create an "expert-led government" to guide Italy out of the marshes in which it is floundering. In it, you could have, for example, the unanimously respected Super Marios: Mario Monti, economist and former EU commissioner; and Mario Draghi, the governor of the Bank of Italy. But others are calling forward, in a new patriotic spirit, other smart guys such as the chairman of Ferrari, Luca Cordero di Montezemolo.</p>
<p>There are signs that the country is finally waking up from its coma. Berlusconi appeared when the so-called <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Italian_Republic#The_First_Republic_.281947-1992.29">"first republic" imploded with the big bang of "clean hands" in 1992</ref>. He was then seen as the outsider, the anti-politician. Today, like then, the leadership of the country is sinking in a profound crisis of credibility. There is a real urgency for a new big bang, a craving for a leader who does not belong to the discredited and mistrusted political caste. Someone who could bring back a sense of integrity and honour, and even add a few ideals to the rotten corpse of Italian politics.</p>
<p>"A return to first principles in a republic is sometimes caused by the simple virtues of one man. His good example has such an influence that the good men strive to imitate him, and the wicked are ashamed to lead a life so contrary to his example." So spoke Machiavelli. He was supposed to be a cynical bastard, but also to understand a thing or two about Italian politics. The exit strategy to uproot Berlusconi needs an inspiring leader, which is what we have not had so far. No leader, no exit.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>