<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Barbara McMahon" categories="World news" date="2005-04-21" description="Silvio Berlusconi resigned as prime minister of Italy yesterday but pledged to form a government with a new programme in an attempt to resolve the political crisis that has engulfed him." fingerprint="7faac83d35b68745" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Italian PM bows to pressure to resign" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/21/italy.barbaramcmahon">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi resigned as prime minister of Italy yesterday but pledged to form a government with a new programme in an attempt to resolve the political crisis that has engulfed him.</p>
<p>The 69-year-old leader was forced into the move as a way of holding together his faltering four-way conservative coalition, which was threatening to collapse and pitch the country into snap elections.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi had been under intense pressure from two allies, the Union of Christian Democrats and the National Alliance, to make sweeping changes to his administration after suffering a heavy defeat in regional elections.</p>
<p>Under the terms of the Italian constitution, Mr Berlusconi is obliged to resign to make changes to his cabinet. Although the move gives him breathing space, it is a political blow. It also means he has been unable to achieve his cherished goal of being the first postwar Italian prime minister to serve an uninterrupted five-year term in office.</p>
<p>Italy has been on a knife-edge over the crisis, which began when Mr Berlusconi's coalition lost badly in regional elections and the Union of Christian Democrats withdrew its support.</p>
<p>Under pressure to present a platform that would appeal to voters, the prime minister was said to have agreed to the resignation strategy on Monday. He had been expected to hand in his resignation to the Italian head of state, President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi in Rome but he refused to do so, saying he would prefer to face a vote of confidence in parliament.</p>
<p>Within 48 hours he had changed his mind and yesterday, as he entered the upper house of the senate, he confirmed: "Yes, I am going to the head of state to resign. I accept the challenge of forming a new government."</p>
<p>He told a packed senate that he had been given assurances from all four coalition parties that they would support his new administration and he called his allies to back his House of Freedoms coalition in a confidence vote today. "With your confidence and your support, we have written important pages in our country's history," he said, addressing the government benches. "With your confidence and your support, I am sure we will write many more."</p>
<p>Outside parliament he said he was determined to see out his full term as prime minister but when asked about the scale of the cabinet reshuffle, Mr Berlusconi seemed to betray his annoyance at the situation he had been forced into. "Change of ministers?" he said. "Yes, but there won't be many."</p>
<p>The coalition closed ranks after the prime minister's declaration. The leader of the National Alliance and Mr Berlusconi's deputy, Gianfranco Fini, who had urged him to resign earlier in the week and present a new administration, praised Mr Berlusconi for his speech, saying it had given a much-needed boost to cohesion within the coalition.</p>
<p>But the centre-left opposition, which has accused Mr Berlusconi of exposing Italy to ridicule, poured scorn on the proceedings. Some called the situation an " indecent farce" and Piero Fassino, leader of the Democratic Party of the Left, described the manoeuverings as "an unacceptable shame".</p>
<p>In the past two days Mr Berlusconi has held meetings with his four coalition partners. It is not yet known what concessions he has had to make, but the expectation is that he will be able to form a government.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi now has a year - the elections are due in 2006 - to improve the centre-right's electoral prospects. He faces a struggle, since polls suggest he has lost the confidence of many of those who voted for him. The battering that the latest infighting has dealt to his standing will also prove hard to overcome.</p>
<p>The country's economic growth last year was slower than almost all of the other EU members. The European commission said it may launch proceedings against Italy's budget deficit, expected to widen to 3.6% this year and 4.6% next year.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who came to power in 2001 on a pledge of lower taxes, is also under pressure to withdraw Italy's troops from the US-led coalition force in Iraq. A poll gave the opposition, headed by the former European commission president Romano Prodi, a lead of five percentage points over the government.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi has presided over Italy's 59th, and longest-serving post-war government.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>