<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-07-20" description="Read the transcript of clips published today by two Italian websites, purporting to contain the Italian prime minister in conversation with an escort" fingerprint="decc4905386d84bf" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi: the 'escort' tapes" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/20/silvio-berlusconi-escort-tapes">
<main>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">An escort, Patrizia D'Addario, is about to enter Berlusconi's Palazzo Grazioli. She asks a man who accompanies her how to behave with Berlusconi. </hi>
</p>
<p>Man: … I'm staying behind […]</p>
<p>Patrizia: But are we having dinner now? Then at what time should we say ... as usual [...]</p>
<p>Man: ... I don't know ... because ... I know that the president is a bit jolly ... he sings ... tells a few jokes.</p>
<p>Patrizia: So we can sing?</p>
<p>Man: … and then you get into some more ... but... there's no problem.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Berlusconi presents himself to the women. Among jokes and laughs, the party takes off.</hi>
</p>
<p>Male voice: Clarissa ...</p>
<p>SB: Ciao, everything OK?</p>
<p>Woman: Absolutely.</p>
<p>SB: Ciao.</p>
<p>PD: Alessia.</p>
<p>SB: Ah, what nice girls you are ... my compliments.</p>
<p>PD: Thank you.</p>
<p>Woman: We're all in black!</p>
<p>SB: Ahhh!</p>
<p>Male voice: All in black!</p>
<p>SB: Among other things, I have... isn't that incredible ... I've ordered 22 costumes for our theatre, you know those costumes, they made them.</p>
<p>Male voice: Are you forgetting something?</p>
<p>SB: So... you, where are you from?</p>
<p>PD: I'm from Milan [but at the moment I'm living in Bari] …</p>
<p>SB: What are you doing?</p>
<p>PD: I'm taking care of a property operation […] it's not going very well because by myself it's a bit hard.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">It is 4 November</hi>
<hi rend="#b"> – two weeks have passed.</hi>
</p>
<p>SB: This [book?...], I've designed this.</p>
<p>PD: You've done a very good job.</p>
<p>SB: Did you have this last time?</p>
<p>PD: Yes.</p>
<p>SB: You were here already last time?</p>
<p>PD: Yes.</p>
<p>SB: Well isn't that incredible... and this one? Take.</p>
<p>PD: No, not this one.</p>
<p>SB: It's the most beautiful one.</p>
<p>PD: The most beautiful one is this one.</p>
<p>SB: Take this one with you, give it to someone as a gift.</p>
<p>PD: No.</p>
<p>SB: No, it would be a waste.</p>
<p>PD: Did you design this one also?</p>
<p>SB: The idea is mine but I haven't designed it. Just look at this ... how it's made. It's a friend of mine who's made it for me. He does everything for me ... I'm also going to have a shower ... and then, then are you going to wait for me in the big bed if you're done before me?</p>
<p>PD: What big bed ... Putin's?</p>
<p>SB: Yes, Putin's.</p>
<p>PD: Oh how nice ... that one with the curtains.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">It is 5 November. Patrizia and her "agent" Giampaolo Tarantini are discussing her sleepless night with the prime minister.</hi>
</p>
<p>PD: Hi, good afternoon.</p>
<p>GT: Good afternoon.</p>
<p>PD: How are you?</p>
<p>GT: Well.</p>
<p>PD: We didn't sleep last night.</p>
<p>GT: I can imagine. How did it go?</p>
<p>PD: Good, no envelope though.</p>
<p>GT: Really?</p>
<p>PD: I swear to you. How come? You told me there would be an envelope [...] gave me a gift, I don't know, a little turtle.</p>
<p>GT: Um.</p>
<p>PD: And then made me a promise.</p>
<p>GT: Which was?</p>
<p>PD: That ... OK, I can tell you, so long as you don't tell anyone. He told me that he would send me people on the construction site. He said it, so should I believe it?</p>
<p>GT: Yes, if he says it. Did you give him your number?</p>
<p>PD: Yes, I gave him my number; he wanted it this morning, and my surname too, and told me that he would help me on the construction site, would send me people.</p>
<p>GT: OK then.</p>
<p>PD: And then told me that he would like to see me with a female friend because ... two of us.</p>
<p>GT: Listen, how? What time did you get back?</p>
<p>PD: Just now, before I called you.</p>
<p>GT: But where are you, in the hotel already?</p>
<p>PD: Yes.</p>
<p>GT: Let's meet for a coffee.</p>
<p>PD: Yes, if you want we will be here in the hotel, we don't even know what time we need to leave.</p>
<p>GT: Amò sent you a message yesterday.</p>
<p>PD: Ah, was it written what time we need to leave? As Barbara said, as soon as I arrived he asked "You have received the envelope, €5,000." I said no, I haven't taken anything.</p>
<p>GT: I wanted to say something to you, he said something about me, no?</p>
<p>PD: He only asked me how long we had known each other, I said for a long time – was that the right thing to say?</p>
<p>GT: Well done, yes.</p>
<p>PD: I said we had known each other a long time, and I said that Barbara is a friend of mine too, he said that he has a girlfriend and would like to have me licked by this girlfriend.</p>
<p>GT: Ahahahah.</p>
<p>PD: I promise you, this is what he said. Very affectionate, all night we didn't sleep.</p>
<p>GT: Good for him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">[...]</hi>
</p>
<p>PD: Hello?</p>
<p>SB: How are you this morning?</p>
<p>PD: How are you?</p>
<p>SB: This morning.</p>
<p>PD: Well.</p>
<p>SB: Everything good?</p>
<p>PD: Yes, you?</p>
<p>SB: Me, yes. I've worked a lot. This morning I went to open this exhibition, I gave a great speech, with applause, and I didn't seem tired.</p>
<p>PD: Ah, like me in fact, I'm not tired, I haven't slept. Only my voice is gone.</p>
<p>SB: Why? We didn't shout.</p>
<p>PD: And yet, I didn't holler, who knows why my voice is gone. Do you know why? Because I took a shower, 10 times with icy water because I was hot.</p>
<p>SB: Great. Listen, everything OK?</p>
<p>PD: Yes, everything is good.</p>
<p>SB: They've worn out. I'm leaving now for Moscow.</p>
<p>PD: OK</p>
<p>SB: I'll call you tomorrow when I get back, OK?</p>
<p>PD: OK, a big strong kiss to you.</p>
<p>SB: Ciao.</p>
<p>PD: Ciao.</p>
<p>SB: Goodbye, treasure.</p>
<p>Woman: Bye. A kiss.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>