<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Politics" date="2010-08-04" description="Prime minister misses one-to-one talks with Italian counterpart but joins him for dinner" fingerprint="5e8e43abb1d3ff24" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="David Cameron,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="David Cameron late for first meeting with Silvio Berlusconi in Rome" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2010/aug/04/david-cameron-late-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>When in Rome, do as the Romans do. Turn up late. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/davidcameron">David Cameron</ref>, on his first visit to the Italian capital since becoming prime minister, arrived almost an hour behind schedule and had to skip planned one-to-one talks with his Italian counterpart.</p>
<p>Instead, he went straight into dinner with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. This can be quite an experience, as numerous young women have testified to Italy's police and prosecutors. Only this week, it was reported that a 38-year-old prostitute, Maria Teresa 'Terry' De Nicolo, had described how she and "perhaps 15" women enjoyed a meal with Italy's prime minister before she and a couple of the others joined him in bed.</p>
<p>The prime minister has already gone to see his counterparts in France and Germany. So it was natural he should take up Berlusconi's invitation to Rome.</p>
<p>The two men had much to discuss. Officials said the agenda included the world economy and its recovery, including how to boost trade between Britain and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, and Afghanistan, where the two countries are among the biggest military contributors. They also said Britain saw Berlusconi and his right-wing government as "influential" in the Middle East and that the talks would cover Israel and the Palestinians, Iran and Turkey. Italy also vigorously supports Turkey's entry into the EU.</p>
<p>That said, anyone speculating that the prime minister was just the slightest bit embarrassed to be in such close proximity to his flamboyant Italian counterpart would not have been dissuaded by the speed with which he swept in and out of Rome without holding a press conference.</p>
<p>The fragrant De Nicolo's alleged encounter with the media tycoon-turned-statesman took place at his private residence, Palazzo Grazioli. But the prime minister was shown to Berlusconi's official home in Rome, Palazzo Chigi, which is about a quarter of a mile away.</p>
<p>It was clear their menu had been carefully vetted to remove any possible culinary double entendres. Officials said they sat down to an unabashedly patriotic meal of Insalata Caprese, Penne Tricolore (pasta in the colours of the Italian flag), strips of Chianina beef from Tuscany, cheese and, of course, Italian ice cream. The only mystery surrounded the vegetables for the main course, which a spokesman for the Italian government described as "unspecified".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>