<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2009-07-10" description="Anna Masera: The Guardian is free to attack Berlusconi, as long as it has the facts. But claims that Italy is unfit for summitry are unfounded" fingerprint="3ffec326d1a3de1d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,G8,The Guardian,Newspapers,Media,World news,Europe" title="More than mafia and spaghetti | Anna Masera" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/10/berlusconi-italy-g8-guardian">
<main>
<p>The Guardian's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/06/g8-considers-expelling-italy">story</ref> on the eve of the Italian-hosted G8 summit, speculating that Italy might be expelled from the G8 due to chaotic management by the government and declining per capita national income, infuriated not only Silvio Berlusconi, but the Italian public – represented by most of the Italian media. The only exception is the leftwing La Repubblica (which is embroiled in a media battle against Italy's premier) and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/10/berlusconi-guardian-italy">Antonio Di Pietro</ref>, the leader of the opposition party <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy_of_Values">Italia dei Valori</ref>, known worldwide as the strongly anti-Berlusconi magistrate of "<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani_pulite">Mani Pulite</ref>".</p>
<p>Berlusconi's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/07/berlusconi-g8-summit-preparations">reaction</ref> to the Guardian story was understandable, given that he was preparing to host an important global summit. But what was worse was an <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/08/editorial-g8-berlusconi-italy">editorial</ref> the next day that blamed Italians for Berlusconi: "If Italy wants Mr Berlusconi as its prime minister, should the G8 want Italy?" it opined.</p>
<p>Why do Italians take issue with the Guardian? First of all, because the notion that Italy might be expelled from the G8 is attributed to anonymous sources such as "one senior G8 member state official" or "a European official involved in the summit preparations". Is this what acclaimed Anglo-Saxon journalism is about: damning a country without decent proof and real sources? Italians mythologise the objectiveness of Anglo-Saxon journalism and this was a let-down.</p>
<p>Second, Italians can take a joke and are often the most critical of their own country. Most are slightly embarrassed when they have to sing the national anthem and don't feel proud of the national flag (unlike Americans, for example) but they do become patriotic when teased by foreigners. That goes especially for the British media, famous for its patronising cliches about Italy as the country of "love, spaghetti, and mafia". Almost every Italian remembers with pride when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2008/dec/08/economy-gdp-uk-italy-france">Italy surpassed Britain as a leading world economy</ref>. It's an ongoing competition that no Italian likes to lose. If the Guardian wants to hit Berlusconi and his government in Italy, it had better not do it by hitting Italy as a whole: the result is only more popularity for the prime minister.</p>
<p>The Italian media has given a huge amount of front-page attention to the Guardian's attack. True, it provided a welcome diversion from the nitty gritty of summitry, and was a bit more interesting for the public than diplomatic relations. But rather more important is that the summit itself produced no evidence that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, by continuing to support Berlusconi, was unfit for summitry.</p>
<p>Did the personal scandal surrounding Italy's prime minister interfere with the business of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref>? No. The leaders met, were entertained and Berlusconi hosted well, without any gaffes for the foreign press to make fun of. The chaos the Guardian predicted did not happen. True, a G8 summit makes little sense without China – not to mention the rising economic powers of India, Brazil, Mexico and South Africa. But that's hardly Italy's fault.</p>
<p>The real question is not whether Italy should be kicked out of the G8 because its prime minister entertained youthful escorts, but whether the G8 should change its membership formula and open its doors to more countries. It seems that it will and it has, according to announcements made this week.</p>
<p>And it is right that promises made about aid to developing countries need to be kept, as Bob Geldof pointed out in the special pre-summit edition of <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/focus/g8/africa/default.asp">La Stampa</ref> where he was appointed editor-in-chief for a day. Geldof interviewed Berlusconi and made him apologise for not giving promised aid to Africa. The result? On the final day of the G8, Italy's premier closed the agenda with a press conference in which he <ref target="http://www.lastampa.it/focus/g8/default.asp">announced</ref> that by the end of August Italy would pay up €160m in aid to Africa. It is likely that with all the media attention this time round, he will honour the promise.</p>
<p>Agreements reached at L'Aquila were not breathtakingly revolutionary, but have summits ever been? There were steps forward. Maybe the Guardian should take a step back and recognise that Italy is not unfit for summitry, after all.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>