<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2008-12-15" description="Eighth most powerful female manager in world marries ballet dancer, Maurizio Vanadia" fingerprint="69a2a22f151ec617" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi daughter ties the knot" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/dec/15/berlusconi-daughter-marriage-italy-news">
<main>
<p>Actors and dancers beware: perform on stage in Milan and you may end up married to a member of the Berlusconi family.</p>
<p>Marina Berlusconi, daughter of Italian prime minister Silvio, this weekend married a ballet dancer she took a shine to while watching him dance in Swan Lake at Milan's La Scala.</p>
<p>The match-up echoes Silvio Berlusconi's own wooing of his second wife, actor Veronica Lario, after becoming mesmerised while watching her perform in a Milan theatre in 1980.</p>
<p>Silvio's oldest child Marina, 42, has inherited her father's business nous and since becoming chairman of the Berlusconi family's Fininvest group has been listed by Fortune magazine as the eighth most powerful female manager in the world and by Forbes as Italy's most influential woman.</p>
<p>But in an interview with Chi magazine, she suggested she behaved more like a schoolgirl when she went to see Maurizio Vanadia dance at La Scala after meeting him socially.</p>
<p>"I was leaning forward so far to see him with the binoculars my mother kept on elbowing me and saying 'Watch out or you will fall into the stalls,'" she said.</p>
<p>The couple's path crossed again when a dancing injury suffered by Vanadia, which forced him into retirement, was treated by a doctor retained by AC Milan, the football club owned by Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Love bloomed and two children followed, before Marina and Maurizio decided to tie the knot on Saturday, an occasion which put Marina's mother, Silvio Berlusconi's first wife Carla Dall'Oglio, together in the same room for the first time with his second wife, Veronica.</p>
<p>"They shook hands," said one guest present, La Stampa reported. "It was a cordial greeting that lasted less than a minute with no kisses."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>