<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2009-05-06" description="Anna Masera: The divorce won't be pretty, and Silvio Berlusconi – or Napoleon, to his estranged wife – is unlikely to reach his Waterloo" fingerprint="4697505dde425d03" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Television industry,World news,Europe" title="The media battle of Berlusconi's life | Anna Masera" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/may/06/berlusconi-veronica-lario">
<main>
<p>Napoleon, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/www.repubblica.it/2009/04/sezioni/politica/elezioni-2009-1/marito-napoleone/marito-napoleone.html">as Silvio Berlusconi's wife baptised him</ref>, is bracing himself for the battle of his life. Italy's premier is angry, but alive and kicking – not just to fight his wife Veronica Lario in court after her request for divorce this weekend, but against the media circus all over the world. What worries him most is that his popularity is at risk.</p>
<p>There aren't any official poll results, on which Berlusconi is used to relying on heavily, but the first signals are negative and his aides are in a bit of a panic, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/www.lastampa.it/redazione/cmsSezioni/politica/200905articoli/43416girata.asp">Ugo Magri of La Stampa reports</ref> . They worry that his magic show might be over. As his wife puts it, he is "like Napoleon". It's Veronica's show now.</p>
<p>A month ahead of the European elections (as well as the administrative vote, and the constitutional referendum), the timing for such a scandal couldn't be worse. The Italian public is passionate about Veronica, and her rebellion against her husband is subjectto widespread gossiping. The accusation that Berlusconi "cavorts with minors" is more exciting than a soap opera, or even one of those reality shows that Berlusconi's <ref target="http://www.mediaset.it/">TV channels</ref> cherish so much.</p>
<p>The opposition leader, Dario Franceschini of the Democratic party, keeps saying that he doesn't want to profit politically from such personal issues, but of course, he does. Antonio Di Pietro's Italia dei Valori is reviewing the penal code, and the Catholic left is, of course, morally indignated. Worse than the opposition, however, is the circus: correspondents from all over the world are flocking to Italy not for the earthquake aftermath, not for the historic multinational car industry acquisitions by Fiat, but to entertain their public with the latest by Silvio. With the G8 summit at the doors of L'Aquila, no wonder Berlusconi — who wants to have a leading role with world leaders, but risks ridicule instead – is anguished. He also hopes to beat his personal record at the European elections: in 1999 he received 3 million preferences; this time he wants to reach four million in order to be able to clear the way for reforms, starting from the constitutional one.</p>
<p>May all this be in vain, all because of Veronica? <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/www.lastampa.it/redazione/cmsSezioni/politica/200905articoli/43387girata.asp">In an interview with Mario Calabresi</ref>, the new editor-in-chief of La Stampa, Berlusconi denied that his private life will influence politics. However, in private talks reported later, he admits, "This story may make me lose votes," while adding, over and over, "I didn't do anything regrettable."</p>
<p>This week he was reunited with his faithful aides at his villa in Arcore, with a Dutch television troupe at the gate. His defence strategy is in the hands of Niccolò Ghedini and his sisters Ippolita and Nicoletta, both experts in marriage law. Veronica Lario's lawyer is Maria Cristina Morelli, who helped Beppino Englaro in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/feb/08/eluana-englaro-assisted-suicide">the famed euthanasia battle</ref> for his daughter Eluana.</p>
<p>Berlusconi is not worried about the financial aspects of the divorce, which will involve his five children. He is worried about his image in politics, since he has relied on it so much so far, andthe reaction of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/www.corriere.it/politica/09_maggio_05/sfogo_cavaliere_verderami_0dde040e-3934-11de-ab3d-00144f02aabc.shtml">the Catholic electorate behind the church</ref>, an important political ally so far. It is so far keeping quiet on the sex scandals, but this is the second divorce for Berlusconi, difficult even for a befriended clergy to swallow.</p>
<p>Advisers have tried to convince him to stay away from television, while the gossip is becoming ever more irresistible, but Berlusconiannounced an appearance on Tuesday evening on the most watched national talk show, Porta a Porta on Rai Uno, to be interviewed by Bruno Vespa, known to be a friendly journalist. With a huge audience guaranteed, Berlusconi's performance will be crawled over for days by both left and right.</p>
<p>Napoleon is braced for the battle of his life. This might not yet be his Waterloo, but it could represent his retreat from Moscow.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>