<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Share" categories="World news" date="2014-04-15" description="The former Italian prime minister has been sentenced to a year of community service at a home for the elderly after his conviction for tax fraud. Here is a look back at some memorable images from his life in Italian politics" fingerprint="5ea6d02f91dcc12d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news;Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi – a career in pictures" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2014/apr/15/silvio-berlsuconi-a-career-in-pictures">
<main>
<head rend="h1">Silvio Berlusconi – a career in pictures</head>
<p>The former Italian prime minister has been sentenced to a year of community service at a home for the elderly after his conviction for tax fraud. Here is a look back at some memorable images from his life in Italian politics</p>
<list rend="ul">
<item> Silvio Berlusconi prepares himself before he welcomes the emir of Kuwait, Sheikh Sabah Al-Ahmad Al-Jaber, at Villa Madama in Rome. Photograph: Danilo Schiavella/EPA</item>
<item> Now at the Chigi Palace in Rome, Berlusconi smiles before his meeting with the then Bulgarian prime minister, Bojko Borisov. Photograph: Ettore Ferrari/EPA</item>
<item> He owns a football club too. Here Berlusconi steps on to the podium after AC Milan beat Juventus to win the Trofeo Luigi, an annual friendly founded by Berlusconi in memory of his father Luigi. Photograph: Olivier Morin/AFP/Getty Images</item>
<item> Back in the Villa Madama, Berlusconi shares a word with Nicolas Sarkozy. Photograph: Gregorio Borgia/AP</item>
<item> Here Berlusconi feigns illness after tasting buffalo mozzarella at a meeting with the Italian agricultural lobby Coldiretti. Photograph: Plinio Lepri/AP</item>
<item> Another light moment for Berlusconi as world leaders have their picture taken at the start of the G20 summit in London. Photograph: Stefan Rousseau/PA</item>
<item> Again with Sarkozy … and Angela Merkel during a news conference at the Elysée Palace in Paris. Photograph: Philippe Wojazer/Reuters</item>
<item> And here's Berlusconi with Dmitry Medvedev, then the Russian president (now prime minister) in Milan. Photograph: Sasha Mordovets/Getty Images</item>
<item> Posing for photographers before the Italian political debate show Porta a Porta. Photograph: Alessandra Benedetti/Corbis</item>
<item> And offering his hand for the talk show host Bruno Vespa to smell during the recording of a TV show in Rome, saying it has 'the scent of sainthood'. Photograph: Plinio Lepri/AP</item>
<item> Still in his days as prime minister, Berlusconi drinks coffee in the Italian senate as the former justice minister Angelino Alfano talks on a mobile phone. Photograph: Tony Gentile/Reuters</item>
</list>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>