<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2004-12-17" description="Italy's head of state took the rare step last night of refusing to sign into law a controversial bill championed by Silvio Berlusconi's government that critics say weakens the independence of Italy's judiciary." fingerprint="efb28334b73582cf" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="President rejects Berlusconi's legal reforms" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/dec/17/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Italy's head of state took the rare step last night of refusing to sign into law a controversial bill championed by Silvio Berlusconi's government that critics say weakens the independence of Italy's judiciary.</p>
<p>President Carlo Azeglio Ciampi gave his prime minister a stinging rebuff when he flung the proposed law back at parliament saying that parts of it were "blatantly unconstitutional".</p>
<p>In doing so the president, normally a figurehead above the political fray, was siding with judges and prosecutors who have protested vehemently at the draft legislation with a number of strikes, the latest of which happened last month.</p>
<p>A parliament in which Mr Berlusconi's supporters enjoy an outright majority approved the proposed legislation soon afterwards. The legal reform bill is a centrepiece of the rightwing government's programme.</p>
<p>But judges and prosecutors fear the legislation will curb the independence of the courts and prevent the judiciary from pursuing allegations against corrupt politicians.</p>
<p>Prosecutors have launched several high-profile cases against Mr Berlusconi in recent years, the latest of which culminated last week in a partial exoneration.</p>
<p>The prime minister and his supporters were last night at pains to play down the importance of the bill's rejection.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi said the problems raised by the president would be tackled swiftly. He predicted the bill would be ratified by February.</p>
<p>"This is a good reform, even if it is a little lightweight," he told reporters on a visit to Brussels.</p>
<p>"It is not the reform we would have liked for Italy's justice problems, which continue to this day. But it is a step in the right direction."</p>
<p>It is unusual for Italian presidents to refuse to sign legislation. Yet President Ciampi has done so twice in little more than two years.</p>
<p>In December 2003, he vetoed another key bill that imposed sweeping changes on television and saved one of the three channels owned by Mr Berlusconi from being forced on to satellite.</p>
<p>An amended measure was eventually put on the statute book.</p>
<p>The government's legal reform bill has been bitterly criticised by opposition politicians as an attempt by the prime minister to pay back judges and prosecutors for being dragged repeatedly through the courts to answer charges of corruption.</p>
<p>Antonio di Pietro, once a crusading anti-graft prosecutor, yesterday called the legislation "an act of vengeance against [Italy's] independent judiciary".</p>
<p>Last week, the most serious legal threat hanging over Mr Berlusconi was removed when a court in Milan cleared him of paying judges for favourable rulings before he entered politics.</p>
<p>However, one of the charges was dropped only because the court decided the alleged offence had been committed too long ago to be considered.</p>
<p>The bill rejected by Mr Ciampi separates prosecutors and judges, who currently belong to the same career structure. It also makes their promotion dependent on passing examinations.</p>
<p>It would force magistrates to choose within five years of entering the profession whether they wanted to pursue a career as a prosecutor or a judge. But defence lawyers argue the changes do not make a clear enough division.</p>
<p>Most controversially, it restricts the freedom of ordinary prosecutors to bring charges and makes them subject to superiors who, critics claim, will be susceptible to influence by the government of the day.</p>
<p>The prime minister has long contended that he is the victim of a politically motivated campaign by leftwing prosecutors.</p>
<p>The bill would ban magistrates from belonging to political parties and would force them to submit to psychological tests.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's supporters argue that the measure is needed to curb the excesses of maverick prosecutors. They also claim that grouping prosecutors and judges together as members of the same profession puts defence lawyers at a disadvantage in court.</p>
<p>If the bill is passed by parliament a second time - with or without amendments - President Ciampi will be obliged to sign it.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>