<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-11-28" description="Tessa Jowell's estranged husband will give evidence via video link from Westminster magistrates court in the bribing case" fingerprint="87ac30c74895658" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,David Mills,UK news,Italy,Tessa Jowell,Europe,World news,Politics" title="David Mills to testify at Silvio Berlusconi trial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/28/david-mills-silvio-berlusconi-trial">
<main>
<p>David Mills, the estranged husband of the former Labour cabinet minister Tessa Jowell, is due to testify by video link at Silvio Berlusconi's trial in Italy for allegedly bribing him.</p>
<p>The British lawyer was expected at Westminster magistrates court after a judge on Friday threw out an attempt by Berlusconi to prevent him from giving evidence. Lawyers for the TV magnate, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/12/silvio-berlusconi-resign-italy-eurozone?intcmp=239">who resigned as Italy's prime minister earlier this month</ref>, had applied for an interim injunction pending a full-scale legal challenge on the issue.</p>
<p>But Mr Justice Bean, sitting in private in London, turned down their application. He said the Italian prosecution had sent a note accusing Berlusconi of attempting to "delay or derail" the trial and added that "on the material before me there would appear to be considerable force in that submission".</p>
<p>Mills, who set up a web of offshore companies for Berlusconi, was tried in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> on charges of accepting a $600,000 bribe from his former client to perjure himself by omission. He was found guilty in 2009, and his appeal was rejected.</p>
<p>Last year, Italy's highest appeals court quashed his conviction. But the judges, in their written ruling, said they had done so because the case had been "timed out" by a statute of limitations.</p>
<p>After Italy's constitutional court threw out crucial parts of a law passed by Berlusconi's government that shielded him from prosecution, the media tycoon was put back on trial, accused of giving Mills the alleged bribe. He has repeatedly denied the charge, arguing he is the victim of a witch hunt by prosecutors.</p>
<p>Mills was originally called to appear before the senior district judge Howard Riddle at Westminster magistrates court on 28 October and a TV link was set up with Milan. But Berlusconi obtained an adjournment by insisting on his right to be present at the trial hearings and then citing his duties as prime minister as a reason for being unable to attend. His trial is due to be timed out early next year.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>