<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-11-12" description="Corruption, vested interests, bunga-bunga girls … and it became a country for old men" fingerprint="afc9813d76a7a729" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Eurozone crisis,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi knew that Italians don't like change or obeying rules" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/12/silvio-berlusconi-italy-change-rules">
<main>
<p>Guido Rossi, Italy's leading corporate troubleshooter, once remarked that his country's worst maladies were "the rejection of rules and an aversion to change". Few of his compatriots would deny these were national characteristics, though many would, I suspect, see them in a more positive light. They would regard the first as thinking for themselves and the second as respect for tradition. At all events, the mess <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> got itself and the euro into last week can, to a large extent, be traced to those traits.</p>
<p>What has increasingly terrified investors is Italy's giant public debt – or rather, a fear that the country's growth potential is so weak that it will be unable to meet the interest payments. The Italian treasury is in the same, vulnerable position as an individual with a vast overdraft, but whose salary never rises: the moment interest rates go up, as they have in the eurozone, he or she is in trouble.</p>
<p>The debt began to grow in the heady days following the upheavals of 1968, when Italy's Christian Democrat-dominated governments bent with the leftwing winds blowing through <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> and began constructing a welfare state. The treasury's spending rose and continued to do so through the economically troubled 1970s as extra cash had to be found to meet the losses of nationalised industries and a rising bill for redundancy pay.</p>
<p>Knowing the difficulty of getting Italians to obey rules, particularly the one about having to pay tax, successive governments turned a blind eye to evasion. There were political and economic reasons for doing so, too. The people who could evade most easily were the shopkeepers, bar owners and other small businesspeople who formed that "middle Italy" which voted Christian Democrat. They also included the stewards of a vast "black economy", accounting for 15-20% of the total, which politicians were loth to interfere with because it was Italy's most dynamic and profitable sector (unsurprisingly, since its labour costs were so low).</p>
<p>In the prosperous 1980s, the debt could have been paid off. But systemic corruption was kicking in. The price of everything sold to the public sector was increased to take account of the <hi rend="#i">tangenti</hi> raked off by the parties. A large part of today's debt consists of the difference between fair prices and what the authorities actually paid suppliers.</p>
<p>But since the authorities were borrowing what they needed by issuing treasury bills, known as BoTs, at succulently high rates of interest, and these were being snapped up, mostly by Italians, no one complained. Least of all the "BoT people", the middle-class investors whose steady investment returns help explain why Italy today is a poor state of rich individuals.</p>
<p>The advent of the euro – and of low, German-style interest rates – cut the return on BoTs. But it also eased the unsustainably high cost of servicing the debt. But that meant Italians had to move gradually towards German levels of competitiveness. The reverse has happened. The gap has increased.</p>
<p>Which is where aversion to change comes in. It is not just the outgoing prime minister who is 75. The young are blocked in almost every walk of life, even rock music – the superstars are Vasco Rossi, 59, Luciano Ligabue, 51, and Zucchero, 56. The top TV current affairs presenter is 77. Berlusconi's best-known news anchor, facing trial for supplying him with "bunga-bunga" girls, is 80.</p>
<p>Italians leaving school or university face a choice between surviving on an endless succession of short-term contracts or going abroad to work, as hundreds of thousands have done. If they stay, they find the efforts of the unions are devoted overwhelmingly towards safeguarding the privileges of the upper tier, disproportionately composed of older, male workers in dying industries or the public sector.</p>
<p>But the unions are merely part of a vast web of vested interest groups. They include closed professions – from taxi drivers to public notaries – firms controlled by shareholder pacts and invisible cartels such as the one discovered some years ago in which city administrations secretly collaborated to suppress competition for local transport franchises.</p>
<p>Italians' determination to prevent change can be awesome. Both the government advisers behind employment law reforms were assassinated: Massimo D'Antona in 1999 and Marco Biagi in 2002.</p>
<p>With official connivance, Italy's universities have resisted for more than 20 years the efforts of their <hi rend="#i">lettori</hi> – foreign language teachers – to obtain the same conditions as Italian lecturers, defying rulings up to and including the European Court of Justice. In August, the lawyers and notaries in parliament were quite prepared to sink the austerity package being rushed through the legislature to stem the last run on Italy's bonds rather than agree to reform of their closed shops.</p>
<p>When Mario Monti said on Thursday "Italy has an enormous job to do", he was not exaggerating. That very day, the final touches were being put to the austerity package, plus other reforms since inserted at the insistence of the EU, in a senate commission. With Italy's financial credibility, the euro and even the world economy in the balance, the commission was, of course, making the austerity package yet more austere… well, not exactly.</p>
<p>Last-minute changes allowed another €100m of spending next year and €50m the year after for various causes – many undoubtedly worthy – close to the hearts of those who could influence the bill. They included everything from dog pounds to sports associations. And special exemption for spending on the works "following the collapse of the building in Via Roma" in Barletta – in the home province of the committee's chairman.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>