<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Maev Kennedy" categories="World news" date="2009-11-12" description="Joaquin 'El Chapo' Guzman is at 41, beating Medvedev, Sarkozy and Chávez, while Mexico's president misses out" fingerprint="e2a9817485b4db6b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Mexico,Drugs trade,Dmitry Medvedev,Nicolas Sarkozy,Hugo Chávez,Lakshmi Mittal,Barack Obama,Vladimir Putin,Gordon Brown,Bill Clinton,Rupert Murdoch,Bill Gates,Silvio Berlusconi,Pope Benedict XVI,Angela Merkel,Hillary Clinton,Warren Buffett,Kim Jong-il,Mark Thompson,Magazines,World news,Business,Politics,Media,Americas,The papacy,Joaquín El Chapo Guzmán" title="Forbes power list puts Mexican drug lord ahead of presidents" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/12/forbes-power-mexican-drug-lord">
<main>
<p>Any attempt to rank the world's most powerful people is likely to be a somewhat dry affair, with serried ranks of politicians, businessmen and media magnates. So it came as a surprise when Forbes magazine launched its first list of the most important international power brokers yesterday with a Mexican drug lord, Joaquin "El Chapo" Guzman, at number 41, ahead of Dmitry Medvedev, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref> and Hugo Chávez.</p>
<p>The mere rumour this year that Guzman might make the list was enough to provoke outrage in Mexico, where the president, Felipe Calderon – who has not made the list – said without naming Forbes: "Magazines are not only attacking and lying about the situation in Mexico but are also praising criminals."</p>
<p>Guzman, estimated to be worth $1bn and believed to be hiding out in the mountains of northern Mexico with a 30m pesos (£1.3m) price on his head, is considered to be more important than the chatshow queen Oprah Winfrey and the Indian steel billionaire <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/lakshmi-mittal">Lakshmi Mittal</ref>.</p>
<p>But if he has his BlackBerry turned on in his hideout, he might not be pleased to read that he is not regarded as the most powerful Mexican. That would be Carlos Slim Helu, in sixth place, not just the richest man in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mexico">Mexico</ref> – where his company owns 90% of both the fixed telephone lines and wireless market – but the third richest man in the world, with a personal fortune estimated at over $68bn (£41bn), or roughly 2% of his country's GDP.</p>
<p>Barack Obama tops the list, which Forbes said was not just about power but exercising it. Hu Jintao, the Chinese president, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/vladimir-putin">Vladimir Putin</ref>, the Russian prime minister, are in second and third place, with Putin's frankly terrifying-looking deputy, Igor Sechin, 39 places lower – and both men ahead of their alleged boss, President Medvedev.</p>
<p>In such company Gordon Brown might feel comparatively grateful to make the list at number 29, all of two places ahead of Bill Clinton, even if well behind the media tycoon Rupert Murdoch, in seventh, Bill Gates, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and the pope at 10, 11 and 12 respectively, Angela Merkel at 15 (apparently, with Hillary Clinton at 17, one of only two powerful women in the world), the investment guru Warren Buffett, and North Korea's Kim Jong-il, in 24th place.</p>
<p>For the sake of his remaining fingernails, it might be as well not to break it to Brown that he is not a respectable third of the way down the list but in fact halfway down. Forbes reckoned it didn't need 100 places and that 67 would do, representing one in every 100 million people on Earth. The only other Briton is the BBC director general, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/markthompson">Mark Thompson</ref>, at 65.</p>
<p>Chávez, the president of Venezuela, is in last place, but he probably has time to improve his ranking: Forbes noted he "seems certain to be president for life after winning vote to eliminate term limits".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>