<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Angelique Chrisafis" categories="World news" date="2009-07-08" description="PM's wife blogs on G8 summit activities and puts photos on Flickr" fingerprint="6e2c23f1a9ce951" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="G8,Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Michelle Obama,X,Technology,Politics,UK news,Social networking,Digital media,Media,Flickr,Sarah Brown,Social media,Europe" title="Sarah Brown leads on Twitter and posts G8 summit spouses' blog" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/08/sarah-brown-twitters-g8-summit">
<main>
<p>An acrimonious divorce, scandal over a young model and nude photos at pool parties – Silvio Berlusconi's family traumas might not seem the ideal backdrop for the genteel spouses' programme at a G8 summit. But the 72-year-old Italian prime minister is not one to scrimp on entertaining.</p>
<p>With his soon to be ex-wife Veronica Lario no longer around to host leaders' wives, Berlusconi was defiant in appointing the equalities opportunities minister and former topless model and TV showgirl Mara Carfagna to co-host the first spouses' event, a midday audience with the pope.</p>
<p>The summit activities of the WAHs (wives and one husband, the German chancellor Angela Merkel's husband, Joachim Sauer, who was absent today) are now as much a media circus as the key political meetings. But Gordon Brown's wife Sarah won admiration across Europe for taking coverage into her own hands, adding to her Twitter presence with a G8 summit spouses' blog. She also posted pictures on Flickr of the wives' "tour of the beautiful basilica gardens" before heading for "a wonderful lunch hosted by the mayor of Rome's wife at the Campidoglio", giving a special mention to the "extraordinary antiquities and the chef's signature Ravioli Carbonara". But she wrote that "good food and good company" – catching up with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/michelleobama">Michelle Obama</ref> and Laureen Harper of Canada – meant she was running late for tea at the presidential Quirinale Palace with Clio Napolitano, wife of the Italian president.</p>
<p>Michelle Obama skipped the visit to the pope as she and her husband will have their own audience with the pontiff on Friday.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>