<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2005-04-20" description="Silvio Berlusconi will today resign as Italian prime minister in a gesture intended to win the support of two rebel coalition partners for a new government to replace his struggling administration." fingerprint="7a48c93dd1a3c744" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi to resign as Italian PM" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/20/italy1">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi will today resign as Italian prime minister in a gesture intended to win the support of two rebel coalition partners for a new government to replace his struggling administration.</p>
<p>The move is a formality - Mr Berlusconi must resign as the head of the present government before he can form a new one - but he is now likely to see out the worst crisis in his four years in government without calling an early election.</p>
<p>Opinions polls suggest that a centre left coalition led by Romano Prodi, the former president of the European commission, would be the main beneficiaries of an election if Mr Berlusconi failed to resolve the crisis.</p>
<p>He had been expected to resign on Monday but made a U-turn in what appeared a last-ditch attempt to fulfil his ambition to become the first Italian prime minister since the second world war to lead a single government for the full five-year term.</p>
<p>"This time, no surprises. Today I resign and I go to the head of state," Mr Berlusconi told the Italian Ansa news agency.</p>
<p>He told the Italian senate he would form a new government to strengthen the weakened coalition around his Forza Italia party.</p>
<p>The crisis was triggered when first the centre right Union of Christian Democrats (UDC) and then the National Alliance (AN) withdrew their support for the government after suffering losses in regional elections earlier this month.</p>
<p>The two parties promised to support a new Berlusconi government if he announced sweeping policy changes and appointed different ministers.</p>
<p>As a condition of their support, the UDC and AN are demanding that the influence of the populist Northern League is significantly reduced in a future Berlusconi administration. Both parties argue that a bill devolving power from Rome to regions panders to the League, which is the only party aside from Mr Berlusconi's own to promise loyal support to the prime minister.</p>
<p>The AN said it would still support the centre right coalition, but that the continued participation of its ministers "depends solely on what Berlusconi will say and do".</p>
<p>The AN is the coalition's second-largest party. If its five ministers - including foreign minister Gianfranco Fini - resign from the cabinet there is little chance of the government surviving.</p>
<p>If Mr Berlusconi's resignation fails to result in a stable governing coalition, Italians could go to the polls as early as June. Mr Prodi has demanded elections to halt what he calls the "endless crisis".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>