<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="Media" date="2003-07-03" description="Media reaction to Silvio Berlusconi's Nazi jibe to a German MEP at the European parliament." fingerprint="69e6905b984fde55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media business,European Union,Italy,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="What the Italian papers say" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jul/03/silvioberlusconi.europeanunion">
<main>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Ernesto Galli Della Loggia</hi> Corriere della Sera (centre)</p>
<p>"What we feared has happened like clockwork. As he addressed the European parliament, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, facing the most predictable attacks from Euro parliamentarians, did not manage to control his nerves or hold his tongue.</p>
<p>"It's already extremely serious not to have lifted a finger to resolve the conflict of interests. But playing cheeky, insolent is pure and simple suicide."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> La Repubblica </hi> (left-leaning) Editorial</p>
<p>"As Silvio Berlusconi drifts tragically further each day, yesterday he crashed into <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>, propelled by his lack of culture, his bravura that is so popular in Italy, flexing his muscles, for lack of competence, and incapable of responding to accusations over his howling conflict of interests.</p>
<p>"Yesterday can be considered the official date of the beginning of the decline of Il Cavaliere. But also, the result is extremely bitter for our country, which is paying an unjust and disproportionate price for Berlusconi's errors and personality."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">La Stampa</hi>(centre) Editorial</p>
<p>"A joke can ruin everything. He should not have opened the way for endless poisonous polemics with a joke that was so twisted in its irony that it was incomprehensible."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Il Messaggero</hi> (left-leaning) Editorial</p>
<p>"Everyone has the right to defend themselves, but if you don't do it in a measured way you end up in a pub atmosphere."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Avvenire</hi> (newspaper of the Italian Roman Catholic Bishops Conference) Editorial</p>
<p>"He should not have fallen into the trap. He not only shot himself in the foot but also gave a golden opportunity to his critics and made a whole country feel ill at ease all day."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Il Manifesto </hi> (communist) Editorial</p>
<p>"This was not a gaffe, an incident, a slip. And even less an ironic joke. The prime minister let rip a vulgar, heavy below the belt attack, not giving a damn about the sensitivities of a nation, or its tragic history. The aim was to hit as low as possible, to hurt, to show who has the power and how he intends to use it. With arrogance, violence and without pity."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Il Giornale</hi> (owned by Berlusconi family) Editorial</p>
<p>"Berlusconi did well to react to the insolent man who insulted him, the Italian government, its ministers, and all of us. He did excellently, in his own way, with his own style and in his own time."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Libero</hi> (owned by former editor of Il Giornale) Editorial</p>
<p>"Berlusconi should not give in to the pressures that will surely come in the coming hours. Maybe Schulz is not a Kapo (concentration camp guard), but he is a villain. And villains deserve not only irony but contempt."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>