<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roy Greenslade" categories="Media" date="2010-05-25" description="One of Italy's top television news readers, Maria Luisa Busi, has resigned from a state-funded TV channel saying that its coverage is biased in favour of prime minister Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="3f6a88ae9082e39d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Press freedom,Italy" title="Roy Greenslade: Italian news reader quits in protest at Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2010/may/25/silvio-berlusconi-press-freedom">
<main>
<p>One of Italy's top television news readers,<hi rend="#b"> Maria Luisa Busi</hi>, has resigned from a state-funded TV channel saying that its coverage is biased in favour of prime minister <hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>.</p>
<graphic alt="Maria Luisa" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2010/5/25/1274777796510/Maria.Luisa.Busi.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p>Busi, left, is reported to have informed her bosses at<hi rend="#b"> Rai 1</hi> of her feelings by pinning a candid letter of explanation on a notice board. Her departure at the weekend follows a series of clashes with the editor of the flagship evening TG1 news programme, <hi rend="#b">Augusto Minzolini</hi>, who was selected for the job by Berlusconi.</p>
<p>She has plenty of support. Rai's president,<hi rend="#b"> Paolo Garimberti</hi>, said her decision was "another worrying signal of a situation that requires maximum attention from the company's top management."</p>
<p>In addition to controlling three of Italy's seven terrestrial TV channels as part of his Mediaset empire, Berlusconi exercises considerable influence on senior appointments at Rai through his position as premier.</p>
<p>Busi did not restrict her complaints to political bias. She also claimed the programme's content has been dumbed down, with too much emphasis on "theft-proof underpants" and not enough reporting on failing schools and hospitals.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Source:</hi>
<ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/tv-news-reader-quits-in-protest-at-berlusconi-1981964.html">The Independent</ref>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>