<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Staff; Agencies; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-12-13" description="Italian prime minister whisked away in a car after falling to the ground following attack" fingerprint="7eca862d915edf0f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi punched in the face in Milan" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-punched-in-face">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has been injured at a rally in Milan tonight after a man threw a model of Milan cathedral at him, according to Italian news reports.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister was whisked away in a car after falling to the ground during the attack. State television showed Berlusconi with blood on his lips as he was lifted to his feet by aides.</p>
<p>Police initially said a young man had punched Berlusconi in the face outside the Piazza del Duomo, but later said the man had hurled a small metal object at the premier from close range. A 42-year-old man was arrested at the scene, according to the Ansa news agency.</p>
<p>Berlusconi is to be kept in hospital overnight following the incident, which happened after the premier delivered a speech to his conservative supporters this evening.</p>
<p>Initial X-rays showed a injuries to two teeth but the 73-year-old prime minister and media mogul said "I'm fine, I'm fine" when he was moved to a hospital room in the northern city, Ansa said.</p>
<p>"What they've done to Berlusconi is an act of terrorism," said Umberto Bossi, head of the far-right Northern League and a close Berlusconi ally.</p>
<p>The attack concludes a rather dismal weekend for Berlusconi, whose approval ratings slid four percentage points in November as his legal troubles mounted, according to an opinion poll in an Italian newspaper on Saturday.</p>
<p>Stripped of immunity from prosecution, Berlusconi faces the reopening of a number of trials against him, including one on charges of bribery and corruption and another for tax fraud.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's approval ratings fell to 50.1% at the beginning of December, from 54.4% in early November, according to an Ipsos poll in La Stampa.</p>
<p>The lower ratings meant Berlusconi's government, which enjoys approval ratings of 53.2%, is more popular than the prime minister himself, the newspaper said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>