<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Julian Borger; John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-07-07" description="Italian PM says Guardian's report of pressure over chaotic summit preparations 'a colossal blunder by a small newspaper'" fingerprint="7e10980f678a749e" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,G8,US news,World news,The Guardian,Media,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi hits back at criticism over G8 summit" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/07/berlusconi-g8-summit-preparations">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has attempted to fend off allegations that preparations for the G8 summit have been so chaotic that Italy's membership of the group was being called into question.</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister said a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/06/g8-considers-expelling-italy">report</ref> in the Guardian, citing senior western officials as saying the US had taken the lead in managing the agenda for the summit, was "a colossal blunder by a small newspaper".</p>
<p>Officials from G8 countries, who did not want to be named, told the Guardian that in the absence of Italian initiatives for the summit, Washington had arranged conference calls among the "sherpas" – the diplomats preparing the summit. There was also fierce criticism of Italy's failure to deliver on promises of overseas aid.</p>
<p>The Guardian today issued a statement saying it wholeheartedly rejected any suggestion that the news story was unfounded.</p>
<p>"I hope that the Guardian is expelled from the great newspapers of the world," said the foreign minister, Franco Frattini. "What the Guardian says is a joke – nonsense."</p>
<p>The defence minister, Ignazio La Russa, suggested a boycott of the paper because of the report.</p>
<p>An Italian foreign ministry spokesman said there had been a misunderstanding about the "sherpa" phone calls. He said one had been organised by the US, but it had been aimed at organising a G20 summit in Pittsburgh in September.</p>
<p>The spokesman said a food security initiative, reported in the Guardian to have been led by the US, had in fact been authored by Italy.</p>
<p>Italy circulated a paper on food security last year, but the Guardian understands that the initiative in its current form, aimed at supporting farmers in developing countries, was put together under US leadership. The "sherpa" calls led by the US were principally concerned with tomorrow's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> meeting in L'Aquila, the Guardian's sources confirmed.</p>
<p>There is increasing pressure from the US and rising powers such as China, India and Brazil for the G8 "rich countries club" to be expanded and for European membership to be consolidated.</p>
<p>Bruce Jones, a senior fellow of the Brookings Institution in Washington, said in the next three years European states would come under pressure to decide among themselves who should represent the EU in the G8 or any larger successor group, as well as in the UN security council and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
<p>All three institutions are due to be reformed to make them more representative of the 21st-century balance of power, and that is likely to bring a dilution of European influence, with some countries having to drop out. "There is already frustration with the Europeans that they have not sorted these things out," Jones said.</p>
<p>Britain also came under fire for its organisation of the G20 meeting in London in April, to which the Spaniards, the Dutch, the Thais and the Ethiopians were invited at the last moment. American officials complained that the expanded guest list made the forum more unwieldy and the G20 format less attractive.</p>
<p>Jones added that said the leading role played by the US, even though it was not hosting tomorrow's summit, was a sign of things to come. "The criticism of the Italians is more than warranted, but there is a broader point here. It is inevitable that the US will play a more central role in the management of an expanded G8. If there are going to be many more players at the table, not all of them western democracies, there's ever more need for a strong central core. That can only be provided by the US."</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>