<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lyn Gardner" categories="Stage" date="2010-06-11" description="King's Head, LondonFrom the true story of the Liverpool fan who watched the 2005 Champions League final with Silvio Berlusconi, John Graham Davies has fashioned a lively if occasionally wearing one-man show, writes Lyn Gardner" fingerprint="e90c94ef35620689" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Theatre,Stage,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,Milan,Liverpool" title="Beating Berlusconi! | Theatre review" url="http://www.theguardian.com/stage/2010/jun/11/beating-berlusconi-review">
<main>
<p>Istanbul, 25 May 2005, the Champions League final. Liverpool are playing like muppets, and are down 3-0 to AC Milan by half time. A devoted fan, Kenny, is so disgusted that he wanders away from his seat, gets lost in a maze of corridors and eventually finds himself in the AC Milan directors' box sitting next to the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, and quaffing champagne.</p>
<p>From a 10-minute anecdote of something that really happened to a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/liverpool">Liverpool</ref> fan, John Graham Davies has fashioned a lively one-man show that is an odyssey through 40 years of Liverpool life. Even for non-football fans, it's a punchy piece of good old-fashioned popular theatre that wears its passions and prejudices on its sleeve: Scousers good; Liverpool FC even better; Maggie Thatcher "a Nazi in a dress"; Manchester United "the crimson haemorrhoids". The partisanship does prove rather wearing for those of us without strong tribal loyalties, and inevitably the show packs less of a punch in N1 than it would playing to the crowd in its home city, where it has been a big success.</p>
<p>Though this is about the fever of the football fan, it is also a skimmed social history of Liverpool, through the riots of 1981 and the Thatcher years to the war in Iraq and the tragic events at Heysel and at Hillsborough. Kenny is a flawed everyman, unwittingly sitting on the sidelines of the events of history.</p>
<p>The show would be greatly improved if it lasted 90 minutes rather than going into extra time, and at a preview performance, Paul Duckworth – who plays dozens of roles with relish – hadn't yet pitched his performance to a small space. But although it may not be perfectly formed, it's a show with balls, in more ways than one.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Until 4 July. Box office: 0844 209 0326.</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>