<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2010-05-26" description="Roberto Mancini: Italy's proposed wire-tapping legislation could hide criminal activity and may also protect Berlusconi's political fairytale" fingerprint="699703fc5603b0f5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Surveillance,Civil liberties - international,Law" title="Duality behind Silvio Berlusconi's 'gag' law | Roberto Mancini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/may/26/duality-silvio-berlusconi-gag-law-wire-tapping">
<main>
<p>This week, the editors and journalists of various Italian newspapers, including those from Silvio Berlusconi's own media, published a joint statement sounding a warning over what will happen in Italy if the notorious "gag" <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/may/21/silvio-berlusconi-telephone-bugging-law">law on wire-tapping</ref> is passed by the senate. At the time of writing, a commission is discussing the draft law, so we cannot exclude any dramatic last-minute turn of events.</p>
<p>How did this situation come about? For two reasons, a criminal one and a political one.</p>
<p>The first concerns the ongoing investigation into the so-called "Bertolaso gang", which led to the recent <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/may/16/italy-sleaze-minister-resign">resignation of the industry minister, Claudio Scajola</ref>. The picture emerging from the investigations is so startling that it has shaken Italian public opinion, usually so cynical and indifferent to scandals.</p>
<p>The civil protection department, following an emergency amendment, was put in charge of "important events". These ranged from the world swimming championships to the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2009/jul/08/g8-gordon-brown">G8 summit at L'Aquila</ref> in 2009, and the anniversary of a saint's birthday. This amusing image of firemen and earthquake experts organising swimming competitions and religious pageants conceals a tainted notion: the legal concept of an "emergency" implies being able to ignore all the rules and regulations regarding tendering contracts for public works worth millions of euros. It is said that these were farmed out to a gang of friends chosen at Guido Bertolaso's discretion and subject to no bookkeeping controls. Wire-tapping revealed to the public how many contractors, friends of the civil protection department, on the very night of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/07/italy-earthquake-cultural-damage">earthquake at L'Aquila</ref>, laughingly congratulated each other on the great opportunity to get new contracts.</p>
<p>So a law, which is a gag on wire-tapping and on newspapers, would help conceal evidence that free competition has been replaced by a network of ambiguous connections, in disdain of any law or regulation. This appears to be accepted in Berlusconi's system, where the expression "free trade" is seemingly just a fancy label.</p>
<p>The second thing making this law so necessary to the government is that it will be an obstacle to any free, critical voice giving unwelcome information.</p>
<p>The crisis in Greece has obliged Berlusconi's government to launch corrective measures to public finances to the tune of €24bn. To Berlusconi, this is a tragedy. His image over the years has been based on the repeat performance of an illusion, suffused in a door-to-door salesman's optimism: just smile and keep on buying. To have to admit to the crisis and to talk of sacrifices, after having deluded Italians into believing they were living in the fake country as seen on television, could be a real drama.</p>
<p>We are now expecting a speech to be delivered on all the television channels – a speech where the premier will tell Italians a fairytale on how the sacrifices will be joyful and equally distributed among all the population. The creation of yet another deception will be so difficult this time that he will have to put a muzzle on all sources of information.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>