<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2011-11-09" description="Rome grinds to a halt as prime minister announces decision to step down later this month following vote on budget" fingerprint="7b0c151d70a09765" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news,Eurozone crisis,Business,Financial crisis,Global recession" title="Italy greets Silvio Berlusconi's resignation with relief and concern" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/nov/09/italian-relief-silvio-berlusconi-resignation">
<main>
<p>Romans reacted with relief at Silvio Berlusconi's resignation, mixed with a fear of what is coming next when they heard he will stand down later this month after passing painful economic reforms the EU has demanded.</p>
<p>"I'm happy since he should have stepped down when his scandals broke and his decline began," said Luisa Amato, a media consultant.</p>
<p>"But if this solves a credibility problem we have internationally, it doesn't make our economic problems go away. And the risk is that any reforms we pass will improve some areas but wreck others, as has just happened with the education system. And who's going to reform the wasteful health system, which is a reservoir of votes?"</p>
<p>Stefano Cohen, an estate agent, said <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> needed a technical government appointed by president Giorgio Napolitano to enact the reforms to liberalise the economy. "We don't have time for elections, and which politician would risk campaigning on a platform of labour reform and other painful measures? Today's news gives a possibility but also brings new challenges."</p>
<p>As Berlusconi mustered just 308 votes on a budget bill on Tuesday, eight short of an absolute majority, before announcing his decision to stand down later this month, Rome ground to a halt to hear the news.</p>
<p>"People in shops today were talking about nothing else and were glued to TVs to hear developments," said Carlo Crispolti, a computer technician. "I am so happy I am ready to throw a party, but the left lacks charismatic leaders and I am concerned that Berlusconi's deputy Angelino Alfano will be put in his place.</p>
<p>"We need a technical government that can go after all the tax evaders, mostly in the north who make up Berlusconi's electorate."</p>
<p>Marta Carbone, an Italian economist shopping near parliament on Tuesday, warned that the reforms Berlusconi has hurriedly put together to lift the Italian economy could falter even if the government was bold enough to carry them out.</p>
<p>In the meantime, the economy is stuttering, with about 14% of Italians now living in poverty and a third of young people out of work. Berlusconi irked a large number of Italians last week by saying things were not all bad since restaurants were full, a boast which prompted his interior minister Roberto Maroni, to say: "You cannot hide the truth."</p>
<p>"The real Greek tragedy is here," said Francesco Papa, a local politician from southern Italy. "Except there is no deus ex machina. If we had been better governed we would have been able to do without the euro, just like Britain, but we threw it away and what wealth there is stays hidden."</p>
<p>Not all Italians are complaining about their lot. The appeal made last week to the nation by a Tuscan entrepreneur Giuliano Melani to buy Italian government bonds and save the nation has snowballed.</p>
<p>With TV cameras following, Melani bought €20,000 (£17,000) worth of bonds from his local bank on Monday, and as he rushed to appear on a chat show on Tuesday, an assistant revealed that 1,000 Italians had already contacted Melani to say they had bought up a total of €2m worth of bonds.</p>
<p>"Silvio Berlusconi is not the problem," said Michele Fidati, the manager of a restaurant near parliament. "The problem is the EU and the markets – we don't know who is running Italy anymore.</p>
<p>"I have had enough, let's just pass these reforms," he added. "My message to the politicians in parliament is please, come together and press those voting buttons now."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>