<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Fiona Winward; Rome; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-06-18" description="Italian premier 'could have women in large numbers for free', says representative" fingerprint="e7e84a2c3a8af339" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi's lawyer denies women were paid to attend parties" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/18/berlusconi-pay-women">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's lawyer has denied fresh allegations in the Italian media that women received money to attend parties at the prime minister's residences in Rome and Sardinia, saying Berlusconi did not need to pay for women.</p>
<p>"He does not need people to bring him women," Niccolò Ghedini told the newspaper Corriere della Sera. "It's seems a bit over the top to think that Berlusconi needs to pay €2,000 [£1,700] for a girl to go with him. I think he could have them in large numbers for free."</p>
<p>Public prosecutors in the southern city of Bari said they were investigating whether payments allegedly made to at least four women by a local entrepreneur, Giampaolo Tarantini, to attend parties "in exclusive locations in Rome and Sardinia" constituted an "induction into prostitution".</p>
<p>The case arose from wiretapped conversations from a separate business corruption probe in which Tarantini allegedly negotiated payments and travel arrangements with the women. Corriere della Sera published an interview on Wednesday with one of the women, 42-year-old former television showgirl Patrizia D'Addario, who claimed she had been asked to attend a party at Berlusconi's Rome residence, Palazzo Grazioli, in October last year.</p>
<p>"I said they would have to pay me and we agreed on €2,000," she said.</p>
<p>Denying the allegations in a terse statement, Berlusconi said: "Once again the newspapers are filled with rubbish and falsehoods. I will certainly not allow this aggression to affect me and I will continue to work as always for the good of the country."</p>
<p>Ghedini told Corriere della Sera that even if the allegations were true Berlusconi would be an "unwitting party" who "could not have known" that the women had been paid to attend the parties. Asked what would happen if the women had stayed after the party, Ghedini said: "If one of these people were to have relations with [the premier], he would continue not to know [that she had been paid] and so there would be no legal or moral consequences."</p>
<p>Ghedini was criticised by female opposition MPs for saying the premier would have been the blameless "end user" of the women.</p>
<p>In the interview with Corriere, D'Addario said she had been flown from Bari and put up in a luxury hotel before the party at Palazzo Grazioli, where she and around 20 other women drank champagne until Berlusconi arrived. "He showed us videos of his meeting with [George W] Bush and photos of his [Sardinian] villa. He sang and told jokes," she said, adding she "realised she had made an impression" on the premier.</p>
<p>However, D'Addario said she returned to her hotel for the night and was paid only €1,000 "because I didn't stay". She claimed she was invited back with two other women several weeks later on the night of the US presidential election, on which occasion she said the premier asked her to stay.</p>
<p>D'Addario said on both evenings she had made secret audio recordings in which Berlusconi's voice could be heard. These are being examined by magistrates. The scandal-stricken premier is in the middle of a public divorce battle with his wife, Veronica Lario, who <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/03/berlusconi-wife-divorce">said she could not stay with a man who "frequents minors" </ref>after he attended the 18th birthday party of schoolgirl and aspiring model Noemi Letizia in Naples in April.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>