<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-08-05" description="After rescue of 370 people by Italian coastguards, Rome asks Nato to investigate if Libyans were left in peril at sea" fingerprint="40ca0b311681afdb" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Refugees,Nato,Libya,Arab and Middle East unrest,Middle East and north Africa,Africa,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,World news" title="Italy demands to know if Libya blockade warship ignored refugees" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/aug/05/nato-ship-ignored-libyan-refugees-claim">
<main>
<p>Italy has demanded that Nato inquire into a report that an alliance warship blockading Libya repeatedly ignored pleas to help several hundred distressed and dying asylum seekers who were stranded at sea after fleeing the wartorn country.</p>
<p>It is the first time Rome has taken such an initiative since the start of the fighting in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/libya">Libya</ref> when people began fleeing across the Mediterranean in often unseaworthy vessels.</p>
<p>Most of the more than 24,000 refugees have arrived on the Italian island of Lampedusa, angering and embarrassing Silvio Berlusconi's rightwing government, which won power vowing to block illegal immigration.</p>
<p>Italy's foreign minister, Franco Frattini, has asked his country's permanent representative to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nato">Nato</ref> to open a debate on whether to amend the alliance's mandate so that it covers "those who for reasons of war are forced to flee on boats, putting their personal safety at risk".</p>
<p>In May, Nato denied an earlier <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/08/nato-ship-libyan-migrants">report by the Guardian that its warships had left dozens of Africans to die aboard another vessel</ref> drifting off the Libyan coast.</p>
<p>Rome's move follows the rescue by Italian coastguards of 370 people in conditions of extreme distress on an overcrowded boat inside Libya's search and rescue area on Thursday.</p>
<p>One body was found aboard the vessel and a survivor said dozens of other corpses had been thrown overboard.</p>
<p>About 50 people were taken to hospital on Lampedusa suffering from shock, exhaustion and severe dehydration. Two were reportedly in a critical condition.</p>
<p>A Nato spokesman in Brussels told the Guardian that it was not clear whether the boat from which they were rescued was the one allegedly refused assistance. "There were a couple of incidents, and we are trying to sort out which incident this refers to," he said. "We are waiting for confirmation from our military colleagues in Naples."</p>
<p>At allied maritime command in Naples, a spokesman said: "Nato always responds and intervenes in cases of emergency, in compliance with international law.</p>
<p>"The commanders of the ships in service with the alliance are well aware of these laws and respect the <ref target="http://www.imo.org/about/conventions/listofconventions/pages/international-convention-for-the-safety-of-life-at-sea-%28solas%29,-1974.aspx">Solas</ref> [International Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea] rules."</p>
<p>According to one survivor, the migrants rescued on Thursday had set off from the Libyan coast the previous Friday.</p>
<p>After their boat's engine failed, they were seen by a Cypriot tugboat which tried to help.</p>
<p>But some of the migrants flung themselves overboard in an attempt to reach the tug and the boat's captain – apparently fearing that the movement of people aboard the vessel might overturn it – pulled away and alerted the Italian authorities.</p>
<p>The Italian news agency, Ansa, citing informed sources, said search and rescue officials relayed the SOS to a Nato vessel 30 miles from the imperilled boat. But, said the report, they did not get "positive responses".</p>
<p>It was not until Thursday morning that four coastguard patrol boats and a helicopter were dispatched from Lampedusa, 100 miles to the north.</p>
<p>Federico Bricolo, chief whip in the Italian senate representing the Northern League, the junior partner in Berlusconi's coalition, said: "Nato must understand it is not there just to shell Libyan cities." He said it should "block vessels departing those coasts and send them back".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>