<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Media" date="2005-04-14" description="Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi yesterday moved to blunt criticism of his dual roles as premier and media mogul. By John Hooper." fingerprint="3ee8d16cb2f7c6cd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Business,Italy,Television industry,Media business,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi cuts networks stake to end conflict of interest calls" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2005/apr/14/business.italy">
<main>
<p>Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> yesterday moved to blunt criticism of his dual roles as premier and media mogul.</p>
<p>Fininvest, the company at the apex of his business empire, announced it was reducing its holding in the Mediaset TV network to just over 34%.</p>
<p>JP Morgan had been put in charge of the sell-off of the 197m shares, which took the form of an institutional placing.</p>
<p>The news sent Mediaset's price tumbling by more than 4% to touch €10.54 before recovering to close at €10.58 (£7.21). Traders said the shares were initially placed at between €10.70 and €10.90.</p>
<p>Fininvest's move follows a setback for Mr Berlusconi's conservative coalition this month in regional elections. It will enable him to say at the next general election, due by spring 2006, that he no longer controls Mediaset and its three television channels. As prime minister, he can also influence three more channels operated by the public broadcaster, RAI.</p>
<p>Together, RAI and Mediaset share more than 90% of Italy's TV market.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's grip on all but one of the country's seven main channels has been a target of criticism in Italy and internationally since he returned to office in 2001.</p>
<p>The pressure on him to do something about his conflicts of interest grew after the regional elections showed he faced an uphill struggle to hang on to power. The prime minister's right-wing coalition lost in all but two of 13 regions.</p>
<p>In a conference call to investors, Francesco Cardinali of JP Morgan made no bones about the political dimension of the operation. "The timing of the placing basically flows from the political context [and] the outcome of the recent regional elections," he said.</p>
<p>Fininvest's deputy chairwoman, Marina Berlusconi, the prime minister's daughter, said the sale "represents an opportunity both for Fininvest and Mediaset" - not to mention the Berlusconi family.</p>
<p>Mediaset's shares have been edging up steadily from a low of €8.22 last August and are not far off their all-time high of €11.26.</p>
<p>There has frequently been speculation that most of the Berlusconi family would be content with a price of over €10, though some members, notably the prime minister's son, Piersilvio, the deputy chairman of Mediaset, were reported to be against any sale.</p>
<p>Fininvest previously held just under 51% of Mediaset. Yesterday's operation laid to rest months of rumour that it was planning to sell part or all of its holding in the TV firm to Rupert Murdoch.</p>
<p>But it is unlikely to quell criticism of Mr Berlusconi's overlapping interests. Fininvest will still be by far the biggest investor in Mediaset and financial commentators agreed that its retained stake gave the prime minister continued, effective control of the TV empire he created.</p>
<p>His prospective challenger at the general election, Romano Prodi, said: "Berlusconi is still the owner and the conflict of interests remains." Even Maurizio Gasparri, the minister responsible for the media in Mr Berlusconi's cabinet, went no further than to say that Mediaset has become "theoretically" vulnerable to takeover.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>