<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2005-04-15" description="Silvio Berlusconi and his followers were dealt a blow yesterday when one of his main coalition partners pulled out of the government, bringing it a step closer to collapse." fingerprint="7e0cdb1d952757b4" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Junior party quits Italy's coalition" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/apr/16/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi and his followers were dealt a blow yesterday when one of his main coalition partners pulled out of the government, bringing it a step closer to collapse.</p>
<p>Leaders of the Union of Christian Democrats (UDC), the third party in the government, agreed that its ministers should resign because of Mr Berlusconi's reluctance to change course after disastrous regional election results. The party will continue to support Mr Berlusconi in parliament, but the credibility of Italy's longest postwar government has been compromised.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi gave little away yesterday, saying only: "If the country's interests must prevail, I will make the most appropriate decisions."</p>
<p>In an atmosphere of political drama the president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, returned to Rome from Bulgaria.</p>
<p>His role will be crucial if Mr Berlusconi resigns.</p>
<p>Marco Follini, the UDC's leader, and one of two deputy prime ministers, said he would quit after failing to convince Mr Berlusconi that the regional results called for more than cosmetic changes.</p>
<p>Mr Follini's case for a radical change is backed by the second party in government, the formerly neo-fascist National Alliance.</p>
<p>But some observers suspect that the UDC, which represents the conservative wing of the Christian Democrat movement, is playing a much longer game. They believe Mr Follini is convinced that Mr Berlusconi's government is doomed and wants to put as much distance as possible between himself and the prime minister.</p>
<p>The right lost in all but two of the 13 regions where voting was held on April 3 and 4. Analysts said discontent with the handling of the economy was the main cause.</p>
<p>Voters in the south, from where the UDC draws most of its support, were concerned about a constitutional reform which would divert more resources to the richer north.</p>
<p>The National Alliance, led by Gianfranco Fini, also depends on the votes of the generally poorer south.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>