<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2011-03-06" description="State TV lawyers say comments by late mother could prompt 'requests for damages for offending memory of the dead'" fingerprint="3712d82d93b7b700" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Censorship,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi film trailer prompts gagging row" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/mar/06/silvio-berlusconi-film-trailer-gagging-row">
<main>
<p>Italy's state TV network is facing accusations of censorship after it banned a trailer for a documentary critical of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, claiming it pokes fun at the prime minister's late mother.</p>
<p>In a filmed interview used in the trailer, which was due to be shown on Sunday, Rosa Berlusconi asserts: "You will never see a photo of Silvio going around with women."</p>
<p>Since his mother's death in 2008, Berlusconi has been plagued by allegations of sleeping with prostitutes and hosting naked soirees, culminating in accusations he paid to have sex with a 17-year-old belly dancer, Karima el-Mahroug.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's lawyer Niccolo Ghedini has said that the prime minister is prepared to give up one day a week – Monday – to attend his trial for underage prostitution, which starts next month, as well as three other trials for fraud and bribery.</p>
<p>State TV network RAI, over which Berlusconi exercises indirect control, said that the trailer for Silvio Forever "includes the statement of a deceased person, twisting the images and the words to satirical ends." That ran the risk, added RAI's legal department, "of requests for damages for offending the memory of the deceased".</p>
<p>Rosa Berlusconi, who once said "I adore my son. I know he is honest, good and brave," has been lauded for her good sense by Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Massimo Donadi, an MP with the opposition <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> of Values party, described the ban on the trailer as "the latest illiberal decision of a servile management" at RAI.</p>
<p>Vittorio Feltri, the former editor of a newspaper owned by the Berlusconi family, condemned the cut. "Someone is really stupid at RAI. Even films against Berlusconi can have ads."</p>
<p>In 2009 <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2009/sep/03/silvio-berlusconi-videocracy-documentary">RAI banned trailers for Videocracy</ref>, a documentary film about Berlusconi's use of female nudity at the private TV stations he controls. The film, argued RAI, was "a political message" and not a real documentary.</p>
<p>RAI is reportedly planning to follow its flagship evening news programme with an editorial by Giuliano Ferrara, a pro-Berlusconi journalist who recently organised a rally attacking magistrates who have been probing Berlusconi's "bunga bunga" parties.</p>
<p>Berlusconi said on Saturday he would launch sweeping legislation this week aimed at limiting the powers of Italy's magistrates and cutting down on their use of wiretaps.</p>
<p>Meanwhile new transcripts of wiretaps of Berlusconi's party guests were published, including one in which Elisa Toti, a model, tells her mother she had been paid 6,000 euros to spend a week with Berlusconi. "You cannot imagine what condition I am in," she reportedly said. "I will need a month, and the money, to recover after that week."</p>
<p>Iris Berardi, a model, was reportedly recorded saying that rivalry between women at Berlusconi's parties last year was so fierce "they could massacre each other".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>