<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-14" description="John Hooper: The ballot will decide whether Silvio Berlusconi governs Italy for a further five years - by which time his influence would be huge" fingerprint="fa01c22f9300e638" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="What is at stake in Italy today" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/14/whatitisatstakeinitalyt">
<main>
<p>A second Italian general election in two years is bound to generate a degree of weariness in politicians, voters and the rest of us. But <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/14/italy">today's ballot</ref> is important - hugely important - for Italy and perhaps too for the rest of Europe.</p>
<p>It will decide whether <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/12/italy">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> governs Italy for a further five years.</p>
<p>He is already the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy.italy">dominant figure</ref> of contemporary Italian politics. He has run Italy for a total of six of the last 14 years. By the time the next legislature has run its course those figures could be 11 years out 19.</p>
<p>His power to subtly shape the opinions of his compatriots is probably greater than that of any politician in the democratic world. He owns three of Italy's four privately owned television stations and from 1994 to 1995 and again between 2001 and 2006 he was indirectly, but ultimately, responsible for the state-owned broadcaster, the RAI. During his last mandate, craven behaviour towards Berlusconi, his allies and their beliefs was sometimes more evident on the RAI than it was in his own group, Mediaset. It was RAI, not Mediaset, that withheld from viewers the reaction in the European parliament to Italy's prime minister comparing a German MEP to a concentration camp guard.</p>
<p>The discussion that made the deepest impression on me during <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/08/italy">this election campaign</ref> was not with a pundit or statesman, but with someone who came to interview me. I would guess she was somewhere between 25 and 30. She worked for a news organisation that is clearly leftwing. She was dressed casually, like a typical, generally progressive Italian.</p>
<p>But, if my guess at her age was correct, the entire period since she had begun to read papers and watch TV and radio news programmes had been spent in the shadow of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. And it was striking just how deeply she had been influenced by his outlook on life.</p>
<p>For 14 long years, Silvio Berlusconi and his friends have been repeating like a mantra the notion that he is a victim of a politically motivated campaign by leftwing prosecutors and magistrates. This she accepted unquestioningly.</p>
<p>She seemed to acknowledge that Berlusconi and co were not exactly angels. But they were one side in a two-sided confrontation.</p>
<p>For her, the judiciary was not an assortment of men and women - some leftwing, some rightwing - whose primary role was to bring suspected offenders to justice. They were a cohesive, extra-parliamentary party, or movement. Rather like, say, the army in some emerging nations, or former KGB in Russia. They were actors, players and their actions, like opening and closing investigations, were timed to inflict damage on the other side, represented by Berlusconi and the rest of the right.</p>
<p>This is part of what Italians are talking about when they say their billionaire former prime minister has undermined legality. They mean that he has done so at a level that is usually not visible. And by 2011, it could seem here to be entirely normal.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>