<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2008-06-22" description="Italian prime minister demands communion despite being banned because he is divorced and remarried" fingerprint="2ca58a2ddd42cdfc" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Catholicism,Italy,Religion,World news,Christianity,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi tells Vatican to lift ban on taking communion" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/23/catholicism.italy">
<main>
<p>After a week pushing for a change in the law to halt his corruption trial, Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, set his sights even higher at the weekend by demanding the Catholic church kill off a rule which stops him taking communion because he is divorced and remarried.</p>
<p>Evidently on a roll and wearing a white panama hat, a relaxed-looking Berlusconi sat in the front row at a service in a church near his Sardinian villa on Saturday as the bishop approached the congregation to offer communion.</p>
<p>"When are you going to change this rule that stops me taking communion?" Berlusconi asked the startled bishop, who had been planning to move swiftly past the prime minister without stopping to pop a wafer in his mouth.</p>
<p>The Catholic church considers a religious marriage unbreakable, as stated in the Bible, meaning Catholics getting a civil divorce cannot then remarry in church, unless an annulment is granted by the church.</p>
<p>Anyone opting instead for a civil wedding second time round can be denied communion, including Berlusconi, who has three children from his second marriage to the actor Veronica Lario.</p>
<p>Until now, the Italian prime minister and media mogul has remained an unwavering supporter of the Vatican's policy of promoting family values and attacking single-sex unions. Berlusconi showed up at last year's church-run Family Day demonstration in Rome, prompting critics to joke that he was well qualified to do so since he had so many families of his own.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, after kissing Pope Benedict on the hand at a meeting at the Vatican, Berlusconi said: "We are on the church's side." He added: "The outlook of my government cannot but please the Pope and the church."</p>
<p>By Saturday, after a week spent seeking to suspend his trial for allegedly bribing the British lawyer David Mills while preparing a blanket law which would give himself immunity from all prosecution, Berlusconi perhaps thought it was time to try his luck with the church.</p>
<p>The embarrassed bishop, Sebastiano Sanguinetti, hinted he could have worked something out in private with Berlusconi, but he was not about to provoke a scandal by giving him communion in front of watching journalists.</p>
<p>"I told him he could take the matter to a higher level, given that he has just been received by the Pope at the Vatican," Sanguinetti told the Italian daily La Stampa.</p>
<p>But in a speech made via satellite to a Canadian church congress on the eucharist yesterday, Benedict appeared to hold firm. "We must do all in our power to receive (communion) with a pure heart," he said, adding, in an apparent reference to remarried Catholics.</p>
<p>"Those who cannot have communion due to their situation will nonetheless find strength in their desire for it and by going to mass," the Pope said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>