<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Ben Child" categories="Film" date="2011-12-27" description="Gérard Depardieu and Isabelle Adjani in talks for movie that may also draw from lives of Bill Clinton and Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="e29004476e54fa34" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Film,France,Dominique Strauss-Kahn,Bill Clinton,Silvio Berlusconi,Gérard Depardieu" title="Dominique Strauss-Kahn sex scandal inspires Abel Ferrara film" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2011/dec/27/dominique-strauss-kahn-sex-scandal-film">
<main>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/filmblog/2009/apr/03/abel-ferrara">Abel Ferrara</ref>, the iconoclastic director of <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4qI60RZ0Gr4&amp;feature=fvst">Bad Lieutenant</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/movie/79262/king-of-new-york">The King of New York</ref>, is working on a film about political sex scandals partly inspired by the one that engulfed <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/dominique-strauss-kahn">Dominique Strauss-Kahn</ref>, the former International Monetary Fund chief and one-time French presidential hopeful.</p>
<p>According to website <ref target="http://www.deadline.com/2011/12/abel-ferrara-working-on-dsk-inspired-project-depardieu-adjani-to-star/">Deadline</ref>, Ferrara, who was worked intermittently in recent years but maintains a powerful reputation as a film-maker with a unique vision, is in talks with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/aug/20/gerard-depardieu-agnes-poirier">Gérard Depardieu</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2011/may/19/isabelle-adjani">Isabelle Adjani</ref> to star in the project, which is still in the early stages of development. The screenplay, by Ferrera and Christ Zois, may also include elements from the lives of other politicians, such as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/clinton">Bill Clinton</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who found themselves embroiled in sex scandals.</p>
<p>"One thing we do know is that there's a common desire amongst Depardieu, Adjani and Ferrara to work together," says producer Vincent Maraval of Wild Bunch films. "But like every day in this business, we have to see if there's a film there. Today, the only reality is that they are writing something inspired by Strauss-Kahn that will focus on addiction and politicians. It's more that the Strauss-Kahn scandal itself."</p>
<p>Interviewed on the subject by French paper Le Journal Du Dimanche, Depardieu refused to be drawn, saying only: "In general, I'm very good at playing characters that I don't like or don't resemble."</p>
<p>Ferrara's newest film is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/feedarticle/9834924">4:44 Last Day On Earth</ref>, which chronicles the events of the final 24 hours before a global apocalypse and stars <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/video/2010/may/10/willem-dafoe-birds-eye-ad">Willem Dafoe</ref>. It played in competition at the 68th Venice International Film Festival in September.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>