<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-07-06" description="What happened when Saint Bob gave Silvio Berlusconi a grilling over his failed aid promises" fingerprint="3836d2aca506e6dd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,G8,Global development,Society,Bob Geldof,Europe" title="You know when you've been Geldof-ed" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/07/bob-geldof-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, is not a man accustomed to tough interviews. So it must have been a shock to submit to a grilling from Sir Bob Geldof over his failed aid promises, published at the weekend in an edition of La Stampa guest-edited by the veteran Africa campaigner. One observer likened their meeting to "a boxing match", and said that both parties came close to storming out. Forget Paxman: as these extracts reveal, there are few inquisitors more terrifying that Saint Bob in time-honoured "give us your fecking money" mode.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Geldof</hi> (waving a copy of the aid commitment Berlusconi had signed at the Gleneagles <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit in 2005, then patently ignored)<lb/> Here is the signature of a country and the honour of a man.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Berlusconi:</hi> I am sorry, we made a mistake.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Geldof: </hi>If Africans [had the money to] buy products, there would be more jobs created in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Berlusconi:</hi> You're right, when you make a promise you need to keep it. We are late and we must catch up. I am sorry not to have kept promises, we have had to deal with all the things that have happened. The crisis, the earthquake. We also have a battle with the opposition and judges who attack us.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Geldof:</hi> But this, prime minister, is not a discussion about the media or the judicial system. We are talking about poor people who cannot defend themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Berlusconi:</hi> We will try not to let you down.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Geldof </hi>(pointing out that Italy has delivered on just 3% of its Gleneagles commitments): It is a question of credibility. Political credibility. You risk becoming "Mr Three Per Cent", the man who keeps just 3% of his promises. (Cue Berlusconi looking even more shamefaced than he has in recent weeks.)</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>