<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Paul Ginsborg; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Books" date="2006-03-05" description="Tessa Jowell's links to Silvio Berlusconi may be enthralling Britain, but the Italian peacock premier has greater things on his mind. Can his heady mix of money, charisma and bluster win him another term? It helps when you own half the country's media ... By Paul Ginsborg." fingerprint="3e904a2db203f70d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Books,Culture,Politics books,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Statesman, salesman, superstar" url="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2006/mar/05/politics">
<main>
<p>The best quip of the Italian election campaign so far has come from the exotically named Vladimir Luxuria, a transsexual candidate for one of the far-left parties. 'Why do you hate <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>?' a television interviewer asked. 'I don't hate him at all,' Vladimir replied. 'On the contrary, we're rather alike. Both of us wear make-up and put on high heels for public occasions.'</p>
<p>Berlusconi is a little man with a large appetite - a dangerous species, to judge by the recent Italian and European past, not to mention the current travails of Tessa Jowell and David Mills. But if he is dangerous, he is so in quite a different way from the dictators of the past. At the beginning of the election campaign he compared himself to Napoleon, inviting much ribald comment. In fact, the contrast with Napoleon is illuminating. Where the one man was all steel, campaigns and conquests, the other is all appearance and promises, smiles and gifts. One talked the hard language of war, the other the exquisitely modern language of images and invention.</p>
<p>It is no good underestimating Berlusconi; left-wing politicians in Italy have been doing that for years. Nor can we dismiss him as a bad Italian joke, as the British do. He has a political project, and it is of considerable interest to the rest of the world. His aim is to establish personal and clan control over the state, but to do so without abandoning the formal rules of modern democracy. His weapons are not those of Mussolini - beatings and purgative castor-oil poured down the throats of unfortunate opponents. They are, instead, vast economic resources, control of the media and direct involvement in politics.</p>
<p>In the Berlusconi model, a prominent business figure with considerable holdings in the media moves from a position where he is flanking the professional politicians into one where he is at the centre of the political stage. He has an adamantine belief in his own abilities to run his country as he runs his business; a fierce patriotism; conservative social values; and a willingness to use his personal fortune to consolidate his political position. As part of the project he brings the independent judiciary to heel and destroys many of the checks and balances that mark the delicate divisions of democratic power. He gains an overriding control of television news, and through his media lieutenants he heavily conditions the overall daily TV diet of publicity, sport, soap opera, variety and chat shows.</p>
<p>His family and friends aid him in this enterprise. His daughter, Marisa, takes control of the country's largest publishing house. His clan is amply rewarded with ministerial posts. The leader himself behaves with great magnificence, passing from one palatial abode to another. He bestows gifts upon all-comers. He can be represented as a modern signore, the despot of a Renaissance city state, though in Berlusconi's case there is scant evidence of enlightened artistic patronage. His is a bald attempt to reassert forms of private control over the state, a modern version of an ancient patrimonialism.</p>
<p>However, this is not Fascism. It is something else, still to find its name in political science. A new Fascist regime would receive short shrift in Italy today. The whole point of the sort of regime Berlusconi has tried to install is that it is based on formal political liberties, on continuing freedoms in everyday life, on spaces left open for opposition in the media system, even on satire aimed at the leader on his own television channels. Berlusconi takes such mild mockings in good spirit, flashing his famous smile at his detractors, and marking in this way his distance from the grimacing Mussolini. His is a great conjuring trick in which everything appears to be quite normal, but nothing is.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's story is briefly told. Born in Milan in 1936, he is the son of a housewife and a bank clerk. After the war, his parents sent him away to be schooled at a strict boarding college run by Salesian priests. Theirs was an ambitious and unusual choice for an Italian family. Silvio was an excellent student, and of the many anecdotes about him at college one of the most repeated is of him selling his homework to companions for sweets or money, rather as the young Rupert Murdoch, in the very different setting of an Australian sheep farm, sold water rats for their skins, sixpence each.</p>
<p>After he graduated from the State University of Milan, Berlusconi set about making a fortune in the building trade. He was outstandingly successful, although doubts have always lingered over the provenance of his early capital. His real break, though, came with the launching of commercial television in Italy in the early 1980s. Thanks to his close friendship with the Socialist leader Bettino Craxi, who was prime minister at the time, and who was later to flee Italy for Tunisia to avoid facing charges of corruption and receiving, Berlusconi was able to take control of the three major commercial channels. For over 20 years he shaped Italian television in his own image - massive inputs of advertising, American films and serials, and endless variety shows. He became a television magnate of great experience and expertise. He also became president of the outstandingly successful AC Milan football club.</p>
<p>Between 1992 and 1994 much of Italy's political class was discredited during the 'clean hands' judicial inquiry into the illegal financing of political parties. Feeling himself to be threatened, Berlusconi decided to launch himself in politics. He founded his own party, Forza Italia!' ('go for it, Italy!'), turned his managers into candidates, and won a spectacular victory in the 1994 national elections. His coalition collapsed in less than a year, but in 2001 he bounced back, winning a clear majority in both houses of parliament. He has governed ever since, adding indirect control of the three public television channels to ownership of his own channels. Elections are scheduled for 9 April, and though Berlusconi trails in the polls, the margins are tight and the outcome uncertain.</p>
<p>Late one evening last week Berlusconi again featured on one of his own television channels, Rete Quattro, which is particularly assiduous at propagating his image. The head of news, Emilio Fede, has asked to be buried in the mausoleum which Berlusconi has constructed for his relatives and friends in the grounds of his beautiful villa at Arcore. Fede offered us a re-run of the day's main event -at least for him: Berlusconi launching his election campaign in Milan. The huge sports centre was full of well-dressed people, many of them young, waving Forza Italia banners. Silvio himself was alone on the stage. He was wearing an immaculate double-breasted suit, his face (successfully lifted in January 2004) was rosy and pink, and his hair (successfully implanted in the summer of the same year) had reclaimed much of the top of his head. He talked for a long time that evening. He is not a particularly good speaker. He lacks Blair's flights of rhetoric, Chirac's sense of solemnity, or Zapatero's sober radicalism. But Berlusconi is unbeatable when it comes to salesmanship. His years in office have not been successful. The economy has stagnated, prices have risen rapidly, and families have difficulties making ends meet. On the world stage he has often behaved like a buffoon, or worse. In July 2003, making his opening speech to the European parliament as President of the Council of Europe, he responded to criticism from the German social democrat Martin Schulz by saying that he would recommend him for the role of camp guard in a film about Nazi concentration camps. The uproar in the international press, including its liberal and conservative sections, was immense. Berlusconi apologised, but then denied that he had ever done so.</p>
<p>No matter. Back in Milan in February 2006, all that has been forgotten. The story that Berlusconi has to tell us about foreign policy is of his personal friendship (for it is that that counts) with Putin and Bush. Italy has not got enough methane gas? 'I phoned my friend Vladimir, and thanks to my intervention, he has ensured Italy an extra quota of power supply.' Pensioners are in increasing difficulty? 'I have given them greater increases than has any other Italian government, and now, with the special over-seventies card which we will introduce, old people will be offered a range of free services such as they have never enjoyed before.'</p>
<p>Every situation is resolved with a new, special offer, and a personal intervention by the prime minister or his minister-friends. The language of the supermarket has met that of the clan.</p>
<p>The world is categorically divided into the good and bad. On the one side are hard-working, religious (or semi-religious), independent, family-loving, consumer-oriented Italians. On the other are the baddies - the communists and ex-communists, and the all too inoffensive Romano Prodi. A special place is reserved for the judiciary. The 'red togas', as he calls them, are responsible for a decade-long persecution of him, his family and his friends. No matter if the judges, especially senior judges, have on more than one occasion found in his favour - sometimes very controversially. It is not enough. All members of his clan have to be cleared.</p>
<p>At the moment this is not the case, in spite of a number of person-specific laws that have been pushed through parliament. Two of his closest friends, the lawyer Cesare Previti and Marcello Dell'Utri, both destined for the mausoleum at Arcore, have been condemned by lower courts. Previti has been found guilty of corrupting the Roman judge Renato Squillante. As for Dell'Utri, he has been condemned by a Palermo court to nine years imprisonment for nothing less than aiding and abetting the Mafia (his appeal has still to be heard). All this is intolerable for Berlusconi. As he said at a mass meeting on 24 January 2004, celebrating his first 10 years in politics: 'Better Fascism than the bureaucratic tyranny of the judiciary.'</p>
<p>Berlusconi's particular brand of political salesmanship and personal charisma have taken root in Italy. And the question is this: 'Do they believe him? And if so, why?' It is not enough to dismiss those who believe in him as misguided, or worse. Nor is it appropriate to buy into the national stereotyping which one hears so much of in northern Europe: 'What do you expect of the Italians? A lovely people, but not much idea of democracy. First they had Mussolini and now they've got Berlusconi'. Such a statement does no justice at all to nearly half of the Italian population which voted against him in 2001, a huge minority which may just make it to a majority this time round.</p>
<p>But the question remains. Those who were listening and applauding in Milan probably accepted that Berlusconi's embellishments and boasts were just that. But it didn't matter. Their belief in their leader was undented, in spite of his dismal record in government. He expresses values they readily identify with. Berlusconi stands for a crucial part of Italian society: the self-employed. Small, family firms have always been very important in Italy, and the things that Berlusconi promises hit vibrant chords with them: less tax, fewer tax controls, no interfering magistrates pushing their noses into people's (private?) businesses, love of the United States and hatred of Communism. Freedom for them, as for Berlusconi, is 'negative' - freedom from interference or impediment.</p>
<p>Of course this is not the whole story. Berlusconi is not alone on the centre-right. He is the head of a coalition which includes Gianfranco Fini's post-Fascists, the racist Northern League of Umberto Bossi, and the more moderate Catholics of Pierferdinando Casini. But it is Silvio Berlusconi who dominates this coalition. With the election campaign in full swing, his is the face we all see - staring out at us from huge hoardings when we stop to have a coffee at a motorway auto-grill, when we turn on the news and he is making a speech to the American Senate, or when we catch a train and find him smiling down on us from the pillars of a publicity temple erected in the atrium of the station.</p>
<p>On a global scale, Berlusconi is also not alone. There are many other figures in Latin American, Mediterranean and North American politics who resemble him in one or more ways - none more so than the present leader of Thailand, Thaksin Shinawatra. Behind Berlusconi there lurks a central and increasingly dramatic problem for democracy: the relationship between media and politics. Modern democracies have been very slow to see the dangers inherent in this relationship, and their collective myopia is reflected in limited and often reluctant regulatory procedures. Indeed, de-regulation has been the order of the day, often replacing a system of safeguards that had been introduced at an earlier date.</p>
<p>We now face a striking paradox - of much less control being exercised by the state at precisely a time when the media system has become much more powerful and all-intrusive. The result is to facilitate the connection of business interests, especially media interests, with the political sphere, and to increase the spaces for manipulation. Nobody knows this better than Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Paul Ginsborg is author of Silvio Berlusconi, Television, Power and Patrimony (Verso). He has also written two major studies for Penguin: A History of Contemporary Italy and Italy and its Discontents. He is Professor of Contemporary European History in the Faculty of Letters, University of Florence</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>