<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-08-02" description="At 76, former prime minister will be spared jail and has already dismissed performing a year's community service" fingerprint="bee0707d1520f763" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi faces house arrest, possibly in bunga-bunga villa" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/02/silvio-berlusconi-house-arrest-bunga-bunga">
<main>
<p>His political opponents have complained for years that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> will never go to jail – now, even after his first definitive conviction, they are unlikely to be proved wrong.</p>
<p>As the 76-year-old is comfortably past the age at which the Italian prison system starts turning people away, he instead faces a choice between spending a year under house arrest or doing community service.</p>
<p>The latter – a path already trodden by a couple of acquaintances, including Lele Mora, the ex-talent scout appealing against a conviction in a separate case of procuring prostitutes for Berlusconi's bunga-bunga parties – has already been dismissed by the billionaire. He was not, he was quoted as saying last weekend, prepared to be treated "like a criminal who has to be re-educated".</p>
<p>And so, for the man whose wealth is estimated by Forbes at $6.2bn, comes the displeasing prospect of having to spend 12 months under arrest in just one of his many houses.</p>
<p>Potential choices include the infamous Villa San Martino at Arcore near Milan, where he held "elegant dinner parties" with a variety of young women, and the Palazzo Grazioli, the imposing building in the centre of Rome where he awaited Thursday's verdict and which would keep him close to the political action.</p>
<p>There's also, of course, the Sardinian estate where, bandana-clad, he welcomed Tony and Cherie Blair back in the summer of 2004.</p>
<p>It was reported on Friday that judges could decide that a more practical solution would be to restrict the former prime minister to a "designated place" such as Milan or the region of Lombardy rather than a specific address. He may, however, have to surrender his passport to the police.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>