<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-05-10" description="Berlusconi denies claims Italy violated international law when navy returned more than 200 'boat people' to Libya" fingerprint="6fbc503f90830f13" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Libya,Italy,World news,Europe,Africa" title="Silvio Berlusconi defends his government's decision to return migrants to Libya" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/10/silvio-berlusconi-italy-immigrants-libya">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has defended his government's decision to return migrants found off its shores to Libya by declaring that his party rejected the idea of a "multi-ethnic" Italy.</p>
<p>His remark prompted an outcry from opposition politicians, already indignant at his refusal to condemn an ally in Milan who last week proposed that seats and carriages on local public transport be <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/08/italy-segregated-public-transport-proposal">reserved for native Italians</ref>.</p>
<p>Immigrants account for an estimated 7% of the population in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. Piero Fassino, a leading opposition politician, said: "Without immigrants, Italy's productive system would have serious gaps."</p>
<p>Berlusconi made his comment after denying claims that Italy violated international law last week when its navy returned to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/libya">Libya</ref> more than 200 "boat people" trying to enter Italian waters.</p>
<p>The UN's refugee agency said the action deprived refugees of the opportunity to plead for asylum.</p>
<p>Berlusconi claimed the left had "opened the doors" to clandestine migrants. "So the left's idea was, and is, that of a multi-ethnic Italy," he said. "Our idea is not like that."</p>
<p>Giovanna Melandri, of the Democratic party, said it wanted a "country in which colour of skin, race and religion do not count". Leoluca Orlando, of the smaller Italy of Values party, said there was a danger of Berlusconi's government returning Italy "to the days of Nazi fascism".</p>
<p>The row erupted as a poll showed that Berlusconi's popularity had not been hurt by his wife's decision to divorce him.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>