<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2005-09-28" description="As Silvio Berlusconi celebrates his 69th birthday, his leadership of Italy's right is being challenged, writes John Hooper." fingerprint="1eb4c36feee2eb85" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Unhappy returns" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/sep/28/worlddispatch.italy">
<main>
<p>It is Silvio Berlusconi's birthday tomorrow. And, from his point of view, it must seem singularly ill-timed.</p>
<p>Since the beginning of the political year, Italy's prime minister has come under mounting pressure from among his allies to stand aside and let someone else lead the right into the general election due before next May.</p>
<p>His birthday focuses attention on one of the main reasons for this. Berlusconi is turning 69. By the end of Italy's next legislature, he will be 74. A facelift and a hair transplant have left him looking conspicuously younger than his years, but they cannot alter the fact that Italy's richest man is now well beyond the age at which most politicians run for high office.</p>
<p>Nor is that the only reason why he is looking vulnerable. Berlusconi in office has turned out to be exactly the opposite of what he was expected to be.</p>
<p>He has learnt to be an able political operator, but - astonishingly for such a talented businessman - he has been a disastrously unsuccessful manager of the economy. Italy is only just recovering from its third recession in four years and last week the finance minister, Domenico Siniscalco, stormed out of the cabinet protesting that Berlusconi refused to take a serious interest in what he was doing.</p>
<p>Talk of life after Berlusconi has been common currency in the corridors of parliament for at least two years now. But this month, for the first time, someone came up with a concrete suggestion as to how Italy's conservatives might effect the transition. The leader of the third-biggest party in government, the Union of Christian Democrats (UDC), suggested the right follow the country's left and hold US-style primary elections to elect a prime ministerial candidate.</p>
<p>The former EU commission president, Romano Prodi, is hoping to stamp his authority on his own rebellious followers by taking on all-comers and - he hopes - defeating them in a nationwide ballot on October 16. The party officials staging this unofficial vote plan to create some 8,000 polling stations up and down the country, and anyone wishing to vote will have to pay €1 to help cover costs.</p>
<p>The leaders of two of the heavyweight parties in the governing coalition have signalled approval for the UDC's idea. Gianfranco Fini of the formerly neo-fascist National Alliance said he had "nothing against it", and Umberto Bossi of the Northern League said it was "better to hold primaries than to fight".</p>
<p>This week, the UDC stepped up the pressure on Berlusconi by suggesting a December date for the primaries. The prime minister has yet to respond. He recently told reporters he was "not afraid of anyone", but he should be. A poll published last Saturday suggested that, if Mr Fini stood, the prime minister would lose.</p>
<p>Since reluctantly accepting his finance minister's resignation, Berlusconi has given another impressive display of his political agility. He moved swiftly to replace Siniscalco with his predecessor, Giulio Tremonti, and put himself in a position to face down his critics in parliament this week by insisting the economy was in robust shape and accusing them of being a bunch of Cassandras.</p>
<p>His adroit performance may prove enough to rob his doubting supporters of the momentum they need to secure a vote on the leadership, but the doubts themselves will not go away and, for all Mr Berlusconi's bluster, the fact remains that the economy is not in good shape.</p>
<p>With or without its charismatic leader, the right will face an uphill struggle to win the next election.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>