<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roy Greenslade" categories="Media" date="2010-09-22" description="Jack Shafer backs Murdoch's bid for complete ownership of BSkyB - and so do I" fingerprint="96b8e48636eeaa6d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Rupert Murdoch,Sky,News Corporation,Silvio Berlusconi,The Sun,News of the World,The Times,Sunday Times" title="Let Murdoch buy Sky - where's the harm?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2010/sep/22/rupert-murdoch-bskyb">
<main>
<p>US media commentator <hi rend="#b">Jack Shafer</hi> comes out strongly against "the UK media establishment" for opposing <hi rend="#b">Rupert Murdoch's </hi>proposed takeover of <hi rend="#b">BSkyB</hi>.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.slate.com/id/2268073/">He writes on Slate</ref>: "Denouncing Murdoch as a potential monopolist every time he buys or starts a media property reveals the idiocy and the dishonesty of his critics.</p>
<quote>
<p>"Obviously, his political foes hate to see Murdoch's megaphone get bigger. But who are his political foes? He has shifted from Tory to Labour and is currently back with the Tories.</p>
<p>"As I've written before, Murdoch has no real politics beyond what's good for Murdoch. Besides, media bosses don't really have half the power ascribed to them.</p>
<p>"So rather than denouncing Murdoch for making politicians bend over, his critics would be better off asking politicians why they're so willing to be the mogul's slave."</p>
</quote>
<p>Gosh! How amazing is that. Well, from my point of view, truly amazing because it is uncannily similar to my column in today's <hi rend="#b">London Evening Standard</hi>, <ref target="http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/markets/article-23880873-let-rupert-murdoch-buy-sky-this-is-not-a-berlusconi-moment.do">Let Rupert Murdoch buy Sky - this is not a Berlusconi moment</ref>.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>