<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2013-02-26" description="Editorial: Italians this week have voted their discontents, their divisions, and their fantasies. Not so very different, then, from other European electorates" fingerprint="27ac01b73824b745" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italian elections 2013,Italy,Europe,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Eurozone crisis,European Union" title="Italian elections: austerity challenged | Editorial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/feb/26/italian-elections-austerity-challenged-editorial">
<main>
<p>Italians this week have voted their discontents, their divisions, and their fantasies. Not so very different, then, from other European electorates. But in Italy the political system, in part because of Silvio Berlusconi's malign institutional heritage, seems perfectly designed to magnify all three.</p>
<p>The result has scared Brussels and Berlin, scared the markets, and scared Italians themselves. What have they wrought? Is Italy headed for permanent political crisis? And could this vote endanger the already threatened common currency, with all which that implies for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> and its future?</p>
<p>Asked a few years ago whether he was worried about the political situation in his country, an Italian economist replied: "I'm not worried, but I am desperate." There is indeed something about Italian politics, at least since the rise of Mr Berlusconi, which induces a state of chronic desperation. Italy "has been in a political, economic and moral crisis for the past 20 years," observed <ref target="http://www.billemmott.com/">one shrewd student</ref> of its affairs, "as it never really succeeded in achieving agreement over reforms" following the collapse of the old party system in 1992. Well, it is still far from that today, although the efforts of Pier Luigi Bersani to tempt the Five Star movement of Beppe Grillo into a common reform programme may offer some hope for the future.</p>
<p>Five Star campaigned, in essence, on the Italian equivalent of the American slogan "Throw the bums out". It did not entirely succeed in that: Mr Berlusconi, the biggest villain of the piece for the <hi rend="#i">grillini</hi>, has ended up in a powerful position in the upper house, although he cannot veto the Bersani-Grillo partnership which, if it happens, may turn out to be a way forward for the country.</p>
<p>But, so far, how the Italians are going to get out of this mess is anybody's guess. A grand coalition of left and right is a possibility, and so is the deal between the centre left and the Five Star movement which Mr Bersani is exploring . But how would either cope with a renewed economic storm, interest rates shooting up, austerity packages unravelling, grim messages from Angela Merkel? How long could such unnatural marriages last?</p>
<p>And if such a government set out to call fresh elections, perhaps with a new electoral law, how would the established parties avert an even greater triumph for Beppe's people? That would not clear up the mess: it would merely create a new one. So, on one level, this was yet another election which failed to solve Italy's chronic political problems. On another, it was a verdict on the German-led austerity policy which is Europe's current remedy for its common currency and other economic ills. Mario Monti, austerity's main man in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, went down with a bang, and Mr Grillo's pledge of a referendum on the euro certainly played a part in the success of his movement.</p>
<p>This was an Italy saying no to austerity. And, with unemployment at more than 11%, according to a recent article in <ref target="http://www.lemonde.fr/international/article/2013/02/22/les-incertitudes-de-l-apres-monti_1837308_3210.html">Le Monde</ref>, more than 100,000 small firms, the backbone of the Italian economy, closing in 2012, and the number of graduates leaving the country reaching a million, that is an understandable negative. Such a verdict cannot be wished away. It is of course far from the first such judgment. The backlash against austerity has brought down incumbent after incumbent across Europe, and, most recently, François Hollande's victory owed something to his pledge to fight austerity. But Italy is the eurozone's third-largest economy, and the vote there this time went less to candidates promising to soften or contest austerity, like Mr Hollande and Mr Bersani, than to those saying, or hinting, that they would reject it.</p>
<p>The German government will be forced to reconsider – or, rather, to reconsider even more than it already reluctantly has. France, coping with its own slipping economic performance, also has difficult choices. In retrospect, 25 February 2013 may go down as the day when Europe's austerity policies, at least as originally conceived, finally hit the buffers.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>