<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2006-04-07" description="Silvio Berlusconi, battling to save himself from a predicted defeat in Italy's general election, made a last-gasp bid for undecided voters yesterday by pledging to do away with yet another tax." fingerprint="b2a913371e3d875d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi pledges more tax cuts to try to avoid defeat" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/apr/08/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi, battling to save himself from a predicted defeat in Italy's general election, made a last-gasp bid for undecided voters yesterday by pledging to do away with yet another tax.</p>
<p>Answering questions on a radio phone-in programme, he said he would cancel the garbage collection levy paid by every Italian household. "Rubbish can become a source of energy," he told a caller. "So this tax can be abolished."</p>
<p>Opposition leaders and mayors scoffed at a promise which, according to the local authorities' association, would leave a hole of up to €3.5bn (£2.4bn) in their coffers. That made it Mr Berlusconi's most ambitious undertaking of the campaign.</p>
<p>On Monday, he pledged to get rid of a government levy on current accounts and the council tax on first homes, which last year brought in €2.3bn.</p>
<p>Sergio Cofferati, the leftwing mayor of Bologna, said: "By tonight, I expect Berlusconi to have abolished irony."</p>
<p>Political sources said polls conducted privately for the parties showed the centre-left opposition ahead by up to 5%. But because of a complex system for allocating seats in Italy's upper house, the 215-seat senate, the margin there could be small - around 12 seats, the sources said.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's campaign has taken on an increasingly desperate air in the final straight, with the prime minister lashing out on all sides against supposed conspirators. He has variously accused journalists, bankers, industrialists and prosecutors of being involved in a plot to remove him. On Thursday, he called for the UN to monitor the poll, suggesting the centre-left was preparing to fix the outcome.</p>
<p>He has also talked of defeat. Yesterday he said: "If I lose, I shall still be in parliament. We shall anyhow be strong, with 270 deputies." Italy's lower house, the chamber of deputies, has 630 seats.</p>
<p>The prime minister's last hopes of victory lay with very low abstention. His aides in Forza Italia think that if the turnout goes above 82% he is in with a chance. But abstention has risen at every election since 1976, so the right faces a daunting task. One reason why Mr Berlusconi has striven to raise the temperature of the campaign is to discourage abstention. But political analysts have been almost unanimous in concluding that his headline-grabbing antics have been counter-productive in another, possibly decisive, respect: they have distracted voters' attention from his council tax pledge, which centre-left leaders feared could have cost them the election.</p>
<p>Voting begins on Sunday, but continues until 3pm local time on Monday when the first exit polls are expected.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>