<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2010-02-28" description="Silvio Berlusconi risks renewed criticism when he unveils his candidate selection" fingerprint="663243259112dfaf" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Unrepentant Berlusconi puts more showgirls up for election" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/28/silvio-berlusconi-single-man-showgirls">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi risked renewed criticism of his selection of candidates for election when he unveiled a list that included a Miss Italy contestant, a former TV weathergirl and a showgirl turned dental hygienist.</p>
<p>Last year the Italian prime minister hastily dropped a group of showgirls from his list of candidates for European elections after his wife said the move was "shamelessly trashy" and demanded a divorce.</p>
<p>But Berlusconi, 73, who describes himself as a "single man" after the start of divorce hearings, has returned to the fray before important regional elections by putting forward Nicole Minetti, 25, the daughter of an English dance instructor who settled in Rimini and married an Italian businessman, Italia Caruso, a former Miss <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> finalist, and Giovanna Del Giudice, who worked at a nightclub frequented by Berlusconi, became a weathergirl on one of his TV channels and was among the women hurriedly dropped from his list of candidates last year.</p>
<p>Joining them on the campaign trail for Berlusconi's Freedom People party this month will be party activist Emanuela Romano, whose father attempted to set himself on fire outside Berlusconi's Rome residence last year in protest after she was dropped.</p>
<p>Also on the Freedom People list in Lombardy are a surveyor employed by Berlusconi and a physiotherapist who has worked at AC Milan, the football club owned by the prime minister.</p>
<p>Minetti, who was confirmed at the weekend as a candidate for Lombardy's regional assembly, first came to attention dressed in a gold bikini and sitting on a swing in a TV show. She later trained to become a dental hygienist.</p>
<p>Aldo Brandirali, a Milan politician and member of Berlusconi's party, was among those who questioned her selection. "We need more seriousness" in politics, he said.</p>
<p>"I have my CV, I am prepared and I am up to fulfilling the role," responded Minetti, before asking journalists: "Can you stop publishing photos from when I worked in TV?"</p>
<p>Minetti appeared at her first rally on Saturday dressed in a trouser suit similar to those now favoured by Mara Carfagna, the former topless model appointed by Berlusconi as minister for equal opportunities.</p>
<p>Reports differ over how Minetti first met Berlusconi. Her grandmother, Teresa, said yesterday she treated the prime minister after he was hit in the face after a rally in December by a man with psychological problems. But Corriere della Sera reported that she had met Berlusconi months earlier.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>