<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Mark Sweney" categories="Media" date="2012-04-03" description="Silvio Berlusconi-owned Italian media company sells last share of debts in Big Brother maker after reporting difficult year. By Mark Sweney" fingerprint="744349f58bb1c340" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Endemol,Television industry,Media business,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe,Business,Investing" title="Mediaset sells final holdings in Endemol" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/apr/03/mediaset-sells-final-holdings-endemol">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's Mediaset said it had offloaded the last of its holdings in Endemol, the maker of shows including Big Brother and Deal or No Deal, following a debt restructure that handed control of the production company to its lenders.</p>
<p>Mediaset, which in March <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2012/mar/23/mediabusiness-italy?INTCMP=SRCH">reported a 36% drop in net profit for 2011 to €225m</ref> (£188m) and slashed its dividend in the face of a difficult year, said that it has sold "around" 6%, or €110m, of Endemol's senior debt.</p>
<p>The company said that the sale, of which it declined to disclose a value – although Italian daily Il Sole 24 Ore said was worth €72m – "corresponds to the total of the stake held [in Endemol] by the group".</p>
<p>Analysts at Citigroup said that the impact on Mediaset's accounts will be "modest" given that the company had valued the debt at €61.6m. "Having already written off its equity investment, this is the end of the saga for Mediaset," said Citigroup in an analyst note. "At least this is positive news."</p>
<p>Mediaset bought a third of Endemol in 2007, alongside Goldman Sachs Capital Partners and Endemol founder John de Mol's investment vehicle Cyrte, in a highly leveraged deal which ran into trouble as the production company's debts mounted.</p>
<p>After more than a year of talks Endemol's owners <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/jan/19/endemol-deal-debt-restructure?INTCMP=SRCH">agreed a deal with lenders</ref> to slash its €2.8bn debt load to €500m in return for giving up control of the company to lenders.</p>
<p>The deal gave Apollo Global Management and de Mol's Cyrte majority ownership of Endemol. Lenders also included Centrebridge, Providence Equity Partners, Barclays, RBS and the Lehman Brothers estate.</p>
<p>During the protracted negotiation period, Endemol shareholders tried to engineer interest in a takeover from potential buyers. Time Warner, which has a strong relationship with de Mol, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2011/dec/12/time-warner-bid-endemol?INTCMP=SRCH">tabled two bids worth about €1bn</ref> but neither were accepted.</p>
<p>Mediaset is thought to have attempted to entice ITV into a joint bid – which took a look at Endemol but never undertook serious work on a bid – and then made an unsolicited bid with private equity firm Clessidra.</p>
<p>RTL, which owns X Factor co-producer Fremantle Media, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2011/nov/09/rtl-endemol-big-brother?INTCMP=SRCH">is also thought to be potentially interested</ref> in entering any sale of Endemol should it go on the block after the debt restructuring is finalised.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i"> To contact the MediaGuardian news desk email editor@mediatheguardian.com or phone 020 3353 3857. For all other inquiries please call the main Guardian switchboard on 020 3353 2000. If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>