<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2004-07-20" description="Umberto Bossi, the ailing leader of Italy's Northern League, resigned yesterday from Silvio Berlusconi's cabinet, dealing the prime minister a severe blow just as it seemed he was free of the tangle of problems enveloping his government." fingerprint="dbd92dbdb4274755" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe,Umberto Bossi,The League" title="Berlusconi hit by minister's resignation" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jul/20/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Umberto Bossi, the ailing leader of Italy's Northern League, resigned yesterday from Silvio Berlusconi's cabinet, dealing the prime minister a severe blow just as it seemed he was free of the tangle of problems enveloping his government.</p>
<p>The leader of the League has been in hospital since March, when he suffered heart failure, and yesterday's decision was, in part, influenced by his need for a long period of convalescence.</p>
<p>It was announced that Mr Bossi would give up his seat in the Italian parliament as well as his job as minister for institutional reform, but that he would take up a place in the European parliament he won at last month's elections. But, the Northern League also made it clear that his decision reflected disenchantment with the direction being taken by the government.</p>
<p>It was the latest stage in a "civil war" within Mr Berlusconi's rightwing coalition set off by the European election results which reflected a sharp drop in support for his Forza Italia (Come on Italy) party and undermined his ability to control his squabbling allies. The Northern League said yesterday it did not intend to bring down the government, but it accused its coalition partners of "blatant betrayal", and warned of "difficult days" ahead.</p>
<p>The League said it was ready to obstruct a key piece of legislation - pension reform - if its own demands for a greater measure of devolution were not met.</p>
<p>The League has been battling to retain its influence within the coalition. Last month's ballot strengthened the position of its arch-rivals, the Union of Centre Democrats, a party that relies heavily on votes from the poorer south and centre of the country, and which sees in devolution a means for making the north even richer.</p>
<p>Similar fears are held by the former neo-fascists in the National Alliance whose leader, Gianfranco Fini, earlier this month succeeded in ousting the economy minister, Giulio Tremonti.</p>
<p>Though a member of Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia party, Mr Tremonti was a key patron of the League.</p>
<p>Last Friday, Mr Berlusconi appointed a non-party technocrat, Domenico Siniscalco as his successor. Mr Siniscalco, a former senior civil servant, is unlikely to look after the League's interests in the same way as Mr Tremonti.</p>
<p>League officials fear its rivals now have their sights trained on a constitutional reform that reached the lower house of parliament yesterday and would give extensive new powers to the regions.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>