<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2004-04-16" description="Silvio Berlusconi's government was last night under attack from several directions as Italians struggled to come to grips with Wednesday's murder of an Italian hostage." fingerprint="5e0a01a5d0245180" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Iraq,Middle East and north Africa,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Italians honour executed hostage as Berlusconi faces more pressure" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/apr/16/iraq.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>An Italian security guard executed by his Iraqi captors was described as a hero last night after it was revealed that his last words before the trigger was pulled were: "Now I'm going to show you how an Italian dies."</p>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's government was under attack from several directions as Italians struggled to come to grips with Wednesday's murder and the appalling prospect that his captors would carry out their threat to execute three other Italian hostages.</p>
<p>The victim, Fabrizio Quattrocchi, 36, was being viewed as a national hero after the foreign minister, Franco Frattini, reported that the video of his execution showed him trying to rip off the hood that had been placed over his head, apparently so that he could look his executioner in the eyes.</p>
<p>Born in Sicily and raised in the northern city of Genoa, Mr Quattrocchi worked as a baker until he turned to security in 2000, Italian newspapers said.</p>
<p>He was contracted to work in Iraq at the end of last year, hoping to use the money to buy a house and start a family, the reports said.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's government faced damaging criticism about its aggressive attitude over Iraq, particularly from relatives of the dead man. In a statement, they accused the government of "wanting to show off its strength by risking the necks of those who are in Iraq".</p>
<p>The strain on the families of those who remained captive became starkly evident yesterday. Two of the remaining hostages' mothers were reported to be under sedation. Earlier, Francesca Bonerba, fiancée of one of the captives, Umberto Cupertino, asked to be taken away by a friend. "I want to go somewhere where I can scream, cry and let out my emotions without anyone hearing me," she told reporters.</p>
<p>Domenica Virzi, the aunt of another hostage, said: "I risk being driven mad by fear and overwhelming pain."</p>
<p>As rightwing groups called for Mr Quattrocchi to be posthumously awarded Italy's highest civil honour, a leftwing cultural group said the govern ment, which has firmly backed US policy in Iraq, was exploiting the plight of the hostages to "wrap up its wrong-headed decisions in patriotism".</p>
<p>But Mr Berlusconi offered no indication of a change in policy. He said the kidnappers had "destroyed a life, [but] they have not cracked our values or our efforts for peace."</p>
<p>In an appeal for unity, Mr Frattini said: "There are moments when Italy has to show the world it is a great nation. This is one of those moments".</p>
<p>Mr Quattrocchi's death was announced by the Arabic TV network Al-Jazeera on Wednesday night and confirmed by Mr Frattini hours later - as the foreign minister sat with relatives of the hostages on a TV talk show watched by millions of Italians.</p>
<p>"Horror in Iraq," said Corriere della Sera. L'Osservatore Romano, the Vatican newspaper, spoke of a "merciless execution."</p>
<p>Roberto Calderoli, of the Northern League, the third biggest party in Mr Berlusconi's conservative coalition, said each country involved in the hostage crisis should expel 1,000 Iraqi and Iranian immigrants a day until the captives were released. "The law of an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth is a cruel one, but it is the only one that criminal animals like this understand", he said.</p>
<p>Vannino Chiti, of the Democratic Left, said the government had shown "no sensibility" towards the hostages' families. Opposition politicians expressed dismay that the foreign minister had identified Mr Quattrocchi as the victim on television before his next of kin had been informed.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>