<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Michael White" categories="Politics" date="2009-12-14" description="Michael White: With the likes of Berlusconi and Blair on the scene we already have all the political populism we can handle" fingerprint="aabf133eb682ad8f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Politics,UK news,The X Factor,Simon Cowell,Media,Television,Television &amp; radio,Television industry,Culture,Tony Blair,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Simon Cowell's Political X Factor? Thanks but no thanks" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/blog/2009/dec/14/simon-cowell-political-x-factor-michael-white">
<main>
<p>What do <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and The X Factor's Simon Cowell have in common? As of this morning, showbusiness and politics.</p>
<p>No, no one's clocked Cowell <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-milan-statue-attack">with a metal model of Milan's duomo and broken a couple of teeth</ref>, though <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2009/dec/14/review-mark-lawson-x-factor">Mark Lawson's review of last night's final</ref> suggests that plenty of people would like to have a go.</p>
<p>What's changed is that the British impresario is threatening to dip a toe into politics. You missed it? Hot on the heels of Joe McElderry's hoist to stardom <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/dec/14/cowell-plans-political-x-factor">Cowell has given an interview to BBC Newsnight</ref> in which he suggests a Political X Factor.</p>
<p>"If you went around the country, it would be five or six issues which I think are really, really important in people's lives," he explains. Oh, no, you don't, Simon; you think it would make great telly and great bank account.<lb/> Cowell illustrates his thinking by adding: "So I think there could be some kind of referendum-type TV show where you can speak on both sides and then open it up to the public to get an instant poll." Yep, we get you, Simon.</p>
<p>What has he got in mind? Knife crime and Afghanistan, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/dec/14/cowell-plans-political-x-factor">according to Patrick Wintour's account in today's Guardian</ref>. Yep, we can follow you on that one, Simon. Weeping mothers make great, voyeuristic TV, don't they? Even better than a succession of sweet teenagers full of hope with a half-decent voice.</p>
<p>As you can probably tell, I'm not keen on The Political X Factor. It doesn't matter if 10 million people – last night's voting figure – picked McElderry over Olly Murs. Not much harm done (except to them) if it all goes pear-shaped.</p>
<p>It does matter if 10 million people think that by voting on TV they have given the government of the day – Brown's, David Cameron's or even Simon Cowell's – a mandate to do something and do it now. Especially when it probably can't be done.</p>
<p>End knife crime? Lock them all up? Bring our boys home tomorrow? Etc. Can you imagine what freaks and exhibitionists would queue to be on the show? It would make Nick Griffin on Question Time or George Galloway sipping milk look as staid and wholesome as Songs of Praise.</p>
<p>Which brings me back to Berlusconi, another populist who escaped the limitations of showbusiness – remember, he started out as a cruise-line crooner – and entered politics via television entrepreneurship.</p>
<p>No one wants the old rogue to get clocked with a duomo. He's 73; it's not kind. There again, when you own much of a country's private-sector TV and have a powerful hand in the public-sector rival by virtue of being prime minister you may be building up trouble.</p>
<p>Rupert Murdoch is smarter than Silvio: he likes to leave a political middleman in place to take the blame when things go wrong – as they do.</p>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-punched-face">Fiona Winward's report from Rome</ref> says that part of the crowd at his People for Freedom party rally in Milan last night was shouting "buffoon". As if to prove them right, Berlusconi boasted that he was still "young and on form" – and opened his shirt to show he "wasn't even wearing a vest" in December.</p>
<p>It's not having his trousers on that civic-minded Italians worry about. Berlusconi is a vain and foolish populist of questionable morals whose survival in office frightens sensible people.</p>
<p>I'm sure Simon Cowell is too sensible to be tempted ... On the other hand, in scary times people often look to handsome, familiar faces, an actor's glib fluency with other people's lines.</p>
<p>In the depth of the cold war after a humiliation in Iran – the embassy seizure – the American people turned to Ronnie Reagan, a charming man with some good qualities, albeit one whose record in office flatters him.</p>
<p>In their current distress over Barack Obama's attempt to give them a post-Bush reality check many Americans are looking to Sarah Palin and her imitators, besides whom Reagan looks like Abraham Lincoln.</p>
<p>Thanks for the offer, Simon. But we don't need any of that to add to our considerable problems. Whatever you think of former wannabe rock singer <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/tonyblair">Tony Blair</ref> – I'm told not everyone likes him – his easy charm and inflated parliamentary majority in 1997 did neither him nor us as much good as people hoped for, did it?</p>
<p>That Blair is in trouble enough as a result of his persuasive skills is evidenced again today by <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/article6955241.ece">a tremendous rant against him for "narcissism" and "sychophancy" from Sir Ken Macdonald in the Times</ref>.</p>
<p>The ex-director of public prosecutions (2003-08) was called a crony and "the criminals' best friend" by the usual suspects when he was appointed under Blair. No longer. On no discernible evidence Macdonald states as fact that Blair was committed to war after his April 2002 visit to George Bush's Crawford ranch-ette and engaged in "alarming subterfuge" to get British forces into Iraq – "a foreign policy disgrace of epic proportions".</p>
<p>Macdonald is a well-regarded lawyer, part of the Matrix Chambers human rights team to which Cherie Booth also belongs (now what's <hi rend="#i">that</hi> about?), who has defended some unpopular clients in his time. Good for him.</p>
<p>But what foreign policy expertise his CV gives him, let alone insight into Blair's psychological make-up, is not clear. Perhaps he discusses Tony with Cherie over a post-work sherry.</p>
<p>"D'you know, I catch him looking in the mirror, Ken."</p>
<p>"That's really deep, Cher'. Do you mind if I jot that down?"</p>
<p>What seems to have triggered the article is Blair's interview with Fern Britton on BBC1, which I missed. That's the programme for which the BBC PR department cleverly generated Saturday's headlines in many papers, including this one. "<ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/politics/article6954043.ece">Blair would have gone to war without Iraqi WMD</ref>," was the Times's version.</p>
<p>Except, of course, that's not what he told Britton. All he said was that, absent WMD, "I would still have thought it right to remove him", and we should all be grateful to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/dec/14/tony-blair-iraq-chilcot-wmd">Guardian reader Ronnie Paris for pointing that out in today's letters column</ref>.</p>
<p>The moral of the story? What with Silvio, Tony and now Sir Ken, we've got all the political populism we can handle, Simon. Thanks, but no thanks.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>