<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Graeme Wearden" categories="Business" date="2013-09-11" description="MEPs unimpressed by commission president’s final State of the Union speech, in which he calls for progress on banking union and warns of risk of political instability" fingerprint="99cec25591b08e97" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Unemployment and employment statistics,Business,Silvio Berlusconi,European Union,Economic growth (GDP),Bank of England" title="Barroso: Europe is on road to recovery - as it happened" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/barrosos-state-of-the-union-uk-unemployment">
<main><p><hi rend="#b">Slightly early finish today.</hi> My colleagues will reopen the liveblog if any big news breaks. Otherwise I'll be back tomorrow. Thanks, and goodnight. <hi rend="#b">GW</hi></p><head rend="h1">Barroso: Europe is on road to recovery - as it happened</head><head class="dcr-1ybxn6r">Wed 11 Sep 2013 16.28 CEST</head>First published on Wed 11 Sep 2013 08.40 CEST<graphic alt="European Commission President Jose Manuel Barroso delivers his annual 'State of the Union' speech during a plenary session at the European Parliament in Strasbourg, France, 11 September 2013." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378891682894/b1efcc0f-aa37-4dbf-a208-544c0a325106-2060x1236.jpeg?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><head class="dcr-1ybxn6r">Wed 11 Sep 2013 16.28 CEST</head>First published on Wed 11 Sep 2013 08.40 CEST<head class="dcr-5ug1dg">Live feed</head><head rend="h2">Photos: Cantor and BGC's Charity Day to remember 9/11</head><p><hi rend="#b">Financial firms BGC Partners and Cantor Fitzgerald </hi>are holding their annual Charity Day to remember the 658 employees who lost their lives in the 9/11 attacks on the World Trade Centre in New York 12 years ago today.</p><p>The two firms (BGC was spun out of Cantor in 2004), have an impressive roster of people working the phones at their offices around the world, raising money for good causes, including Royals and actors.</p><quote><p>Actress Bridget Moynihan taking orders at Cantor Fitzgeralds Charity Day.</p>— Mary Thompson (@MThompsonCNBC)<ref>pic.twitter.com/gSGlzeBtkZ</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p><hi rend="#b">Some quotes from eurogroup president Jeroen Dijsselbloem are hitting the wires</hi>.</p><p>Dijsselbloem, who is also Dutch finance minister, is predicting that Greece will need more assistance once its bailout programme ends in 2014, and that Ireland may need assistance to exit its own programme (points he also made to an EC committee a few days ago).</p><p>He also suggested that Lisbon faces a tougher challenge than Dublin:</p><quote><p>*DIJSSELBLOEM: PORTUGAL EXIT FROM PROGRAM TO BE MORE DIFFICULT</p>— lemasabachthani (@lemasabachthani)<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Here's a video clip of the UK prime minister, David Cameron, answering a question on today's unemployment data (which showed a drop in the jobless rate to 7.7%, but with wages still lagging inflation):</p><head rend="h2">Market update</head><p>After a pretty dull trading session in Europe, Wall Street has opened slightly higher after president Obama backed away from immediate military action in Syria last night (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/11/syria-crisis-obama-edges-towards-diplomacy-live-updates">our Middle East liveblog has the lates</ref>t).</p><p><hi rend="#b">The Dow Jones industrial average is up 37 points, or 0.25%, in early trading.</hi></p><p>Europe's markets are mixed this afternoon -- Italy is the biggest riser, on relief that the question of whether to expel Berlusconi from the Senate has been hoofed into the long grass (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/barrosos-state-of-the-union-uk-unemployment#block-5230131fe4b0cbc84ec2beeb">see 7.56am</ref>).</p><p>Earlier, gold has dropped to a three-week low of $1,356 per ounce after America backed away from immediate military action in Syria last night (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/11/syria-crisis-obama-edges-towards-diplomacy-live-updates">our Middle East liveblog has the lates</ref>t)</p><p>Meanwhile over in <hi rend="#b">Greece</hi>, protesting teachers have cast a pall over the government’s hopes for a strike-free autumn this year.</p><p>Our correspondent Helena Smith reports:</p><quote><p>After taking to the streets last night with a dynamic protest outside parliament, Greek teachers ensured that the school year got off with a bang today promising that all classes will stop as of Monday. Indicative of the mood, pupils greeted main opposition leader Alexis Tsipras with placards proclaiming “we are people, not numbers” when the leftist leader turned up to attend the opening of one school in Athens this morning.</p><p>Tsipras said it sounded ironic to wish schoolchildren “a good year” when teaching staff had decided to stage indefinite five-day rolling strikes in a massive display of opposition over EU-IMF mandated job losses and cuts.</p><p>The walk-outs, the first major industrial action this autumn, has put Antonis Samaras’ conservative dominated coalition on the defensive just as teams of inspectors representing the debt-stricken country’s creditors prepare to fly in.</p><p>Teachers, who last night took to the streets promising to “pull a punch,” appear in no mood for compromise...</p></quote><quote><p>In an explosive letter, addressed to parents and pupils, they appealed for understanding saying government austerity policies had pushed the educational system to the brink. “Can schools function with 16,000 fewer teachers? Can schools function with professors who don’t know in which, or how many, schools they will teach, in what region of the country they will work or, if, they will even have work in the immediate future?” the missive, released by OLME, the union representing secondary school teachers, asked.</p><p>“Can schools work with operational costs that have been reduced by 60 percent, without money for electricity, water or heat?”</p><p>With tensions running high, the education minister Kostas Arvanitopoulos hit back this morning accusing the union of skewing the numbers and resorting to emotional blackmail by addressing the letter to schoolchildren.</p></quote><p>City economists broadly share <hi rend="#b">Jose Manuel Barroso's</hi> belief that the worst of Europe's financial crisis woes are behind it, a new poll found.</p><p>Twenty three analysts polled by Reuters this week said they were confident that the recovery was "durable", while 12 did not. Only only economist (alas, not identified) reckoned the euro area would fall back into recession before the end of 2014.</p><head rend="h2">France to miss growth and deficit targets.</head><p><hi rend="#b">The French government has underlined the weak nature of the European recovery, by warning that it will miss its growth and deficit targets .</hi></p><p>Finance minister <hi rend="#b">Pierre Moscovici</hi> told a press conference on the 2014 Budget earlier today that France's 2013 public deficit will probably be <hi rend="#b">4.1%</hi> of GDP, above the <hi rend="#b">3.9%</hi> agreed with the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/eu">European Union</ref> (<hi rend="#i">and much higher than the 3% which countries are meant to keep below</hi>).</p><p>Paris also sees weaker growth in 2014, cutting its forecast to just 0.9% growth in 2014, down from 1.2%. It is maintaining a prediction of 0.1% growth this year.</p><p>Nigel Farage's response to Barroso has been uploaded to YouTube:</p><head rend="h2">How Barroso laid into Conservative party</head><p>I mentioned <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/barrosos-state-of-the-union-uk-unemployment#block-523040a9e4b0a811a627c879">at 11.07am</ref> that <hi rend="#b">Barroso had criticised the UK Conservative Party for their increased euroscepticism</hi>, warning that they would lose out to UKIP next year -- well, the Financial Times now has the full details:</p><p>Peter Speigel writes:</p><quote><p>José Manuel Barroso lashed out at the leader of the British conservatives in the European Parliament on Wednesday, saying his party was sounding increasingly like the eurosceptic Ukip group and warning the Tories would lose the next EU parliament elections if they continued on the same path.</p><p>Speaking during a parliamentary debate on his annual state of the EU speech, the European Commission president said Martin Callanan, a Tory from northeast England, could never be chosen for a senior EU job – because the Tories were moving out of the European mainstream.</p><p>“I’m not saying that happily, because I think increasingly your party and your group is looking like Ukip and the eurosceptic, anti-European group,” Mr Barroso said, pointing repeatedly at Mr Callanan. “I start to have some doubts that you are going to be elected yourself in Britain, if it’s not going to be Ukip as the first force in British elections.</p></quote><head rend="h2">More here: <ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/07b0e41e-1acd-11e3-87da-00144feab7de.html#axzz2eaGSzPOV">Barroso lashes out at UK conservative leader in EU Parliament</ref></head><p>Barroso's call for action on banking union is an "implicit challenge" to the German government, Reuters reports:</p><quote><p>What we can and must do first and foremost is deliver the banking union. It is the first and most urgent way to complete our union," Barroso told lawmakers in Strasbourg.</p><p>His comments were an implicit challenge to Germany, the EU's leading power, which has worked to limit the scope of a single banking supervisor and slow the drive for a single bank resolution authority and fund,citing legal constraints and the wish to spare its taxpayers from liabilities for others' banks.</p><p>The goal of creating a single framework and backstop for around 8,000 European banks, with mechanisms to wind down failed lenders and protect savers' deposits, is one of the EU's most ambitious and challenging projects.</p></quote><head rend="h2">More here: <ref target="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/09/11/eu-barroso-idUSL5N0H715N20130911">EU's Barroso urges Europe to complete banking union</ref></head><p>Here's some more reaction to the State of the Union speech:</p><quote><p>— Sony Kapoor (@SonyKapoor)</p><ref>#EUrozone</ref>may come to regret the single-minded pursuit of a<ref>#BankingUnion</ref>to the exclusion of everything else<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>If it was</p>— Isa Soares (@IsaCNN)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>legacy speech, then it was a mighty good one: Impassioned+ unequivocal. europe needs optimism<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>— Isa Soares (@IsaCNN)</p><ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>in his<ref>#SOTEU</ref>says:"the recovery is within sight" but there is "no way back to business as usual"<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>I'm surprised that Farage devoted his</p>— Dave Keating (@DaveKeating)<ref>#SOTEU</ref>response 2 climate change denying. Suggests UKIP will make this a big issue in<ref>#EU2014</ref>campaign<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>Barroso</p>— grodaeu (@grodaeu)<ref>#SOTEU</ref>wordcount: europe 69 european 43 year 29 member 27 union 24 crisis 23 one 21 market 20 country 20 people19 together19<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>— Luke Baker (@LukeReuters)</p><ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>seems in the mood to deliver some straight, hard truths. It may not endear him to all, but it's a welcome change of form<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Our eagle-eyed Europe editor, Ian Traynor, identifies a key part of Barroso's speech which I didn't get into the blog earlier:</p><quote><p>— Ian Traynor (@traynorbrussels)</p><ref>#SOTEU</ref>only new thing barroso says in speech is EC shd get new powers to police fundamental rights, penalise member states - trouble ahead<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>And here's the relevant section:</p><quote><p>In last year's State of the Union speech, at a moment of challenges to the rule of law in our own member states, I addressed the need to make a bridge between political persuasion and targeted infringement procedures on the one hand, and what I call the nuclear option of Article 7 of the Treaty, namely suspension of a member states' rights.</p><p>Experience has confirmed the usefulness of the Commission role as an independent and objective referee. We should consolidate this experience through a more general framework. It should be based on the principle of equality between member states, activated only in situations where there is a serious, systemic risk to the rule of law, and triggered by pre-defined benchmarks.</p><p>The Commission will come forward with a communication on this. I believe it is a debate that is key to our idea of Europe.</p><p>This does not mean that national sovereignty or democracy are constrained. But we do need a robust European mechanism to influence the equation when basic common principles are at stake.</p><p>There are certain non-negotiable values that the EU and its member states must and shall always defend.</p></quote><head rend="h2">State of the Union - a few thoughts</head><p><hi rend="#b"> José Manuel Barroso must have been delighted last month when the eurozone recession ended. </hi></p><p>It let him put a more polished gloss in today's speech, and talk about a Europe that is recovering, not still shrinking. But as a succession of MEPs warned, 0.3% growth in GDP does not make up for 26 million people out of work, and rising social angst. No-one, it seemed, wanted to be seen giving Brussels much credit for the fragile recovery.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Political worries?</hi></p><p>The immediate risk of the Italian government collapsing abated last night, when Senators decided not to push for an early decision on whether to banish <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. But political risk remains the big fear for Brussels -- thus Barroso's comment about how nations must stick to their commitments.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Presidential power?</hi></p><p>The speech was a reminder of the limits of Barroso's influence. He repeatedly called for rapid progress on banking union, echoing comments from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/But%20Germany,%20the%20biggest%20economy%20in%20the%20eurozone,%20has%20voiced%20its%20objections%20to%20the%20creation%20of%20a%20single%20authority,%20arguing%20that%20it%20would%20require%20a%20new%20European%20treaty%20that%20may%20take%20years%20to%20agree.">IMF chief Christine Lagarde only yesterday</ref>. But closer banking union is being held up by Europe's biggest country, Germany, which wants to see treaty changes first. And Barroso can't force its hand. </p><p><hi rend="#b">Elections looming</hi></p><p>MEPs have an eye on next year's elections, and recognise that the eurozone crisis means the game has changed. Traditional battles between conservatives and socialists are no longer on the agenda – instead, pro-European parties are preparing for a pitched battle with eurosceptics. <hi rend="#i">The Farageisation of politics</hi>?</p><p><hi rend="#b">Peace in our time</hi></p><p>There was some scoffing last year when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/dec/10/eu-receives-nobel-peace-prize">the European Union won the Nobel Peace Price</ref>. That award, though, seems to have given the EU a new sense of identity and pride. Expect to hear more about world war one over the next year, </p><quote><p>— European Commission (@EU_Commission)</p><ref>#wordcloud</ref>of today's<ref>#SOTEU</ref>speech:<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref><ref>http://t.co/BELsCtsNU9</ref><ref>pic.twitter.com/E3gZy2DCVf</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>The full text of Barroso's speech is <ref target="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_SPEECH-13-684_en.htm">online here</ref>:</p><p>Here's his conclusion:</p><quote><hi>In 8 months' time, voters will decide.</hi><hi>Now, it's up to us to make the case for Europe.</hi><hi>We can do so by using the next 8 months to conclude as much as we can. We have a lot to do still.</hi><hi>Adopt and implement the European budget, the MFF. This is critical for investment in our regions all over Europe. This is indispensable for the first priority we have: to fight against unemployment, notably youth unemployment.</hi><hi>Advance and implement the banking union. This is critical to address the problem of financing for businesses and SMEs.</hi><hi>These are our clear priorities: employment and growth.</hi><hi>Our job is not finished. It is in its decisive phase.</hi><hi>Because, Honourable Members, the elections will not only be about the European Parliament, nor will they be about the European Commission or about the Council or about this or that personality.</hi><hi>They will be about Europe.</hi><hi>We will be judged together.</hi><hi>So let us work together - for Europe.</hi><hi>With passion and with determination.</hi><hi>Let us not forget: one hundred years ago –Europe was sleepwalking into the catastrophe of the war of 1914.</hi><hi>Next year, in 2014, I hope Europe will be walking out of the crisis towards a Europe that is more united, stronger and open.</hi></quote><p>Meanwhile, today's UK unemployment data (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/barrosos-state-of-the-union-uk-unemployment#block-523037e5e4b0a811a627c874">see here for details</ref>) confirms that the housing market is reviving</p><quote><p>Extraordinary 9.9% rise in number of people employed in "real estate activities" between March and June HT</p>— Heather Stewart (@heatherstewart3)<ref>@JobsEconomist</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>Wow.</p>— Gabriele Steinhauser (@gksteinhauser)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>'s reponses at<ref>#SOTEU</ref>much more passionate than his speech.<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Nigel Farage again:</p><quote><p>National democracy I advocate is not about going back to 1913.</p>— EP PressService (@EuroParlPress)<ref>@Nigel_Farage</ref><ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><head rend="h2">Barroso: Greece caused Greece's problems, not us</head><p>And Jose Manuel Barroso is adamant that Greece's economic crisis was brewed in Athens, not Brussels.</p><p>He insisted:</p><quote><p>Who is responsible for the problems in Europe. Is it policy, or is it mistakes in the past?</p><p>It is not true that Greece is a victim of European policies. Greece is the victim of the irresponsible behaviour of the governments of Greece</p></quote><p>He concludes:</p><quote><p>Europe is not the creator of the problems. Europe is the victim of the problems, and it is part of the solution.</p></quote><p>Amnesty says the speech was a missed opportunity to push human rights up Europe's agenda:</p><quote><p>Not one mention of</p>— AmnestyEurope (@amnestyeurope)<ref>#HumanRights</ref>. Missed opportunity by<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>at<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Speaking of Farage, Barroso also suggested that UK voters will support UKIP rather than the Conservative MEPs in next year's European elections -- on the grounds that people will prefer the original over a copy, he argued.</p><quote><p>When</p>— Luke Baker (@LukeReuters)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>is on a role, he's fired up and entertaining. He's right that UK Conservatives beginning to look like UKIP.<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>"We have a duty to our citizens to provide hope", says Barroso, reiterating that he doesn't believe the economic crisis has ended.</p><p>Barroso calls on all pro-European MEPs to work together in next year's European elections to make the case for the European project.</p><p>Clearly wounded by the claims that he's living on another planet, a finger-pointing Barroso tells MEPs that he knows all about the problem of social deprivation and beggars on the streets.</p><p>I know, and I'm fighting that problem. We know the reality and we're trying to do our best, he says.</p><p>Barroso tells Nigel Farage that "ninety nine percent" of scientists believe that man-made climate change is a reality.</p><p>Farage responds by waving his North Pole photos again.</p><head rend="h2">Barroso responds</head><p>Back in Strasbourg, <hi rend="#b">Jose Manuel Barroso</hi> is responding to the various comments made by MEPs about his State of the Union speech.</p><quote><p>Unusually,</p>— Peter Spiegel (@SpiegelPeter)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>starts his response in Portuguese.<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>Ok. Now</p>— Peter Spiegel (@SpiegelPeter)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>is just showing off. Just switched to French. English interpreter didn't miss a beat!<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p><hi rend="#i">And then into English.....</hi></p><p>He denies being unduly optimistic, saying that he never claimed the crisis is over. This is a major political crisis, he says, and it requires a lot of wisdom to guarantee unity and diversity.</p><p>On the UK unemployment data, <hi rend="#b">Heather Stewart</hi>, the Observer's economics editor, writes:</p><quote><p>Despite the improving picture, there was also evidence in the detail of the figures that conditions in the labour market remain tough for many.</p><p>Average pay rose at an annual rate of just 1%, or 1.1% including bonuses – well below the 2.8% rate of inflation – suggesting that living standards are still being squeezed.</p><p>The ONS also highlighted the fact that much of the increase in employment – almost all of it, for women – has been in part-time work, in many cases taken up by employees who would prefer a full-time job if they could find one.</p><p>Almost a third of men, and 13.5% of women, in part-time work or self-employment would prefer to be in a full-time role, according to the ONS.</p></quote><head rend="h2"><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/uk-unemployment-rate-falls-interest-rates">Full story: UK unemployment rate falls to 7.7%</ref></head><p>Britain's households are still being squeezed, today's data shows. That 1.1% rise in weekly earnings (on an annual basis) is well below the inflation rate of 2.8%.</p><p>The pound has rallied this morning, hitting new seven-month highs against the euro and dollar. But an interest rate rise may still be further off than the City thinks...</p><quote><p>7.7pc unemployment, down from 7.8pc, still a long way from 7pc. Markets should relax. A lot more good news on jobs needed before rates rise.</p>— David Smith (@dsmitheconomics)<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>A few more key points from today's UK unemployment data:</p><list rend="ul"><item><hi rend="#b">Weekly earnings excluding bonuses</hi>increased 1.1% y/y in the three months to June. Weekly earnings including bonuses rose by 0.6% y/y.</item><item><hi rend="#b">The employment rate</hi>rose to 71.6% in the three months to July from 71.5%, with 29.84 million people working, an increase of 80,000 over the quarter and 275,000 from a year earlier.</item><item>The number of full-time workers <hi rend="#b">increased</hi>by 95,000 over the three months to July to 21.79 million, accounting for 73% of all employed people. The number of part-time workers decreased by 15,000 to 8.05 million and is down by 74,000 from a year earlier.</item><item>The percentage of long-term unemployed—those out of work for more than 12 months—was 36.2% in the three months to July.</item><item>The unemployment rate for <hi rend="#b">young people aged 16 and 17 years old was 38%</hi>; the unemployment rate for 18- to 24-year-olds was 18.9%.</item><item>The number of vacancies was 531,000 in the three months to August, <hi rend="#b">up 7,000</hi>over the quarter and 53,000 from a year earlier.</item></list><head rend="h2">UK unemployment rate drops</head><p><hi rend="#b">While MEPs were debating Europe, new data showed that Britain's jobless rate has fallen. </hi></p><p>The unemployment rate fell to 7.7% in the three months to July, from 7.8%, with the number of people out of work dropping by 24,000 to 2.49 million.</p><p>The claimant count also fell, by 32,600, to 1.40 million - the lowest level since February 2009.</p><p>The headline jobless rate is particularly closely watched now, as the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor">Bank of England</ref> has said it won't consider raising interest rates until it has fallen to 7%.</p><p><hi rend="#i">I'll pull together some reaction now...</hi></p><p>This tweet from MEP Guy Verhofstaft has caused quite a stir:</p><quote><p>The pro-European forces should unite against Euroscepticism. This will define</p>— Guy Verhofstadt (@GuyVerhofstadt)<ref>#EP2014</ref>election campaign.<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>Retweets not endorsements, but I'm still a little taken aback at a Commission spox retweeting this from Verhofstadt</p>— Allie Renison (@AllieRenison)<ref>https://t.co/ppd85YkOZU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><head rend="h2">State of the Union, a summary</head><p><hi rend="#b">The debate is continuing, and can be followed here or on the BBC Parliament channel.</hi></p><p>But here's a quick round-up:</p><p><hi rend="#b"> José Manuel Barroso has declared that Europe's economic crisis is easing.</hi></p><p>In hie final State of the Union speech in Strasbourg, the EC president said the panic that gripped the region over the past few years was abating. But politicians need to remain vigilant, and tackle growth and unemployment.Barroso declared:</p><quote><p>For Europe, recovery is within sight. Let's not overestimate the progress, but neither should we underestimate what has been done.</p></quote><p><hi rend="#b">Barroso added</hi> that MEPs have a debt to the region's 26 million unemployed to make sure the fragile recovery does not falter. He cited two priorities -- hammering out a final deal on the next EU budget, and implementing banking union.</p><p> And once again, Barroso called for <hi rend="#b">closer political union</hi> as a solution to Europe's problems, arguing that;</p><quote><p>Europe must focus on where it can add most value. It needs to be big on big things and smaller on smaller things.</p></quote><p>And the EC president also reminded MEPs that 99 year ago, member states were entering years of conflict. Europe must learn the lessons of world war one, he insisted. It is a project of peace.</p><p>Barroso also cited fighting climate change, achieving closer trade links, and creating a single market for telecoms as priorities for the year ahead.</p><p><hi rend="#b"> Coverage starts at 8.12am, with Barroso's conclusion at 9.00am.</hi></p><p> The speech did not set the Strasbourg parliament alight. A series of MEPs have criticised Barroso for taking a too-optimistic view. One reminded him that just 31 new jobs were created in Spain last month, while another pointed to beggars on the streets as a sign that social cohesion is unraveling. Reaction starts at <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/sep/11/barrosos-state-of-the-union-uk-unemployment#block-52302320e4b00fa1bc127a7d">9.05am</ref></p><p>British Liberal MEP <hi rend="#b">Andrew Duff</hi> says it is important that the European Council is 'held to account' as it tries to move towards closer political union.</p><graphic alt="Laurence Stassen MEP" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378891307467/b6637367-67ac-499f-ba50-54fb18a0405c-620x356.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p><hi rend="#b">Laurence Stassen</hi> of the Netherlands is blunter, challenging Barroso to take his message that 'things are getting better' onto the streets of Europe.</p><p>What planet are you on, she asks, adding that next year's European elections will see a real change in Europe's direction.</p><p>One more key line from the debate -- Spanish socialist MEP Juan Lopez Aguilar has also chided Barroso for being too confident.</p><p>In Spain, people are giving up hope of ever getting a job, he says. We need to do more to stimulate economic growth, he say -- saying Europe is only achieving meagre growth at present.</p><graphic alt="Juan Lopez Aguilar MEP" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378890929523/3e924250-9aef-4ddf-ab21-2741103b1caa-620x345.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p>Aguilar also touches on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/the-nsa-files">the NSA scandal</ref>, saying it is completely unacceptable that the communications of European citizens have been intercepted by American intelligence.</p><p>Austrian MEP <hi rend="#b">Jorg Leichfried</hi> wades into <hi rend="#b">Nigel Farage</hi>, much to Jose Manuel Barroso's clear amusement .</p><p>You make these comments, Leichfried tells Farage, but what have you ever done? You've never drafted a single position.</p><quote><p>How can you justify that to your voters? How can you justify that you've done no work?</p></quote><p>Farage doesn't seem phased by this prospect.</p><graphic alt="Nigel Farage" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378889340718/4537e0b7-6c35-45f1-80bc-e2670beaad7a-620x348.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p>Farage then attacks the Brussels' green agenda, and its attempts to tackle climate change.</p><p>Waving two NASA photos of the North Pole, he declares that the ice cap has grown significantly over the last couple of years. You're made a terrible mistake, he claims.</p><p><hi rend="#i">Much muttering among other MEPs, with many waving their 'blue cards' in an effort to intervene.</hi></p><quote><p>UKIP's Farage: "There has been no global warming, sirs, for the last 20 years. Let's scrap carbon tax"</p>— Georgi Gotev (@GeorgiGotev)<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><head rend="h2">Farage: Euro will die a very slow and painful death</head><p>Now Nigel Farage of UKIP takes the floor.</p><p>He applauds Barroso's consistent support for federalism -- "you probably picked it up as a Maoist" (<hi rend="#i">Barroso was a communist in his youth</hi>)</p><p>It's been a good time for some people, Farage says, but it's been "a disaster" for poor people.</p><p>Farage says that Brussels' austerity push has driven unemployment in peripheral countries far higher than would otherwise be the case, adding:</p><quote><p>The euro will die a very slow and painful death, but you're all in denial about that.</p></quote><p>Cyprus's communist MEP, Takis Hadjigeorgiou, also criticises Barroso's optimism over the European economy. He can only be so upbeat because he lives in a different Europe than the rest of us, Hadjigeorgiou claims.</p><p>He points to beggars on the streets of Strasbourg as proof, before reminding MEPs of the Cypriot bailout package:</p><quote><p>In my country, where the decisions taken by the troika destroyed the economy, the commission is now associated with the economic crisis.</p></quote><graphic alt="Martin Callanan MEP" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378888518407/a4938c82-4c1d-4fa7-bb40-5c218a2d97b5-620x349.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p>Now an alternative take. We need<hi rend="#b"> less Europe, not more</hi>, says <hi rend="#b">Martin Callanan</hi> of the European Conservatives and Reformists (who also represents North East England).</p><p><hi rend="#b">Callanan</hi> begins by taking a few merry pops at senior European politicians, saying they're swarming around hoping to replace Barroso as president of the EC.</p><quote><p>It's like a giant hustings meeting</p></quote><p>He points to Vivienne Reding, and Olli Rehn -=- although "if he gets the job I imagine we'd all have a late lunch".</p><p>(<hi rend="#i">surely an early lunch?</hi>) </p><p>Anyway, <hi rend="#b">Callanan'</hi>s argument is that "we need a new euro-realistic agenda". To be proudly German, or Polish is not anti-European, he argues.</p><p>Rebecca Harms cites the fate of whistle-blower Edward Snowden, as an example that Europe isn't living up to Barroso's vision of peace and social justice.</p><p>What does that say about Europe, when Edward Snowden is holed up in Russia?</p><p>Other MEPs are now chipping in, demanding to know Harms position on data protection and suchlike...</p><p>The debate continues, with European Green's co-chair Rebecca Harms MEP warning that Europe "keeps dwelling in public finances", but we neglect the state of Europe's private banks.</p><p>Banking union is needed to bring lurking problems to their balance sheets.</p><p>Harms also takes a pop at Angela Merkel for phoning other European leaders and threatening that German industry will pull out of their countries unless they toe the German line on climate change.</p><graphic alt="Guy Verhofstadt" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378887522241/95d4d4a1-5bb3-432a-a4aa-db38490a8468-620x349.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p>In a typically passionate intervention, <hi rend="#b">Guy Verhofstaft</hi> is arguing for closer European political and economic union to tackle the region's economic problems.</p><p>We should have a common government, a common treasury, which would mean cheaper borrowing for governments.</p><p>And the European Central Bank's mandate should be changed, so that it focuses on growth rather than inflation.</p><p>And in conclusion, <hi rend="#b">Verhofstaft</hi> says next year's European election will not be between left and right, but between eurosceptics "who believe you can put the world outside your borders" and the rest.</p><p>Guy Verhofstaft, who leads the European Liberals and Democrats group, also criticises Barroso for arguing that the recovery is underway.,</p><p>Rather, Verhofstaft argues, it proves that we merely hit the bottom.</p><p>Europe risks a Japan-style lost two decades, without more decisive action.</p><p>Swoboda concludes by laying into Barroso for botching the European budget (he, like many MEPs, wanted more funds for the European project).</p><p>He warns that his Socialist and Democrats group won't support the budget, or MFF, unless it contains more funding to help fight youth unemployment.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Hannes Swoboda</hi> also reminds Barroso of the social problems in Europe, and issues such as rising attacks on migrants.</p><p>And even in Italy, he says, where<hi rend="#b"> Cécile Kyenge</hi> has faced <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/26/italian-politician-compares-black-minister-prostitute">a series of racist insults</ref> since joining Enrico Letta's government.</p><quote><p>We should be proud to have a black minister in one of our European governments.</p></quote><p><hi rend="#b">Swoboda</hi> agrees that Europe needs to be stronger -- how can we support foreign minister Catherine Ashton's work otherwise?</p><head rend="h2">Hannes Swoboda blasts Barroso</head><graphic alt="Hannes Swoboda" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378886731441/7572ecaa-4ebc-41c7-ae78-f3e6831b39a9-620x351.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p>The various leaders of political groupings in the European Parliament are responding to Barroso.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Hannes Swoboda</hi>, head of the European Socialists and Democrats, tears into the EC president for the upbeat tone of his speech.</p><quote><p>Once again, you have presented a glass that is half full as fully full.</p></quote><p>Swoboda is unamused that Barroso spoke of recovery in Europe, pointing out that there is still 60% youth unemployment in Greece.</p><p><hi rend="#b">How many jobs were created in Spain last month, he continues. 31. Just 31. It's a scandal. </hi></p><head rend="h2">Barroso Conclusion</head><p><hi rend="#b">So what does Barroso actually want?</hi> He rounds up his speech by setting two priorities.</p><p>First, getting final agreement on the next EU budget, the <ref target="http://ec.europa.eu/budget/mff/index_en.cfm">Multiannual Financial Framework</ref>. (<hi rend="#i">this sparked furious battles last year as EU leaders such as David Cameron and Angela Merkel fought Brussels' push for another rise in funding</hi>).</p><p>Second, implementing banking union in the eurozone.</p><p>This progress is essential to deliver growth, and fight unemployment - especially youth unemployment. That is our priority, say Barroso, who repeats that the crisis is not over, "it is in its decisive phase".</p><p>And with another nod to the conflict of 1914-1918, Barroso says he hopes that next year European citizens can be walking confidently out of the crisis.</p><p><hi rend="#b">And that's the end of the speech.</hi></p><p>Barroso gets a polite round of applause, but there's none of the whooping and cheering that you see when the US president delivers the State of the Union.</p><p>On next year's elections... "It is up to us to make the case for Europe".</p><p>Barroso also criticised those who nationalize success and Europeanize failure -- good, or bad, we're in this together.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Some people blame Europe for the financial crisis, says Barroso .... but they're wrong</hi>.</p><p>Mismanagement in the financial markets is to blame (<hi rend="#i">cue scattered applause</hi>)</p><p>He then makes a good point, about how Europe's citizens and companies are interconnected.</p><p>There are links between one country's debt, and another country's banks, between companies and customers, between one country's workers and another country's companies.</p><p>Barroso harks back to the days of WW1...</p><quote><p>nice. RT</p>— Olly Barratt (@ollybarratt)<ref>@BrunoBrussels</ref>: 'Those who want to roll back our integration and go back to isolation: the war, the trenches,'<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref><ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>The big issue for next year's European elections are whether voters are presented with a 'cartoon' Europe, or the real one.</p><head rend="h2">Barroso: we need closer political union</head><p><hi rend="#b">And as predicted, Barroso is calling for close political union in Europe.</hi></p><p>Do you want to improve Europe,or give it up, he asks. "If you don't like Europe, improve it".</p><p>We need closer integration on certain issues and "political union must be on the horizon", Barroso declares:</p><quote><p>Europe must focus on where it can add most value. It needs to be big on big things and smaller on smaller things.</p></quote><p>Barroso offers the hand of friendship to the Ukraine, saying Europe won't turn its back on Kiev.</p><quote><p>Barroso hits out at Russia: Ukraine is seeking closer ties to the EU - we can't turn our back on them and ignore their rights</p>— British Influence (@BritInfluence)<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p><hi rend="#b">Barroso touches on the ongoing crisis in Syria</hi>. Europe has sent €1.5bn of aid to the country, and will do everything possible to help refugees fleeing the civil war.</p><p>The use of chemical weapons is an act that deserves clear condemnation and a strong reaction.</p><p>The proposal to put Syria's chemical weapons behind use is a potentially posiotive development, and the Assad regime should respond swiftly, he says.</p><p>Brussels continues to believe that only a political resolution can end the crisis.</p><head rend="h2">Barroso: Europe should be proud</head><p><hi rend="#b">Barroso reminds the Strasbourg parliament that next year will mark the 100th anniversary of the start of the first world war.</hi></p><p>It is because of Europe that former enemies sit around the same table.</p><p>Last year's Nobel Peace Prize reminded us of that achievement. Europe is a project of peace.</p><p>We should not be arrogent, but we should be proud.</p><p>"Does anyone believe that we would have any credibility left in the international community if the eurozone had collapsed," asks Barroso.</p><p>As suspected, Barroso's solution to today's problems is more Europe, rather than less.</p><p>He's admitting that the eurozone crisis has rattled the region, saying</p><quote><p>We have had a real stress test for the EU. There is no more business as usual, no going back to the old normal.</p></quote><p>And citizens won't be convinced by rhetoric and promises....</p><p>At the moment, with markets not fully convinced by the situation in Europe, political risk is the biggest threat, he adds:</p><quote><p>— pascale lamb (@PascaleLamb)</p><ref>#SOTEU</ref>barrosso wants to prevent a jobless recovery but that's exactly what we have. 26 million unemployed is ensured by pursuing austerity<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Europe isn't the problem, says Barroso, it's part of the solution.</p><p><hi rend="#i">Discuss....</hi></p><p>Redefine's Sony Kapoor isn't convinced...</p><quote><p>The State of the European Union is perilous, depressing &amp; fragile, if we are honest</p>— Sony Kapoor (@SonyKapoor)<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>Dear</p>— Sony Kapoor (@SonyKapoor)<ref>#Barroso</ref>, it's one thing to be optimistic, but it would be nice not to overplay it. Also perhaps, a tiny bit of contrition?<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>One single year EU budget represents more money ... than the Marshall plan of old times, says Barroso.</p><p>A few more points.... Barroso says a single market for telecoms that will benefit consumers, and that the EU must crack on with closer trade links with faster-growing markets overseas.</p><p>On the environment he promises progress:</p><quote><p>Europe alone cannot fight climate change, but we must lead the effort.</p></quote><graphic alt="EC president Barroso" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2013/9/11/1378884479017/b72c3d8e-15c2-481e-bd83-a70813051959-620x355.png?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/><p><hi rend="#b">Europe needs to avoid a jobless recovery</hi>, declares Barroso (<hi rend="#i">skating over the point that the eurozone's relentless austerity programmes are blamed by many for causing the unemployment crisis</hi>).</p><p>The EC president declares:</p><quote><p>The current level of unemployment is economically unsustainable, politically untenable and socially unacceptable.</p></quote><p>Onto some proposals...</p><p>Barroso says that European countries need to implement banking reform, starting with the 'single supervisory mechanism' that has been on the table for months.</p><p>These rules will mean that taxpayers are longer in the front line for paying for banks when they fail, he explains.</p><head rend="h2">Barroso: recovery is in sight</head><p>Barroso rattles through some financial facts....Bond spreads are coming down, stock markets are up, Greece is regaining competitiveness and close to achieving a primary budget surplus.</p><p>And here's the key line:</p><quote><hi>For Europe, recovery is within sight. Let's not overestimate the progress, but neither should we underestimate what has been done.</hi></quote><quote><p>EU's Barroso says G-20 summit marked 1st time in years that EU wasn't lectured on how to fight crisis, but got praise &amp; appreciation</p>— Juergen Baetz (@jbaetz)<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>Europe has fought back over the last five years, says Barroso. So the question facing Europe now, is "do we talk it up, or talk it down", asks Barroso.</p><p>But he also concedes that the EU is only starting to persuade citizens that things are getting better.</p><p><hi rend="#b">Barroso says that EU officials received appreciation from other world leaders at the G20 meeting. </hi></p><p>Not because the crisis is resolved, though, because it isn't, Barroso says. But it <hi rend="#b">will</hi> be fixed unless Europe now becomes complacent.</p><p><hi rend="#b">But Europe is fighting back, Barroso says.</hi></p><p>He says that when he met senior economists a year ago, many of them feared a break-up of the eurozone.</p><p>But today, he points out:</p><quote><p>No-one has left, or been forced to leave the eurozone.</p></quote><p>Barroso reminds MEPs that the financial crisis began five years ago with the collapse of Lehman Brothers.</p><p>This triggered a financial crisis, and an unprecendented social crisis in Europe.</p><p>This crisis is still "holding back out households and companies".</p><p>Barroso begins... saying that European voters will give their verdict on the way Europe is performing in just eight months time (at the next European Elections).</p><p>Recently, he says, Europe has been discussed in homes and coffee houses, more than ever before (<hi rend="#i">and we know exactly why that is</hi>)</p><p>Schulz tells MEPs he is hoping for a wide-ranging, lively debate after Barroso's speech. He's also banging on about the 'transparency' of the European parliament, in contrast the the European Council.</p><p>Is he pitching to replace Barroso as head of the EC?!</p><quote><p>I think someone forgot to tell</p>— Peter Spiegel (@SpiegelPeter)<ref>@MartinSchulz</ref>that it's not his State of Union address.<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>All 28 commissioners in plenary to listen to the state of the union speech by president Barroso.</p>— Cecilia Malmström (@MalmstromEU)<ref>#SOTEU</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><head rend="h2">State of the Union begins</head><p>The Head of the European Parliament, Martin Schulz, is introducing President Barroso now...</p><p>This is the scene as MEPs waiting for the Speech to start.... (it's also being broadcast on BBC Parliament, I note)</p><p>A heads-up... UK business secretary Vince Cable is set to warn today that Britain's economic recovery isn't has robust as some, including the chancellor George Osborne, are claiming.</p><p>Our chief political correspondent, <hi rend="#b">Nick Watt</hi>, reports:</p><quote><p>Coalition divisions over the government's central economic policy will be highlighted on Wednesday when Vince Cable criticises George Osbornefor showing complacency over Britain's recovery.</p><p>In a sign of his continuing concerns over the chancellor's handling of the economy, the business secretary will say that this attitude represents one of a series of dangers to the economy.</p><p>Cable will also challenge Osborne, who used a speech on Monday to hail the government's help for the housing market, when he warns of an uncontrollable housing boom.</p><p>Labour said the speech, to be made at a joint government/CBI industrial strategy conference, was "an embarrassing slapdown to George Osborne's deeply complacent and out-of-touch speech".</p></quote><head rend="h2">More here: <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2013/sep/11/vince-cable-george-osborne-complacency">Vince Cable warns against George Osborne's complacency over recovery</ref></head><head rend="h2">How Italian lawmakers delayed showdown over Berlusconi</head><p>Reuters has the details of how Italian politicians backed away from an early decision on Silvio Berlusconi's possible expulsion following last month's tax fraud conviction:</p><quote><p>Italian lawmakers on Tuesday pulled back from a showdown over the political future of Silvio Berlusconi after allies of the billionaire media tycoon threatened to bring down Prime Minister Enrico Letta's unstable ruling coalition.</p><p>A meeting of a cross-party Senate committee charged with deciding whether Berlusconi should be barred from the Senate following a conviction for tax fraud ended without holding a vote, easing political tensions at least for the time being.</p><p>The centre-left Democratic Party (PD), which has the largest presence on the 23-member committee, accepted centre-right demands to slow down hearings on the case, but it maintains its position that Berlusconi must lose his seat.</p><p>The meeting ended at around midnight (2200 GMT). Hearings will resume on Thursday at 1300 GMT, Senator Benedetto Della Vedova of Mario Monti's Civic Choice said.</p><p>"The discussion will start again in the next few days and it will take a long time," the Senate group of the anti-establishment 5-Star Movement, which is most hostile to Berlusconi, said in a tweet as the meeting neared its end.</p></quote><head rend="h2">More here: <ref target="http://uk.reuters.com/article/2013/09/11/uk-italy-berlusconi-idUKBRE9891HC20130911">Italian lawmakers delay showdown over Berlusconi</ref></head><p>Frederik Ducrozet, economist at Crédit Agricole, isn't amused:</p><quote><p>Italian lawmakers are wasting their time with the fate of one man when the country needs cohesion and swift policy implementation</p>— Frederik Ducrozet (@fwred)<ref>#sad</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>The press pack are assembling...</p><quote><p>After getting lost in</p>— Peter Spiegel (@SpiegelPeter)<ref>@Europarl_EN</ref>building in<ref>#Strasbourg</ref>for about 20mins, finally found press room.<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>'s<ref>#SOTEU</ref>speech in 35mins<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><quote><p>For the record, press corps that gets</p>— Peter Spiegel (@SpiegelPeter)<ref>@europarl_en</ref>press room earliest: definitely the<ref>#Danes</ref>!<ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>The State of the Union speech will be streamed live, <ref target="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/president/soteu2013/index_en.htm">here</ref>.</p><head rend="h2">Barroso's speech and UK jobs data loom</head><p><hi rend="#b">Good morning, and welcome to our rolling coverage of the latest events across the world economy, the financial markets, the eurozone and the business world.</hi></p><p>Europe isn't America. But just like the US president, the head of the European Commission gives an annual State of the Nation speech to outline his vision for the EU, and explain where the Union is heading.</p><p><hi rend="#b">José Manuel Barroso</hi> will deliver the speech at the European Parliament in Strasbourg, from 9am CET (8am BST). With the eurozone crisis having been calmed over the last year, Barroso is likely to renew his call for tighter political and economic links to bind Europe together.</p><quote><p>Less than 1 hour to</p>— Pia Ahrenkilde (@ECspokesPia)<ref>@BarrosoEU</ref>'s<ref>#SOTEU</ref>speech in<ref>@Europarl_EN</ref>. follow on<ref>http://t.co/CtVkqVv6kV</ref><ref>pic.twitter.com/mUbTdtaLmR</ref><ref>@EU_Commission</ref><ref>September 11, 2013</ref></quote><p>This is the final State of the Union speech before Barroso's term as EC president expires. But a tub-thumping call for closer union could also remind us of the tensions between member states, over issues from banking union to austerity bailout packages -- and encourage those who want Britain to have a looser link with Europe.</p><p>Barroso will also be taking questions on twitter tomorrow -- using the #askbarroso hashtag.</p><p><hi rend="#b">The other key event this morning is the latest UK unemployment data, due at 9.30am. </hi></p><p>It could show that the headline unemployment rate has fallen, but also confirm that real wages continue to lag inflation. Both are important issues. <hi rend="#b">Living standards</hi> is rising up the political agenda, while <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor">Bank of England</ref> is committed to keeping <hi rend="#b">interest rates</hi> at record lows until the unemployment rate drops from 7.8% to 7%.</p><p>I'll be tracking Barroso's speech, and the jobs data, in the blog, along with other events through the day. <hi rend="#b">That will include political developments in Italy</hi>, where last night a committee decided not to take an immediate decision in Silvio Berluconi's possible expulsion from the Senate....</p></main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>