<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2010-10-16" description="Outspoken anchorman Michele Santoro says the prime minister's influence lies behind his two-week ban by the RAI state TV network" fingerprint="bb384a78100eeb07" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Television industry,World news" title="Berlusconi 'vendetta' takes Italy's Paxman off air again" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/17/michele-santoro-silvio-berlusconi-rai-television">
<main>
<p>His fans see him as Italy's Jeremy Paxman, an aggressive but penetrating TV anchorman. Prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who owns most of the country's private channels and wields indirect control over the state network, RAI, sees him as a dangerous leftie. Meet Michele Santoro, the temporarily banned hero of Italian current affairs broadcasting.</p>
<p>Santoro, who presents Italy's top current affairs show, <hi rend="#i">Annozero</hi>, was handed a two-week suspension last week by RAI's managing director, Mauro Masi.</p>
<p>The outspoken broadcaster had accused the RAI management of denying contracts to his co-presenters and appeared to half-utter the Italian equivalent of "go fuck yourself" on air. But his two-show ban, he claims, is to do with a vendetta waged against him by the prime minister, whose speeches Santoro once compared with those of Mussolini.</p>
<p>In his latest show, Santoro addressed Berlusconi about his suspension: "We are the top current affairs show on Italian TV, which is why you – who I have always respected – are so put out. We are not losing, we are strong, and that is a huge problem." The grey-haired presenter then appealed to his audience to sign a petition against his suspension.</p>
<p>Unusually among Italian broadcasters, Santoro has made a habit of probing the dark corners of Berlusconi's political and business empire, covering corrupt contracting allegations, supposed dalliances with prostitutes, and alleged past links to the mafia.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has shrugged off countless inquiries. But what reportedly enrages him is the audience ratings Santoro wins – numbers that grow every time the prime minister allegedly urges RAI functionaries to sabotage the show.</p>
<p>When <hi rend="#i">Annozero</hi>, alongside all other political talk shows, was pulled off RAI by the government ahead of regional elections in March – officially to guarantee balanced broadcasting – Santoro struck a deal with Sky, opening his show with the Mussolini comparison.</p>
<p>Masi, who joined RAI 18 months ago after serving in Berlusconi's cabinet office, has also become a target. When he was wiretapped in a criminal probe and the transcripts were leaked, Santoro delighted in revealing how Masi had said that "not even in Zimbabwe" did governments work so hard to censor the press. Masi made his comment after an official at Italy's TV watchdog complained that Berlusconi rang him regularly to try to force him to axe <hi rend="#i">Annozero</hi>.</p>
<p>"The clash between Santoro and Masi is a clash between two megalomaniacs," wrote <hi rend="#i">Corriere della Sera</hi>'s Aldo Grasso. "The first believes he is the incarnation of freedom of expression; the latter, who knew nothing of TV until recently, believes he is the absolute boss of public television."</p>
<p>"It's me or Masi," Santoro responded last week as the battle of nerves between the two escalated. With record ratings of six million for <hi rend="#i">Annozero</hi> on Thursday, the smart money is on a new boss at RAI.</p>
<p>For Santoro, all this represents a remarkable comeback. Many thought his career was over in 2002, when his show was cancelled after Berlusconi accused him and two other presenters of making criminal use of RAI. He did not broadcast again for four years.</p>
<p>After news of his latest ban broke, supporters of Gianfranco Fini, Berlusconi's former ally, were quick to claim that the real bias on RAI is on the flagship news programme, where a new director, Augusto Minzolini, has made on-air speeches praising Berlusconi as a revolutionary. Berlusconi claimed last year that it was unacceptable for state TV to criticise the government.</p>
<p>Historically, RAI's rosters are full of appointments by politicians, but never before has the prime minister controlled its commercial rivals as well.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's stranglehold, which has helped to push Italy to 72nd place, just behind Tonga, on the Freedom House ranking of press freedom, has been bolstered by the sustained attacks on Berlusconi's foes by <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi>, the newspaper owned by Berlusconi's brother. But even <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi> was forced to admit that Masi had been outwitted by Santoro, complaining that Berlusconi's critics at RAI were now stronger than ever.</p>
<p>Nino Rizzo Nervo, a board member at RAI, said Santoro would beat his two-show suspension. "He will appeal and I am certain he will win," he said.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>