<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Philip Willan" categories="World news" date="2003-08-22" description="The Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, will embark on a fence-mending exercise tonight when he attends an opera in the company of the German chancellor." fingerprint="7d8f802f9200e709" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Germany,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi makes friendly overtures to Schröder" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/aug/22/germany.italy">
<main>
<p>The Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, will embark on a fence-mending exercise tonight when he attends an opera in the company of the German chancellor.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi is expected to join Gerhard Schröder at a performance of Bizet's Carmen in the Roman amphitheatre at Verona, along with Romano Prodi, the president of the European commission and his probable rival at the next general election.</p>
<p>The diplomatic initiative with Germany's leader was brokered by Mr Prodi and the leftwing mayor of Verona, Paolo Zanotto, and will demonstrate publicly that the two men have put the tensions of early July behind them.</p>
<p>Mr Schröder cancelled his Italian holiday after Mr Berlusconi's quip about a German MEP being suited to a film role as a Nazi concentration camp guard.</p>
<p>Leftwing opponents of Mr Berlusconi are reportedly preparing to disrupt the concert, though some hecklers say the most effective protest would be prolonged ironic applause.</p>
<p>Opera will also be on the menu the following weekend when Mr Berlusconi plays host, at his luxury villa in Sardinia, to the Russian president, Vladimir Putin.</p>
<p>The music-loving Italian leader has reportedly secured the services of the tenor Andrea Bocelli for a private concert in the gardens of Villa Certosa, with arias from Tosca and Turandot alternating with popular Neapolitan songs. Mr Berlusconi, who remembers the skills he developed in his youth as a cruise ship crooner, may even break into song himself - his job has not prevented him recording a CD with the Neapolitan singer Mariano Apicella.</p>
<p>Nothing is being left to chance for Mr Putin's visit. Security will be strengthened by the presence of three Russian warships on a goodwill visit to the Italian navy. And, on the aesthetic side, modifications to the villa's gardens have included an enlarged lake and the addition of 400 species of cacti.</p>
<p>As the private owner of Italy's equivalent of Camp David or Chequers - Villa Certosa is just the most welcoming of seven residences - Mr Berlusconi has something of an advantage over his poorer political rivals as he embarks on what the newspaper Corriere della Sera has dubbed his "bel canto diplomacy".</p>
<p>The villa has also hosted political colleagues from the European Popular party and heads of state and government from eastern Europe, as well as Mr Putin's teenage daughters last summer.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi clearly hopes that his billionaire diplomacy will consolidate his position as a big player on the international scene.</p>
<p>He will be less happy if people remember that his early real estate acquisitions in Sardinia were made under the guidance of Flavio Carboni, a local businessman who is also a leading suspect in the murder 21 years ago of the banker Roberto Calvi.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>