<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Football" date="2012-12-05" description="Mario Balotelli's agent does not believe any Italian club could afford to buy the Manchester City striker" fingerprint="78cff129fc7bed1d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Mario Balotelli,Manchester City,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Football,Transfer window,Sport" title="Mario Balotelli is 'as valuable as the Mona Lisa' says striker's agent" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2012/dec/05/mario-balotelli-mona-lisa-agent">
<main>
<p>Mario Balotelli's agent does not believe any Italian club could afford to buy the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/manchestercity">Manchester City</ref> striker, or pay his wages.</p>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2012/nov/16/football-transfer-rumours-mario-balotelli">Speculation has increased about the former Internazionale player</ref>, who has started just one of City's last eight matches in all competitions through a combination of injury and non-selection.</p>
<p>The Milan president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, fuelled the rumours on Tuesday by confirming his interest in the 22-year-old ahead of their Champions League defeat to Zenit St Petersburg. But the City forward's agent, Mino Raiola, was quick to deny the link, saying Milan could not afford his client.</p>
<p>"No Italian club could afford him," he told Sky Sport Italia. "Balotelli is as valuable as the Mona Lisa. And City have been very clear – they don't want to sell."</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> head coach, Massimiliano Allegri, is a confirmed admirer and hinted he would like to see Balotelli play alongside the youngster Stephan El Shaarawy, who has scored 14 goals in all competitions this season.</p>
<p>Allegri said: "I think they have done great things with the Italian national team. [Balotelli] is a great player with extraordinary physical and technical qualities. However, given his qualities, I believe he has thrown away a few years of his career."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>