<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Leigh Phillips" categories="Business" date="2011-08-21" description="MPs and unions concerned over unelected EU bodies demanding governments impose cuts" fingerprint="8ffec19719732c96" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Business,Greece,Italy,Ireland,Portugal,European Central Bank,Silvio Berlusconi,Angela Merkel,Nicolas Sarkozy,Global economy,Economics,Europe,Austerity" title="ECB austerity drive raises fears for democratic accountability in Europe" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/aug/22/debt-crisis-europe">
<main>
<p>The EU's attempts to deal with the financial crisis by imposing austerity on member states will further alienate voters already disenchanted at the lack of accountability in Brussels and Frankfurt, leading European politicians and union leaders have warned.</p>
<p>In a succession of interventions aimed at appeasing markets and shoring up the balance sheets of eurozone countries, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> (ECB) has demanded austerity policies in Greece, Portugal, Ireland and Italy, in the latter case even telling Silvio Berlusconi which measures must be instituted when and how. The Italian prime minister acquiesced, complaining that his administration was being made to look like "an occupied government".</p>
<p>Antonio Di Pietro, a leading liberal MP, said: "Italy is under the tutelage of the EU, and a country under tutelage is not a free and democratic one."</p>
<p>Paul Murphy, an Irish MEP, told the Guardian that there had been a "massive shift away from democratic accountability since the start of the crisis". He added: "There needs to be a check on the enormous power of the ECB, which is unelected, and has basically held a government to ransom."</p>
<p>The European Public Sector Union, Europe's largest trade union federation, has accused the ECB of directing Italian fiscal and labour policy in secret. Jan Willem Goudriaan, its deputy general secretary, said: "Europe cannot be governed through secret letters of bankers, officials or an unaccountable body."</p>
<p>Goudriaan is also worried about the range of proposals on the table for deeper eurozone economic integration, all of which involve removing fiscal policy – spending decisions on schools, hospitals, traffic lights, the police, almost everything that a government is responsible for – from the realm of parliamentary debate.</p>
<p>"It is very worrying that few address the democratic nature of the eurozone's proposed economic government," he said.</p>
<p>Last week, the German chancellor, Angela Merkel, and French president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref>, announced that they would push for the creation of a eurozone economic council to police the austerity measures of governments, to be headed by Herman Van Rompuy, the EU president. Separately, Germany's economy minister, Philipp Rösler, has proposed the creation of a new, unelected EU institution, a "stability council" that would impose automatic sanctions on countries that do not adhere to rigid budget discipline and pro-business labour policies.</p>
<p>And the head of the ECB, Jean-Claude Trichet, has called for a European finance ministry, charged with dictating to countries their spending policies.</p>
<p>"All these proposals, discussions about economic government, are about undermining democracy in order to impose a European shock doctrine," said Murphy. "EU elites need to remove points of pressure that can be mounted on governments. If the mass of people are opposed to austerity, they can mount pressure on governments to hold that in check. So the only way it can then be imposed is undemocratically."</p>
<p>Yiorgos Vassalos of Corporate Europe Observatory, a Brussels-based pro-transparency group, expressed concern at a "clear trend" in favour of unelected institutions taking over decision-making. "European powers [are] distancing themselves from voters while at the same time [there is] a growing tendency towards building closer relationships with corporate and specifically financial lobbies.</p>
<p>"These two trends are explosive and can only lead to a loss of legitimacy for the EU institutions."</p>
<p>Philip White, of the London-based Centre for European Reform, explains that EU leaders are torn between meeting the demands of the markets and upholding democratic norms: "The stage we are at in the eurozone crisis presents politicians with a deeply uncomfortable position: trying to convince markets that they are taking the necessary action to place economies on a more sustainable path and that the euro is here to stay while on the other hand to persuade their electorates that they are respecting democratic traditions."</p>
<p>"If you look at the debt and deficit numbers, if the EU were a unitary, democratic state, as a whole it is in a perfectly manageable situation, but it's not one, so all these questions make the crisis much more difficult to handle. The crisis is less an economic crisis than a political, democratic and institutional one."</p>
<p>"It's going to become more and more difficult to disguise from voters what is happening."</p>
<p>Monica Frassoni, president of the European Greens, is a staunch European federalist, but she is frightened by what sees occurring.</p>
<p>"The Greens have always been very pro-European, very in favour of deeper European integration and European governance, but this is very different from simply having an EU finance minister without any democratic accountability. There is a real issue of a loss of sovereignty of member states, stamping out the capabilities of governments. This is not democracy at the EU level," she said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>