<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian sport" categories="Football" date="2015-07-03" description="Milan president Silvio Berlusconi has demanded Sinisa Mihajlovic lead the club back into the Champions League next season" fingerprint="7a5ae67d0882db34" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Milan,Champions League,Football,Silvio Berlusconi,European club football,Serie A,Sport" title="Milan must qualify for Champions League, says Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/jul/03/milan-silvio-berlusconi-champions-league-sinisa-mihajlovic">
<main>
<p>The Milan president <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has demanded that the new manager Sinisa Mihajlovic lead the club back into the Champions League next season after officially presenting the Serbian at the club’s preseason training camp.</p>
<p>“It’s categorically imperative that Milan return to the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/championsleague">Champions League</ref> and Europe next season,” said Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Mihajlovic, who stood down as Sampdoria manager last month, was appointed two weeks ago and becomes Milan’s fourth manager in less than two years following the sackings of Filippo Inzaghi, Massimiliano Allegri and Clarence Seedorf.</p>
<p><ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2011/may/31/serie-a-season-review-bandinis">Since winning the Serie A in 2011</ref>, Milan’s fortunes have declined and the <hi rend="#i">Rossoneri </hi>have failed to qualify for Europe in recent years, finishing eighth and 10th in the past two seasons.</p>
<p>However, the club have spent considerably in recent days, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/jul/02/milan-luiz-adriano-shakhtar-donetsk-brazil">signing Shakhtar Donetsk’s leading all-time scorer Luiz Adriano for €8m (£5.7m)</ref> and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/jul/02/carlos-bacca-milan-sevilla">are close to confirming a €30m deal for Sevilla’s Carlos Bacca</ref>.</p>
<p>Mihajlovic has signed a two-year contract, with the option for a third season, at a reported €2.5m a year and the former Internazionale player said on Friday that “I often played against Milan, so I know how much respect this shirt represents.”</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>