<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roy Greenslade" categories="Media" date="2012-09-14" description="Roy Greenslade: It's no wonder that British newspapers and magazines have refused to run paparazzi pictures published in France" fingerprint="7ad1954b8c35c6c0" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Catherine, Princess of Wales,Magazines,France,Privacy &amp; the media,Privacy,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Prince William,Prince Harry,Diana, Princess of Wales,News photography,The People,Daily Star,The Sun,Press Complaints Commission,Amanda Holden,Bauer,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Not again! History repeated as magazine runs topless Kate pictures" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/greenslade/2012/sep/14/duchess-of-cambridge-magazines">
<main>
<p>Here we go again... now it's <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2012/sep/14/kate-william-furious-topless-photographs">Kate, Duchess of Cambridge, getting the paparazzi treatment</ref>, just as her late mother-in-law did 15 years ago and her brother-in-law did just a couple of weeks ago.</p>
<p>No wonder the Duchess and her husband, Prince William, <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-19595221">are reported to be furious.</ref> With memories of Princess Diana in mind, they must feel history is repeating itself.</p>
<p>The statement issued by the Palace this morning, calling the privacy intrusion "grotesque and totally unjustifiable", makes an explicit reference to Diana:</p>
<quote>
<p>"The incident is reminiscent of the worst excesses of the press and paparazzi during the life of Diana, Princess of Wales, and all the more upsetting to The Duke and Duchess for being so."</p>
</quote>
<p>Clearly, British newspapers and magazines refused to publish the topless pictures of Kate because it would be a blatant breach of the editors' code of practice to do so.</p>
<p>The photos were obviously taken without the Duchess's consent, and they were snapped in a place where she and her husband had, to quote the code, "a reasonable expectation of privacy."</p>
<p>As for "the public interest", there is no earthly way of constructing an argument to justify publication on such grounds.</p>
<p>The Kate pictures are different from those involving <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/prince-harry">Prince Harry</ref>, who was pictured last month while naked in a Las Vegas hotel.</p>
<p>Though <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/sun">The Sun</ref> advanced a public interest defence for publishing the Harry picture, it was very specific to the circumstances.</p>
<p>Aside from its argument that the pictures were "in the public domain" by virtue of having been published on many websites, the paper claimed there were security implications and questions about his position in the army. <ref target="http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/sun_says/article4502239.ece">"We believe Harry has compromised his own privacy,"</ref> it said.</p>
<p>That paper thin argument to justify publication would not be possible in relation to the Kate pictures.</p>
<p>Nor is it a matter of newspapers giving special privileges to royalty. One key decision taken by the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/pcc">Press Complaints Commission</ref> about sneak pictures of people in a private place dates back to 2001 and involved the DJ Sara Cox. She was pictured nude on a private beach on an island in the Seychelles.</p>
<p>The PCC did not adjudicate because <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2002/feb/25/thepeople.mondaymediasection">it convinced the offending paper, The People, to apologise</ref>, and Cox went on to sue the paper, which eventually<ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2003/jun/07/pressandpublishing.privacy"> paid her and her husband £50,000 in an out-of-court settlement.</ref></p>
<p>Similarly, Amanda Holden and her then husband, Les Dennis, <ref target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2001/dec/21/pressandpublishing.humanrights">were paid £40,000 in an out-of-court settlement </ref>after the Daily Star published sneak photographs of them. Neither were legal precedents, because they didn't go to trial.</p>
<p>The editors' code certainly did draw a line between public places and private places, offering a large measure of protection for the latter.</p>
<p>It is interesting that the pictures of Kate and William are appearing in a French magazine because <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/france">France</ref> has very strict privacy laws. Presumably the magazine, Closer, is willing to take the legal heat should the prince and his wife decide to sue.</p>
<p>It is also sobering to recall that Diana's death in 1997 occurred in France when she was being pursued by the paparazzi. (Incidentally, she was not pictured topless. She was pictured in a bikini while pregnant - by newspaper staff photographers - and there were many other bikini shots taken by paparazzi over the years).</p>
<p>Finally, some callers to radio phone-in programmes this morning have indicated that there could be a public backlash should any British publication dare to publish sneak pictures of the Duchess. I would doubt that. Hypocrisy in this matter runs deep.</p>
<p>But the British-based version of Closer - published by Bauer Media - had better watch out. Despite its French namesake being owned by a different company - Silvio Berlusconi's Mondadori - it could just find itself being punished by a boycott.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>