<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Owen Gibson" categories="Football" date="2006-01-12" description="The latest move in a multimillion-pound game of chess between Silvio Berlusconi and Rupert Murdoch has seen Juventus used as a pawn." fingerprint="130ca9ffeaa76e55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European club football,Football,Sport,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Football: Berlusconi's Juve move leaves Europe on edge" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2006/jan/12/europeanfootball.sport">
<main>
<p>The latest move in a multimillion-pound game of chess between Italy's prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and the News Corp media mogul Rupert Murdoch has used one of the world's most glamorous football clubs as a pawn.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's Italian media group Mediaset last month paid €218m (£150m) for the rights to show live coverage of Juventus's home games for the 2007-08 and 2008-09 seasons. In recent years Mediaset has been going head to head with Murdoch's Sky Italia in the battle for football-mad Italian viewers and the soap opera has been given added spice by the fact that Berlusconi - who also owns Milan - and Murdoch were friends who were once believed to have a pact not to compete with one another.</p>
<p>The relationship between Serie A's biggest clubs and the broadcasters that pour money into the game has long been a complex one. Unlike this country Italian clubs negotiate their own deals with broadcasters. Consequently the biggest clubs can rake in large sums while smaller clubs have to settle for as little as €3m a season. Just as Premier League football had driven the growth of Sky over here, Murdoch sought to repeat the trick in Italy when he launched the pay TV satellite service Sky Italia 2½ years ago after buying its main rival there. For $467m (£265m) a year the deal covered all the biggest matches, helping to attract 3.4 million subscribers.</p>
<p>But according to the European Commission competition ruling under which News Corp was allowed to merge Stream and Telepiu to form Sky Italia, all of its rights contracts must be limited to two years and apply only to satellite. That left the door open for Berlusconi's Mediaset to launch its own innovative pay-per-view operation 12 months ago.</p>
<p>First Berlusconi's government announced the most ambitious timetable in Europe for switching off the country's analogue signal and moving to an all-digital landscape by 2006. Then it agreed to subsidise the set-top boxes required. In the meantime Mediaset agreed separate deals with the biggest clubs to show their games over digital terrestrial and offered fans the opportunity to buy them on a game-by-game basis by purchasing viewing cards from tobacconists and corner shops. The cards have proved a success and sales of DTT set-top boxes (the same technology as Freeview in the UK) have begun to take off. More than 3m Italian homes now have DTT technology.</p>
<p>Despite a continuing probe by Italian anti-trust authorities, Mediaset is pressing ahead with extending its deals with Italy's biggest clubs beyond the two years that Sky Italia is permitted. The deal with Juventus, expected to be the first in a string of contract extensions with the big clubs, guarantees live coverage until 2009 and they have also paid an extra €30m for an option on the 2009-10 season.</p>
<p>The battle for Italian pay TV subscribers is being watched keenly by the biggest clubs around Europe, as they consider whether collective selling or individual deals best serve their interests. The issue became live again in the UK when many speculated that the only way Malcolm Glazer could afford the interest payments on the loans he secured to buy Manchester United would be for the club to break away and negotiate its own TV deals.</p>
<p>The Premier League quashed that speculation after its own meeting with Glazer and instead points to Italy as an example of the damage the lack of a collective agreement can do. Despite Chelsea's dominance this season, the Premier League chief executive Richard Scudamore has long maintained that it is the power of collective bargaining that has made the Premier League so consistently watchable and an attractive proposition for fans and broadcasters.</p>
<p>"It enables us to keep a competitive balance while also offering sufficient rewards for the top clubs to compete with their European counterparts," said a spokesman. All the clubs buy into the idea that a strong league is essential, he said, while the EC had also now accepted the argument that collective selling was good for the game and the fans.</p>
<p>On a philosophical level the Premier League argues that much of the value of the rights resides in the fact that the matches are taking place in the context of the competition. Chelsea v Arsenal has far less value as a pre-season friendly than as a title decider, in other words. Whereas Chelsea last season received 1.6 times as much as the bottom club Southampton, the ratio in Italy and Spain where deals are negotiated individually can be as much as nine times.</p>
<p>Talk to them individually and some clubs will hint that, as technology enables more and more games to be shown on a variety of platforms, more rights will revert to them and as a result they will increase the revenues they bring in individually. But whenever changes to the current system are mooted they tend to be shouted down. Three years ago Manchester United argued for a greater share of international rights revenues and were outvoted 19-1 by other chairmen.</p>
<p>The experience of Italy and Spain, where multi-layered negotiations have resulted in a tangled web of deals, have made the Premier League more determined to maintain the principle of collective selling. Mediaset's success with pay-per-view cards could have another consequence come the next round of domestic Premier League rights deals. Setanta, the ambitious pay-TV operator that has poached a brace of key Sky executives to lead its bid for Premier League rights, already offers Scottish Premierleague games through digital terrestrial television in a similar way to Mediaset.</p>
<p>Any successful bid it makes for one of the six packages of live Premier League matches available, due to be tendered in March, could well extend the idea to English football.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Rights around Europe</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">England Negotiated collectively</hi>
</p>
<p>In the current deal Sky show 138 live matches per year. Altogether the Premier League received around £1.6bn from broadcasters.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Greece Negotiated separately</hi>
</p>
<p>Live rights for the biggest clubs are scattered between broadcasters. Alpha TV, for example, has the rights to Apollon Kalamaria, Chalkydona, Iraklis Thessaloniki, Olympiakos, Neos Panionios Athens and Skoda Xanthi home matches.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">France Negotiated collectively</hi>
</p>
<p>Canal Plus, the largest pay-TV operator in France, paid €1.8bn (£1.2bn) for exclusive rights to Ligue 1 in December 2004. Some analysts think the pay-TV group overpaid.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Germany Negotiated collectively</hi>
</p>
<p>Pay-TV operator Premiere has the live coverage. Highlights are shared between the free-to-air broadcasters. Altogether the Bundesliga brought in €1.26bn (£866m) from broadcasters.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Spain Negotiated collectively</hi>
</p>
<p>After the merger of the two biggest pay-TV services to form Sogecable, La Liga clubs agreed to negotiate collectively for the first time. But the lion's share of the revenue goes to the bigger clubs. The deal is up for renewal next year.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>