<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Dominic Fifield" categories="Football" date="2009-05-25" description="Milan's president, Silvio Berlusconi, has said he will make a decision on Carlo Ancelotti's future after the game against Fiorentina on Sunday" fingerprint="64de5a3b18a2c34f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Chelsea,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Football,Sport,Carlo Ancelotti" title="Chelsea forced to wait another week on Carlo Ancelotti decision" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2009/may/25/carlo-ancelotti-chelsea-milan">
<main>
<p>Chelsea's pursuit of the Milan manager, Carlo Ancelotti, is set to drag on for a further week after the <hi rend="#i">Rossoneri</hi>'s president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, admitted that the issue will only be addressed once it is known whether the club has qualified for the Champions League.</p>
<p>Defeat to Roma at San Siro yesterday left <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> still uncertain of a top-three finish, and a return to Europe's elite club competition without the need to play in a qualifying round, with a potentially awkward trip to the fourth-placed Fiorentina, three points adrift, to come on Serie A's final afternoon this weekend.</p>
<p>Berlusconi and the club's managing director, Adriano Galliani, had hoped to make an announcement on Sunday though the side's inability to secure the critical win will prolong the state of limbo. "Milan have not chosen their coach yet [for next season]," said Berlusconi in the wake of the wasteful 3-2 home defeat to Roma. "We have promised, again, to sit around a table with Ancelotti at the end of the season and take decisions that will be good for Milan and good for Ancelotti. He is a serious individual and part of the family here, so we will sit down and make a decision together at the end of the season."</p>
<p>Ancelotti's representatives agreed terms in principle with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/chelsea">Chelsea</ref> over a three-year deal at Stamford Bridge in talks last month, though the Italian has sent out mixed messages over whether he intends to fulfil his commitment in recent weeks as his potential parting of the ways with Milan has loomed larger.</p>
<p>In the build-up to the Roma game he stated to the Italian media both that he was "100% certain" he would still be the Milan's manager next season but, in the same breath, that he would also welcome "the chance to coach Chelsea" and had spoken with the club's owner, Roman Abramovich.</p>
<p>Chelsea remain confident of prising Milan's manager of eight years away from San Siro as a long-term replacement for Guus Hiddink, who is due to return to his duties with the Russian national team next week. The Premier League club hope to make an announcement after the FA Cup final against Everton on Saturday.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>