<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Stephanie Kirchgaessner" categories="World news" date="2015-05-19" description="Italian regulators to investigate rights deal hatched in June 2014 between rival broadcasters owned by Rupert Murdoch and Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="58c88999c121fddc" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Serie A,Sky,Media,Television industry,European club football,Football,Sport,World news,Europe,Rupert Murdoch,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Inquiry launched into Sky Italia and Mediaset over Serie A football rights" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/may/19/inquiry-sky-italia-mediaset-serie-a-football-rights">
<main>
<p>Italian regulators have launched an investigation into possible collusion between rivals Sky Italia and Mediaset – the country’s two major broadcasters – in connection with the 2014 sale of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/serieafootball">Serie A</ref> football broadcasting rights.</p>
<p>The Italian financial authority, the Guardia di Finanza, said it had conducted “inspections” in six locations in regard to the sale of TV rights to the media groups owned respectively by Rupert Murdoch and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, but declined to comment on the exact nature of the investigation.</p>
<p>The competition authority, which was also involved in the inspections, said it had opened an inquiry into the broadcasters and professional football leagues in connection with bids for Serie A matches during 2015-2018. </p>
<p>It said it was investigating possible “sharing agreements” between <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/bskyb">Sky</ref> and Mediaset and that it appeared that the final agreement between the parties did not necessarily reflect the bids that had been made.</p>
<p>It said it was investigating the possible restriction of competition, against EU rules, and the possible exclusion of new entrants into the market. The authority said the probe would be finished by 30 April 2016.</p>
<p>Sky Italia is a full subsidiary of Sky, Europe’s largest pay-TV broadcaster by number of customers, and its largest shareholder is Murdoch’s 21st Century Fox. Mediaset is an Italian media conglomerate owned by Berlusconi, the former Italian prime minister.</p>
<p>Both groups share TV rights to air football matches in Serie A, Italy’s top league. </p>
<p>Recent media reports have speculated that Sky had approached Mediaset about a possible takeover of the company’s unprofitable pay-TV business, Mediaset Premium, but the offer was rejected. According to a report by Reuters, the groups <ref target="http://uk.reuters.com/article/2015/04/24/uk-sky-mediaset-pay-tv-idUKKBN0NF1XD20150424">remained in informal contact</ref> over a possible deal.</p>
<p>Sky Italia said in a statement that it was cooperating fully with the authorities and was “confident that it operated with integrity throughout the process”.</p>
<p>“The final agreement regarding the rights to Serie A for 2015-2018 differed to the initial result when the bids were opened,” the company said.</p>
<p>“It is entirely understandable therefore that the [competition authority in Italy] should wish to satisfy itself as to the behaviour of all parties involved.”</p>
<p>Mediaset did not return a request for comment.</p>
<p>The investigation centres on a deal that was hatched in June 2014 between the Serie A football clubs, Sky Italia, and Mediaset. </p>
<p>The terms of the deal kept in place the previous TV deal, with Sky Italia preserving the right to air all live matches on satellite, and Mediaset winning all rights on digital terrestrial.</p>
<p>Under the previous contract, the rights were valued at €2.487bn (£1.8bn), while the new contract generated €2.829bn for the football clubs, an increase of 14%, according to a 2014 analysis by Tim Westcott of IHS Technology.</p>
<p>“This is a respectable return, though less than the 23% France’s LFP [football league] achieved earlier this year and much less than the last auctions for the Premier League in the UK and Ireland and the Bundesliga in Germany,” Westcott wrote.</p>
<p>He added that Mediaset appeared to have got “slightly the better” of the new rights agreement because it was awarded coverage of all 20 Serie A clubs from the start of the season and would have exclusive rights for Uefa Champions League games in Italy for three years.</p>
<p>The probe was revealed on the same day that news broke of another scandal in Italian football. About 50 people were arrested on Tuesday and 70 are under investigation over a match-fixing scandal in Italy’s lower leagues – the Lega Pro and Serie D, the third and fourth Italian football tiers. The match-fixing was allegedly linked to the Calabrian-based ’Ndrangheta mafia.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>