<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-08-04" description="Barbara Berlusconi is first family member to speak out on scandals damaging Italian prime minister" fingerprint="2eb0432bd5f6972d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Media,Magazines,Europe" title="Berlusconi daughter 'amazed' at father's links with teenager" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/aug/04/berlusconi-barbara-vanity-italy">
<main>
<p>One of Silvio Berlusconi's daughters has publicly distanced herself from the Italian prime minister, saying she was amazed to learn of her 72-year-old father's relationship with a teenage girl.</p>
<p>The interview is the first given by any of Berlusconi's children since the first of the scandals broke when his second wife, Veronica Lario, announced in May that she intended to file for divorce. At almost the same time, it was reported that the prime minister had attended the 18th birthday party of an aspiring actor and model, Noemi Letizia.</p>
<p>"I was amazed," Barbara Berlusconi said in an interview to be published in the Italian edition of Vanity Fair tomorrow, adding that public officials should enhance moral values and that they cannot make "a distinction between [their] public life and private life".</p>
<p>Asked about the links between her father and Letizia, Barbara, the eldest child of Berlusconi's second marriage, said: "My story is that of a girl who lived her youth in a normal and tranquil fashion. I never frequented old men. These are psychological links of which I have no experience."</p>
<p>Barbara, 25, who has two children and is unmarried, said of her parents' marriage problems: "I want to be close to both my parents, because what does not come out is that their suffering is profound and touches them both."</p>
<p>Asked whether her parents' break-up signalled the end of a great love, she told the magazine: "I am sure that it was for mamma. But certainly in 30 years of life together, they have always had their mutual good at heart."</p>
<p>Asked about the contrast between the prime minister's conduct and his enduring popularity, she said: "I think that a society expresses a common sense of morality. Political representatives, who are expected to govern well, [and] make the community prosper, are also expected to safeguard the values that [the community] expresses, possibly to raise them. I do not believe therefore that a politician can permit himself a distinction between public life and private life."</p>
<p>Berlusconi has never fulfilled a pledge to explain in parliament his relationship with Letizia, who applied for a job on one of his television channels.</p>
<p>The initial scandal over the connection between them was subsequently overshadowed by another concerning parties at his villa on Sardinia and in his Rome residence attended by escorts allegedly paid by a businessman seeking health service contracts. One of the escorts, who has said that she spent the night with Berlusconi in the hope of an increased payment, has supplied prosecutors with recordings she claims to have made in the prime minister's bedroom and elsewhere.</p>
<p>The prosecutors are investigating the businessman on suspicion of corruption and the aiding and abetting of prostitution. Though Berlusconi's lawyer has questioned the authenticity of the tapes, the prime minister himself has not done so. Last month, he acknowledged that he was "no saint".</p>
<p>Polls have shown that, although Berlusconi's popularity has fallen since the scandals erupted, it remains high for a prime minister in the throes of a recession. His approval rating among the electorate is still running at almost 50%.</p>
<p>The only previous references by the prime minister's children to their parents' divorce came after Dario Franceschini, the leader of the Democratic party, Italy's biggest opposition group, asked voters whether they would want their children to be brought up by Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Barbara joined her younger sister, Eleonora, and younger brother Luigi in an indignant statement declaring: "We feel that we grew up, and were brought up, in a balanced family environment that was strong on principles."</p>
<p>But it is no surprise that Barbara eventually chose to speak out. She has plenty of form in criticising her father, which has made her an unlikely heroine of the left. Last year, she said the conflict of interest between Berlusconi's vast business empire and his political role was damaging to public life.</p>
<p>"I am convinced that the question needs to be regulated," she said. She has also refused to join her father's Forza Italia political party.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>