<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Oliver Laughland; Guardian staff reporter" categories="From the Guardian" date="2011-07-15" description="Oliver Laughland on the people and stories in the media spotlight in the last seven days" fingerprint="865a63bd9922fc09" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,George Michael" title="Our pick of the week: The story, the stat, the quote, the tweet" url="http://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2011/jul/15/our-pick-of-the-week">
<main>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">The story</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Bunga bunga cuts</hi>
</p>
<p>What happens when you cross the shock doctrine with a bunga bunga party? The Italian austerity package of course. Proof that not everything in the news is about Rupert Murdoch or Fern Britton's midriff, the Italian government forces through a cuts package imposed after the IMF called for "more front-loaded spending measures". And who do most commentators blame for the sorry state of affairs that's left nearly one in 10 unemployed? The man who, according to the Economist, "screwed an entire country", Mr Berlusconi himself.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">The stat</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">One in 10 pets ...</hi>
</p>
<p>... have their own social media presence. Poor animal owners, they just don't help themselves, do they? Although one "social media expert" told the press that networking pets was a "natural" phenomenon, it's hard to see how signing your dog up to Facebook or your cat to an online animal dating service is anything other than a cry for help.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">The quote</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Niko Alm</hi>
</p>
<p>"The only dogma allowed in the Church of the Flying Spaghetti Monster is the rejection of dogma." The words of a modern day Nietzsche? Maybe not. But an adherent of "pastafarianism" who adorns his head with a pasta strainer to show the faith, has at least got his religious order past the Austrian transport authorities as his new driving licence has a photo of him crowned with the strainer. Next stop, apparently, is to get the religion sanctioned by the government.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">The tweet</hi>
</head>
<p>"Like i said, glad to help... :))" The use of a double smiley emoticon feels like proof that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/music/georgemichael">George Michael</ref> is causing trouble for News International as he helps the police with Operation Weeting. The singer had previously used Twitter to divulge how Rebekah Brooks had turned up uninvited to his party, offering him tantalising details of how the News of the World had landed so many scoops about his private life.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>