<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2015-05-25" description="He’s holding his cute dog, he’s watching Eurovision – bunga bunga-loving Berlusconi is in the midst of a posting frenzy. And it all has a political purpose" fingerprint="3eb0d22ab864c725" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Instagram,Technology,Europe,UK news" title="Uh-oh. Silvio Berlusconi is on Instagram | John Hooper" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/25/silvio-berlusconi-instagram-talian-prime-minister">
<main>
<p>He’s back! Last week, Silvio Berlusconi made his debut <ref target="https://instagram.com/silvioberlusconi2015/">on Instagram</ref>. Since then, he and his media advisers have thrown themselves into the task of updating the former Italian prime minister’s image – and images – with an almost reckless energy.</p>
<p>From a standing start on Tuesday, they managed to post 78 photographs in five days (several of them artfully filtered) and accrue around 21,500 followers. There are pictures of Silvio Berlusconi addressing rallies, Silvio Berlusconi with his fragrant, 29-year-old girlfriend, <ref target="https://instagram.com/p/24MR7ItQEc/?taken-by=silvioberlusconi2015">Francesca Pascale</ref>; Silvio Berlusconi <ref target="https://instagram.com/p/24gi-WNQH2/?taken-by=silvioberlusconi2015">with their dog</ref>, Dudù and Silvio Berlusconi hard at work at his desk on, if not affairs of state these days, maybe something to do with his party, his businesses or AC Milan.</p>
<p>The reason for this flurry of activity is not hard to guess: on Sunday, elections are to be held in seven of Italy’s 20 regions. It will be the first big test of public opinion for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Berlusconi</ref> and his Forza Italia party since he returned to active politics in March. That was after he finished 10 months <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/30/silvio-berlusconi-community-service-alzheimers-dementia">of community service</ref> at a home for dementia patients – the sentence imposed on him following his conviction for tax fraud.</p>
<p>This article includes content provided by Instagram. We ask for your permission before anything is loaded, as they may be using cookies and other technologies. To view this content, <hi rend="#b">click 'Allow and continue'</hi>.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has learned from Italy’s young prime minister, Matteo Renzi, that social media can win over voters on a grand scale. But they can also be uncomfortably revealing, and one of the media tycoon’s latest postings to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/instagram">Instagram</ref> has a doleful air that is strikingly at odds with the others.</p>
<p>In one image, a wonky camera angle relegates the great man to a corner of the frame where he sits at a table resting his chin on his hand on a Saturday night watching … <ref target="https://instagram.com/p/3Cq1rqtQNt/?taken-by=silvioberlusconi2015">the Eurovision song contest</ref> on the telly. It all seems a very long way from those wild <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/mar/27/pass-notes-bunga-bunga-berlusconi">bunga bunga parties</ref>. On the table, there are some half-drunk glasses of wine. But you sense a cup of Ovaltine would not look out of place.</p>
<p>If, over the past few years, the 78-year-old former prime minister has lost momentum, then so too has his party. Currently, Forza Italia is polling on average less than 12%. Renzi’s Democratic party (PD) is averaging more than three times that figure. Yet at the last general election in 2013 – bunga bunga and the economic crisis not withstanding – Forza Italia’s precursor party won 22% of the vote. And in 2008 it stormed back to power with 37%.</p>
<p>This article includes content provided by Instagram. We ask for your permission before anything is loaded, as they may be using cookies and other technologies. To view this content, <hi rend="#b">click 'Allow and continue'</hi>.</p>
<p>As the leader of a movement with an ever-shrinking consensus, Berlusconi is becoming the Nick Clegg of Italian politics, and for a not dissimilar reason. Before Renzi seized power at the beginning of last year, and apparently believing that an understanding with the prime minister-to-be could help with his various legal problems, Berlusconi agreed to back Renzi’s plan for constitutional reforms. Until just a few weeks ago, the two men were tied together in a kind of non-aggression pact.</p>
<p>With Berlusconi unwilling, and his followers unable, to mount effective opposition, the way was open for the new leader of the Northern League, Matteo Salvini, to fill the breach. His party, which espouses a hard right agenda not unlike that of the National Front in France, has leapfrogged Forza Italia (though it still polls less than 15%). Berlusconi thus needs to use every trick in the book to reverse his and his party’s seemingly unstoppable decline. Instagram could be one of many.</p>
<p>But will it be effective? <ref target="https://instagram.com/matteorenzi/">Renzi</ref>, who has demonstrated a Barack Obama-like mastery of social media, was using Instagram long before many US politicians. Yet for the past 12 months he and his team appear not to have put up a single post. So either they know something the rest of us don’t. Or Italy’s geeky young prime minister has just allowed himself to be outflanked by a granddad.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>