<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-12-20" description="After months of scandal, the Italian prime minister has a weapon with which to split his opponents" fingerprint="36ba032d9122d70d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Wounded Berlusconi turns Milan attack into a political fightback" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/dec/20/berlusconi-milan-attack-sympathy">
<main>
<p>No doubt, for anyone outside Italy, the attack on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> in Milan's cathedral square last week seemed pretty straightforward: a man with a history of mental illness hit him in the face with a viciously jagged object and put him in hospital for the best part of a week; the Italian prime minister will take it easy over Christmas before resuming his duties in the new year. A deplorable incident, but one of a kind to which prominent, controversial politicians are unfortunately susceptible. Berlusconi himself was hit with a camera tripod four years ago.</p>
<p>In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, however, last Sunday's assault has acquired an entirely different, and much greater, significance. It has cast a pall of apprehension over the country, raising fears that could be self-fulfilling that Italy could lapse back into political violence. Partly as a result, the incident has transformed the country's political scene, allowing Berlusconi's supporters to drive his adversaries on to the defensive and give the prime minister his first real breathing space in eight long months.</p>
<p>Video footage of the incident showed his assailant, Massimo Tartaglia, 42, bringing down the object in his hand with all his might and releasing it just inches from the prime minister's face. His weapon turned out to be a model of Milan's many-spired cathedral, its Duomo, made of compacted marble dust. As he was driven away to hospital, covered in blood, the leader of the Italian right may well have reflected that it was a fittingly awful end to a thoroughly ghastly year for him.</p>
<p>Things began to go wrong on 28 April. That was the day Veronica Lario, his wife of 18 years, first gave a hint of the trouble she was about to heap on him when she lambasted her husband's plan to find seats in the European parliament for a string of attractive young women, most of whom had previously been known more for their anxiety to break into television than any noticeable interest in politics. The idea, said Lario, was "shameless trash".</p>
<p>Five days later, it was reported that she had decided to leave Berlusconi, declaring that she could no longer remain "with a man who consorts with minors" – apparently a reference to 18- year-old Noemi Letizia, a Neapolitan who also aspired to a life in the spotlight and whose birthday party Berlusconi had attended the previous month. Just as the scandal over their still unexplained relationship was abating, the prime minister was knocked sideways by the publication of an interview with a call girl who said she had spent the night with him and recorded their pillow talk.</p>
<p>Patrizia D'Addario was one of about 30 women alleged to have been taken to dinners at Berlusconi's private residence in Rome last winter by a man who is under investigation on suspicion of drug trafficking and aiding and abetting prostitution. Her alleged recordings, which include some excruciatingly intimate exchanges, were later posted to the web for all to hear.</p>
<p>Then, within three days in October, the television and property magnate-turned-politician was left reeling by successive blows. The company at the heart of his business empire was ordered to pay damages of €750m (£665m) for having bribed its way to victory in a takeover battle. Meanwhile, he himself was stripped of the immunity from prosecution he had secured the year before from a parliament which is dominated by his supporters.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Berlusconi was having to contend with ever more open and insistent criticism from the man who should be his closest ally – Gianfranco Fini, who earlier this year led his party into Berlusconi's Freedom People movement.</p>
<p>The former neo-fascist Fini has carved out a niche for himself as a born-again progressive, a conservative in the mould of David Cameron, and since being elected speaker of the lower house of parliament after the right's election victory last year, has become ever more impatient with the prime minister's high-handed approach to legislation.</p>
<p>Outsiders might conclude that Berlusconi had no one but himself to blame for his difficulties. But in the Alice-through-the-Looking-Glass world of Italy's billionaire leader, it is never he who is to blame, but those who criticise him.</p>
<p>His wife had fallen into a trap prepared by the centre-left opposition. His refusal to confront the questions raised by his involvement with young Noemi and the women who trooped through his home in Rome was an indictment not of Berlusconi, but of those journalists who insisted on demanding answers.</p>
<p>As for his legal setbacks, they were simply proof of what he has been saying for a decade and a half: that they are nothing to do with the way he ran his businesses, but the result of a conspiracy by leftwing prosecutors. No evidence has ever been produced to substantiate this contention, but it has been repeated so often by the prime minister, and the media outlets he owns or controls, that it is now widely believed in Italy.</p>
<p>Scarcely had Berlusconi woken up after his first night in hospital than his followers were promoting an interpretation of what had happened that was to transform Tartaglia's replica Duomo from a weapon into an early political Christmas present. The prime minister, according to this version, amplified by his media influence, had not just been attacked by a disturbed individual. He was the victim of a "climate of hatred" for which his critics were entirely responsible.</p>
<p>No one would deny that Italian politics have become disturbingly polarised – and personalised. Berlusconi looms over Italy in a way no leader has since the founding of the republic after the Second World War. Eight days before he was attacked, about 250,000 Italians packed into Rome for No Berlusconi Day, a demonstration aimed, not at their government or its policies, but its leader.</p>
<p>One reason, however, why political debate in Italy revolves to such an extent around the doings and sayings of one man is that so much political activity in the country he leads relates to his personal affairs. His latest government, like its two predecessors, has swiftly been hamstrung by the need to devote hundreds of hours of cabinet and parliamentary time to bills that are designed to get Berlusconi out of his courtroom entanglements.</p>
<p>Last Tuesday the right's counterattack took on a distinctly menacing air when Fabrizio Cicchitto, the Freedom People's leader in the chamber of deputies, stood up to address the lower house. Cicchitto, once a member with Berlusconi of the notoriously conspiratorial, rogue Masonic lodge P2, told his fellow deputies that Tartaglia's hand had been "armed" by those he said were morally responsible for the vitriolic atmosphere. And he proceeded to name them one by one in a speech that turned into a denunciation reminiscent of the politics of a one-party state.</p>
<p>The culprits included <hi rend="#i">La Repubblica</hi>; its weekly sister publication <hi rend="#i">L'Espresso</hi>; the presenter of a current affairs programme on the publicly owned RAI network; a new radical daily, <hi rend="#i">Il Fatto</hi>; and an investigative journalist, Marco Travaglio, whom Cicchitto described as a "media terrorist". Certain unnamed prosecutors were on the blacklist. Cicchitto also named the more abrasive of Italy's main opposition groups, the Italy of Principles party, while pointing a finger at some in the biggest opposition movement, the Democratic party, whose leader, Pierluigi Bersani, had been at Berlusconi's bedside the day before.</p>
<p>There is nothing to suggest that any of these people or institutions approved of the attack. On the contrary, they had all condemned it (though the leader of the Italy of Principles party, Antonio Di Pietro, had suggested Berlusconi had brought it on himself – a remark that earned him appalled rebukes from many in the centre and on the left).</p>
<p>Neither was there anything to indicate that anybody but Tartaglia had been involved in the attack – until, that is, one Andrea Di Sorte came forward the same day to say he thought he had seen the prime minister's assailant reach behind him as if "to get hold of something from someone who, obviously, I didn't see". Di Sorte is a leading official in an organisation set up by Berlusconi's fans.</p>
<p>That night the already volatile atmosphere turned explosive. At 3am on Wednesday, in another part of Milan, Italy's leading business school, the Luigi Bocconi University, was shaken by a blast. A pipe bomb left in an underground passageway between two buildings went off defectively, causing only very minor damage.</p>
<p>"Even if it had exploded properly, it would not have caused deaths," a police officer was quoted as saying by the Berlusconi family daily, <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi>. "The timer set to that hour is a clear signal that those responsible for the act didn't want to harm anyone".</p>
<p>Yet, to judge by the rest of the paper's coverage, Italy was all but tipping into civil war.</p>
<p>"And Now Come the Bombs" its headline on Thursday screamed. "After the statuette – the dynamite." Using a phrase which has a powerful and ominous historical resonance, the paper said the explosion was another result of "the campaigns by <hi rend="#i">cattivi maestri</hi>". This is a term once used to describe Marxist academics blamed for inciting young people to violence after the student revolts in 1968. Like Cicchitto, <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi> was overtly equating Berlusconi's peaceful critics with sponsors of terrorism.</p>
<p>Responsibility for the blast was claimed by an organisation calling itself the Informal Anarchist Federation, a so far untraced group that has been responsible for 19 low-level terrorist incidents since 2003.</p>
<p>As most commentators appealed for calm, it seemed as if those in, or associated with, the government were doing everything in their power to raise the political temperature.</p>
<p>"The hands of the clock of history are going backwards," warned Berlusconi's education minister, Mariastella Gelmini, in a clear reference to the "Years of Lead", so-called because of the number of bullets exchanged between leftwing and rightwing extremists. The cover of the Berlusconi-owned weekly news magazine, <hi rend="#i">Panorama</hi>, which came out on Friday, showed the prime minister with his face covered in blood alongside the headline "Wanted – Alive or (even better) Dead".</p>
<p>Yet while his followers have been spreading a message of alarm verging on hysteria, Berlusconi himself has sounded a different note. His first statement after the attack was sent to his party's website and included the assertion that "love always wins out over envy and hatred". After leaving hospital, another statement was put out in his name in which he declared that "my pain will not have been in vain if a greater awareness of the need for a more placid and honest language in Italian politics comes out of what has happened".</p>
<p>That statement also contained appreciation for Pierluigi Bersani's reaction to the attack and a hint there might be scope for greater collaboration in future. But there was a catch.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was ready to talk with the leaders of the mainstream opposition, "if they are really able to keep their distance in an honest fashion from the small number of those who stir up violence". A former prime minister, Massimo D'Alema, was among the first to protest. "We have never uttered words of hate against Berlusconi," he told an interviewer. "To change the political climate, what is necessary above all is to respect the institutions [of state] and make them work, starting with parliament."</p>
<p>The craftily worded statement from Berlusconi's office crystallised the dilemma that now faces the opposition. If it refuses to collaborate, it risks looking churlish or worse in the eyes of a nation suffused with sympathy for a 73-year-old man who has been beaten up. But if it takes up the prime minister's offer of collaboration, it may have to sacrifice fiercely held convictions.</p>
<p>The measures the media tycoon plans to get through parliament with the help of the opposition include some that are profoundly distasteful to most people on the centre-left. His lawyers, who are also MPs for the Freedom People, have drawn up two bills. According to the body which oversees the judiciary, one of them, which would curb the length of legal proceedings, could put an end to up to 100,000 trials.</p>
<p>The injured, yet paradoxically strengthened, Berlusconi is offering the opposition a Faustian choice. It can grab at a chance to water down legislation it abhors, but at the cost of giving the prime minister the moral backing he seeks. Or it can watch impotently as the legislation is passed in any case.</p>
<p>D'Alema, for one, is tempted by the offer of compromise. "It is almost better to pass a law tailor-made for Berlusconi so as to curb the damage to law and order," he said in a comment that dismayed many of his colleagues.</p>
<p>Dividing the opposition is not the only bonus the prime minister has derived from the attack. Fini's criticisms have come to an abrupt halt and the right has been given a chance to fight back against a new enemy, whose power caught it by surprise earlier this month.</p>
<p>Though Berlusconi's followers tried to make out that No Berlusconi Day was engineered by the Italy of Principles movement, it really marked the arrival in Italy of a new kind of protest, born spontaneously on the web. But the internet, and in particular the social networking sites that were used to organise the demonstration, were also used for some of the most distasteful reactions to the assault on Berlusconi – comments welcoming it and celebrating Tartaglia as a hero.</p>
<p>Last Thursday the cabinet discussed a bill to introduce new curbs, but without reaching agreement. That may be a first sign of rationality seeping into the fevered debate stirred up by last Sunday's attack.</p>
<p>As Berlusconi returned to his home outside Milan on Friday, Fini did his bit to lighten the mood as Christmas approached, by sending a present to the editor of <hi rend="#i">Il Giornale</hi>. Inside, there was some Valium.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>