<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Madeleine Bunting" categories="Opinion" date="2009-07-01" description="Madeleine Bunting: If Berlusconi sets the tone at next week's G8, it will be a disaster for a cherished Labour goal" fingerprint="53d948b705b28a97" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,UK news,G8,Silvio Berlusconi,Global development,Society,Labour,Conservatives,Politics,Aid and development,Katine" title="The anti-aid agenda | Madeleine Bunting" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/01/aid-g8-berlusconi-labour">
<main>
<p>The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/29/silvio-berlusconi-g8-summit-allegations">G8</ref> is less than a week away but already the Italian presidency is seen as having a disastrous impact on aid. Uninterested, disorganised and short is likely to be the summary of the summit by the end of next week: the G8 leaders, according to the latest plans, will have only three hours sitting down together.</p>
<p>While the developing world reels from the economic downturn, Italy has shown no ambition for the aid agenda. It is falling dramatically behind on its own commitments made in 2005 at <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/apr/22/darling-refuses-cuts-overseas-aid">Gleneagles</ref> and is instituting draconian cuts of 56% in its aid budget this year. Italy will end up with the lowest rate of aid – less than 0.1% of GDP – in the G8, despite its reiterations of commitment to the European agreement to reach 0.51% by 2010.</p>
<p>Italy's lamentable performance is prompting a crisis of identity for the G8. Accusations of summit ceremony with no substance have always dogged the event, but given that it no longer represents all the biggest economies (China is not a member), or the biggest populations (such as China or India), its one last claim to world leadership has been as the world's biggest aid donor. But even that claim now looks fragile in Italy's hands. Spain has overtaken Italy in GDP per capita and now has one of the highest aid rates in the EU, handsomely ahead of Italy. The question of whether <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has forfeited his right to a place at the top table is likely to hover over events next week.</p>
<p>But the failures of Rome are only one aspect of how to ensure the survival of one of Labour's most cherished achievements over the last 12 years: pushing increased aid up both the international and domestic agenda. By 2010 Britain is on track to have increased its aid budget to 0.62% of GDP, one of the highest in the EU and not far short of the totemic <ref target="http://www.unmillenniumproject.org/press/07.htm">0.7%</ref> set by the UN in 1970. While many departments are braced for cuts, aid is to increase – and the Tories have promised to abide by the increases. Labour has established a new political consensus on aid domestically, and an international profile on the issue which is widely admired. But can it hold?</p>
<p>That is part of the impetus behind the white paper expected next week from Department of International Development (DfiD). It indicates a growing unease across many parts of government that now is the time to lash the legacy down, to make it as difficult as possible for the Tories to unpick. The aim is to make aid analogous with the NHS or the BBC, a significant part of British identity. That means that a lot more people need to know what DfiD does, and this is what lies behind proposals to rebrand with a logo of UKaid.</p>
<p>It's all laudable stuff, but difficult. At heart, aid is a moral argument about interconnectedness in a small world, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/labour">Labour</ref> has doggedly championed that message under the likes of Clare Short, Hilary Benn and, now, Douglas Alexander. The Tories have bought into that, because as one observer put it: "It's a cheap way to detoxify the brand, aid represents only 1% of government spending." But the concern is that the Tories might dilute the primacy of poverty reduction – diverting money into Foreign Office objectives, perhaps dismantling Dfid, as John Major and Douglas Hurd suggested recently. So the new white paper will try to buttress the moral argument with an awareness of self-interest: African economies, if strong enough, offer huge potential markets.</p>
<p>With energy draining away at an international level and a critique of aid gathering strength with the likes of economist <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/may/30/international-aid-moyo-africa">Dambisa Moyo</ref>, it's a vulnerable moment for the aid agenda. The fear is that achievements are hard won – involving huge effort in mobilising people on to the streets – and can easily fall apart: commitments dropped, and targets missed when everyone thought the job had been largely done.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>