<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2012-04-12" description="Italian former prime minister's lawyer denies payments were attempt to sway testimonies in trial over underage prostitute" fingerprint="3fe2c3add042c64d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi paid €127,000 to witnesses in trial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/12/silvio-berlusconi-paid-witnesses-ruby-trial">
<main>
<p>Italy's former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has handed out cash gifts worth more than €100,000 to young women due to testify in his trial on charges of paying an underage prostitute.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has reportedly paid €127,000 (£105,000) to three witnesses since his trial began last April. The trial centres on Moroccan runaway Karima el-Mahroug, known as Ruby the Heart Stealer, who attended so-called "bunga bunga" parties at Berlusconi's mansion outside Milan in 2010.</p>
<p>Prosecutors allege the parties were organised by Nicole Minetti, a former dental hygienist turned TV showgirl who was nominated a councillor for the Lombardy region by Berlusconi's party. Minetti, who is also standing trial separately for procuring prostitutes for the former prime minister, was paid €55,000 by him in two instalments in October and November, prosecutors say, according to Italian newspaper Corriere della Sera.</p>
<p>Two regular guests at those parties, sisters Eleonora and Imma de Vivo – models who appeared on an Italian celebrity reality show – received €72,000, paid by Berlusconi via their father, in July and October.</p>
<p>One party guest, dancer Maria Makdoum, has told prosecutors she saw the de Vivo twins dancing around Berlusconi in their knickers and bra at one of his after-dinner bunga bunga sessions. Berlusconi "was touching their intimate parts and they were touching him," she said.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's lawyer, Niccolò Ghedini, admitted payments had been made to Minetti and the de Vivos, but denied they were intended to sway their testimony.</p>
<p>"The linking of the payments with the fact they are witnesses in the so-called Ruby trial is absolutely spurious and without foundation," Ghedini said.</p>
<p>"With his usual generosity, Berlusconi has sought to help, in a totally transparent fashion through bank transfers, those people who have been caught up in the media storm built around inexistent claims and who are living through an extremely difficult period economically, professionally and on the home front."</p>
<p>The trial continues on Monday.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>