<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-02-01" description="Girlfriend in a Coma, co-directed by British author and journalist Bill Emmott, was due to be shown in Italy on 13 February" fingerprint="76289ae71902bfd9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Censorship,Silvio Berlusconi,Mario Monti,Culture,Film" title="Film-maker accuses Italian government of censorship after premiere is called off" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/01/filmmaker-accuses-italian-government-censorship">
<main>
<p>He was persona non grata in Italy during the reign of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who was so irked by the Economist's unrelenting criticism that he gave its then editor the rather unlikely title of The E-Communist.</p>
<p>But the British author and journalist Bill Emmott proved on Friday that, even after Berlusconi's departure from Palazzo Chigi, he still appeared to have the ability to cause a stir.</p>
<p>He has hit out at the Italian government and a leading contemporary arts centre in Rome after the Italian premiere of his film, a highly critical look at the country and the problems it faces, was cancelled for being too political in the run-up to the election later this month.</p>
<p>"I think this confirms the thesis of the film … which is that a true understanding of the nature of Italy's problems and of what needs to happen – a kind of cultural revolution – has not begun; that there is still a sense of denial and a sense of resistance to the full reality of what has happened in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>," said Emmott, who said he was the victim of censorship.</p>
<p>The documentary, Girlfriend in a Coma, named after a song by the Smiths, was directed by Emmott and Annalisa Piras, and features interviews with Italian figures including technocratic prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/mario-monti">Mario Monti</ref>, author Umberto Eco and anti-Camorra writer Roberto Saviano. It has been screened in several European countries and the United States and was due to be shown in Italy at the National Museum of the 21st Century Arts on 13 February.</p>
<p>However the museum, commonly known as the Maxxi, contacted the screening's organisers on Friday to inform them that, due to guidance from the ministry of culture, it was "compelled" to postpone the event until after the vote on the 24 and 25 February.</p>
<p>The museum is managed by a foundation funded by the culture ministry, which denied having issued any instructions for the postponement of the premiere and said the museum was referring to general guidelines about political involvement. A spokeswoman for the director of the Maxxi's foundation, Giovanna Melandri, said the decision had been taken out of respect for the state museum's "institutional propriety" during the "delicate" election run-up.</p>
<p>"There is no censorship, there was no order," she said. "As we told Bill Emmott this morning, it would be a pleasure to welcome him here after the elections," she said.</p>
<p>But Emmott, under whose editorship Berlusconi attempted twice to sue for libel, and twice failed, said he would protest directly to the office of the prime minister, Mario Monti, as well as to the museum and culture ministry. "My reaction is one of disbelief," he said, adding that he hoped whoever had taken the decision would think again.</p>
<p>"I think that, in most democracies, reason would prevail and that the ministry and the Maxxi would realise that free speech and free discussion generated by a non-political independent film was absolutely appropriate during an election campaign. That's what would happen in Britain, France or Germany."</p>
<p>Other screenings will go ahead in cities including Milan, Pisa and Venice.</p>
<p>Asked if the culture ministry would encourage the Maxxi to reinstate the premiere, a spokesman said: "We cannot say that because the Maxxi is a private concern under the vigilance of the ministry, but we cannot say what to do or what not to do. It's its own decision."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>