<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Agnès Poirier" categories="Opinion" date="2009-09-17" description="Agnès Poirier: It's easy to laugh at Umberto Bossi's ideas to drop the national anthem, flag and language, but Italians should take more notice" fingerprint="24824cd7c938ef57" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe,Umberto Bossi" title="Italy's eccentric man of the north | Agnès Poirier" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/sep/17/italy-north-umberto-bossi">
<main>
<p>Have you ever heard of Padania? It's an old politico-geographical concept that comes back regularly in Italian politics. Padania covers broadly what we would call north Italy, enclosing the regions of Piedmont, Lombardy, Emilia-Romagna and Veneto. Padania is the favourite word of the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lega_Nord">Lega Nord</ref>, vitriolic Umberto Bossi's party, which keeps asking for nothing less than Italy's complete dismantlement and the immediate secession of Padania, its most industrious and richest part.</p>
<p>As Italy prepares for celebrations in 2011 of the 150th anniversary of its unification, Lega Nord's recent furious invectives feel like insidious venom. For about a decade and until this summer, Bossi, as a regular guest-star minister in Silvio Berlusconi's different governments, had kept his dreams of secession quiet and had focused on keeping Berlusconi on a very rightist political agenda.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago, however, Bossi couldn't contain himself any longer and lashed out against the national anthem, its national flag and the country's common language.</p>
<p>It has now become usual practice for the Lega Nord's 60 MPs and 30 senators to boo each time they hear <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0qYk9Jt6MeA"> Fratelli d'Italia</ref> (Brothers of Italia) play. </p>
<p><hi rend="#i">Fratelli d'Italia</hi>may not be the most memorable and powerful national anthem in the world, but it is nonetheless Italy's choice of hymn. Of course, the ebullient North Leaguers rather prefer the heady and melodramatic melodies of Giuseppe Verdi, himself a man of the north. The magnificent</p>
<p>
<ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7K68tdN3fYw">from Nabucco has been chosen as Lega Nord's choice of anthem. Italian art critic Andrea Martini commented:</ref>
</p>
<hi rend="#i">Va Pensiero</hi>
<quote>It is of course ironic that they should prefer Verdi. Verdi may have died in Milan but he was very much engaged politically in the<ref>Risorgimento</ref>, the unification of Italy, alongside Garibaldi and<ref>Cavour</ref>. Also, Umberto Bossi doesn't seem to have a clue about<hi>Va Pensiero</hi>'s lyrics and its historical references. Nabucco is the story of the Jews' battle for freedom against the Babylonians. At the time, Verdi was mirroring the fight for Italian unification. Besides, technically, Verdi was French, as he was born, at the time, in a French-controlled province.</quote>
<p>The Lega Nord doesn't stop here. Alongside the national anthem, Bossi would also like to get rid of the Italian flag, <hi rend="#i">il tricolore</hi>, in favour of regional fanions. He also hopes his party will help make his patois from Lombardy compulsory in schools after the 2011 regional elections.</p>
<p>Bossi's demands may sound at best eccentric and at worst dangerous, but he may soon have the means to implement them partially in the regions in which his party seem to be getting stronger and stronger after each election. In April 2008, during the last regional elections, Lega Nord scooped 8% of the votes in north <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. Last June, at the EU elections, it reached 10%, sending nine MEPs to the EU parliament in Strasbourg.</p>
<p>It is easy to laugh at Bossi's anachronistic and reactionary posturing but if the Italians don't pay more attention, he may soon one day be in a position to put in place his deeply divisive policies.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>