<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="James Callow" categories="Football" date="2010-07-20" description="Silvio Berlusconi has publicly demanded that Milan's new coach Massimiliano Allegri fields more than one striker this season" fingerprint="7eecd26f116bcfb9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Milan,Silvio Berlusconi,Football,Sport" title="'New Milan manager must play two strikers,' says Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2010/jul/20/milan-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi contrived to put Milan's new coach Massimiliano Allegri in the shade by publicly demanding his team play with more than one striker this season.</p>
<p>In an extraordinary news conference on the first day of pre-season training, the Italian prime minister and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/acmilan">Milan</ref> owner fielded every question and left Allegri and several team members to sit in silence.</p>
<p>Berlusconi told the new coach what tactics he should use after falling out with last season's coach Leonardo as Milan again ended the campaign without a trophy.</p>
<p>"We don't want to see just one forward up front. To win you have to score. To have chances you've got to have forwards close to the goal," Berlusconi said.</p>
<p>"I appreciated Leonardo a lot but I disagreed with him in how he fielded the team. Ronaldinho must play on the shoulder of the strikers even if he has a tendency to drift left."</p>
<p>Ronaldinho has been linked in the media with a move away but Berlusconi was adamant the playmaker was staying.</p>
<p>"He is the No1 attraction at Milan," he said, "Ronaldinho does not want to leave. I'm sure he is happy to stay."</p>
<p>The futures of Gennaro Gattuso and Klaas Jan Huntelaar look less certain.</p>
<p>"I would be happy for Gattuso to stay but we are not against people saying they want to leave," Berlusconi said. "We can't exclude [the sale of Huntelaar] even if we are convinced of his qualities as a main striker."</p>
<p>The 73-year-old, who arrived by helicopter, welcomed the new signings Mario Yepes, Marco Amelia and Sokratis Papastathopoulos but was lukewarm over the prospect of luring the Barcelona striker Zlatan Ibrahimovic back to Italian football.</p>
<p>"I don't know how well he'd fit into the Milan dressing room," he said of the former Inter player."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>