<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Alexander Chancellor" categories="Opinion" date="2011-06-03" description="Alexander Chancellor: David Bernstein should be proud of his stance over Sepp Blatter's re-election as Fifa president" fingerprint="7e11db73bba2dedd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Sepp Blatter,Fifa,David Bernstein,Football,Silvio Berlusconi,G8,World news" title="The English FA was right to stand up to Fifa and its cosy idea of a 'family' | Alexander Chancellor" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/jun/03/fifa-family-values-david-bernstein">
<main>
<p>We English may be priggish and at times hypocritical. But let us be proud of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2011/jun/01/fa-heavy-defeat-fifa-david-bernstein">the stance taken by the chairman of the English Football Association, David Bernstein</ref>, against the coronation of Sepp Blatter as president of Fifa. Bernstein was reportedly taken aback by the hostility of others among Fifa's 208 national associations to his proposal that the election of the president be postponed until more challengers emerged, following the withdrawal of two earlier ones because of corruption allegations. Nobody, not even representatives of the other UK football associations, spoke in his support, even though his proposal was an eminently reasonable one.</p>
<p>Instead, he had to put up with much abuse, in particular from Julio Grondona, the Argentinian Fifa vice-president, who said to the congress in Zurich: "<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/blog/2011/jun/01/sepp-blatter-fifa-english-media-fa">We always have attacks from England</ref>, which are mostly lies with the support of journalism. This upsets and disturbs the Fifa family."</p>
<p>The word "family" here, and also as used by Blatter, sounds as if it is intended in the mafia sense: loyalty and <hi rend="#i">omertà</hi> being its binding obligations. Allegations of corruption should be dealt with privately and in such a way as not to undermine the confidence of the world's football fans in the probity and integrity of those who decide where the World Cup is held. Even though Grondona himself is on record as having said that he would support England's bid to host the World Cup in 2018 "if you give back the Falkland Islands, which belong to us", and despite all the question marks about how Qatar managed to secure it for 2022, we are supposed to accept that everything has been handled in the most honourable and objective manner.</p>
<p>Well, not entirely. Even Blatter accepts that some changes do need to be made, but it is hardly confidence-inspiring that his main proposal is to bring in the 88-year-old Henry Kissinger, a controversial figure if ever there was one, to advise <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/fifa">Fifa</ref> on matters of transparency and justice. How much will Kissinger be paid, I wonder? If Bernstein is feeling a little depressed by the way things have gone, may he recall Winston Churchill's remark: "You have enemies? Good. That means you've stood up for something, sometime in your life." Bernstein has done just that and should be proud of himself. By the same token, the British government should not be afraid to chastise the European Union bureaucracy for expenses claims that leave British members of parliament looking prim. Reports say, for example, that the EU's 27 commissioners spent £6.6m on private jets during the four years up to 2010.</p>
<p>The British government should not be accused of disloyalty to the European "family" by rigorously objecting to increases in the EU commission's budget. Nor should it think that it is universally hated in Europe for its stand on such matters. I have just got back from Italy, where a leading article in the country's principal newspaper, Corriere della Sera, was admiring of the fact that David Cameron and Ed Miliband were going on their holidays by easyJet, whereas Italian government ministers, pleading security considerations, took government aircraft on even the most frivolous of missions. This is an area in which we still command some grudging respect.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Knocking on the exit door</hi>
</head>
<p/>
<p>I was in Italy during the local elections this week in which Silvio Berlusconi, who had presented them as a referendum on himself, suffered a crushing setback. His candidates for mayor of Naples and Milan were both decisively defeated, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/30/silvio-berlusconi-defeat-in-milan">the successful Milanese candidate was a lawyer</ref>, Giuliano Pisapio, who had opposed the prime minister in one of the various bribery cases against him. Berlusconi tried to brush the results aside, promising to learn the lessons and carry on with his rightwing coalition government until the next general election in 2013. But the predominant view was that his reputation for invincibility had been fatally undermined and that the 74-year-old – the longest serving Italian prime minister since Mussolini – was at last on the way out.</p>
<p>We will see; but the most striking thing was that nobody I talked to, and no commentator in the press, attributed his humiliation to the behaviour for which he is internationally famous – his carryings-on with teenage women and his alleged involvement in bribery and corruption. Italians seem to care little about those things. If they turn against him, it will not be because of them but because of his failure to deliver the reforms that he promised so many years ago – the release of Italy from stifling bureaucracy and its adoption of the Anglo-American free-market model. But his concern to protect his own business interests has stopped him doing that and left a lot of people feeling let down.</p>
<p>He also lost a lot of support by ranting on at Barack Obama and every other leader at last week's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit in Deauville about the "dictatorship" of the Italian judiciary that was trying to bring him down. This not only embarrassed the leaders concerned but also left him looking unpatriotic among his own citizens. He was seen to be knocking his own country, which is not what political leaders are supposed to do.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>