<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Angela Giuffrida" categories="World news" date="2022-10-18" description="La Presse agency publishes audio suggesting 20 bottles arrived for 86th birthday after pair ‘re-establish’ ties" fingerprint="f7d0005db325d304" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Vladimir Putin,Russia,Italy,Ukraine,Europe,World news" title="Berlusconi said he received vodka from Putin for birthday, reports say" url="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/oct/18/silvio-berlusconi-said-he-received-shipment-of-vodka-from-vladimir-putin-say-reports">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has allegedly said Vladimir Putin gave him 20 bottles of vodka for his birthday after he “re-established” relations with the Russian president.</p>
<p>Berlusconi turned 86 on 29 September, four days after a coalition including his Forza Italia party won the general election.</p>
<p>Italy’s three-time former prime minister, an old friend of Putin’s, is reported to have told a meeting of Forza Italia parliamentarians in Rome on Tuesday that the shipment of vodka was accompanied by a “very sweet letter”.</p>
<p>Forza Italia denied he made the comments, but <ref target="https://www.lapresse.it/politica/2022/10/18/berlusconi-ho-riallacciato-i-rapporti-con-putin/">an audio clip published by La Presse news agency appeared to suggest otherwise</ref>.</p>
<p>In the audio reported by La Presse, Berlusconi said he returned Putin’s gesture by sending him bottles of Lambrusco wine.</p>
<p>“Russian ministers have said on several occasions that we are at war with them, because we are providing arms and funding to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ukraine">Ukraine</ref>,” Berlusconi allegedly said.</p>
<p>“I can’t personally give my opinion because if it is told to the press it will turn out to be a disaster, but I am very, very, very worried. I re-established relations with President Putin, a little bit. I knew him as a peaceful and sensible person.”</p>
<p>Berlusconi has publicly condemned the war but just days before the elections he told an Italian TV show that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/sep/23/berlusconi-claims-russians-pushed-putin-into-ukraine-war">Putin was pushed to invade Ukraine by the Russian people and by ministers</ref> who wanted Volodymyr Zelenskiy’s administration replaced with “decent people”.</p>
<p>“Putin was pushed by the Russian population, by his party and by his ministers to invent this special operation,” Berlusconi told Porta a Porta.</p>
<p>“The troops were supposed to enter, reach Kyiv within a week, replace Zelenskiy’s government with decent people and then leave. Instead they found resistance, which was then fed by arms of all kinds from the west.”</p>
<p>Forza Italia is <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/oct/16/italy-berlusconi-calls-meloni-patronising-and-bossy-as-relations-fray">a junior partner in a coalition led by Giorgia Meloni’s Brothers of Italy</ref>, a party with neofascist roots, and Matteo Salvini’s far-right League.</p>
<p>Due to be sworn into government next week, the coalition has pledged to continue Italy’s support of Ukraine and the EU sanctions against Russia over the invasion.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>