<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lorenzo Tondo" categories="World news" date="2019-12-14" description="Grassroots protests have brought tens of thousands of people on to the streets of Rome" fingerprint="72e6f401f5e1caae" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Protest,Europe,Matteo Salvini,Silvio Berlusconi,Brothers of Italy" title="'Sardines' against Salvini: Italy's fight against the far right" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/dec/14/sardines-pack-piazza-in-rome-for-protest-against-matteo-salvini">
<main>
<p>Tens of thousands of people crammed together in Rome on Saturday as part of the growing “sardines” movement against the leader of the far-right League and Italy’s former deputy prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/matteo-salvini">Matteo Salvini</ref>, and his allies.</p>
<p>Protesters converged in Piazza San Giovanni early in the afternoon in a bid “to further shake up the country’s politics and battle xenophobia”, in what was billed as their biggest rally.</p>
<p>“We are very happy and reached our goal,” said one of the movement’s founders, Mattia Sartori, 32.</p>
<p>“We are anti-fascist, pro-equality, against intolerance, against homophobia,” Santori told AFP, as protesters sang the anti-fascist anthem Bella Ciao.</p>
<p>“We are weary of this culture of hatred,” the movement’s representative in the Italian capital, Stephen Ogongo, a 45-year-old journalist of Kenyan origin, told AFP. ‘‘We will no longer tolerate language that is racist, fascist, discriminatory or sexist.”</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/19/sardines-against-salvini-italians-pack-squares-in-protest-against-far-right">Sardines movement</ref> began in November after Santori, from Bologna, sent an urgent message to three friends late at night telling them to meet the next day. It was a couple of days before Salvini and his coalition partners, the smaller far-right party Brothers of Italy, and Silvio Berlusconi’s Forza Italia, were due to launch their campaign for the Emilia-Romagna regional election at an indoor sports arena in Bologna.</p>
<p>The four friends hatched a riposte to Salvini’s boasts about filling Italy’s squares with supporters. The sports arena had a capacity for 5,700 people, and via an announcement on Santori’s private Facebook page, the group invited people to a counter-rally at Bologna’s Piazza Maggiore, with the aim of attracting 6,000 people.</p>
<p>What happened next confounded their expectations: 15,000 people filled the Bologna square. As Salvini’s far-right electoral alliance pursued its campaign, the Sardines converged in other Emilia-Romagna cities before spreading across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and beyond.</p>
<p>Hundreds of migrants also joined the Sardines on Saturday in Rome to protest against Salvini’s hardline immigration policies.</p>
<p>Before being ejected from government in August after his failed gambit to collapse a coalition with the Five Star Movement (M5S) and bring about snap elections, Salvini’s main achievement when in office was to introduce draconian anti-immigration measures, including closing seaports to migrants.</p>
<p>“They told us that immigration is a problem in order to hide real problems,” said Pietro Bartolo, a member of the European parliament who is known as the “doctors of migrants” and who has dedicated years of his life to addressing the refugee crisis in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>“We have to resist,” added Bartolo, who joined the protest. “Laws that criminalise those who save people are laws against our constitution. These laws are a shame.”</p>
<p>Salvini has mocked the movement, writing on Twitter that he prefers kittens as “they eat sardines when hungry”.</p>
<p>However, in a poll in November, 40% of Italians said that the movement now represents Salvini’s “most dangerous enemy”.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>