<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="James Richardson" categories="Football" date="2006-11-14" description="Silvio Berlusconi insists the Rossoneri can pull their season round - but after their third straight home defeat, no one in Italy believes him." fingerprint="7e21106a99eb2753" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European club football,Football,Sport,Milan,Silvio Berlusconi" title="This Milan team is finished" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2006/nov/14/europeanfootball.acmilan">
<main>
<p>To look at him, you wouldn't figure that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> was an expert when it comes to keeping your hair on. Still, among the wails of dismay that followed Milan's historic defeat on Saturday against Roma, it was Silvio and Silvio alone who tried to keep things chipper. "You can't win 'em all", he jovially admonished glum hacks as he emerged from Milan's locker-room. "After all, even I lost an election recently! I've told the players to keep believing in themselves, just as we believe in them. We'll be back."</p>
<p>Touching stuff but, not for the first time, some may find it hard to share in the great man's convictions. After all, in Saturday's game Roma had patently banged another nail into the wide-bodied coffin of the Carlo Ancelotti era, with Milan's proudly battling former champions left punchdrunk by the younger, faster visitors.</p>
<p>The 2-1 defeat came courtesy of a magnificent Francesco Totti brace, either side of an equaliser from Cristian Brocchi, and was Milan's third home loss in a row; the first time that this giant club has posted such a record in 40 years. Admittedly, all three defeats have come against the leading teams in Italy but, coupled with their recent 2-0 loss at newly promoted Atalanta, they leave little further room for debate. Twenty points from first place, nine from the Champions League positions: domestically, this Milan team is finished.</p>
<p>There remains the question of whether Uncle Silvio can fashion another, better side from what little is on offer come January's transfer window, but don't get your hopes up. While Berlusconi has made a series of desperate-sounding hints about Ronaldinho and the much-missed Andriy Shevchenko ("he told me just yesterday he'd love to come back" offered a shamelessly straight-faced Silvio on Saturday), he's also admitted that the club have struggled to balance their books. Thus more low-key moves for Lazio right-back Massimo Oddo and Udinese frontman Vincenzo Iaquinta might be a possibility.</p>
<p>In the meantime the top teams are getting further away, and Roma with them. While Inter and Palermo won their games the next day to stay four points clear, it was Roma's San Siro exploits that stole all the attention - not surprisingly, given that this was the first time in almost 20 years that they'd won this fixture. Roma are now being hailed as title favourites by many of the same sections of the press that declared them 'in crisis' a few weeks back when they drew with Chievo and Ascoli.</p>
<p>Two things have happened at Roma since those dark days: the wild-eyed Brazilian wingman Amantino Mancini has returned, and so has the real Francesco Totti. The difference these two made on Saturday was evident. While Mancini restored the side's rather un-Italian width, Totti took care of the history-making up front.</p>
<p>The scoring began just seven minutes in. Alessandro Nesta, who these days is showing all the touch in defence of a young Donald Rumsfeld, hoisted an incoming ball blindly back over his shoulder into the Milan area and, while Nesta's team-mates froze in confusion, Rodrigo Taddei chipped the loose ball towards Totti, who spun and volleyed into the top corner.</p>
<p>One-nil up, Roma now looked in a state of grace, with their midfielders buzzing and twinkling past their hapless opponents in a dazzling display of one-touch football. But, as the game wore on, Milan's confidence grew. Their own midfield stars began to essay a few shots from range and, after both Clarence Seedorf and Ricardo Oliveira had struck the woodwork, Brocchi then found the equaliser 11 minutes into the second half with a blast from outside the area.</p>
<p>Roma in turn began to rain shots in on the Milan goal and, seven minutes from time, the pressure paid off in style. First the substitute Alberto Aquilani pulled off a <hi rend="#i">rabona</hi> - crossing his right leg behind his left to strike the ball - to surprise Milan's rearguard with an inch-perfect pass wide to Mancini, and his cross back in was thumped past Dida by the head of the flying Totti.</p>
<p>Afterwards - having sucked his thumb in celebration - Roma's captain chose to quietly downplay the significance of the win. "You bet I believe in the title! We can beat anyone!" he oh-go-on-thened. His enthusiasm is understandable; when Roma play as they did on Saturday it is hard to pick any team above them.</p>
<p>They also have arguably the best blend of players of any of the leading sides. Against Inter's been-there-done-that ennui and the relative inexperience of Palermo's provincial pool, Roma blend born-and-bred local boys - Totti, Daniele De Rossi, Aquilani and Aleandro Rosi - with foreigners who've yet to have their hunger dented by actually winning anything.</p>
<p>On Saturday it worked a treat, as it had in the previous week's 3-1 thumping of Fiorentina. Still, you can't help remembering that, when the Champions League rolls around, Roma often stop their world-beating and start drawing with the likes of Ascoli. This could hand their rivals a sizeable advantage for, unlike the <hi rend="#i">giallorossi</hi>, Inter have the depth to cope with the continent's demands, and Palermo only have the Uefa Cup to worry about.</p>
<p>Since Palermo host Inter in under two weeks, let's save any further conjecture on their chances until then. In the meantime, with Ascoli's Attilio Tesser becoming Serie A's third coaching casualty of the season after seven defeats in 11 games (an improvement on last season, when he lasted just one game at Cagliari) - and with Udinese's Giovanni Galeone set to be the next to go for conceding five goals at Lazio - week 12 brings a curious mix of matches, the probable highlight of which is Roma's Sunday afternoon clash with Catania</p>
<p>Catania, you say? The Sicilian side that's returned to Serie A after 24 years of debt and disaster, that likes to play with at least four up front and that, despite the second-worst defensive record in Italy, is currently out of the Champions League places only on goal difference? That Catania? Curiously enough, yes.</p>
<p>Southern Italy's least-conventional side should provide an interesting test of Roma's title mettle this Sunday, in a game I'll have the increasingly rare pleasure on hosting live on Bravo. If you see only one more live game this year, it's probably this one, but otherwise you can catch the usual round up back here in a week. See you then.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Results:</hi> Ascoli 0-1 Empoli, Catania 3-2 Livorno, Fiorentina 3-1 Atalanta, Lazio 5-0 Udinese, Messina 2-2 Cagliari, Milan 1-2 Roma, Palermo 3-0 Torino, Parma 1-2 Internazionale, Sampdoria 3-0 Chievo, Siena 0-1 Reggina.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>