<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2003-07-25" description="He cannot be prosecuted, and now Silvio Berlusconi is seeking to prohibit even the investigation of his past activities, writes John Hooper." fingerprint="9f2c892a54a4b77f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Above the law" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jul/25/italy.worlddispatch">
<main>
<p>We are starting to learn the true meaning of "immunity" in the Italy of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>Last month, the Italian parliament approved a hugely controversial law that granted immunity from prosecution to five top state officials - the president, the head of the constitutional court, the speakers of the two houses of parliament and the prime minister. The immediate effect was to suspend Mr Berlusconi's trial on charges of bribing judges.</p>
<p>But that - we now learn - was not all. Last Friday, the new law was invoked by Mr Berlusconi's justice minister to stop in its tracks an inquiry into alleged tax fraud by the prime minister's businesses.</p>
<p>Prosecutors in Milan have been investigating claims that two of Mr Berlusconi's firms - his holding company Fininvest, and his TV group, Mediaset - worked together to cheat Italy's taxpayers of 80m euros (£57m). The allegation is that two offshore subsidiaries of Fininvest were used to buy American film rights and then sell them on to Mediaset at inflated prices that allowed the TV network to reduce its profits and thus its tax bill.</p>
<p>In May, the prosecutors began the process of gathering evidence from the US. For courts in one country to admit evidence gathered in another, the standard procedure is a so-called "rogatoire": the lawyers send a request to their justice ministry, which passes it to the embassy of the country in question, which passes it in turn to its government whose agents then set about gathering the required evidence.</p>
<p>This process had already begun - the US embassy in Rome had been sent the prosecutor's "shopping list" - when the justice minister, Roberto Castelli, stepped in. He got the "shopping list" back from the embassy and returned it to Milan saying the request was at odds with the new law.</p>
<p>The prosecutors' "mistake" was to have added Silvio Berlusconi to the list of suspects earlier this year. They claim to have evidence that the prime minister, who withdrew from the day-to-day management of his group in the mid-1990s, was nonetheless aware of the alleged scam and even set out guidelines for its execution.</p>
<p>But, since Mr Berlusconi can no longer be prosecuted, the ministry's case is that the investigation as a whole is illegal.</p>
<p>The government and its supporters insist the rogatoire has only been suspended while the justice minister seeks expert advice on the scope of the law. Suspiciously, however, nobody has so far been able to identify the expert he is said to be consulting.</p>
<p>The ministry's argument would anyway be more understandable if it were not for the fact that, while the immunity bill was in parliament, members of Mr Berlusconi's own party repeatedly assured their opponents that it was intended solely to block trials and not investigations. Now, they are saying something altogether different.</p>
<p>One MP from Mr Berlusconi's Forza Italia ("Come on Italy") party claimed that a clause, which no one seemed to have noticed, applies the provisions of the law to "every stage and circumstance of the judicial process".</p>
<p>That will certainly have come as news to Italy's president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, whose officials have let it be known that he only signed the immunity bill on to the statute books on the understanding that it applied exclusively to trials and not investigations.</p>
<p>The prosecutors, for their part, have argued that - whatever the scope of the law - Mr Caselli's intervention is at odds with Italy's penal code, which states that the justice ministry can only stop a rogatoire at the outset.</p>
<p>Their superiors have returned the justice minister's reply to him, describing it as "unreceivable". Using language rarely heard, even in Italy, in exchanges between the courts and the government, Milan's deputy chief prosecutor, Armando Spataro, said: "We are at one of the most serious junctures in the war on the courts declared by a section of the political classes which is in government ... we are dealing with a minister who, ignorant of the letter and the meaning of the law, is attempting to take the place of the judges."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>