<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-09-28" description="Prime minister needs majority to avoid resignation and his survival could hang on support of rebel Gianfranco Fini" fingerprint="7fa8d0b59a218f34" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi gambles on crucial confidence vote in Italian parliament" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/sep/28/silvio-berlusconi-gamble-confidence-vote">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi today decided to take an unexpected, all-or-nothing gamble by submitting his government to a confidence vote in parliament. If he loses he will have to resign, and even if he fails to secure an outright majority in the lower house tomorrow, he could step down.</p>
<p>Estimates based on declared voting intentions all suggested Italy's billionaire leader and his rightwing administration could get an absolute majority only if a rebel group, led by his former lieutenant, Gianfranco Fini, came back into line. Intermediaries acting on the PM's behalf were reportedly engaged in intensive, behind-the-scenes efforts to lure away deputies elected for the opposition. Pierluigi Bersani, the leader of Italy's biggest opposition group, the Democratic party, reminded Berlusconi that "if someone is promised an appointment or … an income, that is corruption – stuff for the judges."</p>
<p>Italian politics have focused on tomorrow's vote for almost two months, against a lurid background of sleaze and dirty tricks allegations. After Fini and other discontented members of the governing Freedom People movement set up their own parliamentary group, Berlusconi survived a first test in parliament on 4 August.</p>
<p>But the rebels' abstention left him without an absolute majority, and effectively a prisoner of Fini. Tomorrow's vote was called to ensure the rebels would back what the PM singled out as the five key points of his government's programme for the rest of the legislature.</p>
<p>Fini's group, Future and Freedom for Italy (FLI), is committed to voting only for measures in the government's original programme. But Berlusconi has included among his five points a reform of court procedure that was not agreed on after the 2008 general election and which critics say is intended solely to get him out of his personal difficulties with the law.</p>
<p>An FLI deputy, Fabio Granata, said the attitude of the group would depend on Berlusconi's speech to parliament before the vote: "If things that are not in the programme are put in there, we will not vote for it."</p>
<p>That may not, however, hold good for all Fini's followers. One has already returned to the Berlusconi camp and several others have expressed misgivings, both about the way the FLI is being run and the wider impact of their revolt.</p>
<p>The prime minister has several times drawn attention to the fact that a new bout of political instability could have serious effects on the financial markets' already fragile confidence in Italy and the euro. Appeals for national unity have already smoothed the path from opposition to government majority for at least seven lawmakers.</p>
<p>But the rebel votes, when added to those of the Berlusconi loyalists, still appeared to leave the government four short of an outright majority. And that was without allowing for deputies who failed to make the ballot due to illness.</p>
<p>Ever since the split in the government's ranks, the atmosphere on the Italian right has grown steadily more poisonous. Newspapers close to Berlusconi have carried a string of reports linking Fini and the family of his partner, Elisabetta Tulliani, to an allegedly shady property deal.</p>
<p>The Fini camp has claimed, and the government has furiously denied, that intelligence services were used to produce evidence. Tulliani's brother, Giancarlo, was found to be renting a flat in Monte Carlo bequeathed to Fini's former party, the "post-fascist" National Alliance.</p>
<p>The flat, allegedly sold at below-market value, belongs to a company registered in the Caribbean island of St Lucia. Last week, the island's finance minister recognized as genuine a letter saying the company's beneficial owner was Giancarlo Tulliano.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>