<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Leigh Holmwood" categories="Media" date="2006-09-26" description="8am: The BBC's Panorama is to investigate allegations that media secretary Tessa Jowell's estranged husband David Mills took a 'bribe' from former Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi. By Leigh Holmwood." fingerprint="2fb30a8f4ce173cd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Politics,BBC,Italy,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,David Mills,Europe" title="Panorama looks into Berlusconi 'bribe' affair" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/sep/26/politics.bbc">
<main>
<p>The BBC's Panorama is to investigate allegations that culture secretary Tessa Jowell's estranged husband David Mills took a "bribe" from former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>The programme, which is expected to air on BBC1 next month, is likely to prove particularly testing for Ms Jowell, who separated from Mr Mills six months ago.</p>
<p>The investigation could also prove uncomfortable for the corporation at a time when Ms Jowell is completing her thinking on the BBC's case for an inflation-busting licence fee rise.</p>
<p>The programme, which will be fronted by reporter John Sweeney, will look at allegations that Mr Mills took a £345,000 "bribe" in the 1990s from Mr Berlusconi.</p>
<p>The case, which is due to be heard in a Milan court in November, centres on allegations that Mr Mills created a financial network through which the former Italian premier's Mediaset TV empire evaded more than £40m in tax.</p>
<p>If found guilty Mr Mills faces 12 years in prison.</p>
<p>A BBC spokesman confirmed the programme was in production, but said Mr Mills, who has consistently denied the allegations, would not be taking part.</p>
<p>The investigation is the latest in a series of Panorama programmes that have proved uncomfortable for the BBC.</p>
<p>The programme's recent investigation into football bungs led Bolton manager Sam Allardyce to ban all BBC outlets from his press conferences, while an uncompromising look at the corporation's involvement in the Dr David Kelly affair proved embarrassing for executives.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the BBC met the Football Association on Monday to discuss handing over evidence from its Panorama investigation about alleged corruption within the game.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> To contact the MediaGuardian newsdesk email <ref target="mailto:editor@mediatheguardian.com">editor@mediatheguardian.com</ref> or phone 020 7239 9857</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> If you are writing a comment for publication, please mark clearly "for publication".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>