<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Jessica Reed" categories="Opinion" date="2008-05-22" description="Jessica Reed: The French president likes to pose as a champion of press freedom. In reality, he has wooed media magnates and bullied their journalists" fingerprint="f7c0dbaf07ad9f8d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="France,Politics,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Press freedom,Europe" title="Sarkozy, the new Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/may/22/sarkozythenewberlusconi">
<main>
<p>In the early hours of December 5 in central Paris, six secret service agents knocked on the door of investigative journalist <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillaume_Dasqui%C3%A9">Guillaume Dasquié</ref>: "Monsieur, this is the French Directorate of Territorial Security. You are under arrest for compromising national security."</p>
<p>Armed with a warrant, they meticulously searched his home and demanded that he give up any documents concerning an article he had written for the Le Monde in April 2007, which was titled "<ref target="http://www.lemonde.fr/societe/article/2007/04/16/ce-que-les-services-francais-savaient-de-ben-laden-en-2000_896448_3224.html#ens_id=892780">September 11: the French had long known</ref>".</p>
<p>The investigation published in the French newspaper related how the secret service agency had warned the US government about possible al-Qaida terrorist plots before 9/11. The allegations were substantiated by a 358-page classified report obtained by Dasquié from an insider. Following the search, the journalist was then taken to the outskirts of town to the counter-espionage headquarters, where he was <ref target="http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=24662">detained</ref> for 34 hours. After being threatened with a lengthy prison sentence and continuously pressured to reveal his sources, the journalist agreed to give the name of an indirect source.</p>
<p>This disturbing episode was possible thanks to the very imprecise French law addressing journalists' sources. The 1881 penal code vaguely stipulates that every journalist has the right to withhold information to protect the confidentiality of sources, but many dirty tricks can be played to override this legal protection: detentions, charges for the violation of a judicial investigation's confidentiality or accusations of stealing documents. Indeed, the European Court of Human Rights has <ref target="http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=15284">condemned</ref> France several times over for not guaranteeing adequate protection for journalists' sources.</p>
<p>Last Friday, the French parliament debated a controversial new law aimed at recognising a journalist's right to protect sources - a promise made by Sarkozy during his presidential campaign. The bill, which was drafted by Sarkozy's protegee justice minister <ref target="http://commentisfree.theguardian.com/colin_randall/2007/07/datis_malchance.html">Rachida Dati</ref>, is highly controversial and is viewed as a mockery by journalists' unions - with reason. The bill states that, in special cases, reporters could be asked to name names if a "pressing imperative" requires it.</p>
<p>This clause recalls the much blogged-about case of <ref target="http://commentisfree.theguardian.com/jeff_jarvis/2006/08/a_blogger_behind_bars.html">Josh Wolf</ref>, a citizen journalist who spent eight months in prison for refusing to disclose his sources, and it doesn't take long to understand that too many interpretations of this law are possible. Fears were certainly not alleviated by the incredibly unlikely example picked by Dati to <ref target="http://www.france24.com/en/20080516-french-parliament-splits-journalism-bill-france-journalism">justify</ref> the legislation:</p>
<quote>
<hi>"A newspaper receives a letter from a kidnapper. He threatens to kill the child in 48 hours unless ransom is paid. The investigators have no leads. It is urgent to act to save the life of the child; the journalist invokes the confidentiality of his sources. Can we take the risk of allowing a child to be killed?"</hi>
</quote>
<p>In truth, it would seem that Sarkozy's promise to reform French law to protect journalistic freedoms is nothing but hypocritical. Indeed, a more subtle state pressure has been exerted on the French press, which has been suffering bouts of acute Sarkozymania for the past year. As Sarkozy has been piling on prime-time interviews, weekly front pages and even glossy magazine covers, his <ref target="http://www.opendemocracy.net/globalization-institutions_government/france_telepolitics_4492.jsp">privileged relationships</ref> with media tycoons <ref target="http://www.forbes.com/lists/2006/10/08C6.html">Martin Bouyges</ref> (godfather to one of Sarkozy's son) and <ref target="http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2007/fortune/0711/gallery.power_25.fortune/25.html">Bernard Arnault</ref> are often mentioned with suspicion by journalists.</p>
<p>Case in point: when a Paris-Match editor ran pictures of Sarkozy's ex-wife Cecilia Sarkozy and her lover, he was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2006/jun/28/pressandpublishing.france">ordered</ref> to quit on the spot. The fact that media magnate Arnaud Lagardère (whom the president refers to as "not a friend, but a brother") owns the magazine was brought up by scandalised journalists, who issued a statement asking for the "firm and absolute guarantee" of editorial independence so that "this unprecedented event never happens again."</p>
<p>Furthermore, following the withdrawal of a news piece reporting that Cecilia Sarkozy did not vote for the second elections round, outraged journalists working for the newspaper Le Journal du Dimanche <ref target="http://tempsreel.nouvelobs.com/speciales/medias__pouvoirs/20070514.OBS7007/le_jdd_renonce_a_publierun_article_sur_cecilia_sarkozy.html">wrote</ref> an open letter to Lagardère, who had allegedly intervened and told editors to kill the story. In another case, when still on the campaign train, the president is also said to have threatened that, if elected, he would fire the heads of the public regional channel, France 3, because he did not like its coverage. Similar examples abound: last week, AFP journalists <ref target="http://www.iht.com/articles/2008/05/12/europe/afp.php">condemned</ref> "attempts at political pressure" following a feud with the spokesman of Sarkozy's <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_for_a_Popular_Movement">Union for a Popular Movement party</ref>.</p>
<p>Nicolas Sarkozy's huge circle of influencial friends is seen by many as the latent "Berlusconisation" of the media. Le Monde Diplomatique <ref target="http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/2006/09/BENILDE/13928">hinted</ref> at this even before the elections, reporting that Sarkozy had been working on building his own network of friends in the media world for more than 20 years, which he "planned on using for his supreme ambitions". The headlines are often diverted to his wife and the brand of sunglasses he is wearing (<ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/debate/columnists/article-537608/Sarkozy-A-man-desperate-Steve-McQueen-whos-like-poor-mans-Fonz.html">Ray Bans</ref>, if you're asking), while Sarkozy gets away with voicing startlingly provocative, even <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1565757/Nicolas-Sarkozy's-adviser-accused-of-racism.html">racist</ref>, sentiments with relative impunity.</p>
<p>While visiting Tunisia last month, he <ref target="http://www.globalvoicesonline.org/2008/05/11/tunisia-sarkozys-visit-spurs-blog-reactions/">proclaimed</ref> his desire to "unite the intellect of the north and the labour of the south". He also complimented Tunisia on its "progress of space for freedoms" while explaining that he did not desire to give anyone lessons.</p>
<p>What, indeed, would he have to teach anyone on that topic?</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>