<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Leonardo Clausi" categories="Opinion" date="2008-08-08" description="Leonardo Clausi: Berlusconi is no Mussolini, but in the way he handles the media, at least, there are parallels to be drawn" fingerprint="bed2c82d94e78309" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Leonardo Clausi: Berlusconi is no Mussolini, but there are parallels to be drawn" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/aug/08/italy.berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has once again proven to his detractors his unrivalled media skills. He has been shoving himself in front of cameras in the streets of Naples, surrounded by sombre bodyguards, brandishing a <ref target="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/2519418/Silvio-Berlusconi-sweeps-the-streets-of-Naples.html">broom</ref> to demonstrate that the rubbish emergency that has beleaguered the city and the country is a thing of the past.</p>
<p>So far, nothing more than the same populist posing, which Berlusconi relishes. But there's something in this latest images that won't have escaped the historically literate: the similarity with the stocky and muscular physiognomy of Il Duce, who had himself <ref target="http://www.valsesiascuole.it/crosior/1_vercellese/fascismo_risicoltura.htm">photographed</ref> harvesting bare-chested during the so-called battaglia del grano (battle of wheat) in the late 1920s. It was a powerful image, charged with immediacy and significance, an amalgam of the modern and the archaic that even today characterises contemporary Italian culture.</p>
<p>And yesterday, more than half a century later, someone was at it again. Not that this is entirely original, or a unique quality of Italian populism. Every contemporary political leader is used to immersing himself into the adoring (sometimes less so) crowd, listening to the grievances of the people and kissing their babies. But they rarely indulge in such a no-nonsense rolling up of shirt-sleeves: there's a lot of power in the image of an immensely rich leader taking matters into his own hands. And again, one is reminded of the meaning of the battaglia del grano. It was based on the principle of "autarchy", the economy of self-sufficiency promoted by the regime as a reaction to the hostility of the international community. It meant "we can do it by ourselves". Like Berlusconi in the streets of Naples, yesterday.</p>
<p>But let's make it very clear, Silvio is not Benito (and thank God for that). To begin with, Mussolini was fiercely bald and had a jaw that expressed a steely resolution. He never smiled. He did not glory in his riches, and money and the preservation of it weren't amongst his priorities in entering politics. Most of all, Mussolini started out as a socialist, something that is too often forgotten. And of course, the catastrophes he dragged his country into are too well known to list. Berlusconi is different. He might be bald, but his hair has that special quality normally associated with Phoenixes: it grows back on a regular basis. He smiles a lot, a bit too often maybe. His smile is perfect, the 32-toothed smile of a salesman, reassuring, expressing the confidence of power and wealth.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, it goes without saying, didn't start out as a socialist, but as a building contractor. Socialism to him has always had the decaying smell of poverty, it is something that never crossed the threshold of his imaginative mind. To his credit, in a very un-Italian way, he has never abruptly changed alignment. He's always sided with the strong, and ever since, like a reverse Robin Hood, has stolen from the poor to give to the rich.</p>
<p>But the fact that a comparison is repeatedly drawn between the two men, especially abroad, it is not merely chance. The populism, the autocracy, the cult of personality: these are common to both. And there's another factor that encourages otherwise historically reckless parallels: the use of the media.</p>
<p>If Mussolini famously stated that "Il cinematografo è l'arma più forte" (cinema is the strongest weapon), demonstrating a perfect grasp of the zeitgeist (totalitarian regimes have got the importance of "educational" cinema earlier than liberal democracies), Berlusconi has really pushed the boundaries of propaganda through visual media. In this he was helped, of course, by a more than sympathetic political environment, one set up 30 years ago by his great ally, Bettino Craxi, then leader of the Socialist party, who died in self-imposed exile for corruption, and who today has been officially rehabilitated and declared a martyr.</p>
<p>He might not be Mussolini, but getting rid of Berlusconi won't be easy. Actually I suspect it will be impossible. Why? He has systematically destroyed the nation's powers of discernment with a 30 year-long barrage of trashy and tendentious TV. Like a skilled jeweller, he has moulded and refined the taste and the ideology of a couple of generations.</p>
<p>And there's more than a good chance that he will end his devastating tenure at Italy's helm as president of the republic. Stunts like yesterday's only confirm how far ahead of the rest of the pack he is.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>