<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2008-04-17" description="Letters: Your leader on Italy's parliamentary elections recycles cliched views about the ephemeral nature of Italian democracy without noting the changes that this vote has wrought" fingerprint="234f402f11a19dc9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Letters: Look on bright side of Berlusconi's win" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/apr/18/italy">
<main>
<p>Your leader on Italy's parliamentary elections (April 15) recycles cliched views about the ephemeral nature of Italian democracy without noting the changes that this vote has wrought. It is certainly true that Berlusconi's victory may "solve nothing" in the short term, but you ignore the fact that, on the left, the election has given birth to something unknown in postwar Italian politics: a unified progressive party. To suggest that the best hope for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to avoid political torpor would be if the Partito Democratico were to enter into a grand coalition with Berlusconi's union of populists and neo-fascists is naive, given that there will finally be something close to bipolarism in the Italian parliament.</p>
<p>I would have thought that, rather than hoping the Italian people might give up on the idea of electing their governments according to ideology, your newspaper might have taken this opportunity to express its support for the incoming Italian opposition and wished instead that the PD might lead a renaissance in the standard of political debate south of the Alps.<hi rend="#b">Laurence Hooper</hi><lb/> University of Cambridge</p>
<p>I am more inclined to draw upon the positive outcomes: the political marginalisation of the far left and the far right - neither wing having obtained a single seat in either chamber. Both fascism and communism are ideological streams that have been soundly defeated. A less emotional analysis would yield the conclusion that, despite the questionable figure of Berlusconi at its head, the incoming government offers a much-needed absolute majority in both the assembly and senate so that it is, mechanically at least, much more feasible that the crucial and painful legislation the sistema Italia so desperately requires will be approved. Italians, having looked in vain to the left to salvage the wreck of the Italian economy, have perhaps resolved that it is better to choose the devil that they already know. <hi rend="#b">Stefano Mariani</hi><lb/> London</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>