<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2003-12-24" description="The Italian cabinet passed an emergency decree yesterday to save one of the prime minister's private TV channels, in what critics have called the most blatant case of Silvio Berlusconi altering laws to protect his business interests." fingerprint="7eeecb2f5084ff5c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Italian cabinet steps in to aid Berlusconi channel" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/dec/24/italy.media">
<main>
<p>The Italian cabinet passed an emergency decree yesterday to save one of the prime minister's private TV channels, in what critics have called the most blatant case of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> altering laws to protect his business interests.</p>
<p>The decree overrules a previous court decision that Retequattro should move to satellite by the year-end, a move that would cost it as much as €250m (£175m) annually in advertising revenue.</p>
<p>Tuesday's decree was announced after the president, Carlo Azeglio Ciampi, rejected an earlier media bill amid concerns that it was formulated to favour the expansion of Mr Berlusconi's media empire.</p>
<p>Mr Ciampi has the final word on the Retequattro decree too, but was expected to sign it later in the week.</p>
<p>At present, Mr Berlusconi is thought to control more than 90% of Italian television through his three Mediaset channels and his office, which gives him indirect control of the state broadcaster Radiotelevisione Italiana (RAI).</p>
<p>The bill thrown out by the president paved the way for the privatisation of RAI and would allow Mr Berlusconi's holding firm to expand into radio and newspapers in 2009.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi argued the law was vital to modernise the Italian media. If parliament votes through the bill a second time President Ciampi will be obliged to sign.</p>
<p>Under Tuesday's decree, Retequattro, which carries the most pro-Berlusconi news, can continue broadcasting as usual until April 30, when a media watchdog will judge whether having three "Berlusconi" channels stifles competition. If so, Retequattro will have to go by May 30.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi has dismissed as "urban legend" the idea of a conflict of interest between his business and political roles.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>