<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-10-08" description="Emergency meeting called, allegedly to discuss Berlusconi's behaviour and the risk that he was tipping Italy into constitutional crisis" fingerprint="ffa40b0d9087f71d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Media,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi lets rip in all directions after loss of immunity" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/08/silvio-berlusconi-immunity-television">
<main>
<p>Like an enraged, wounded animal, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> struck out indiscriminately at his perceived tormentors yesterday, after Italy's constitutional court stripped him of his immunity from prosecution.</p>
<p>Tonight the head of state, President Giorgio Napolitano, summoned the speakers of both houses of parliament to an emergency meeting, apparently to discuss Berlusconi's behaviour and the risk that he was tipping <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> into constitutional crisis.</p>
<p>Within less than 24 hours of yesterday's judgment, the prime minister had insulted the constitutional court, questioned the impartiality of the president and his predecessors, and held a female MP up to ridicule on live television.</p>
<p>Gianfranco Fini, the rightwing speaker of the chamber of deputies, who has stood at the TV magnate's side since the start of his turbulent political career, openly deplored his reaction. "Silvio Berlusconi's indisputable political right, conferred on him by the voters, to govern and reform the country does not relieve him of his precise constitutional duty to respect the constitutional court and the head of state," Fini said.</p>
<p>The bizarre sequence that prompted Fini's intervention began the previous evening when, after issuing a restrained statement in reaction to the court's decision, the prime minister launched into a rant outside his Rome residence. Among his targets was the court which, he said, was a "political body" whose members had been "chosen by three leftwing heads of state".</p>
<p>The president, who has limited powers but exerts immense moral influence, is the guarantor of the constitution and meant to be above party interests. Napolitano was a communist until the party dissolved itself and went on to become part of the centre-left opposition Democratic party. His two predecessors, a former governor of the Bank of Italy and a Christian Democrat, have both joined the Democratic party since leaving office.</p>
<p>On a late-night TV show that Berlusconi joined by phone, he told the watching millions that Napolitano should have used "his influence" to get a different ruling from the court.</p>
<p>When a studio guest, Rosy Bindi, a former centre-left minister, expressed outrage at his suggestion, Berlusconi replied: "I recognise you are increasingly more beautiful than intelligent." A shocked Bindi hit back with an allusion to the sex scandals surrounding the prime minister, saying she was "a woman who is not at your disposal".</p>
<p>Among many who weighed in to support Bindi was a party colleague, Giovanna Melandri, who said the remark had summed up "the Berlusconi philosophy towards women"; the diminutive prime minister had shown himself to be "taller than he is well-mannered".</p>
<p>Unabashed, an irate Berlusconi renewed his attack on the president today. Napolitano, he told a radio interviewer, "was elected by a leftwing majority. His roots are entirely in his leftwing history and his most recent appointment, of one of the judges to the constitutional court, showed which side he is on."</p>
<p>The senate's opposition deputy speaker, Vannino Chiti, said: "The prime minister's attack on the president of the republic is very serious. Berlusconi is a man of division. To safeguard his interests he would be prepared to destroy the country."</p>
<p>The Catholic bishops' newspaper, Avvenire, also sounded an apocalyptic note. An editorial said Italy was "on the edge of a precipice".</p>
<p>But tonight the signs were that Berlusconi does not intend calling demonstrations, let alone a snap election. "The government will carry on calmly, unconcernedly and with more grit even than before," he vowed.</p>
<p>The law overturned by the court had extended immunity from prosecution to the president, the two parliamentary speakers and the prime minister. It led to the suspension of one trial in which Berlusconi is a defendant and his removal from another in which his co-defendant was the British lawyer, David Mills, husband of the Olympics minister, Tessa Jowell.</p>
<p>Mills will launch his appeal against a jail sentence of four-and-a-half years that he was given in February after being convicted of accepting a bribe from Berlusconi – a verdict that logically is tantamount to establishing that a bribe had been paid by Berlusconi.</p>
<p>His lawyer is expected to ask the court in Milan for leave to call the prime minister as a witness.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>