<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Football" date="2014-07-04" description="The Milan president, Silvio Berlusconi, has revealed he came close to selling Mario Balotelli to an unnamed Premier League club before the World Cup" fingerprint="3227d5fd1cab0e17" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Mario Balotelli,Milan,Transfer window,Silvio Berlusconi,Football,Sport" title="Mario Balotelli almost moved to England before World Cup – Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2014/jul/04/mario-balotelli-england-world-cup-berlusconi-milan">
<main>
<p>The Milan president, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, has revealed he came close to selling Mario Balotelli to an unnamed Premier League club before the World Cup.</p>
<p>The Italy striker has been strongly linked with a return to England this summer, with Arsenal reportedly keen to acquire his services for around €35m (£28m).</p>
<p>The former Manchester City striker scored the winner against England but that was his only goal in three appearances in Brazil, as Italy suffered early elimination from the tournament.</p>
<p>“Other than Italy, I lost during the World Cup,” Berlusconi was quoted as saying in Gazzetta dello Sport. “I was about to sell Balotelli to an English team for several millions. But after this World Cup who will buy him any more?”</p>
<p>His daughter Barbara Berlusconi, Milan’s vice-president, last month hinted at the possibility of a Balotelli transfer this summer by saying he is “replaceable”.</p>
<p>Balotelli’s agent has also suggested his client will move away from the San Siro. Mino Raiola claimed the 23-year-old was “sad and desperate” after being widely criticised in the Italian media following his disappointing World Cup.</p>
<p>Balotelli, who still has four years left on his contract with the <hi rend="#i">Rossoneri</hi>, has scored 30 goals in 54 matches for Milan since his move from Manchester City in January 2013. Milan are keen to sell Balotelli for financial reasons. They will not compete in Europe next season for the first time in 16 years after finishing a disappointing eighth in Serie A.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>