<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-06-04" description="Release of photographs prompts Italian PM to admit he is suspect in inquiry into alleged misuse of public funds" fingerprint="1ff8522c93f7cf2f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi in further trouble after claims of flight for star in official plane" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/04/silvio-berlusconi-plane-inquiry-public-funds">
<main>
<p>The furore surrounding <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> took a new turn today when the Italian prime minister admitted he was a suspect in an inquiry into the alleged misuse of public funds after photographs circulated in Italy showing he had used an official aircraft to fly entertainers to his villa on Sardinia.</p>
<p>Speaking to a Milan television station, Berlusconi confirmed that he had been formally placed under investigation, but added the probe would be "swiftly shelved". The inquiry is the direct result of a controversy surrounding the 72 year-old media tycoon's still unexplained relationship with an 18-year-old aspiring model and actress, Noemi Letizia.</p>
<p>On Saturday, responding to an application by Berlusconi's lawyers, prosecutors in Rome ordered the seizure of some 300 pictures taken by a photographer on Sardinia, where the prime minister has a villa and estate. Berlusconi learnt of the photographs after they were offered to a news magazine he owns.</p>
<p>They included scenes of parties at the villa attended by Letizia and other young women aspiring to a career in showbusiness. According to Berlusconi's lawyer, one of the photographs showed the former Czech prime minister, Mirek Topolanek, naked by the side of a pool.</p>
<p>Among the impounded pictures, however, the investigators also found several taken at nearby Olbia airport before one of the parties. They showed Berlusconi's favourite singer-songwriter, Mariano Apicella, his assistant and an unidentified woman in dark glasses disembarking from the prime minister's official plane. The prosecutors extended their inquiry to include Berlusconi after a consumer association representing taxpayers demanded they do so.</p>
<p>Berlusconi said: "There is a precise regulation that allows the prime minister to take people with him at nil cost." But, as the newspaper La Stampa observed, the regulation – brought in by Berlusconi himself – did not take effect until August last year. The prime minister's friends were photographed leaving an aircraft paid for by the taxpayer three months earlier in May.</p>
<p>The TV and property billionaire said one of the reasons he had invited the Czech republic's then prime minister to his island retreat was to "promote a friendship" before Topolanek took up the rotating presidency of the European Union on January 1. He said the Czech was once of several heads of state and government to whom he had "offered all that I receive from them, including shows with artistes. But this is not a burden on the [Italian] state."</p>
<p>His admission came three days before Italians are due to vote in the European parliamentary elections. The latest polls show that Berlusconi's popularity ratings, though hit by the scandal, remain high. His rightwing Freedom People movement is hoping for 45% of the vote in Sunday's European ballot.</p>
<p>Berlusconi also enhanced his reputation for undiplomatic asides todaywhen, in one of a string of interviews, he said Angela Merkel was "not very easy from the point of view of human relations". He added that he had nevertheless managed to build with her a relationship of "very great trust and friendship". He astonished other leaders at a Nato gathering in April when he kept the German chancellor, his host, waiting at the entrance to the meeting while he finished a long mobile telephone call.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>