<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2003-07-05" description="Sophie Arie compares flamboyant Silvio Berlusconi with his more serious rival Romano Prodi." fingerprint="55aadb69d311cf07" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,European Union,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="The Knight v the Sausage" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/jul/05/italy.eu">
<main>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">·</hi>
</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Il Cavaliere, as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> is known, has pioneered a new politics in Italy based on football terminology and showmanship. His party is called after a football chant, Forza Italia (Come on Italy!) He called his own entrance into Italian politics 'going on to the pitch'</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> The two men personify the political split through the heart of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> - between the centre-right coalition, which includes post fascists and the anti-immigration Northern League, and the left, which includes former Communists who now go under the party name of Democrats of the Left. Power swung from Mr Berlusconi in 1994 to Mr Prodi in 1996 and back again in 2001. Mr Prodi, who is expected to return from Brussels to Italian politics next year, is widely seen as the opposition left's best bet to replace Mr Berlusconi in 2006</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> In terms of personal style, the two men could not be more different. Il Professore likes to spend his spare time riding his bicycle while Il Cavaliere has complained recently that his demanding job means he cannot spend enough time in his various luxury villas or on his private yacht</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">·</hi> Their mutual disdain has frequently bubbled to the surface, most clearly when Mr Prodi commented that Nazi propaganda chief Goebbels was 'just a kid' compared to Mr Berlusconi, who describes his less flamboyant rival as 'a good cyclist'</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>