<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Dominic Rushe" categories="Business" date="2011-10-07" description="Move by ratings agency Fitch ends three-day rally on Wall Street and raises fears about the health of Europe's banks" fingerprint="100c8b8501332642" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,US economic growth and recession,Rating agencies,Silvio Berlusconi,Economic growth (GDP),Nicolas Sarkozy,Angela Merkel,Italy,Spain,US economy,Business,World news,US news,Fitch" title="Italy and Spain downgraded by Fitch over eurozone crisis" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/oct/07/italy-spain-credit-downgrade-fitch">
<main>
<p>The eurozone crisis intensified on Friday when Spain and Italy were downgraded by the ratings agency <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/fitch">Fitch</ref>, heightening fears over the health of Europe's banks.</p>
<p>The move ended a three-day rally on Wall Street and erased early gains on the stock markets that followed <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/oct/07/us-new-jobs-unemployment-rate">better-than-expected US employment figures</ref>.</p>
<p>The euro fell against most major currencies, piling fresh pressure on European politicians to restore confidence in the single currency. Germany's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</ref> said Europe needed to find a solution for its banks by 17 October. Analysts from Capital Economics estimate the total financial package may top €200bn (£172bn).</p>
<p>Merkel and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/nicolas-sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref> of France are due to meet in Berlin on Sunday to discuss the crisis, with bank recapitalisation expected to be at the heart of their negotiations.</p>
<p>The cut on <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> – to A-plus from double-A-minus – leaves its rating four steps down from the coveted triple-A designation. Fitch said its outlook on the country is negative, implying more cuts to come. The agency said that Italy's high level of public debt and low rate of potential growth renders its economy especially vulnerable to external shocks.</p>
<p>"The downgrade reflects the intensification of the eurozone crisis that constitutes a significant financial and economic shock which has weakened Italy's sovereign risk profile," Fitch said in a statement. "A credible and comprehensive solution to the crisis is politically and technically complex and will take time to put in place and to earn the trust of investors," the agency added.</p>
<p>Spain's credit rating was cut by two notches, to double-A-minus from double-A-plus, with Fitch blaming government spending, weak economic growth and the eurozone debt crisis for the fall.</p>
<p>"The downgrade primarily reflects two factors – the intensification of the euro area crisis and secondly, risks to the fiscal consolidation effort arising from the budgetary performance of some regions and downward revision by Fitch of Spain's medium-term growth prospects," it said. Spain too was "especially vulnerable" to an external shock.</p>
<p>In Italy, premier Silvio Berlusconi's office moved to highlight some of the positive notes in the Fitch report, noting that that the agency has concluded Italy's bid to stabilise and gradually reduce its debt to gross domestic product ratio was "eminently achievable."</p>
<p>The director-general of Italy's central bank, Fabrizio Saccomanni, said there was nothing new in the report, and that the agencies were following a "herd-like" mentality in their downgrades. On Tuesday, Fitch's rival Moody's also cut Italy's credit rating. Standard &amp; Poor's cut Italy's rating in September.</p>
<p>In the UK, Moody's cut its ratings for 12 banks and building societies, downgraded amid speculation that Europe is preparing action to bolster the finances of the continent's banks by next weekend. Moody's said the downgrade of the UK's banks was necessary because the government was stepping back from bailing them out when they ran into difficulty. "The downgrades do not reflect a deterioration in the financial strength of the banking system or that of the government," Moody's said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>