<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2014-04-15" description="The 77-year-old's past as a crooner on a cruise ship may come in handy during his year of community service as a carer" fingerprint="feead06792be9387" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi to 'entertain' the elderly and help at meal times" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/15/silvio-berlusconi-care-worker-duties-entertainment-helping-meal-times">
<main>
<p>If the small, unremarkable town of Cesano Boscone had ever intruded on Silvio Berlusconi's serene consciousness before yesterday, it was probably as the home of Massimo Tartaglia, the man who attacked him in 2009 with a souvenir model of Milan's cathedral.</p>
<p>For the next year, however, Italy's former prime minister is going to be spending more time there than he had ever imagined. A court in Milan ruled yesterday that as his sentence for tax fraud the billionaire media mogul would be performing community service in Cesano – "once a week and for a period of no less than four consecutive hours" – in a centre for the elderly and disabled.</p>
<p>"We had our confirmation from journalists," Paolo Pigni, director of the <ref target="http://www.sacrafamiglia.org">Fondazione Sacra Famiglia</ref>, told the Guardian, sounding as surprised as anyone else. In the past, he said, those coming to the foundation on court-mandated community service would help out with general volunteer activities.</p>
<p>"They support – but do not substitute – the health workers," he said. "They accompany [the patients] as they move around, help with entertainment-related activities and during the meals."</p>
<p>It is not clear in which of these particular activities Berlusconi is expected to excel, but his past as a 1960s cruise ship crooner could feasibly come in handy. As was illustrated at his "elegant dinners" at Villa San Martino – just 25 miles from Cesano – he has a keen eye for entertainment in diverse forms.</p>
<p>In Cesano, however, with "the non self-sufficient elderly", the audience's average age might be significantly closer to his own than that of his party guests at Arcore.</p>
<p>Ridicule aside, the sentence from the <hi rend="#i">tribunal</hi>e<hi rend="#i"> di sorveglianza</hi> in fact gave the 77-year-old something to smile about – faintly – at a time of unprecedented political woes. For weeks Berlusconi had been concerned – "anguished", as one aide put it – about the verdict, which came more than eight months after his conviction for tax fraud was made definitive by Italy's supreme court and judges handed down a four-year sentence, immediately commuted to a year.</p>
<p>While jail had never been a serious possibility due to Berlusconi's age and crime, house arrest had – and it would have had a drastic impact on his plans to campaign, on behalf of his Forza Italia (FI) party, in the European elections next month.</p>
<p>Instead, judge Pasquale Nobile de Santis set out a series of restrictions that, though in stark contrast to Berlusconi's less than ascetic habits, are expected to allow him just enough time to continue his political activities. The ex-premier will be subject to a curfew of 11pm. He will not be able to leave the region of Lombardy except to go to his home in the centre of Rome – and he will be able to do that every week from Tuesday to Thursday, providing he is back at Arcore by 11pm on the Thursday. If all goes well, Berlusconi could even expect the year to be shortened, eventually, to ten and a half months.</p>
<p>"The decision of the <hi rend="#i">tribunal</hi>e<hi rend="#i"> di sorveglianza</hi> of Milan seems balanced and satisfactory, in relation, to the demands of Berlusconi's political activity," said his lawyers, Franco Coppi and Niccolò Ghedini in a statement. An FI senator, Manuela Repetti, praised "a wise choice" she said would help to "de-embitter" the political climate.</p>
<p>The landscape, however, remains unusually grim for Berlusconi, who was thrown out of the senate in the autumn and has been barred from holding public office for two years.</p>
<p>The opposition FI leader finds himself in a peculiar position: despite these obstacles, he retains a position of huge power in Italy, where the prime minister, Matteo Renzi, is relying on his support for a number of important reforms. The two dined together on Monday night at Palazzo Chigi in Rome.</p>
<p>But Berlusconi's party's power structure shows signs of crumbling. On Sunday, his former spokesman and gatekeeper Paolo Bonaiuti quit FI – Italy's biggest centre-right party, citing "political disagreements and personal misunderstandings".</p>
<p>"I don't know if it's the end, but the decline is certainly evident," Giuliano Urbani, a former FI MP and ex-government minister under Berlusconi, told La Repubblica. "When even a person like Bonaiuti leaves Berlusconi, it seems clear to me that we are at the end of a chapter … It's like when a castle built with playing cards stays up only because they are supporting one another. If you start taking one out, the whole lot falls down."</p>
<p>Polls before the European elections put FI in third place behind Renzi's centre-left Democratic Party and Beppe Grillo's anti-establishment Five Star Movement.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>