<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Media" date="2003-11-13" description="An American actor and model has said she will sue Silvio Berlusconi's TV empire over a miscarriage she says she suffered because of a 'prank' orchestrated by a reality show, writes John Hooper." fingerprint="6efa129f298185d1" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media business,Television industry,Italy,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Model to sue Berlusconi after TV prank" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/nov/13/silvioberlusconi.broadcasting">
<main>
<p>An American actor and model has said she will sue Silvio Berlusconi's TV empire over a miscarriage she says she suffered because of a "prank" orchestrated by a reality show.</p>
<p>In an interview broadcast by another Berlusconi programme on Tuesday night, Philadelphia-born Randi Ingerman sobbed as she gave her version of events.</p>
<p>"I was pregnant", she said. "Immediately after the prank, I lost blood. Then I lost the child I was expecting."</p>
<p>The producers of the show, Scherzi a Parte (Joking Apart), were expected to make a reply to her claims on last night's edition of the same programme.</p>
<p>Scherzi a Parte specialises in practical jokes, but with a distinctly cruel edge.</p>
<p>On October 9, a friend lured Ms Ingerman, 36, who lives in Milan with her Italian husband, to a fashionable jeweller's shop.</p>
<p>There, she was submitted to what, in an interview with the daily newspaper Corriere della Sera, she termed torture.</p>
<p>First, an actor working for the programme and posing as a clairvoyant told her that her husband was cheating on her. Then, she was accused of stealing jewellery from the shop.</p>
<p>On being told it was a practical joke, Ms Ingerman lashed out at her persecutors and smashed several display cabinets in an attempt to get at the hidden cameras.</p>
<p>Scherzi a Parte's filmed sequences are shown during a studio recording to which the "victims" are invited. Ms Ingerman said she decided to go, but objected to the way the sequence was presented and refused to sign a release form allowing the company to transmit it.</p>
<p>She said that, notwithstanding her refusal and an undertaking from the producers to recut the film sequence, the entire programme was broadcast on October 17. "In the meantime, on the 16th I lost more blood and the day after I miscarried. I was in the sixth week of pregnancy. Four days later, I went to America and my gynaecologist ... told me that the stress had contributed in large measure to the interruption of the pregnancy."</p>
<p>It had already been reported that Ms Ingerman intended suing Mr Berlusconi's television group, Mediaset, though it was not known why. According to an earlier report, her lawyers had demanded €100,000 (about £69,000).</p>
<p>Few showbiz figures are ready to criticise, let alone sue, Mediaset because of its stranglehold on television in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. It controls all three of the biggest commercial channels.</p>
<p>What is more, now that Mr Berlusconi is running the government too, entertainers who fall foul of his television empire can have a hard time getting on to the channels operated by the rival, public broadcaster, RAI.</p>
<p>Ms Ingerman became an actor after a career in modelling. She had a part in the 1992 Jack Nicholson-directed spy thriller Deadly Rivals.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>