<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="David Gow; Nicholas Watt; Larry Elliott; Jill Treanor" categories="Business" date="2011-10-26" description="Summit agrees plan to recapitalise weak banks and increase bail out fund – but details of how to do it put off until next month" fingerprint="23c00b7349b2c4eb" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Euro,European Union,Euro,Economics,Europe,Silvio Berlusconi,Angela Merkel,World news,Business" title="EU summit: crisis rumbles on as EU leaders produce half-finished deal" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/26/eu-summit-eurozone-crisis-leaders">
<main>
<p>EU leaders are anxiously awaiting the verdict of the financial markets after the latest attempt to solve the euro crisis reached deadlock.</p>
<p>Crucial talks with private creditors over the losses they would take on Greek government bonds ran into a roadblock after a second euro summit in four days had earlier endorsed plans to recapitalise Europe's weaker banks by €106.5bn, with Germany said to be raising the threat of a disorderly default. Bankers, according to sources, believe the EU as a whole dare not take this "nuclear option".</p>
<p>Proposals to increase the €440bn bailout fund's firepower "several fold" or closer to €1trn according to a draft statement, were also put on hold.</p>
<p>The man leading the Greek "haircut" talks on behalf of the banks and insurance companies, Charles Dellara of the Institute for International Finance (IIF), said there was "no agreement on any element of a deal," raising the threat of a default by Greece. The banks have offered to accept writedowns of 40% but the EU, led by German chancellor <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/angela-merkel">Angela Merkel</ref>, insists on at least 50% – and perhaps up to 60%.</p>
<p>Dellara and bankers later went into emergency talks with Merkel, French president Nicolas Sarkozy, and IMF managing director Christine Lagarde in the private office of European Council president Herman Van Rompuy.</p>
<p>Merkel and Sarkozy, EU sources said, were commuting back and forth between the full summit and the office where they were holding the talks with bankers, in a desperate attempt to save the summit.</p>
<p>Europe's financial markets were closed by the time the first of a number of official statements emerged from the talks, but on Wall Street the immediate response was one of relief, with the Dow Jones closing up 162 points, or 1.4%.</p>
<p>The day of make-or-break talks began with drama in the Italian parliament, where one of Silvio Berlusconi's closest allies was involved in a fist fight. Meanwhile, Merkel had pleaded with the Bundestag to allow her to leverage up the size of the European Financial Stability Facility (EFSF) to provide a bulwark against possible speculative attacks on Italy and Spain.</p>
<p>"This is a medium-sized bazooka," British sources said, as eurozone leaders admitted they would have to increase its firepower to more than €1tn if the markets were to be pacified. "But please try harder."</p>
<p>EU sources have repeatedly said the €440bn fund could be "leveraged up" fivefold.</p>
<p>The outcome was far from the comprehensive rescue deal that some in the markets had been demanding, and investors will now be seeking more clarity about exactly how much capital will be pumped into Europe's banking sector.</p>
<p>Last night the pan-European regulator the European Banking Authority (EBA) revealed that around 70 bigger banks across Europe would face not only raising extra capital, but extra steps to restart the "term unsecured funding market".</p>
<p>This was required "to help banks to continue their lending activities in 2012 and to avoid a spiral of forced deleveraging and the ensuing credit crunches, which would affect the real economy," the EBA said.</p>
<p>Markets, likely to be unsettled by the lack of comprehensive decisions at the summit, may be further spooked by the EBA's admission that the final total for the recapitalisation fund might not be known until later in November.</p>
<p>Banks will be frustrated by the assertion that they must withhold bonuses and dividends until they have enough capital. As expected, the UK's banks are not deemed to need any extra capital buffer. But for Greek banks the sum is €30bn and for Spain it is €26bn – a bigger number than perhaps expected. Italian banks need €14bn, French banks €8.8bn and Germany's around €5bn .</p>
<p>Some of the world's biggest banks are fiercely resisting attempts to write down Greece's debt by 60%, with expectation mounting of a compromise that would leave the country's private sector creditors with losses of 50%.</p>
<p>Italy, seen as the biggest threat to the eurozone stability, faces intense pressure to produce a credible plan to reduce its debt, which is 120% of national output.</p>
<p>Jean-Claude Juncker, president of the Eurogroup, said: "Our Italian friends know well that we have to assume that we will be informed this evening that there will be significant, structural [budget] consolidation efforts from Italy. That is a must".</p>
<p>The Dutch prime minister, Mark Rutte, said the markets would not be content with "mediocre compromises", adding: "We need today to talk about Greece and ensure that Greek debt is sustainable and that we're finally finished with this business. We must talk about the banks and how they get through this difficult phase … We must ensure that this bazooka, the European rescue fund, is strong enough to show the market that we mean it. We also have to make sure this can't happen in the future. We need strong supervision and live up to our promises."</p>
<p>The plan to recapitalise the banks hinges on increasing the EFSF and success in ending the 18-month struggle to resolve the problems of Greece – where debt has ballooned to €360bn, requiring annual interest payments of 10% of national output. Merkel said Greek debt should be cut to 120% of GDP by 2020, effectively meaning a 50% write down on bond holdings.</p>
<p>Tense negotiations between EU officials and the banks centre on the EU's demands that private creditors accept Greek debt is turned into new loans, with half written off, 15% returned as cash and 35% converted into long-term loans.</p>
<p>Merkel is holding out for as tough a settlement as possible, and has stuck to her demand that the ECB play no role in guaranteeing the bailout fund's increased firepower. David Cameron, however, told EU leaders the ECB may eventually have to take on a key role. "In the end it comes down to this. Can the eurozone create enough of a firewall?" UK sources said. "Ultimately the ECB can stand behind the euro and say: we have as many euros as it will take to defend the single currency."</p>
<p>Cameron said as he left: "Well, we made some good progress tonight. It's very much in Britain's interests that we sort out these problems and solve this crisis. We have made good progress on the bank recapitalisation; that wasn't watered down, it has now been agreed. It will only go ahead when the other parts of a full package go ahead and further progress on that needs to happen tonight."</p>
<p>The draft eurozone statement makes plain the revamped EFSF will combine two elements: insuring the first losses on issues of new debt, and setting up a series of "special purpose investment vehicles" using capital from sovereign wealth funds in, say, Asia, IMF loans and other sources. The EFSF would again guarantee the first-loss part of these but German government sources indicated that there was no agreement on whether this should be 20% or 30%.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>