<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2008-05-08" description="John Hooper: When Silvio Berlusconi makes an election promise it's advisable to read his lips very very carefully" fingerprint="727059a8b13ad2e5" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Gender,Inequality,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="A woman's place" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/may/08/awomansplace">
<main>
<p>Even before swearing in <ref target="http://www.repubblica.it/speciale/2008/squadra_governo/index.html">his new government</ref>, Silvio Berlusconi had broken his first election pledge. That, at least, will be the view of a lot of Italians - in particular, Italian women.</p>
<p>During the election campaign, Berlusconi promised to have at least four women in his cabinet. And the list of ministers released late on Wednesday did indeed contain four women's names.</p>
<p>But another of Berlusconi's campaign pledges was to have a new, super-slimline cabinet of just 12 members. So, not surprisingly, voters assumed a third of the next government would be female.</p>
<p>That might have been thin pickings by contrast with, say, Spain where more than half of <ref target="http://www.la-moncloa.es/MinistrosyMinistras/default.htm">Jose Luis Rodriguez Zapatero's ministers</ref> - nine out 17 - are women. But it would have been a giant leap for Italy where, if memory serves me right, someone recently discovered there were proportionately fewer women in parliament than in Morocco.</p>
<p>But Italian voters should know by now that their billionaire leader is a brilliant salesman, and assuming anything when dealing with a salesman can lead to bitter disappointment. Just as you should read the small print of the contract handed you by that nice young man selling life insurance, so you should take note of the exact words used by silky Silvio, and never more so than during an election campaign.</p>
<p>Now that the cabinet list is out, it can be seen that, while there are only 12 ministers who merit the name (of whom two are women), there are another nine described as "ministers without portfolio", even though they have specific responsibilities.</p>
<p>So not only has Italy ended up with a cabinet not much smaller than those of the recent past (<ref target="http://www.governo.it/Governo/Governi/berlusconi3.html">Berlusconi's last government</ref> had 23 ministers), but the proportion of women in the cabinet is less than a fifth, and the share of women among those given a real ministry and a substantial budget is one-sixth.</p>
<p>One - <ref target="http://www.camera.it/cartellecomuni/leg16/include/contenitore_dati.asp?tipopagina=&amp;deputato=d301449&amp;source=%2Fdeputatism%2F240%2Fdocumentoxml%2Easp&amp;position=Deputati\La%20Scheda%20Personale&amp;Pagina=/CartelleComuni/Leg16/Deputati/Composizione/SchedeDeputati/SchedeDeputati.asp%3Fdeputato=d301449&amp;Nominativo=GELMINI%20Mariastella">Mariastella Gelmini</ref>, a regional co-ordinator of Berlusconi's Forza Italia party - got education. The other, <ref target="http://www.camera.it/cartellecomuni/leg15/include/contenitore_dati.asp?tipopagina=&amp;deputato=d38350&amp;source=%2Fdeputatism%2F240%2Fdocumentoxml.asp&amp;position=DeputatiLa%20Scheda%20Personale&amp;Pagina=Deputati/Composizione/SchedeDeputati/SchedeDeputati.asp%3Fdeputato=d38350">Stefania Prestigiacomo</ref>, who had a junior post in the last government, was rewarded with the environment ministry.</p>
<p>Of the other two women with mere "portfolios", one is <ref target="http://www.maracarfagna.net/">Mara Carfagna</ref>, aged just 32. She will have a hard job living down her (quite recent) past as a <ref target="http://www.lagazzettadelmezzogiorno.it/GdM_interni_NOTIZIA_01.asp?IDCategoria=273&amp;IDNotizia=202026">topless model</ref> and beauty queen ("Miss Smiles and Songs"). All the more so since Italy's new prime minister has given her responsibility for equal opportunities.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>