<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Kathryn Hopkins" categories="Business" date="2010-03-22" description="ritish technology company Smiths Group topped the list of the FTSE 100's biggest gainers today after it announced plans to expand in the US." fingerprint="2c28905383a6046e" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Business,FTSE,Icap,Wolseley,Smiths Group,Investec,Greece,Angela Merkel,European Union,Silvio Berlusconi,Eurozone crisis,Europe" title="FTSE 100 ends day in negative territory as concerns over Greece's debt crisis resurface" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2010/mar/22/marketforces-ftse">
<main>
<p>British technology company <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/smithsgroup">Smiths Group</ref> topped the list of the FTSE 100's biggest gainers today after it announced plans to expand in the US.</p>
<p>Smiths said that it is acquiring Kansas City-based Interconnect Devices Inc. from a private equity firm, Milestone Partners, for $185m. This will be Smiths' biggest buy since Philip Bowman became the company's chief executive in 2007.</p>
<p>"The most interesting thing about Smiths' acquisition is that it is being done," said an analyst at Evolution Securities.</p>
<p>"Smiths is seen as more of a seller than a buyer but this deal suggests that the group may be looking at refocusing on its growth businesses to become, by a combined process of disposals and acquisitions, a growth midcap again, rather like the Smiths of old."</p>
<p>Meanwhile, South African investment bank and asset manager <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/investec">Investec</ref> did well on its first day in the FTSE 100, finishing up 2.41% at 552p.</p>
<p>The day's biggest loser was ICAP, which finished down 2.58% at 381.4p after it announced that it would be cutting 114 jobs as it admitted that its move into stockbroking has floundered.</p>
<p>Separately, building materials group <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/wolseley">Wolseley</ref> said that it may sell off underperforming units and cut costs further as market conditions remain challenging.</p>
<p>It said that over time, the group's intention is to operate fewer, larger, related businesses in core geographies.</p>
<p>"We won't dally too long if we see a business that can't perform for us in the long term," said Ian Meakins , the group's new chief executive.</p>
<p>"They are beginning to respond to treatment now, but clearly over time, what we want to do is to get those businesses to perform. We will then either reclassify them, or will exit."</p>
<p>The plumbing and heating products giant has been hit hard in the downturn, but chief executive Ian Meakins said that the company was seeing some "stabilisation" in its key markets.</p>
<p>In the six months to January 2010, pre-tax losses narrowed to £261m, from £464m a year earlier. Revenues were down 15.1% at £6.3bn.</p>
<p>An analyst at Panmure siad: "The H1 results are better than we had expected although EBITA was in-line, with the difference explained by smaller Construction loan losses and group interest charge.</p>
<p>"The outlook, as expected, remains challenging, with limited visibility and patchy demand patterns. After a good recent run and full valuation, we stay cautious."</p>
<p>Shares in the company were down 2.1%, or 34p, at 1613p.</p>
<p>Overall, Britain's leading index ended the day in negative territory amid concerns over Greece's debt crisis ahead of a key EU summit this week. The FTSE 100 finished down 5.58 points, or 0.1% at 5644.54.</p>
<p>At the weekend, European leaders sent out conflicting messages over aid to Greece, with Germany's Angela Merkel urging Athens to solve its debt problems alone and Italy's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> strongly backing European Union support.</p>
<p>"There is still a degree on concern about Greece but because it has been around for so long it has been priced in into the sentiment in the market unless something dramatic happens," said Joshua Raymond, market strategist at City Index.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>