<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper; Giles Tremlett" categories="World news" date="2009-06-05" description="Spanish newspaper that published pictures of Italian prime minister's semi-naked guests faces legal action" fingerprint="9fca520f93e3575d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Spain,World news,Newspapers,Media,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi fights back over photos of topless guests at villa" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jun/05/silvio-berlusconi-villa-topless-holiday-pictures">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi and his associates mounted a vigorous damage-limitation exercise yesterday after the publication of photographs by a Spanish newspaper showing naked and semi-naked guests, including a former Czech prime minister, at his villa on Sardinia.</p>
<p>His lawyer announced legal action against El País, which released five of the pictures, and threatened a lawsuit against "whoever republishes the photographs in Italy". One shows two young women topless, one wearing a tanga. Another is of a naked man standing by a swimming pool in what appeared to be a state of sexual arousal.</p>
<p>Mirek Topolanek, the former Czech prime minister who was Berlusconi's guest last year, confirmed in Prague he was the man depicted. But added "It is clearly also the result of a photo-montage."</p>
<p>In the photograph of the two women, and another in which Berlusconi is pictured walking, fully clothed, with an unidentified young woman, also clothed, there are what appear to be poolside statues of naked sirens.</p>
<p>El País quoted the photographer, Antonello Zappadu, as saying that "virtually every weekend" Italian air force flights brought Berlusconi's friends, dancers and television hostesses to his 60-hectare weekend retreat. The paper said Zappadu had pixellated out the faces of his subjects to protect their identity.</p>
<p>The prime minister told a radio interviewer: "These are people who are bathing in a private Jacuzzi in a private room". But his account was hard to square with the images on El País's website, in which all the subjects are clearly outdoors. A Jacuzzi is visible only in one photograph.</p>
<p>Italian news agencies reported that several thousand images taken by the Zappadu were being examined by the prosecutors who had them confiscated last Saturday at Berlusconi's request. The prime minister learned of the photographs' existence after Zappadu tried to sell them to one of his magazines, Panorama, for €1.5m (£1.3m).</p>
<p>Asked if he thought the pictures might upset Catholic voters, he replied: "Excuse me. When you take a shower, do you keep your jacket and tie on?"</p>
<p>Berlusconi faces the first big test of his popularity since returning to office at the European election in Italy tomorrow. And late on Thursday, in an apparent effort to deflect attention from his personal affairs, he played the race card as never before.</p>
<p>With early results from the Netherlands showing huge advances by the anti-immigrant right, he told a rally in Milan: "It seems as if one is not in an Italian or European city, but in an African city." He later said his remark had been prompted by a walk through the centre of Milan, claiming that 60% of the people he saw were foreigners. "I asked myself if this Italy of the future is the one Italians want. The answer is no," he said.</p>
<p>Such is the cast-iron division of the electorate into pro- and anti-Berlusconi camps, it is unclear whether the controversies surrounding him will have more than a marginal effect on Sunday's ballot.</p>
<p>"It's certainly not a pretty business," said Massimo Rossi, a security guard on duty near the prime minister's Rome <hi rend="#i">palazzo</hi>. "But the fact is Berlusconi is governing the country quite well."</p>
<p>Margot Calanca, an executive secretary, said: "I've found it all scandalous from the outset so it's not made that much difference to my opinions."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>