<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Alexander Chancellor" categories="Opinion" date="2009-05-28" description="Alexander Chancellor: It's been alleged that Berlusconi called up 17-year-old Noemi Letizia out of the blue after seeing her in a model agency brochure" fingerprint="7ece43071136d655" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,European elections,Cherie Blair,Politics,Newspapers,Media,Europe" title="You can tell how much trouble Berlusconi is in - even the Blairs are distancing themselves from him" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/may/29/silvio-berlusconi-noemi-letizia-repubblica">
<main>
<p>A year ago, in an interview with an Italian magazine, Cherie Blair recalled with rapture the time in 2004 when she and Tony were Silvio Berlusconi's guests at his holiday villa on Sardinia's Emerald coast. Many in Britain had been revolted by the sight of a Labour party leader cavorting shamelessly in public with a rightwing billionaire of doubtful constitutional allegiance, but four years after this cringe-making episode his wife confessed to having found it all thrilling.</p>
<p>"I have never had an evening like the one I had in Sardinia," she said. "Fireworks lit up the words 'Viva Tony', and we all sang Summertime together." She also spoke with pride of the "friendship and trust" that existed between Tony and Italy's strutting little cockerel of a prime minister.</p>
<p>But that was then. This week she described the Sardinian freebie again on an Italian TV show, but in rather a different way. There were no references to fun and friendship but, instead, mockery of the bandana worn by Berlusconi to cover up what she insisted (despite his own refusal to admit it) had been a hair transplant, and a defensive claim that the only reason she and Tony had accepted his invitation to Sardinia in the first place was to secure his support for Britain's 2012 Olympic bid. It is a measure of the trouble Berlusconi must be in that the once unctuous Blairs now see fit to distance themselves from him.</p>
<p>A contributory factor in Cherie's change of mood could have been the dreadful publicity that her best-ever holiday destination has recently attracted. For it was at Berlusconi's Villa Certosa - his private 90-acre theme park complete with a fake volcano, cacti transplanted from the desert, and seven swimming-pools - that the then 17-year-old Noemi Letizia, the young woman at the heart of his present trouble, spent her last new year holiday. This was revealed in an interview with the left-leaning newspaper La Repubblica this week by Letizia's boyfriend at the time, a young Neapolitan called Gino Flaminio.</p>
<p>Although the 72-year-old prime minister totally rejects Flaminio's version of how he and the adolescent aspiring model became acquainted, he does not deny that he brought her by private plane to Sardinia for the new year celebrations at Villa Certosa. According to Flaminio, citing Letizia as his source, Berlusconi's dozens of guests included between 30 and 40 other young women; and the entertainment he laid on for them included, as for the Blairs, a singsong and a firework display, though this time there was only one singer - the one-time cruise-ship crooner Berlusconi accompanying himself on the piano.</p>
<p>The crisis for Berlusconi began when his wife Veronica, outraged to learn that he had attended Letizia's 18th-birthday party in Naples and given her a gold necklace worth thousands of pounds, announced she would divorce him because she could not stay with a man who was "not well" and "frequented minors". Berlusconi's subsequent claim that he knew Letizia only because he had been a friend of her parents for years brought him charges of lying and prompted La Repubblica to publish 10 questions for him to answer about their relationship - questions including how often he had met her and whether it was true, as she had suggested, that he had promised to help her into showbusiness or even politics.</p>
<p>Predictably, Berlusconi ignored the questions, accused La Repubblica and the opposition parties of mud-slinging for base political motives, and said he had nothing to hide but would hide it anyway because of his right to a private life. But the crisis didn't go away as he had hoped. Instead it escalated with the discovery that Letizia had been flown to Milan for an (unsuccessful) audition as a weather girl on one of Berlusconi's TV networks, and with Flaminio's allegation that the prime minister had actually called her up out of the blue after seeing her photographs in a model agency brochure. Now we await Berlusconi's next move.</p>
<p>No one has accused him of any sexual impropriety, and there are no grounds for suspecting it. But as in most scandals involving politicians and women, the proclaimed issue is not what Berlusconi did but whether he is telling the truth about it. The opposition parties argue that for a prime minister to lie even about his private life makes him unfit for public office. The news magazine L'Espresso, a sister publication of La Repubblica, this week ran a feature entitled "<ref target="http://espresso.repubblica.it/dettaglio/il-grande-bugiardo/2083513&amp;ref=hpsp">The Great Liar</ref>", in which it accused Berlusconi of lying not only about his relationship with Letizia but about a series of things, starting with his unequivocal statement that nobody had paid any money to David Mills, the British lawyer and estranged husband of Tessa Jowell, who has been given a four-and-a-half-year jail sentence by an Italian court for taking a £400,000 bribe from Berlusconi.</p>
<p>It is a curious reversal of traditional assumptions that Britain's political crisis is about financial corruption while Italy's is, however obliquely, about sex. The two crises are obviously completely different, but they have bothprovoked the same calls for transparency in government and for reforms that will restore public trust in political institutions. They also make next week's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/european-elections">European elections</ref> unusually exciting.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>