<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2007-08-21" description="Silvio Berlusconi is reportedly planning to found a new political movement with which to wrest back power in Italy." fingerprint="f783d29992544b45" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi 'planning new political party'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2007/aug/21/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi is reportedly planning to found a new political movement with which to wrest back power in Italy.</p>
<p>Speculation about his strategy has focussed attention on the opposition leader's increasingly close political links with a successful businesswoman and former Miss <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> contestant, tipped to be the new party's general secretary.</p>
<p>Michela Brambilla - known as "La Rossa" because of her striking red hair - has built up a network of some 15,000 grassroots political clubs known as "Freedom Circles".</p>
<p>Several Italian dailies reported today that the TV magnate had arranged with a notary public to register the name and logos of an as yet non-existent Freedom party. A branding exercise of that sort would be in line with the approach to politics of a leader who started his business career as a salesman and created Forza Italia! from nothing by exploiting the regional network of his advertising firm, Publitalia.</p>
<p>However, the role the putative Freedom Party would play, and what relationship it would have with the Freedom Circles, remains unclear.</p>
<p>On Sunday, the newspaper La Stampa said Mr Berlusconi conceived it as a response to the centre-left's efforts to build a dominant party, taking in both former Communists and progressive ex-Christian Democrats. The new centre-left movement, to be known as the Democratic Party, is to be launched in October.</p>
<p>But Mr Berlusconi's long-held aim of forging a single, rightwing party were again rejected this week by his closest ally, Umberto Bossi of the Northern League. Other speculation has pointed to the new Freedom Party as a complement to - or replacement for - Forza Italia!</p>
<p>The membership of Ms Brambilla's Freedom Circles extends well beyond Mr Berlusconi's existing party. In particular, it has attracted younger voters disillusioned with conventional politics, whose support could determine the outcome of Italy's next general election.</p>
<p>Those close to the opposition leader, who lost power last year, say he is convinced a new vote will have to be held in early 2008, and the current rules give a big advantage to the more united coalition.</p>
<p>The 39 year-old Ms Brambilla, a former head of the Italian young retailers association, endeared herself to Mr Berlusconi with her entrepreneurial outlook and straight talking. She is known, among other things, for needing only a few hours sleep a night. Mr Berlusconi has called her a "wonderful person" and hinted she could be his political successor.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>