<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Barbara McMahon" categories="World news" date="2005-06-23" description="It should have come as no surprise to the people of Finland that Silvio Berlusconi put his foot in it with their president." fingerprint="3d0f536e79e5de24" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Finland,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi's flirty words about EU food standards" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/jun/24/italy.barbaramcmahon">
<main>
<p>He has branded Italian magistrates mad men, likened a German MEP to a Nazi and offended Jews in his home country and abroad.</p>
<p>So it should have come as no surprise to the people of Finland that <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> might put his foot in it with their president.</p>
<p>The two countries were yesterday trying to untangle the Italian prime minister's latest diplomatic gaffe, which he contrived from the seemingly innocuous issue of the EU's food standards agency.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi said he had persuaded president Tarja Halonen that it should be based in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, and suggested that he had flirted and charmed her into making the decision. "When you seek a result it is necessary to use all available weapons and therefore I brushed up all my playboy skills and I used a series of tender pleas to the president," he said.</p>
<p>For good measure, he then made a derogatory remark about food in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/finland">Finland</ref>, singling out smoked herring.</p>
<p>The Finnish president was not amused. Italy's ambassador in Helsinki was summoned to explain the remarks and receive an official rebuke.</p>
<p>Politicians and the media in both countries have now weighed in.</p>
<p>In Italy, Renzo Lusetti of the Margherita party called it "another Berlusconi own goal", while lawmaker Antonio Pietro described the remarks as "inappropriate".</p>
<p>According to the Ilta-Sanomat newspaper in Finland, hundreds of readers had sent in emails calling the remarks sexist while Lasse Lehtinen, a Finnish social democrat MP, speculated that Mr Berlusconi's recent facelift "may have affected his brain".</p>
<p>Most Italians have been splitting their sides and writer Natalian Aspesi said in La Repubblica newspaper that Italians had more important things to worry about, such as the economy.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi's spokesman said the comments were "light-hearted and a way of expressing friendliness".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>