<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2003-02-18" description='Silvio Berlusconi has been accused in a UN report of undermining the Italian judiciary and acting as if he is "above the law".' fingerprint="6fbad38d9a338714" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi scorns judiciary, UN says" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/feb/18/italy.sophiearie">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has been accused in a UN report of undermining the Italian judiciary and acting as if he is "above the law".</p>
<p>The report criticises the prime minister, who is on trial for corruption, for scorning the judges, manipulating the legal system to his personal advantage and delaying much-needed judicial reforms.</p>
<p>The report, which has not been officially released but was leaked yesterday to Reuters news agency, is highly embarrassing to Mr Berlusconi, who is due to meet the UN secretary general, Kofi Annan, in Rome today.</p>
<p>It says: "It is not proper for the prime minister, being the chief executive of the government, to be seen to be taking advantage of procedural weaknesses in the system.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who controls much of Italy's media and is the country's richest man, has brushed off several corruption investigations since his election in June 2001.</p>
<p>In an impromptu television address in January he said that he would not resign even if found guilty by the court in Milan trying him for trying to bribe judges to influence a corporate buy-out in his favour in 1985.</p>
<p>He said that "leftwing Jacobin magistrates" were putting the constitution at risk, and complained of "incredible judicial persecution" when the supreme court rejected his allegation of judicial bias.</p>
<p>"The government is of the people and of those who represent them, not of those who won a civil service exam and now wear a toga," he said in the television address.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi argues that power has gone to the heads of the judiciary since the tangentopoli (Bribesville) corruption investigations brought down the Christian Democrat government in the early 1990s.</p>
<p>When a court ruled in November that the former prime minister Giulio Andreotti had masterminded the murder of a journalist, Mr Berlusconi described it as "justice gone mad".</p>
<p>The report, written by Dato Param Cumaraswamy, the UN's special rapporteur on the independence of judges and lawyers, said that such public outbursts "undermine judicial independence, which is pivotal for the rule of law in a democracy".</p>
<p>Mr Cumaraswamy said that by choosing not to attend two court sessions, one involving a business associate, Mr Berlusconi had "showed not only disrespect for the majesty of the courts but was seen as being above the law".</p>
<p>The report argues that by failing to reform Italy's legal system, Mr Berlusconi is perpetuating a system that helps defendants avoid judgment.</p>
<p>The Milan trial has dragged on for nearly three years, constantly stalling on minor legal technicalities.</p>
<p>Critics say Mr Berlusconi has used his influence in the media to stay out of jail by intimidating the trial judges.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who was in Brussels yesterday for an EU summit, made no comment.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>