<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Barney Ronay" categories="World news" date="2010-12-15" description="The fracas over the Berlusconi vote is just the latest example of tempers fraying in debating chambers around the world" fingerprint="b61a5223d676871f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Politics,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Politicians who don't pull their punches" url="http://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2010/dec/15/politicians-punches-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Tuesday's victory for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> in a confidence vote in the Italian parliament was marked by brawling in the corridors of power as representatives in the Chamber of Deputies had to be separated by ushers. Although, as is often the case on these occasions, the actual fighting was just a bit disappointing. We asked former world super-middleweight champion <hi rend="#b">Joe Calzaghe</hi> for his opinion of the Italian brawl and four other recent dust-ups – and he was largely unimpressed with the technique on show.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#i">Italy, December 2010. Berlusconi supporters brawl with members of the breakaway party formed by his former ally Gianfranco Fini</hi>
</head>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#i">Argentina, November 2010. </hi>
<ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mjk9NVTstso">
<hi rend="#i">Graciela Camaño slaps colleague Carlos Kunkel</hi>
</ref>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Graciela Camaño slaps colleague Carlos Kunkel</hi>
</p>
<p>You can see the menace in her eyes as she's building up to it. It's a lovely shot with really good accuracy right on the bridge of the nose. What she does well is move out quickly once she's got the punch away. She might have got a bit more power – it was more a slap – but these are hit-and-run tactics and she got her shot off well. I enjoyed that.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#i">Ukraine, April 2010. </hi>
<ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SfCRyLlyqJI">
<hi rend="#i">MPs throw eggs and grapple during a debate over the Russian naval presence in Crimea</hi>
</ref>
<hi rend="#i">.</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">MPs throw eggs and grapple during a debate over the Russian naval presence in Crimea</hi>
</p>
<p>I can't imagine this happening in the UK. You'd be taken down by Special Branch as soon as you got your eggs out. I was disappointed to see them holding on so much, but they fight a bit like the Klitschkos [Vladimir and Vitally, Ukrainian world champions]. There is only really one clean punch in there. It's an overhand, clubbing shot. A little bit sneaky, but sometimes it's got to be done.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#i">Taiwan, July 2010. </hi>
<ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=50XRz65GKwE">
<hi rend="#i">MPs fight over a trade pact with China</hi>
</ref>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">MPs fight over a trade pact with China</hi>
</p>
<p>There's a lot of energy, but the execution of the shots is poor. It's a free-for-all. It's like going to a boxing match and the crowd are in the ring. They need to get their balance and take some proper shots. There's even a backhand punch. It's a girly shot.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#i">Russia, March 2005. </hi>
<ref target="http://www.spike.com/video/fight-in-russian/2667885">
<hi rend="#i">Liberal Democratic party leader erupts over pro-Kremlin dominance in legislature</hi>
</ref>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Liberal Democratic party leader erupts over pro-Kremlin dominance in legislature</hi>
</p>
<p>The man with the beard stays on his feet quite well. He's got decent footwork and there's some good work to the body just before he falls over. I think his jacket is holding him back a bit. He's half getting undressed, half trying to land a big right hand. But I can definitely see some talent. He's quite handy for a politician and looks like he might have been in a boxing ring.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>