<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sonia Lucarelli; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-06" description="Sonia Lucarelli: Silvio Berlusconi's flamboyancy is making Italy a joke in the world's media. In the runup to an election, it's not good enough" fingerprint="b38841fb9108b649" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Italy in the eyes of the world" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/06/italyintheeyesoftheworld">
<main>
<p>As the electoral campaign in Italy reaches its climax, one wonders what the rest of the world feels about these elections. The impression is that they would be of no interest at all if it were not for Silvio Berlusconi, the country's richest man, who has already captured the media's attention during his tenure as prime minister and is now ahead in opinion polls. Indeed, Berlusconi's rather flamboyant attitude has attracted a lot of attention in the international press, which widely <ref target="http://www.martinfrost.ws/htmlfiles/berlusconi5.jpg">reported</ref> on his horn-shaped hand above the head of the Spanish foreign minister, his <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3039912.stm">attack</ref> against German MEP Martin Schulz who he likened to a concentration camp's official, or when he <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3101198.stm">claimed</ref> that Mussolini never killed anyone, rather "sent people on vacation through exile".</p>
<p>Equally, Berlusconi's conflicts of interest and less-than efficient government have been frequently criticised. In Britain, the Guardian has <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/nov/18/comment.eu">called</ref> him a scoundrel and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/aug/28/italy.syria">slavish</ref> towards the US, while according to <ref target="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article3285700.ece">the Times</ref>:</p>
<quote>
<hi>" ... the self-made billionaire left Italy with a ballooning public deficit and near-zero growth. When Mr Berlusconi narrowly lost to Mr Prodi in 2006 he even refused to leave office, claiming that the vote had been rigged. He eventually disappeared to his luxury seaside villa in Sardinia, cheering himself up with parties, performances of his own songs -- he is a former cruise-ship crooner -- fireworks and a fake volcano."</hi>
</quote>
<p>A research group based at the University of Pisa (the group, run by Luciano Bardi, is part of a project coordinated by Angelo Panebianco and funded by the Italian ministry of university research) has confirmed the extraordinary press coverage of Berlusconi in the foreign press by analysing the coverage of Italy in the main newspapers of countries such as Spain, Britain, Russia, Canada, the US and Egypt in 2002 and 2006. For instance, Canada's <ref target="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/">Globe and Mail (subscription required)</ref> has described Berlusconi as outrageous, promoting "sleaze at the top". The newspaper also accused him of "disgracing his country in the eyes of the world". In Britain, Timothy Garton Ash in the Guardian <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/apr/13/comment.italy">described him</ref> as "a master of the burlesque".</p>
<p>Italy is portrayed abroad as a country that needs sympathy, but not trust or political appreciation. If it is true that Italy's cultural heritage is still important and appreciated, socio-cultural stereotypes continue to be strong and these are reinforced by a press coverage that privileges the more colourful stories. As an example take the recent article on the Guardian <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/feb/27/italy1">reporting</ref> of as a "landmark judgment with far-reaching social implications" the fact that "Italy's highest appeals court has ruled it is a criminal offence for Italian men to touch their genitals in public".</p>
<p>The survey undertaken by the research mentioned above, however, has produced two further results from which one can draw political advice for the new government. First of all, Italy is described as an international player by proxy, thanks to its long-term membership in the European Union. This is rather crucial if one considers that the strategic importance of the EU is not sufficiently recognised in the Italian domestic debate, which still suffers from the anti-European rhetoric that abruptly appeared in the Berlusconi era, and unfortunately survived it.</p>
<p>A second message from observing Italy's representation abroad is the general appreciation for the country's mission in Lebanon in 2006. This has been regarded as a long-awaited act of assuming responsibility not only by the "usual suspects" (Britain, the US), but also by countries that have a less of a direct interest in sharing the burden. It must be recognised, however, that Italy's important contribution to peacekeeping worldwide tends to be neglected precisely in those countries that most have a long-term tradition in the field (such as Canada). Recently the Economist published a list of countries contributing soldiers to the Nato mission to Afghanistan, ISAF, and omitted to mention in its sum-up table Italy's 2,000-plus soldiers, apparently relegating them to the "others" category.</p>
<p>The message is clear: involvement in international peacekeeping or similar missions is a way to gain international credibility, but Italy has not been able to capitalise sufficiently on its own efforts. This is due also to the characteristics of public debate on the use of force in the country, which suffers from an unresolved taboo. The domestic inability to call different missions by their individual names, and rather instead grouping them all in the category of "peacekeeping", has already created several difficulties for Italian soldiers in the field who have suffered from inadequate and unclear rules of engagement.</p>
<p>Whoever wins the forthcoming elections desperately needs to reconstruct Italy's credibility both at home and abroad. A coherent European policy, an end to a personality-led style that enforces existing national stereotypes and a more courageous and consistent foreign policy are key elements to this end. Should the new government fail to reach these aims, it would have negative feedback in a country that, as accurately described by Ian Fisher, <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/13/world/europe/13italy.html">suffers</ref> from a deep malaise and lack of self-confidence.</p>
<p>Frustrated by the politicians' empty promises, annoyed by an ageing political system protective of its own power and privileges, Italians do not seem to love or appreciate their country any more. Should the international image of Italy be once again portrayed through the stories of Berlusconi's personal circus-like performances, Italians' self-esteem can only shrink further.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>