<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2014-04-13" description="Marcello Dell'Utri, suspected of escaping justice, awaits ruling over appeal against sentence for colluding with Sicilian mafia" fingerprint="92ae424c95b5c605" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe,Lebanon,Middle East and north Africa,Mafia,Vladimir Putin" title="Silvio Berlusconi associate to appear in Beirut court over Lebanon arrest" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/13/silvio-berlusconi-associate-appear-beirut-court-lebanon-arrest">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's longstanding associate with whom he co-founded Italy's main rightwing party is expected to appear before a magistrate in Beirut on Monday at a hearing for a decision on the legality of his arrest.</p>
<p>Marcello Dell'Utri, who allegedly acted as a mediator between the Cosa Nostra and Berlusconi, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/12/berlusconi-ally-caught-in-lebanon-after-fleeing-italy">was detained at a five-star hotel in the Lebanese capital</ref> at the end of last week. This has come before a final ruling by the Italian supreme court, due on Tuesday, on his appeal against a seven-year sentence for colluding with the Sicilian mafia. The 72-year-old senator's lawyer said it was illogical to think his client was seeking to escape justice, since he had used his own name and credit card to book into the hotel.</p>
<p>Berlusconi was quoted on Sunday as having said it was he who had sent Dell'Utri to Lebanon. The daily La Repubblica said the former prime minister told a delegation from his Forza Italia ("Come on Italy") party that he was responding to a request from <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/vladimir-putin">Vladimir Putin</ref>,. The Russian president had asked him to do what he could to help the leader of Lebanon's Kataeb party, Amine Gemayel, to regain the presidency.</p>
<p>The warrant for Dell'Utri's arrest cited a bugged discussion between the senator's brother and a friend which the judges said showed there was a "serious and concrete danger" of Dell'Utri's trying to establish himself abroad before the supreme court ruling. Some Italian newspapers on Sunday published extracts from the transcripts of the recordings.</p>
<p>Speaking on 8 November 2013, Alberto Dell'Utri, the senator's twin, said: "Ten days ago, Marcello dined in Rome with … an important politician from the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/lebanon">Lebanon</ref> who has been president and is putting himself up in the forthcoming elections and on 14 November he is planning to go to Beirut to see."</p>
<p>However, the two men, whose conversation was taped as part of a separate investigation, also discussed the possibility of the senator might in future shuttle between Lebanon and west Africa on a diplomatic passport issued by the authorities in Guinea-Bissau as part of a scheme to exploit the country's mineral riches. The transcripts indicated that Alberto Dell'Utri was proposing his brother should make a big donation to the country through an NGO set up by Berlusconi for building hospitals in Africa. Alberto Dell'Utri's friend suggested a figure of €5m (£4.1m) might be appropriate.</p>
<p>"All that Marcello needs to do is go to Silvio and tell him: 'Silvio, I'm going to Guinea-Bissau': explain everything to him … 'I'm founding a soccer school for the kids,'" Alberto Dell'Utri commented.</p>
<p>Marcello Dell'Utri – then the head of the advertising arm of Berlusconi's vast business empire – created Forza Italia! from scratch in 1993, appointing his own executives to be its earliest officials. His conviction for collaboration with Cosa Nostra refers only to a period ending the previous year.</p>
<p>Lawyers expressed conflicting opinions on the difficulties of extraditing Dell'Utri from Lebanon if the supreme court upholds his conviction on Tuesday. Dell'Utri denies any wrongdoing.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>