<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-09-16" description="Two men offer resignations after links to inquiry into suspected Berlusconi blackmail – but company denies wrongdoing" fingerprint="6ae8039c96bfa158" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Arms trade,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Ministry of Defence,Defence policy,Europe,World news,Politics,UK news,Finmeccanica" title="Arms company Finmeccanica could lose two executives over Italy bribery claims" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/sep/16/arms-finmeccanica-executives-italy-bribery">
<main>
<p>Two top executives of Britain's second-biggest defence supplier have offered their resignations following the publication of Italian court documents claiming the group used bribery to win contracts.</p>
<p>Salvatore Metrangolo, president of a subsidiary of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/finmeccanica">Finmeccanica</ref> group, which employs almost 10,000 people in the UK, announced tonight he was stepping down. Hours earlier, a company spokesman said that Finmeccanica's commercial director, Paolo Pozzessere, had "offered to stand aside from his role until all relevant issues [were] clarified".</p>
<p>Both men figure in court documents relating to an inquiry into the suspected blackmail of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>. The documents showed that police had recorded conversations involving Finmeccanica executives who, according to prosecutors, "on several occasions spoke on the telephone not only about relationships with leading personalities in the politics and armed forces of foreign countries, but also, more explicitly, of the need to pay them in order to be able to win tenders for the supply of arms [and] defence and security equipment".</p>
<p>No charges have been laid against either Finmeccanica or any of its executives. The company's spokesman said its commercial director "categorically denies any wrongdoing of any kind".</p>
<p>A statement issued by the firm on Wednesday said he had acted "to safeguard Finmeccanica's reputation".</p>
<p>Much of the evidence in the continuing investigation remains secret. But it has already highlighted the fact that Finmeccanica employs some unusual agents to acquire business. They include a former Colombian beauty queen and a fugitive newspaper editor wanted for allegedly blackmailing Italy's prime minister over his sex life. Finmeccanica, which is one-third owned by the Italian government, operates 16 offices and factories in Britain where it has invested some £2bn over 15 years. Its UK chairman is Sir Kevin Tebbit, a retired permanent secretary at the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/ministry-of-defence">Ministry of Defence</ref> and former director of cabinet for the Nato secretary-general.</p>
<p>According to its UK website, "strong ethics are fundamental to how Finmeccanica engages in business and we promote a culture of principled behaviour". All UK operating companies have adopted Finmeccanica's group-wide code of ethics that sets out the responsibilities and obligations that all employees must uphold."</p>
<p>But, according to the judge overseeing the inquiry into the blackmailing of the prime minister, there are suggestions that some of the group's executives and representatives are involved in "shady deals".</p>
<p>The judge was responding to a request from prosecutors in Naples for authorisation to maintain wiretaps as part of their investigation. In their request, the prosecutors cited discussions about moving cash between Swiss bank accounts and others in which code names were used.</p>
<p>"The telephone calls demonstrated that representatives of companies in the Finmeccanica group are able to influence tender competitions held abroad by means of contacts with senior officials in the local governments to the point of overturning already decided outcomes," they wrote. "It appears obvious that the recourse to disguised terms like… the doctor [or] the nurse hide high-level, and probably corrupt, contacts able to impose their will."</p>
<p>Earlier this month, the same prosecutors ordered the arrest of Giampaolo Tarantini, a Bari businessman who has admitted supplying around 40 women for parties at Berlusconi's Rome residence. They accused him and his wife of blackmailing Berlusconi and claimed the money was collected for them by one Valter Lavitola, editor of a small-circulation Rome newspaper for whom an arrest warrant was also issued.</p>
<p>Lavitola, who was abroad at the time, is still on the run.</p>
<p>Finmeccanica acknowledges that he combined his activities as a journalist with those of an agent for the firm. According to the judge overseeing the blackmail inquiry, Lavitola had "frequent contacts" with Finmeccanica's commercial director.</p>
<p>In one wire-tapped conversation when the journalist was, by his own account, in Panama, he began discussing the payment of his commission with Pozzessere, when he was cut short. The Finmeccanica executive was said to have told him: "The account in Bulgaria is no good" and that, because of company restrictions, he would have to be paid in either <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> or Panama.</p>
<p>Another person who worked closely with Finmeccanica was Debbie Castañeda, the 1996 Miss Bogota. The 33-year-old Castañeda left Colombia for Italy to pursue a modelling career and was hired as a presenter for a television show on Berlusconi's Mediaset network.</p>
<p>According to a source close to Finmeccanica, she was hired as a sales agent. She mainly worked on the firm's behalf in Panama and her contract ran out at the end of June or July, the source said.</p>
<p>Two of the conversations referred to in the court papers concern her protests at being cut out of the 5% commission on a deal worth €600m.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>