<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Business" date="2010-05-25" description="Package of 'very tough' spending cuts and tax rises in Italy to be approved tonight in attempt to avert an 'epoch-making crisis'" fingerprint="7fef88b75233173b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Business,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Greece,World news,Europe" title="Italy to slash deficit to avoid Greece's fate" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2010/may/25/italy-slash-deficit-avoid-greece-crisis">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's cabinet is due to meet tonight to approve an ambitious package of deficit-cutting measures which, his closest aide said, was designed to save Italy going the same way as Greece.</p>
<p>The government's spokesman, Paolo Bonaiuti, said a draft bill contained measures to cut spending and boost revenue totalling €24bn (£20.5bn) over the next two years. But the cabinet will not finalise the bill until meetings have been conducted between government representatives and delegations from local government, trade unions and employers' associations.</p>
<p>Using some of the most apocalyptic language heard from a European government representative since the crisis began, Berlusconi's right-hand man, Gianni Letta, said the package included "very heavy, very tough sacrifices" to "save our country from the Greece risk". He noted that other countries had implemented similar cuts "in the desperate, but I hope successful, attempt to dispel an epoch-making crisis and save the euro".</p>
<p>Though nominally only a junior minister without portfolio, Letta is closer to the prime minister than anyone in his cabinet. His rhetoric marked an abrupt about-turn by a government which has hitherto adopted a strategy of resolute optimism.</p>
<p>Though GDP fell by more than 5% last year, Berlusconi and his finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, have assured the public that Italy was spared the worst of the downturn, and even though it has the eurozone's highest public debt as a share of GDP, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2010/apr/29/italy-government-bond-sale">they have sought – with some success – to persuade markets that Italy is a case apart</ref>: that its overall debt is in line with the European average.</p>
<p>Government sources said the package included a three-year wage freeze for the public sector, salary cuts for higher paid government employees and higher taxes on bonuses and stock options in the financial sector. But the largest single heading is reportedly for the expected benefits of a clampdown on tax evasion, and that may prompt scepticism from markets that want to see guarantees of deficit reduction.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>