<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="Media" date="2003-07-02" description="Press review: Non-Italians fear the prospect of Silvio Berlusconi's tenure." fingerprint="3f9e522db320b745" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media business,Italy,Media,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="The editor: Berlusconi's tenure" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jul/02/silvioberlusconi.italy">
<main>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Quentin Peel</hi><lb/> Financial Times, July 1</p>
<p>"As Italy takes over the presidency of the European Union today, alarm bells are ringing around the continent. The concern is at the prospect of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, the Italian prime minister, taking the EU chair.</p>
<p>"[Mr Berlusconi] has called into question a fundamental relationship between Italy and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> that has been used for decades to discipline the country's often chaotic politics and economy. And his blatantly self-serving style of government suggests he has little concern for the rules of good governance that the union demands of all its new members. The danger is that during the presidency, Italy's divisions will become part of the EU agenda. But in the long run it is not the EU that will suffer most. It is Italy itself, and its European reputation."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Pierre Rousselin </hi><lb/> Le Figaro, France, July 1</p>
<p>"Is Mr Berlusconi too rich? Is his smile too dazzling? Is his street-trader straight talking too disturbing for starchy Eurocrats? Il Cavaliere certainly has a fondness for punchy formulas that are rarely compatible with the skillfully calculated nuances of European politics. A born seducer, he tends to want to please the person he is speaking to at any given moment. That often gives rise to a geometrically variable diplomacy that his partners find difficult to follow.</p>
<p>"Over the course of the presidency, [the EU] will have to do everything possible to improve its relationship with the US - a relationship that was singularly damaged during the Iraq crisis. It is up to Mr Berlusconi alone to take the Atlanticism that has attracted so much disapproval from his detractors and use it to the advantage of Europe.</p>
<p>"If all goes well, the president of the Italian council can expect, in 2004, to sign a new treaty of Rome that will enlarge the constitution of Europe to 25. For a man who became a millionaire by means that were sometimes suspect, that would represent a true international consecration."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Andreas Middel</hi><lb/> Die Welt, Germany, July 1</p>
<p>"The concerns of the other EU countries, which are thoroughly understandable, are to do with Mr Berlusconi's lack of a European concept. Someone who repeatedly and fervently demands the admission of Russia and Turkey to the EU shows little feeling for the political and cultural mesh that binds the EU together. The concern that Mr Berlusconi will use the six months of EU presidency as a means of promoting himself is totally justified."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> El Pais </hi><lb/> Editorial, Spain, July 1</p>
<p>"At a crucial moment for European construction, when the EU must finalise its constitution and heal the wounds caused by the war in Iraq, the job of navigating the way forward has, from today, passed to the Italian government.</p>
<p>"Italy has for many years been synonymous with the European ideal. But with Mr Berlusconi at its helm it has moved away from this central position, to the concern of both the Italians and the rest of Europe.</p>
<p>"One might doubt the seriousness of a government presided over by someone who provokes rows and sensationalism instead of profundity. With regard to EU foreign policy, Mr Berlusconi has already violated the pact agreed by the 15 by travelling to the Middle East and meeting Ariel Sharon without greeting Yasser Arafat. It would be difficult to provoke more of a rumpus in a shorter period."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Times </hi><lb/> Editorial, July 1</p>
<p>"Italy's term, which starts today, is from the outset the 'Berlusconi presidency'. The tycoon prime minister's determination to make his mark as a moderniser ought to be seen as an asset the man of the moment, you might think; yet all across Europe, the prospect of this presidency has prompted dark mutterings about Italy's - and specifically Signor Berlusconi's - unfitness to lead the EU.</p>
<p>"To depict any Italian prime minister as a would-be dictator is absurd in a country where power is so highly dispersed that reform, whether of state pensions or rigid labour laws, is next to impossible. Mr Berlusconi has made little headway with Italy's deep-seated problems, but he gets credit for tenacity. Like all politicians weary of home truths, he is serious about expanding his, and Italy's, international role. His domestic battles need not absorb all of his energy. It is in Europe's interest that they should not."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Gérard Dupuy </hi><lb/> Libération, France, July 1</p>
<p>"The Italian prime minister poses three threats to the legitimacy of a liberal democracy. That a powerful press baron can occupy his country's principal political role is a heresy in itself. Worse, [he] has imposed a servile journalistic model on his businesses - a model he hopes to spread throughout Italian television by means of his political power. Mr Berlusconi is a danger to freedom of speech. He is also conducting an aggressive smear campaign against the Italian judiciary - Mr Berlusconi is a danger to the independence of the judiciary.</p>
<p>"The influence that economic power brings to bear on political decisions has always been the achilles heel of liberal institutions. But the Italian premier has no such scruples. Mr Berlusconi is a danger to political integrity. If the constitutional design of the EU serves any purpose at all, it is to stop a man like Mr Berlusconi."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>