<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-01-07" description="Former PM announces his party's support for Northern League, raising fears election will yield no outright winner" fingerprint="1ea950edb6a3df66" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe,Italian elections 2013,The League" title="Silvio Berlusconi renews rightwing alliance ahead of Italian elections" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jan/07/silvio-berlusconi-alliance-italian-elections">
<main>
<p>The former Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has renewed an alliance with his erstwhile coalition partners in the Northern League, raising the chances that next month's election will yield no outright winner and yet more political instability.</p>
<p>In a move unlikely to reassure the markets, the 76-year-old media magnate said that if the rightwing coalition won he would prefer to serve as finance minister rather than prime minister. The position, he said, "would allow me to demonstrate once again that I have no political ambitions". Given Berlusconi's latest poll ratings, such an outcome is improbable.</p>
<p>"The premier will be decided if we win," he told Italian radio, explaining that he would stand as the coalition's "leader of moderates" and that his People of Freedom (PdL) party would support Roberto Maroni, de facto head of the regionalist League, as governor of the Lombardy region around Milan, one of the country's chief battlegrounds.</p>
<p>The League, which campaigns for greater fiscal autonomy for northern Italy and tighter controls on immigration, had been holding out against an alliance with Berlusconi, insisting it would only lend him its support if he vowed not to use it to run for a fourth term as prime minister.</p>
<p>Reflecting the drawn-out negotiations, Berlusconi unveiled the deal by declaring "Habemus papam" – a term usually reserved for the announcement of a new pope. He had signed an agreement with Maroni in the early hours of Monday morning, he said.</p>
<p>According to an opinion poll published on Sunday in the Corriere della Sera, the united forces of Berlusconi's PdL and the League are on course to win only 26%-28% of the vote on 24-25 February, despite the billionaire politician's repeated declaration that he will again exceed 40%.</p>
<p>The centrist coalition led by the technocrat prime minister Mario Monti stands to win about 14%-15% of the vote, according to the poll, with the comedian Beppe Grillo's Five Star Movement on 13-14%.</p>
<p>A centre-left bloc led by the Partito Democratico (PD) is far ahead on 38-39% but Berlusconi's announcement threatens the possibility of an outright victory for the party and its leader, Pier Luigi Bersani.</p>
<p>The PD looks set to dominate in the lower house of parliament, but could be blocked in the Senate by the rightwing coalition. That prospect could result in the PD seeking the services of Monti to form a governing coalition, a scenario that would please the markets and other EU leaders, many of whom want the former European commissioner to stay at the helm of Italy as it continues to battle the eurozone crisis and recession.</p>
<p>Since declaring his intention to take part in the election in order to keep <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> on the road to fiscal discipline and economic recovery, Monti, 69, has abandoned much of his studiously apolitical image.</p>
<p>He has engaged in multiple television and radio interviews and even a live Twitter Q&amp;A session in which – to the dismay of some supporters – he used smiley emoticons and the thoroughly unprofessorial exclamation "wow!" He has also sharpened his criticism of Berlusconi, describing him as politically and personally volatile and drawing attention to the former prime minister's often contradictory statements.</p>
<p>But Berlusconi, whose party supported the technocratic government until November, has returned the criticism, calling Monti a "minor leader" and questioning his credibility. On Monday, Berlusconi reiterated his criticism, telling Italian television his successor's decision to continue in politics was "immoral".</p>
<p>"When he [Monti] was made prime minister he said – and he told me this, too – that once his mandate had expired, he would no longer be a political player. In a year of government, he has not produced any necessary reform and all the economic indicators are negative. My judgment of Monti is very negative," he said.</p>
<p>An alliance with the Northern League is likely to shift Berlusconi's coalition further to the right. Within hours of the alliance's unveiling, it emerged that one of the football fans suspected of shouting racist chants at Kevin-Prince Boateng during last week's Pro Patria v Milan match was a local councillor and <hi rend="#i">leghista </hi>[League supporter]. The League rejects all charges of xenophobia or racism.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>