<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2009-07-09" description="Letters: In Italy this government is not accustomed to free debate, or to hearing the truth being told" fingerprint="3ed8c3aefb94831d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="G8,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Spotlight on the Guardian's G8 Italian job" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/10/letters-italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>I do not know who the anonymous sources were for your article (<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/06/g8-considers-expelling-italy">Calls grow within G8 to expel Italy as summit plans descend into chaos</ref>, 6 July), but my experience of the preparatory meetings was very different. As director general of Bioversity International, one of the research centres supported by the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research, and being based in Rome, I was invited to represent international agricultural research in the run-up to the G8.</p>
<p>Your judgment, at least as far as the draft final statement on food security is concerned, is overly harsh. The Italian government put considerable effort into early versions of the statement, which was certainly not a US-led initiative. <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> sought input from many parties - including those who are in most urgent need of food security and those who have most to contribute - and created a draft text that needed little further negotiation to reach agreement. Where the US has taken a lead is in making good on earlier pledges to increase the aid budget and to recognise the importance of agricultural development in helping to reduce the need for emergency assistance to combat future famines. Investment in agriculture remains the surest way to put poor people on the road to development and food security.<hi rend="#b">Emile Frison</hi><lb/> Bioversity International, Rome, Italy</p>
<p>As a member of the Italian parliament and former magistrate who ensured that many corrupt politicians and businessmen were brought to justice in the 1990s, I wish to apologise to the editor and staff of the Guardian for the utterly predictable reaction of prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> and our foreign minister, Franco Frattini.</p>
<p>The Guardian does its best to keep the public informed. In Italy this government is not accustomed to free debate, or to hearing the truth being told. While sections of the article dealing with preparations for the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g8">G8</ref> summit may be debatable, the rest of it contains little that can be refuted. Freedom House puts Italy in 73rd place as regards freedom of the press.</p>
<p>The real problem is that our information is firmly in the grip of one individual, namely our prime minister, which must be one of the worst cases of conflict of interests in the western world.</p>
<p>There is another issue. A law known as the Alfano Bill prohibits the prosecution of none other than Berlusconi himself, as well as the incumbents in three other senior government posts. Thanks to the Alfano Bill, he can no longer be prosecuted for bribery, while David Mills, his attorney, has been sentenced to four years and six months imprisonment for perjury. The constitutional court will rule on the constitutionality of the Alfano Bill in October. The Guardian and other foreign media must not allow the spotlight to move away from Italy. <hi rend="#b">Antonio Di Pietro</hi><lb/> Rome Read a fuller version at <ref target="http://theguardian.com/commentisfree">theguardian.com/commentisfree</ref></p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>