<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Ben Quinn" categories="World news" date="2011-09-09" description="Italy's prime minister tells supporters in party's youth wing 'there's nothing I consider a real mistake'" fingerprint="2e5b903f9f229617" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Beleaguered Berlusconi: any regrets? I've had none" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/sep/10/berlusconi-regrets-none-italy">
<main>
<p>Coming from a politician who has previously likened himself to Napoleon and Jesus Christ, there was perhaps always going to be one answer when <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> was asked what in the past he would change if given the chance.</p>
<p>"No, there's nothing that I consider a real mistake," replied the Italian prime minister, who has suffered a draining away of political support in recent times as he fended off accusations of sleeping with teenage prostitutes and charges that his country's economy is now heading for the rocks under his erratic stewardship.</p>
<p>Looking relaxed in an open-necked shirt as he addressed members of the youth wing of his People of Freedom party, a jovial Berlusconi made the comment in response to a question from one supporter. In between his trademark tirades against the left, communists and magistrates, he went on to describe himself as a "generous, diamond-like" person as he talked about vices, Muammar Gaddafi and dancing with his beloved mother.</p>
<p>He revealed he no longer smoked or gambled, and has not danced since doing a waltz with his mother, who died in 2008 at the age of 97.</p>
<p>"Just one thing – which I don't consider a vice – has remained and I hope it stays with me for years to come," he added, in an apparent reference to his self-confessed fondness for beautiful women, to cheers and clapping.</p>
<p>At a push, however, the 74-year-old had no regrets.</p>
<p>"I have a high regard for myself and I have nothing to reprimand myself for when I look at myself in the mirror," he said. "Perhaps at times I've exaggerated with irony, but never with brutal offences like those directed towards me."</p>
<p>Quite which offences he had in mind was unclear, but Berlusconi watchers can list a longer line of gaffes ranging from his description of Barack Obama as "suntanned" through to his claim to have seduced the Finnish president, Tarja Halonen. On other occasions, he held up two fingers behind a Spanish minister's head at an EU summit photograph and likened a German member of the European parliament to a concentration camp guard. Berlusconi admitted to some mixed feelings about his decision to turn on Gaddafi, with whom he had developed a warm friendship in recent years.</p>
<p>He said <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, which backed Libyan rebels fighting Gaddafi, had made the right decision by first courting and then abandoning the Libyan dictator, but that turning on Gaddafi left him feeling "very bad".</p>
<p>Recalling that Gaddafi had erected a billboard in Libya of the two leaders and given his own feelings on friendship, Berlusconi said he considered resigning over the Libyan saga, but was "physically prevented" by his staff from doing so.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>