<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-06-24" description="Italy's former prime minister is due to hear the verdict in a trial in which he is accused of having sex with an underage dancer" fingerprint="7fa8d22cd14646f6" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi and other players in his sex trial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jun/24/silvio-berlusconi-sex-trial">
<main>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>
</head>
<p>Three-times prime minister whose party is back in government courtesy of Enrico Letta's left-right coalition. Denies paying for sex with "Ruby Heartstealer" when she was 17 and exerting pressure on police to release her, claiming she was related to Hosni Mubarak. Insists nothing illegal went on at his elegant soirees.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Karima el-Mahroug</hi>
</head>
<graphic alt="Karima El-Mahroug" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/About/General/2013/6/23/1372009517187/Karima-El-Mahroug-006.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p/>
<p>Moroccan-born Mahroug attended several parties at Berlusconi's mansion in 2010. Admits receiving thousands of euros from the billionaire, but says it was simply an act of generosity on his part. Denies having sex with him and denies having worked as a prostitute.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Nicole Minetti</hi>
</head>
<graphic alt="Nicole Minetti" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/About/General/2013/6/23/1372009596409/Nicole-Minetti-006.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p/>
<p>Anglo-Italian former dental hygienist who treated Berlusconi on the night he was attacked with a statuette of Milan's cathedral in 2009. Had recently become a regional councillor for his party when she fetched Mahroug from a police station in 2010. Accused in a separate case of procuring prostitutes for the then prime minister, she denies the charges, saying she felt a "sentiment of true love" for him. She is no longer a PdL councillor.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Ilda Boccassini</hi>
</head>
<graphic alt="Ilda Boccassini " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/static/sys-images/Guardian/About/General/2013/6/23/1372009774742/Ilda-Boccassini--006.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none"/>
<p/>
<p>Dubbed Ilda the Red by some, the formidable prosecutor who has led the case against Berlusconi is known for her confrontation of the powerful, including mafia gangsters. Since taking on this case, she has received threatening letters and bullets in the post. A magazine owned by the Berlusconi family has published photographs of her with less than flattering captions.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>