<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-12-14" description="Italian prime minister clings to power but win is marred by scandal and growing opposition to his rule" fingerprint="faae852890b5c645" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="A confidence vote victory for Berlusconi deepens rift in Italian politics" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-confidence-vote-analysis">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's victory today in two confidence votes blunts a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/07/silvio-berlusconi-gianfranco-fini-ultimatum">rebellion by followers of his former deputy, Gianfranco Fini</ref>, but ushers in a period of renewed political uncertainty for Italy.</p>
<p>It has prompted claims that the billionaire prime minister bought his way out of trouble, raising tension at a time of mounting anger and frustration among the government's opponents.</p>
<p>As a result of the vote, Berlusconi has avoided being forced to resign. But, as even some of his allies noted in the runup to the debate, he will find it difficult to lead the country with such a razor-thin majority.</p>
<p>The prime minister signalled during the debate before the vote that he would try to widen the support for his government by wooing the conservative Union of Christian and Centre Democrats (UDC).</p>
<p>The UDC, led by Pier Ferdinando Casini, forms the most rightwing element in the opposition. It was part of Berlusconi's last government, in power until 2006.</p>
<p>This ploy could fail for two reasons. One is that Casini's dream is to form a powerful "third force" in the centre of the Italian political spectrum and, with the defection from the government of Fini and his supporters, he is closer to its realisation. The other is the probable objection of Berlusconi's main ally, the Northern League.</p>
<p>The anti-immigrant League and its leader, Umberto Bossi, who are riding high in the polls, would prefer an early election to resolve the foreseeable stalemate. Given their leverage over Berlusconi, it is likely they will get one, even if they have to wait until spring.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Italy's prime minister will remain embattled. On 11 January, the constitutional court is to rule on a law that grants Berlusconi temporary immunity from prosecution. If the decision goes against him, he will return to court to face charges of having bribed his former offshore legal adviser, David Mills.</p>
<p>Successive scandals have virtually paralysed his administration, and there is growing discontent in Italy over the slow pace at which its economy is recovering from the global recession. The jubilation on the government benches that greeted today's result is unlikely to endure.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>