<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="Media" date="2003-06-18" description="Italy's billionaire prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, made a symbolic appearance at his trial for corruption yesterday, blustering against his adversaries but giving little strong new evidence, while parliament prepared to pass a law giving him immunity." fingerprint="7f7688be3b649fcc" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,Newspapers &amp; magazines,Italy,Television industry,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi bullish in second court appearance" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2003/jun/18/pressandpublishing.italy">
<main>
<p>Italy's billionaire prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, made a symbolic appearance at his trial for corruption yesterday, blustering against his adversaries but giving little strong new evidence, while parliament prepared to pass a law giving him immunity.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi protested his innocence, claiming the trial - for allegedly corrupting judges during the 80s - had been a long, entirely fictitious smear campaign.</p>
<p>"There is nobody here. There is no murder weapon. There is no motive," Mr Berlusconi told a packed Milan courtroom. "All there is is a fantasy cooked up by the person who invented this theory [of corruption]. And I am exposed to having ... tonnes of mud slung at me."</p>
<p>After delivering his comments, Mr Berlusconi withdrew, saying he did not have time to take any questions. He invited judges to travel to Rome to question him between his government commitments, but the judges declined.</p>
<p>His appearance, the second in his three-year trial, was something of a closing act, because the Italian parliament is on the point of passing a law that will save the prime minister and four other top Italian officials from prosecution while in office. Mr Berlusconi's term as prime minister has two years to run and analysts say that by then the trial would be unlikely to resume.</p>
<p>The Italian senate approved the immunity bill this month and the lower house of parliament is expected to pass the law this week. Mr Berlusconi proposed the bill himself amid a climate of anguish over the possible damage of a corruption conviction during Italy's rotating European presidency, which starts on July 1.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>