<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-06-07" description="Turnout down in Italy as conservative voters appear to abstain after topless photos row" fingerprint="3f98d1ad1a22ff8c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European elections,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi's troubles overshadow European election" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/jun/07/silvio-berlusconi-european-election">
<main>
<p>Voters in Italy today cast their ballots against a background of unabated sexual controversy surrounding the prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>At noon, the turnout was more than 3% below the figure at the same point in the 2008 ballot. Low turnouts in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> tend to favour the left.</p>
<p>It was notable that the highest levels of abstention were mostly in regions that traditionally favour the right, possibly suggesting conservative Catholic voters had registered their disapproval by staying away.</p>
<p>The Spanish newspaper El País kept up its pressure on Berlusconi todayby publishing two more photographs of the goings-on at his holiday villa. One showed two young women topless under an open-air shower, one apparently running a hand through the other's hair. The second picture was of two young women – possibly the same ones - leaving what the newspaper said was the billionaire politician's villa.</p>
<p>On Friday, Berlusconi's lawyer threatened legal action against El País. The paper had, by then, published five of the several hundred photographs that were taken by a local photographer and impounded after Berlusconi protested that they violated his privacy and that of his guests.</p>
<p>The prime minister's Freedom People movement was hoping to win at least 40% of the vote in the first big test of public opinion since last year's general election. It was expected his allies in the populist Northern League could benefit from the rise in anti-immigrant sentiment across <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref>.</p>
<p>The ballot was also expected to be crucial for the future of Dario Franceschini, leader of Italy's biggest opposition group, the Democratic party (PD). The PD, which bled support after taking 33% of the vote at the general election, was aiming for at least 27% this time.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>