<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-02-18" description="Silvio Berlusconi is above the maximum age at which he can be imprisoned" fingerprint="ffaed30411a5b70c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi: Immunity granted by parliament could yet be voided by top court" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/feb/18/silvio-berlusconi-immunity-prosecution">
<main>
<p>After he was voted back into power last year, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> made it a priority of his government to pass a law that would give him immunity from prosecution. Yesterday's verdict shows just how valuable that move was.</p>
<p>However, Italy's prime minister is not yet safe. The law, which came into effect in July, is under consideration by the constitutional court, which could still overturn it - just as it threw out similar legislation in 2004 during Berlusconi's government.</p>
<p>The new law extended protection to the prime minister and four other top officials of state. After it reached the statute book, the judge who gave yesterday's verdict suspended the charges against Berlusconi, but went ahead with those against his former legal adviser, David Mills.</p>
<p>If the immunity law is declared unconstitutional, the charges against the prime minister could be revived. But given the slow pace of Italian justice, it is unlikely that a conviction could be secured quickly - and the offence of which Berlusconi was accused is timed out by a statute of limitations next February.</p>
<p>However, the trial that ended yesterday is not the only one in which the two men are co-defendants. They are also accused of tax-dodging and other financial offences in a case that involves the trading of television film rights. In that case, the judges took a different view of the immunity bill and suspended the trial of all the defendants - including Berlusconi and his erstwhile lawyer. In so doing, they also stopped the clock on the statute of limitations. The result is that if the immunity law is ruled unconstitutional, the prosecutors will have more time in which to secure convictions.</p>
<p>Even if found guilty, Berlusconi can rest assured he will never go to prison. He may look younger, but he is over 70. That is the maximum age at which a defendant can be imprisoned under Italian law.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>