<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Duncan Campbell" categories="World news" date="2010-09-21" description="What does a 1977 photograph of Silvio Berlusconi with a gun at his side tell us about the Italian prime minister?" fingerprint="7f829125bd84c76d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Italy" title="Berlusconi: me and my Magnum" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/sep/21/berlusconi-photograph-magnum">
<main>
<p>A little known picture of Silvio Berlusconi in 1977 has been unearthed by the Italian magazine L'Espresso, <ref target="http://news1.capitalbay.com/news/unseen_seventies_photo_of_silvio.html">showing the billionaire Italian prime minister with a gun lying casually on his desk</ref>. So what does a .357 Magnum Smith &amp; Wesson tell us about a man?</p>
<p>"Either he's showing off and saying that he's very important and his testicles are bigger than everyone else's or he's using it to make a statement to the press that he has a very effective form of self-defence," said a firearms expert.</p>
<p>Created in 1934 by Elmer Keith, an Idaho rancher and hunter, and Phillip Sharp, for the firearms manufacturers Smith and Wesson, it was being marketed the following year as a potent way of dealing with gangsters who had started wearing bulletproof vests. The new product proudly claimed to be able to blast its way through body armour and it was soon adopted by law enforcement officers as the most effective weapon of the time. The then director of the FBI, J Edgar Hoover, was presented with an early model.</p>
<p>Smith &amp; Wesson has been producing firearms in Norwich, Connecticut since 1852, and it supplied both the US Cavalry on the western frontier and the Russian imperial government. Clint Eastwood made one of the company's products famous in Dirty Harry and its weapons have appeared in films from Lethal Weapon to Return of the Living Dead and, most recently, in Resident Evil: Afterlife, where they are wielded by Milla Jovovich.</p>
<p>To buy a .357 Magnum Smith &amp; Wesson today would cost around $700 but to do so in the UK would be to break the law, handguns being virtually banned by the 1997 Fireams Act passed in the wake of the previous year's massacre at Dunblane. Should Berlusconi want to update his arsenal, Smith &amp; Wesson's newest line includes the S &amp; W 500 for $1,600. Also known as the "bone collector".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>