<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2009-08-07" description="Roberto Mancini: It may dominate world news, but the real story in Italy concerns criminal gangs, business deals and the north-south divide" fingerprint="3bd8c18f9633ffdd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,European Union,Mafia,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi's sex life is not the real issue | Roberto Mancini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/aug/07/italy-corruption-state-organised-crime">
<main>
<p>As the Italian summer reaches its height, the sexual <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/aug/04/berlusconi-barbara-vanity-italy">exploits of Silvio Berlusconi</ref> (and the half-baked response of the Catholic church) continue to dominate the news as he enjoys the so-called "Italian way of life" to perfection. But the more important story lies elsewhere. Here's a list of interesting recent events, which may or may not be linked.</p>
<p>First, the ex-president of the republic, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_Azeglio_Ciampi">Carlo Azeglio Ciampi</ref>, has threatened to resign from the presidency of the committee organising the celebration of 150 years of national unity. Not surprising, since his committee exudes apathy. In reality, the celebration of the roots of Italian unity no longer interests anyone; in the minds of the republic's citizens, it's been dead for some time. Over the past 15 years the federalist (and occasionally separatist) convictions of the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lega_Nord">Northern League</ref>, ineffectively balanced by a rightwing government with – at least in regard to the media – Peronist tendencies, has <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jul/26/editorial-silvio-berlusconi-eu-scandals">gradually eroded</ref> the unifying and fundamental values of the country.</p>
<p>The average Italian's historical memory is now awakened only during football championships. His loyalty, love and respect is reserved for his own birthplace or his close family clan. The Renaissance revival is unimportant to him and he is quite indifferent to historical figures such as <ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/garibaldi-the-first-global-action-hero-455348.html">Garibaldi</ref> and <ref target="http://www.ohio.edu/chastain/ip/mazzini.htm">Mazzini</ref>.</p>
<p>Second, a Sicilian branch of the <ref target="http://www.ilpopolodellaliberta.it/">PdL</ref>, Berlusconi's political party, have threatened to set up a "<ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/aug/02/italy-silvio-berlusconi-sex-scandals">party of the South</ref>", to counterbalance what they claim is the undue influence of the Northern League on the government. The prime minister has, as usual, solved a tricky political problem and stifled the revolt by throwing money at it, promising the region of Mezzogiorno a huge increase in resources and public works.</p>
<p>Is southern <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> really treated so unfairly? The south has remained at developing world levels not because of plotting and scheming by northerners but because of the swindling tendencies of their own ranks of local public officials, often in cahoots with the mafia and their associates. Southern Italy's public officials have deftly nursed the myth of second-class citizenship while in reality exploiting colossal state financing.</p>
<p>In the last 20 years, the mafia, Camorra and 'Ndrangheta have established cross-regional rapport and a profitable collaboration with businessmen from northern Italy. There are plenty of people who badmouth the south and southerners but are more than happy to share lucrative business deals with the mafia. In the north, as in the south, "<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pecunia_non_olet">pecunia non olet</ref>".</p>
<p>Third, to mark the 17th anniversary of the car bomb which murdered the anti-mafia magistrate Paolo Borsellino in Palermo, the <ref target="http://www.tribunalecatania.it/home.php">Catanian chief prosecutor</ref> has re-opened the inquiry. New testimony alleges that the military wing of the Corleonese mafia, which carried out the attack, were acting on behalf of government institutions. <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvatore_Riina">Totò Riina</ref>, the Corleoni family boss currently serving life imprisonment for murders including the masterminding of the Borsellino hit, has <ref target="http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1914284,00.html">broken his silence</ref> because he is "fed up with paying for everyone", hinting that the state was involved in the murder. It could be that it's a bluff by the old boss to muddy the waters and minimise his own responsibilities. But maybe we're seeing a coded message to his former political associates.</p>
<p>If so, the boss's cell – despite its location in a maximum security prison – will be a dangerous place, just like the cell of <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michele_Sindona">Michele Sindona</ref>, convicted felon and banker to the Vatican who was mysteriously poisoned in prison 23 years ago.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>