<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Ed Vulliamy" categories="Opinion" date="2014-10-30" description="Ed Vulliamy: President Napolitano’s court appearance confirms that the bond between power and the shadows never went away" fingerprint="26a04b0191a0d705" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Mafia,Silvio Berlusconi,UK news" title="Italy’s mafia and state are under the spotlight, and not before time | Ed Vulliamy" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/oct/30/italy-mafia-state-president-napolitano-court">
<main>
<p>Even in Italy, it is beyond the norm for a head of state to testify in a mafia trial. President <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/oct/28/italian-president-evidence-mafia-trial">Giorgio Napolitano giving evidence on Tuesday</ref> to judges from the Palermo anti-mafia pool at the Quirinale presidential palace was a first.</p>
<p>The president gave three hours of evidence in the case against Cosa Nostra boss Salvatore Riina and 11 others – a trial that seeks to convict perpetrators of a series of attacks on the Italian state during the tumultuous early 1990s: the <ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/sicilian-tragedy-world-problem-first-falcone-now-borsellino-two-leading-judges-have-been-murdered-and-mafia-crime-is-spreading-across-the-globe-the-state-must-fight-back-rather-than-leaving-it-to-individuals-says-charles-richards-1534567.html">murders of two iconic anti-mafia judges</ref> Giovanni Falcone and Paolo Borsellino in 1992, and a string of bomb attacks.</p>
<p>The president’s involvement arises from implications in a memo by Napolitano’s legal adviser at the time – when he was president of the chamber of deputies – Loris D’Ambrosio, now deceased, suggesting a high-level accord, or some kind of negotiation, between Riina and the heights of state during the assault upon it.</p>
<p>I remember the time well, covering the events for this newspaper: an entire political class was under arrest in a scandal called <hi rend="#i">Tangentopoli</hi> – Kickback City – but even in that context the sudden violence was shocking, reminiscent of a time Italy thought it had consigned to the so-called <ref target="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/3372239.stm">years of lead</ref> in the late 1970s and early 80s.</p>
<p>But actually, we now know that the surge of mafia killing in 1992-93 bore all the hallmarks of themes that underpinned the years of lead, when I was a student in Italy. The kidnap and execution of the then Christian Democrat leader Aldo Moro by the <ref target="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/494142/Red-Brigades">Red Brigades</ref>, the murderous bomb in Bologna station in 1980 and others in Milan, Brescia and aboard a train were, differently, expressions of what Italians call the “strategy of tension” by the state. In the mix: the extreme left and right, the secret services, the army, the mysterious P2 masonic lodge – and inevitably, Cosa Nostra. The state’s strategy was to cause mayhem in order to increase repression of it.</p>
<p>Tuesday’s testimony by President Napolitano is said to have established that there was no actual negotiation between his office and the mafia. But the fact that it took place, and the mention in D’Ambrosio’s memo of <hi rend="#i">indicibili accordi</hi> – unspeakable accords – affirm that the Italian state was still in contact with the mafia during the early 1990s. Around the same time, the prime minister who exemplifies the era from the years of lead to <hi rend="#i">Tangentopoli</hi>, <ref target="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/people/a/giulio_andreotti/index.html">Giulio Andreotti</ref>, was accused of mafia association, convicted twice and cleared at the highest, third, level of justice.</p>
<p>But there is another thread to this. It is no coincidence that the wave of arrests of politicians and the mafia attacks of 1992-93 took place at a time during which Napolitano is said to have met Riina’s representatives. A vacuum was opening at the apex of Italian power, and the old fear returned that it might be filled by the Communist party, even though the PCI had changed its name and dropped the hammer and sickle.</p>
<p>That vacuum had to be filled in order for the status quo – the miasma of relationships between the state, organised crime, freemasonry and commerce – to remain intact. Oddly, a file was opened by another anti-mafia pool in the Sicilian mafia stronghold of Caltanissetta, implicating a business tycoon and media magnate from Milan, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, and his right-hand man, Marcello Dell’Utri, who was during the early 1990s urging Berlusconi to go into politics, for the sake of his own immunity from prosecution and to ensure that the old alliances held.</p>
<p>The investigation was shelved after Berlusconi, guided by Dell’Utri, won the landmark election of 1994, launching <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> into what appeared to be a new era, but was actually the continuance of business as usual.</p>
<p>There is no suggestion that Berlusconi and Dell’Utri were behind the murders of Falcone and Borsellino, or the bombs in Florence and Rome. But Berlusconi’s odyssey through the court system is legendary. Dell’Utri, meanwhile, has been convicted of mafia association and in April was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/12/berlusconi-ally-caught-in-lebanon-after-fleeing-italy">caught in Lebanon</ref> after fleeing Italy. He has been portrayed as Berlusconi’s ambassador to Cosa Nostra, and vice-versa, although Berlusconi has always denied mafia connections. Berlusconi’s other top aide, Cesare Previti, has been <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/aug/07/italy">convicted of corruption</ref>.</p>
<p>What Napolitano’s court appearance suggests that the nexus between power and the shadows never went away. And that during that time, of apparent mafia war against the state, adjustments were being made to the “unspeakable accords” to ensure the status quo.</p>
<p>This was done contrary to appearances: the opaque world of Andreotti’s Christian Democrats, with its occult shadows and Catholic sobriety, had given way to a brash new world of semi-naked dancing girls and striptease quiz shows on TV channels owned by the new prime minister.</p>
<p>But in reality nothing had changed beyond the replacement of the cult of state by that of corporate power. The unspeakable accords held firm. What is interesting, however, is that in Italy, the work is done to expose these perfidies: if you go into any <ref target="http://www.lafeltrinelli.it/">Feltrinelli</ref> bookshop, you will see shelves of books that detail them, by brave reporters working with equally bold examining magistrates like those in Palermo, past and present.</p>
<p>In Italy, the dots between power and organised crime have been largely joined. The same cannot be said of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2012/jul/29/lord-green-hsbc-tax">our country</ref>, and the “unspeakable accords” that allow people like Berlusconi to hide their fortunes in tax havens under British jurisdiction.</p>
<p>Tuesday’s testimony affirmed that the line in Italy between legality and criminality is a lie; it does not exist. What it says to us in Britain is that we are far behind the Italians in exposing – and confronting – the lie of that line; exposing the unspeakable accords that bind our own society.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>