<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Stephanie Kirchgaessner" categories="World news" date="2015-03-11" description="Court decision has ‘lifted a burden’, says former Italian PM, as spokesman says he will now prominently campaign in upcoming regional elections" fingerprint="be20c01b9066c34d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy" title="Berlusconi vows political comeback after sex case acquittal upheld" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/mar/11/berlusconi-vows-political-comeback-after-sex-case-acquittal-upheld">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has vowed to return to frontline Italian politics after the country’s top court cleared him of charges of paying for an underage prostitute and using his political clout to cover it up.</p>
<p>“The decision has lifted a burden from my heart,” the former prime minister told the Corriere della Sera newspaper after the verdict. “And there is a joy, certainly, but there is also a huge regret to think about how things would have turned out differently if I was not a victim of this terrible travesty.”</p>
<p>A spokesman said Berlusconi would prominently campaign in upcoming regional elections “defending the values for which he has always fought and that revolve around freedom”.</p>
<p>The judges arrived at the ruling 10 hours after proceedings began in the supreme court to determine whether the 2014 acquittal of Berlusconi on sex and abuse of office charges ought to be upheld.</p>
<p>The man who held Italy’s highest office three times – for a total of nine years – still faces other legal challenges and has separately been convicted of tax fraud. But Wednesday’s late-night verdict drew a definitive line under the case that did the most damage to the billionaire politician, transforming him from a world leader into a laughing stock that other presidents and prime ministers did not want to associate with.</p>
<p>Amid a myriad of past and current allegations – from corruption and bribery to tax fraud – it was the prostitution case that exposed Berlusconi’s involvement in so-called “bunga bunga” sex parties and the 78-year-old’s alleged taste for young girls.</p>
<p>The former prime minister was originally convicted in 2013 but acquitted a year later. He has long denied paying for sex with Karima el-Mahrough – the woman at the centre of the case who is known as Ruby – and maintained that he believed the Moroccan was the niece of Hosni Mubarak, the former Egyptian president.</p>
<p>He also denied knowing that she was only 17 when they had sex in 2010, while he was serving as prime minister. The minimum legal age for prostitution is 18 in Italy.</p>
<p>The supreme court judges ultimately endorsed the former leader’s version of events, rejecting prosecutor Edoardo Scardaccione’s argument that Berlusconi had a “dragon’s passion for minors”.</p>
<p>“The Mubarak’s niece episode was worthy of a Mel Brooks film,” the prosecutor said during arguments. “The whole world was laughing at us.”</p>
<p>In the early hours after the verdict, Berlusconi was still lamenting all that he had lost. “Who will give me back the years? Who shall compensate me for this suffering, and of what we have lost?” he said.</p>
<p>But it is unlikely that Berlusconi’s legal victory will translate into a new dawn for him politically.</p>
<p>His waning influence was on full display this week after a political reform measure backed by Matteo Renzi, Italy’s prime minister, passed the lower chamber of parliament even after Berlusconi, who remains at the helm of the conservative Forza Italia party, dramatically vowed to oppose it.</p>
<p>Berlusconi and Renzi, who is a left-leaning centrist from the Democratic party (PD), had enjoyed a mutually beneficial pact that ensured Forza Italia would support the prime minister’s reform agenda, but that deal has recently fallen apart without causing Renzi much harm – for now.</p>
<p>“No courtroom can give Berlusconi back his clout,” said analyst Francesco Galietti. That is because Berlusconi is no longer seen by conservatives as the indispensable leader who can unify conservative and rightwing Italians.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show that support for Forza Italia has fallen to 13% from 25% at the time of Berlusconi’s forced resignation in 2011, at the height of Italy’s debt crisis.</p>
<p>His mantle has been taken over in part by Matteo Salvini, the head of the rightwing Northern League, which is trying to supplant Forza Italia as the country’s primary conservative party.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has not only experienced political fumbles. His media empire has also been tested during Italy’s long running recession. Fininvest, the Berlusconi family’s Milan-based holding company, reported a €428m (£301m) loss in 2013 and Mediaset, the largest Italian broadcaster, also controlled by Berlusconi, lost nearly €50m in the first nine months of 2014.</p>
<p>The former premier raised €377m last month following the sale of a 7.8% stake in Mediaset as part of an attempt to bolster his finances.</p>
<p>The Italian press has also been rife with speculation that the media mogul is mulling a sale of all or part of his football club, AC Milan, following a report that he had started talks with Bee Taechaubol, director of the Thai Prime Company Limited, a Thai private equity group. Berlusconi’s company has denied the club is for sale.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>