<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2008-09-28" description="John Hooper talks to Italian comedian Sabina Guzzanti about religion, Berlusconi and freedom of speech" fingerprint="763813119020ff1c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Religion,World news,Comedy,Stage,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Dangerously funny: John Hooper talks to Italian comedian Sabina Guzzanti about religion, Berlusconi and freedom of speech" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/sep/29/italy.religion">
<main>
<p>'I didn't pick on the Pope," Sabina Guzzanti insists as she stirs her coffee. "That was the only remark they hit upon in a 20-minute address. It made it look as if I delivered a speech to say the Pope's a poof." We are sitting at a table outside a cafe in the graffiti-covered San Lorenzo district of Rome, home to students and immigrants. Guzzanti is wrapped in an overcoat and scarf against the onset of autumn. The temperature has plunged to 22C.</p>
<p>If ever there were someone who reaffirmed Dario Fo's vision of the comedian as heir to the deeply subversive medieval giullare, or jester, then it is this 45-year-old satirist with the face and air of a naughty, knowing elf. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, she has been in and out of headline-grabbing controversies for at least 10 years.</p>
<p>But this month she went global. On September 10, prosecutors in Rome asked for leave from the government to put her on trial, charged with "contempt of the Pope". Addressing a big leftwing rally in the Italian capital, the comedian had said: "In 20 years [the former Cardinal Joseph] Ratzinger will be dead and will end up in hell, tormented by queer demons - not passive ones, but very active ones."</p>
<p>Within 48 hours, her case had even worked its way into the US presidential election. Sitting alongside John McCain on Barbara Walters' morning talkshow, The View, the actor Whoopi Goldberg asked: "Did you know that in Italy a comedian called Guzzanti risks five years in jail for a joke about the Pope?" It brought howls of dismay from the live audience.</p>
<p>Quite a few Italians, too, were shocked to discover that it was an offence in their country to poke fun at the pontiff. The offence was introduced in 1929 by a treaty between the papacy and Italy's then fascist dictator, Benito Mussolini. The treaty was revised in the 1980s and one of the changes was to remove the offence of which Guzzanti was accused.</p>
<p>"But in Italy there is this habit of passing lots of new laws and only seldom remembering to cancel the old ones," says Guzzanti. "So the new ones and the old co-exist."</p>
<p>On September 18, Silvio Berlusconi's justice minister decided the case should be dropped. By then, as Guzzanti observed, her critics and the Italian right in general had "made a bloody awful spectacle of themselves to the rest of the world". The affair gave outsiders a rare glimpse of the wackiness rife in the Italian legal system.</p>
<p>But the fact that anyone should try to use a 79-year-old law of dubious validity to nail Guzzanti gives an inkling of the apoplectic rage she can inspire in her conservative compatriots. It may not be a coincidence that Guzzanti used the same rally to voice, in characteristically blunt fashion, a claim that had been hinted at in newspaper reports and talked about in bars across Italy. This was that Berlusconi had had an affair with his equal opportunities minister, a 32-year-old former topless model, Mara Carfagna, and that explicit evidence of their relationship had come to light in a telephone conversation recorded during an investigation into other matters. Berlusconi has denied the allegation and Carfagna threatened to sue Guzzanti, but has never done so.</p>
<p>"She didn't do so because I could have asked to read and bring to court the [transcripts] of the [telephone] intercepts," she says.</p>
<p>Like many a giullare, the price of her jibes at the rich and powerful has been exile - not from the realms of an affronted prince, but from the kingdom of the mighty Silvio, Il cavaliere ("the knight"), as he likes to be called.</p>
<p>Though most Italians have long come to accept it, his control of what they see on their television sets is flagrantly, and perilously, abnormal. Since being sworn in again this year as prime minister, he has had direct or indirect control of six of the seven channels from which the vast majority of Italians get their news and the other information on which they base their opinions.</p>
<p>Not the least important thing about Guzzanti is that she embodies what this means. In practice, it is forbidden in Italy to give Berlusconi anything more than a gentle ribbing, or ask the really hard questions about how he obtained his wealth and power. That is precisely what she did on her TV programme five years ago when Berlusconi was last in power. It was taken off the air by the state-owned RAI after only two episodes. Lawyers for one of Berlusconi's companies then sued Guzzanti for €20m in damages. They did not win because the judge ruled that the things she had said about him on air were true. But she has never been allowed back onto RAI, except for the very occasional guest performance.</p>
<p>The frustration that this must engender in a talented performer is sometimes given by others, particularly on the Italian centre-left, as an explanation for what are regarded as her vulgar excesses, such as her quip about the Pope. Understandably enough, the theory generally goes, she is trying to force herself back into the public eye.</p>
<p>If you want to really wind up Guzzanti - if you want to see a glint appear in her eyes like a struck match - then all you have to do is set out this view. "This is defamatory," she says. "This is said by people who are very much against me and are the worst enemies of any sort of change. I can have visibility whenever it suits. I'm very popular, certainly a lot more popular than they are. If I take part in these rallies, it's not to get visibility. It's a complete bore going to rallies. It's always the same four of us from the arts who go. So really they ought to thank us because we have the courage to say what others don't, including those who write these shitty articles. Anyway, what I say is not outrageous. It's true."</p>
<p>It is clear that Guzzanti holds the Pope in low esteem. Referring to his role as former head of a Vatican department in the sex abuse scandals that have rocked the Catholic church, she argues he had "besmirched himself with several very serious offences".</p>
<p>But the reason, she says, that she had brought him into her speech to the rally in Rome was that she sees some aspects of the Vatican's conservative teaching as underpinning a "rapid authoritarian escalation" in Italy. She cites a string of recent incidents in which suspected far-right-wingers have beaten up gay people. "The discrimination [in Catholic doctrine] against homosexuals - now that really ought to be an offence, especially if it provokes behaviour that is homophobic and violent."</p>
<p>The row over her speech - and this is why Goldberg picked up on it - goes to the heart of a topical debate. Though issues of faith are becoming increasingly entangled with politics, many people of faith want religious institutions and their leaders to be accorded a special respect that is not conceded to, say, politicians. The prosecutors' application to indict Guzzanti can be seen as an attempt to establish that principle - one she absolutely refuses to honour.</p>
<p>"First of all," she says, "what I was speaking about were the politics of the Pope. It's not as if I'd shot off my mouth on theological issues. It is the Pope who should have respect for our political institutions. At the point at which he gets involved in politics I have every right to criticise him for his political activity. Second, I am not even in agreement with the general principle. I believe that in a democracy there is no right not to be offended. I think that anyone ought to be free to say whatever he or she likes at any moment.</p>
<p>"If someone says things that are offensive, gratuitous and stupid, one has to assume there will be others able to demonstrate that what you said was offensive, gratuitous and stupid."</p>
<p>For that reason, she is against the limitations on Holocaust denial. And the Danish cartoonists who ridiculed Mohammed? An instant's hesitation, then she says: "I'm on their side."</p>
<p>Rather than respect for religion, she says, what is increasingly evident is "submission, fear". Pussyfooting around someone else's ideas is tantamount to "treating him like an idiot who can't bear to hear an opinion different from his own. That is not necessarily respect."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>