<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Martin Kettle" categories="Opinion" date="2006-04-24" description="Martin Kettle: Silvio Berlusconi's reponse to election defeat is endangering Italian democracy." fingerprint="4f3e536d9307f50c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,European club football,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="A no-lose situation" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/apr/24/furtherthoughtsontheberlus">
<main>
<p>I took a certain amount of ordure from some readers a couple of weeks back when I argued that Silvio Berlusconi's response to the Italian election results was skating along the touchline of acceptability and had some of the makings of an attempted coup d'etat.</p>
<p>My initial reaction to some of the critics was that they were probably right. I had allowed my delight at the results to affect my judgment. I had exaggerated a bit. It was, after all, fair enough to ask for a recount in a close election. Disputing an election is not synonymous with coup ambitions.</p>
<p>But now I wonder if I wasn't righter than I realised at the start. Berlusconi <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/italy/story/0,,1759827,00.html">said yesterday</ref> that he intends to turn up for work as usual at the prime minister's office when the Italian legislature meets again this week. And that raises this question. What part of the word loser doesn't he understand?</p>
<p>My earlier critics said that sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander. If Al Gore was entitled to challenge the results in Florida in 2000, which he clearly was, then Silvio Berlusconi was also entitled to do so in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> in 2006. I agree with that. But that's where the comparison ends. When the ruling came in the US, Gore accepted the result with immense dignity. But when the ruling came through in Italy last week, Berlusconi simply ignored it. Yesterday's performance in Trieste shows that was not an aberration. And now there is more to come.</p>
<p>Maybe you can argue that Berlusconi remains within his constitutional rights to stay in office until the Italian parliament has formally voted in support of the new centre-left government of Romano Prodi. Maybe you can argue that, given the undoubted closeness of the election result, he is entitled to play political hardball by making things as hard for Prodi as he possibly can, perhaps with a view to extracting some concessions in order to end his protest. Maybe it's simply an ego thing.</p>
<p>But don't try to tell me that anything that Berlusconi is doing reveals a respect for democracy. In the end, the ultimate achievement of a democratic system is that it allows power to be passed between enemies without violence or disorder. Those are the rules that Gore played by, however bitter he must have felt, and they are the rules that any democratic system plays by too. But Berlusconi is now breaking those rules. He is behaving like the Inter Milan fans who tried to take the European Champions League tie from his own AC Milan in 2005 by rioting. If he can't win, he will try to get the game called off. But is democracy a game?</p>
<p>I don't say that Berlusconi will necessarily attempt a coup in the classical sense. I don't think he is about to attempt a pronunciamento. He won't be seizing the radio and TV headquarters this weekend - not least because he owns them already. But I do say that every single thing he has done since April 10 has been a challenge not to the result, but to democracy itself. Italian democracy is still work in progress - and Silvio Berlusconi is a threat to it. Italians will have to live for a long time with the consequences of what Berlusconi is doing in these weeks - and none of those consequences will be good.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>