<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sian Elvin" categories="World news" date="2014-04-15" description="Silvio Berlusconi is not the first high-profile person to be ordered by a court to perform work in the community" fingerprint="b8e9a1c5316922e7" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,World news" title="Six other famous faces sentenced to community service" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/apr/15/famous-community-service-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Chris Brown</hi>
</head>
<p>The American R&amp;B singer was given community service as part of his sentence for assaulting his girlfriend Rihanna in 2009. Among the tasks he said he completed were picking up rubbish, painting walls, washing police cars and fire engines and waxing floors.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Naomi Campbell</hi>
</head>
<p>In 2007 the supermodel was sentenced in the US to five days of community service after pleading guilty to striking her housekeeper in the head with a mobile phone. On her last day she turned up at the New York sanitation department in a Dolce &amp; Gabbana sequin dress and stilettos, and left in a silver Rolls-Royce. When asked by Grazia magazine why she had dressed like that, she said: "Why shouldn't I have done? Why should they expect me to go looking bedraggled or something?"</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Boy George</hi>
</head>
<p>The Culture Club singer was arrested in New York in 2005 on suspicion of possessing cocaine and falsely reporting a burglary. The drug possession charge was dropped after George denied the cocaine was his, but he pleaded guilty to wasting police time and was sentenced to five days of community service, ordered to attend drug rehabilitation classes and was given a fine of $1,000. His task was to sweep the streets of New York, but after 30 minutes he was moved when he was mobbed by fans and the media.</p>
<head rend="h2">Snoop Dogg</head>
<p>The rapper was sentenced to 800 hours of community service in 2008 after being investigated for illegal possession of drugs and a handgun. Having previously set up his own Snoop youth football league – with a "Snooper Bowl" championship game – he was allowed to spend half of his service with his team as it counted towards helping young people.</p>
<head rend="h2">Lindsay Lohan</head>
<p>The actress and model was sentenced to community service after two drink-driving arrests in 2007 and a case of theft in 2011 when she took a necklace worth $2,500 from a jewellery store. She was turned away from two placements at a women's shelter and a morgue due to turning up late, being disruptive and leaving after one hour when she was required to complete four hours per shift. Following her violation of the regulations she was given more community service and 30 days in prison. She eventually completed her hours in 2012.</p>
<head rend="h2">Kanye West</head>
<p>Last month the hip-hop star was given 250 hours of unspecified community service as well as two years' probation and 24 anger management lessons, as part of his sentence for assaulting a photographer at Los Angeles airport last year.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>