<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Esther Addley" categories="Media" date="2009-12-27" description="From Michael Jackson to the G20; duck islands to Twitter - the people, events and items that most transfixed Britain's media" fingerprint="e2e25837d5dcc575" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Media,National newspapers,Newspapers &amp; magazines,World news,UK news,Michael Jackson,Recession,MPs expenses,G20,X,Silvio Berlusconi,Climate crisis,Swine flu,Military,Afghanistan,UK weather,Social media" title="The newsmakers of 2009" url="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2009/dec/27/newsmakers-2009">
<main>
<p>So how was it for you? The Queen described 2009 as a year best forgotten and, not for the first time, the monarch had a point. There will, no doubt, be some who thrived over the past 12 months – that Jedward pair haven't had an entirely dreadful year – but the list of those glad to see the back of 2009 is perhaps rather longer.</p>
<p>And so, out of consideration for Tiger Woods, Thierry Henry, former Speaker Michael Martin, Julie Myerson, Roman Polanski, Jade Goody's (currently imprisoned) widower Jack Tweed and the parents of the "balloon boy" Falcon Heene, we will keep this brief.</p>
<p>Which were the stories that most transfixed the media in 2009? Using an entirely unscientific yardstick ‑ how many times they were mentioned in British national newspapers ‑ we present our arbitrary selection of the newsmakers of the year.</p>
<head rend="h2">Michael Jackson</head>
<p>No surprises here. With one last <hi rend="#i">sha-mon!</hi> , and six separate doses of prescription drugs, the King of Pop moonwalked offstage for the final time on 25 June, becoming one of the biggest stories of the year. Since the beginning of 2009, 7,603 articles have appeared in the British national press about <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/music/michaeljackson">Michael Jackson</ref>, or an average of more than 20 a day, every day. In contrast, Farrah Fawcett, right, died of cancer on the same day. Her tally — 263.</p>
<head rend="h2">Recession</head>
<p>2009 may seem, looking back, like the year when we fixated on the questionably acquired wealth of others, but a little investigation reveals that in matters financial, our own poverty is many times more interesting.</p>
<p>Thus while <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/mps-expenses">MPs' expenses</ref> won a highly respectable 10,606 mentions in the national press, and 11,378 articles were published on the subject of bonuses, feverish discussion involving the word "recession" (u-shaped, w-shaped, brief or bottomless) brought a total of no fewer than 52,368 articles in 2009. And we are still no clearer about when it will end.</p>
<head rend="h2">Moat</head>
<p>Speaking of expenses, the acquisition of an uncensored copy of our estimable MPs' expense claims created quite a few new stars this year ‑ step forward Margaret Moran, MP for Luton South, who claimed £22,500 for dry rot in Southampton; take a bow Elliot Morley, who kept on claiming mortgage interest even after his mortgage was paid off. But there's no question what became the most talked-about symbol of the scandal ‑ Sir Peter Viggers' £1,645 floating duck island. Right?</p>
<p>Actually, wrong. The duck domain did merit a creditable 735 separate stories, but in fact it is the £2,115 claimed by Douglas Hogg to clear the moat at his Lincolnshire mansion that emerges as the star of the crisis, at 897 articles. Even Jacqui Smith's adult movies (686) can't compete. And as for David Cameron's wisteria-trimming (112) ‑ seems we weren't much bothered.</p>
<head rend="h2">G20</head>
<p>Britain hosted a summit and lots of famous and powerful people came, which got us all excited. Protesters thronged the City of London. And a newspaper seller, Ian Tomlinson, died after an encounter with riot police: 7,226 articles.</p>
<p>Well, of course. It will come as little surprise that the social networking phenomenon, without question one of the media's obsessions in 2009, merited 7,332 articles in the national press. What is perhaps more striking is the speed at which its cultural dominance has been achieved. In 2008, that number was 305.</p>
<p>And what of the people who owe some of their cultural currency this year to Twitter? Stephen Gately, the Boyzone singer who died in October, had 987 mentions; Jan Moir, the Daily Mail columnist accused of writing a homophobic piece after his death, 237. Daniel Hannan, the ultra-Eurosceptic MEP whose comments on the NHS sparked a Twitter fightback: 350. And Neda Soltan, the young Iranian woman whose death after being shot during a protest became a symbol of that country's rebellion? 285.</p>
<head rend="h2">Silvio Berlusconi</head>
<p>Well, let's just say it's been a busy year. There was the earthquake in L'Aquila, and the incident at the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/g20">G20</ref> summit in London when the Queen had to tell him to pipe down during a photocall, and his own G8 summit in July. Plus all that stuff about the alleged call girls and his (estranged) wife saying he "frequents minors". And then, just as the Italian prime minister was settling down for a quiet Christmas with what's left of the family, somebody punched him in the face with a souvenir statue of Milan's cathedral. 3,027 stories.</p>
<head rend="h2">Climate change</head>
<p>11,171 articles were published in British national newspapers in 2009 on the subject of climate change. Is that a lot? Hard to tell, but in 2008 the tally was 8,001, so one might say awareness of perhaps the most important existential crisis to face humanity is moving in the right direction. Mind you, The <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/twitter">X</ref> Factor got 11,908.</p>
<head rend="h2">Swine flu</head>
<p>It's official, swine flu (8,047) is 2.3 times more entertaining than Susan Boyle (3,453).</p>
<head rend="h2">Helmand</head>
<p>Last year, Helmand province, a lush corner of southern <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> in which 42% of the world's opium crop is grown, was mentioned in 2,588 news articles. In 2009 that tally was 5,649. 106 British soldiers have died in Afghanistan this year, most of them in Helmand.</p>
<head rend="h2">Barbecue summer</head>
<p>Remember that? Me neither. And yet such is the power of hope, and regret, when it comes to Brits and the weather that 2009's non-existent barbecue summer still merited, at 433 articles, more mentions in the national press than Belle de Jour (187), Samantha Cameron (386), right, EU president Herman Van Rompuy (327) and the Christmas no 1 bunfight victors Rage Against the Machine (303). And it goes without saying that I, for one, have very high hopes for 2010.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>