<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Business" date="2003-10-03" description="Allies of Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, closed ranks yesterday to vote through the lower house of parliament his government's controversial communications bill, reports John Hooper." fingerprint="3fe8c1bebaa0cd7c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Business,Italy,Media business,Media,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi allies win day for TV bill" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2003/oct/03/italy.citynews">
<main>
<p>Allies of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, closed ranks yesterday to vote through the lower house of parliament his government's controversial communications bill.</p>
<p>Twice in the two days leading up to the final vote, the government suffered defeats when amendments sponsored by the opposition were backed by rebel MPs from the conservative majority.</p>
<p>Inclusion of the amendments meant further delay for a measure that has already had a stormy passage through the legislature. In <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, laws have to be approved in identical form by both houses of parliament, so the communications bill will have to return to the senate before becoming law.</p>
<p>Critics say it will tighten Mr Berlusconi's already formidable grip on the Italian media but the government has defended the measure as promoting freedom of choice.</p>
<p>The prime minister owns three of Italy's seven main TV channels and indirectly controls a further three, operated by the state broadcaster, Rai.</p>
<p>The bill would allow Mr Berlusconi's Mediaset group to hold on to all three of its main TV channels, despite court rulings requiring it to spin off one.</p>
<p>It would legalise cross-ownership of broadcast and print media from 2009 and allow any one media group to take a bigger share of overall advertising than at present.</p>
<p>The bill also sets the guidelines for the introduction of digital terrestrial TV in 2007, a move that will at least quadruple the number of channels.</p>
<p>But, according to critics, it is unlikely the changeover can take place so soon, and there are fears that the new rules will just carry over the existing duopoly from analogue to digital.</p>
<p>Yesterday's final vote in the chamber of deputies was won by 318 to 261.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>