<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-12-14" description="'No diktats' says prime minister as he rejects compromise plea by rebels ahead of tomorrow's double showdown" fingerprint="ffad11b79ab3d739" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi faces crucial confidence vote in Italian parliament" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/13/silvio-berlusconi-italy-confidence-vote">
<main>
<p>Italy's embattled prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, is heading for a do-or-die, double showdown in parliament today after brusquely rejecting a last appeal for compromise from the party rebels who have pushed his government to the brink.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's administration is expected to win a vote of confidence in the upper house, the senate, but is significantly more vulnerable to a motion of no confidence in the chamber of deputies.</p>
<p>All 35 members of a group led by Berlusconi's former deputy, Gianfranco Fini, today signed an appeal calling for the prime minister to step down after tomorrow's ballot in the senate and before learning his fate in the lower house. If he agreed, they undertook to back a new government led by Berlusconi but with a revised programme. They warned that if he did not, they would vote as a bloc for his removal.</p>
<p>The document succeeded in patching up a split among Fini's followers and increased the chances of a razor-thin margin between yes and no votes.</p>
<p>According to one calculation, the result would be a dead heat if none of the rebels switched allegiance back to the government. Apparently confident of victory nevertheless, the prime minister brushed aside the rebels' offer. "I don't resign. No diktats," he said.</p>
<p>Addressing the senate earlier in the day, Berlusconi had warned that a defeat for his government would send the country spiralling into the maelstrom of the eurozone debt crisis. It would be "political madness", he told the upper house. But he also signalled that, even if he won, he would seek to broaden his majority by bringing into government the conservative Christian Democrat Union of the Centre (UDC), a process that could prolong the country's simmering political crisis for weeks.</p>
<p>An important consideration will be how many of three heavily pregnant deputies manage to cast their votes in the lower house. Federica Mogherini of the Democratic party, Italy's biggest opposition group, said she would be exactly nine months pregnant. "If Marta [the name she has chosen for her second daughter] decides to be born on time, and I go into labour, then there's nothing I can do," she told the daily La Repubblica.</p>
<p>Adding to the drama, thousands of demonstrators are expected in Rome to register their own protests against the Berlusconi government. They include students, revolutionary Marxists and victims of the earthquake which struck the central Abruzzo region last year. Up to 3,000 riot police have been deployed to the maze of cobbled lanes in the centre of the capital to prevent the demonstrators getting near either of the two houses of parliament. Other sensitive locations, including Berlusconi's private residence, will be closely guarded.</p>
<p>The government has been without a guaranteed majority in the lower house since July when Fini's followers stormed out of the governing majority to set up a parliamentary group of their own. Though addressed to the senate, key passages of the prime minister's speech this morning were clearly aimed at some of the more ambivalent rebels in the chamber of deputies.</p>
<p>At the weekend six of Fini's supporters signed an appeal for peace talks with Berlusconi. That initiative was promptly stamped on by their leader who announced that his group would join the opposition after Tuesday's ballots, regardless of the outcome. "The votes of the centre-right's electorate cannot be taken and added to those of the opposition," Berlusconi told the senate. "Free parliaments are called to represent and interpret the popular will, not replace it."</p>
<p>Even though its public debt is proportionately the highest in the eurozone, Italy has not so far come under the same market pressure as Greece, Ireland and Portugal. But, in an ominous development last month, investors suddenly demanded a higher premium for holding its debt.</p>
<p>Political uncertainty could spook the markets and further increase Italy's borrowing costs. That in turn would weaken the grip that Berlusconi's finance minister, Giulio Tremonti, has managed to keep on Italy's budget deficit and add to its public debt, creating a vicious circle from which the country might find it hard to escape.</p>
<p>Berlusconi told the senate: "Our country needs stability and governability for reforms [to be carried out]."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>