<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Carole Cadwalladr" categories="Opinion" date="2011-02-06" description="Carole Cadwalladr: Boots' new paternity testing kit misses the point about being a father" fingerprint="7be8b07781a59a8a" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Parents and parenting,Silvio Berlusconi,John Bercow,UK news" title="Fatherhood is not in the DNA – it's in the love | Carole Cadwalladr" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/feb/06/fathers-sally-bercow-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>It's off to Boots to stock up on the basics: aspirin, toothpaste, a DNA paternity testing kit. Yes, forget Jeremy Kyle, you can have your own "Who's the daddy?" showdown without even leaving home: last week, Boots started selling DIY AssureDNA kits over the counter for £30.</p>
<p>Having once witnessed Jeremy Kyle impart the results of a paternity test to a young couple in a pub car park in Hemel Hempstead, where the mother swore and yelled at a man Kyle referred to as the "so-called father", an adolescent with the eyes of a rabbit who'd just spotted a 30-tonne articulated lorry speeding towards it, I would urge a note of caution. It's really not a pretty sight. Even without a daytime TV host and the kind of audience disappointed if there's no actual blood involved, the emotions I witnessed – terror, panic, despair, anger – are likely to be the same.</p>
<p>The technology has been around for a while, of course, it just hasn't been out there on the shelves of your high-street chemist, between the Vicks nasal spray and the Sanatogen tablets, the kind of last-minute impulse purchase you pick up when you only popped in for a lip salve.</p>
<p>Forget the overpriced face serum, this weekend you could walk out with a whole new daddy, an outcome which, if a 2005 study from Liverpool John Moores University is to believed, is likely to be the case in one in 25 families. That means 4% of fathers, it found, were unknowingly raising a child who was not biologically theirs.</p>
<p>The Boots test has the ability to change that or, at least, to change the "unknowing" aspect of it. The truth is out there, whether everybody involved wants it or not. The whole world is experiencing what radical transparency looks like in the context of governments and nation states; the after-effects of the WikiLeaks revelations. This is what it looks like when applied to human relationships. It's a new kind of radical transparency – a WikiLeaks of the human heart, with everything that entails: explosive revelations leading to outcomes unknown.</p>
<p>In the meantime, what? A stream of men rushing to Boots? Leading the charge, a certain Boris Johnson whose possible "love-child" the <hi rend="#i">Daily Mail </hi>published another photo of last week: bouncing baby Stephanie with her shock of strawberry blonde hair and cherubically chubby cheeks? (Her mother, Helen Macintyre, has known Boris for years and her ex-partner, a Canadian-born property developer called Pierre Rolin claims that an affair between the two was the reason they split up.)</p>
<p>There's all sorts of reasons why the truth is better than a lie: the father's right to know, the CSA, hereditary illnesses, questions of both financial and moral support. And sometimes, as in Boris Becker's case, who fathered a child in the broom cupboard of Nobu with a waitress during a gap between courses, the child is so much a chip off the old block that a DNA test is just a formality for the courts.</p>
<p>But genes tell only one version of the truth, based on a sequence of nucleic acids, not on life, experience or love. Spare a thought for poor Paula Yates. Finding out her biological father wasn't Jess Yates, the man who raised her, but the gameshow host Hughie Green, a man whom Jess hated, was another of life's hammer blows that eventually overwhelmed her.</p>
<p>An AssureDNA test may tell whose sperm did or didn't fertilise your mother's egg but what it can't tell you is who your father is. Your father is the man who cares for you as a father. Your child is the one who you raise as your child. This test can't tell you who loves you. Or whom you love. Or how much. Or why. The fundamental unknowability of another's heart is a universal feature of the human condition. To which not even a £30 test from Boots holds the answer.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Barbara Ellen is away</hi>
</p>
<head rend="h2">With friends like Berlusconi, who needs enemies?</head>
<p>Hosni Mubarak's foreign friends may be disappearing by the day, but there's still one old pal prepared to stand shoulder to shoulder with the Egyptian premier. Step forward <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who described him as "the wisest of men".</p>
<p>But, then, when it comes to flouting international condemnation and resisting calls for his resignation, Mubarak is a mere ingenue compared with Berlusconi. The Italian prime minister faces his own Tahrir Square in the form of a Facebook group which has decided to march on his villa outside Milan. There, they will chant slogans and throw condoms and knickers in protest. This, apparently, recalls the hail of coins that a crowd pelted on former prime minister Bettino Craxi when he was accused of corruption, although there are some who worry that it's about as useful as throwing cocaine and vodka at Charlie Sheen's house, a man who has taken Berlusconi's concept of bunga bunga and raised it to a whole new level.</p>
<p>In response, Berlusconi has continued his one-man PR blitz, phoning a third late-night television show in less than a month, this time calling it "a television whorehouse". To clarify: apparently this was <hi rend="#i">not</hi> a compliment.</p>
<head rend="h2">Please, Sally, keep it under wraps</head>
<p>Oh, Sally, Sally, Sally. I'd ask why, but I worry that this will only encourage further attention-seeking behaviour. We've got the point: you're attention-seeking. Now put your bra back on, love, and just step away from the cameras.</p>
<p>Sally Bercow, who rose to fame as the Speaker's wife, but who now has a portfolio career as a publicity-hungry-tabloid-staple-cum-wannabe MP, has been at it again, "accidentally" stripping off for the London <hi rend="#i">Evening Standard</hi>,<hi rend="#i"/>failing to realise that doing a photoshoot in a bedroom for a feature called "Sex and the City" might, you know, result in her having her picture in the papers.</p>
<p>But it's hard to keep up with Sal. Once, she was social secretary of the Oxford University Conservative Association. Now, she's a "Labour activist". She used to work in advertising and PR. Now, she's no idea how these newspaper thingies work.</p>
<p>Well, Sally, it's like this. When your husband is the Speaker of the House, and you slag off the prime minister on Twitter, the newspapers will print it. When you strip off for a newspaper, that newspaper will print it. I know, it's difficult to get your head around, isn't it?</p>
<p>And when the public tires of you, and you find you have to streak naked across College Green, and still the world yawns and wonders what's on telly, you will have reaped what you have sowed, as I believe it's called.</p>
<p>The kindest thing, perhaps, is to treat her as you would a small child or a pet and simply ignore the unwanted behaviour. Don't reward it. Don't say the words "harmless" and "fun". It's for her own good, believe me. Otherwise, what will be next? Peeing on the carpet and throwing tantrums in the street? Dry humping the prime minister's leg?</p>
<p>Cruel to be kind, people, cruel to be kind.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>