<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington; Rajeev Syal" categories="World news" date="2009-10-10" description="Marina Berlusconi defends Italian prime minister after removal of his immunity from prosecution" fingerprint="7ab4810f5087d75c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Tessa Jowell,Politics,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi's daughter accuses his opponents of 'manhunt'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/11/berlusconi-daughter-accuses-opponents-manhunt">
<main>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">After a dreadful week for Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister's eldest daughter has claimed a "manhunt" is under way to overthrow him and subvert Italian democracy. </hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Marina Berlusconi, 43, leaped to her father's defence following the decision by Italy's constitutional court to remove his immunity from prosecution while in office. "In dictatorships they send tanks into the piazzas," she told the Corriere della Sera newspaper. "In a democracy like ours, you jab and you use subtle means that are officially legal and therefore even more insidious. The aim is the same, to overturn the verdict of the electorate." </hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Before passing an immunity law in 2008 covering himself and three other government officials, Berlusconi was facing a charge of paying a £430,000 bribe to tax consultant David Mills, the estranged husband of Olympics minister Tessa Jowell, to give evidence in his favour in Italian trials. Yesterday Mills offered to act as a defence witness in any criminal trial Berlusconi may now face. </hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Speaking from his home in the Cotswolds, Mills said: "Since I am the person who unwittingly and unintentionally got him involved in all of this, it is a matter of honour that I will give evidence in his trial and I will explain why he had absolutely nothing to do with the payment concerned and that he is completely innocent of any corrupt activity at all.</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Ms Berlusconi, who is president of the family holding company, Fininvest, said the cadre of plotters out to topple her father was made up of "a publishing group, a few television commentators, a group of magistrates, a few academics and senior civil servants". </hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Referring to Carlo De Benedetti, honorary president of the energy and media group CIR, whose newspaper La Repubblica has led attacks on Berlusoni since a series of sex scandals broke, she said: "De Benedetti would have wanted to be like Berlusconi, only he never managed it." </hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>