<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Matthew Tempest" categories="World news" date="2004-03-04" description="Tony Blair today held a mini-summit in Rome with the Italian prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, which was dominated by recent bombing attacks in Iraq." fingerprint="6d8bc3df92c7d25f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="European Union,Politics,World news,Italy,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Iraq dominates Blair-Berlusconi talks" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/mar/04/eu.politics">
<main>
<p>Tony Blair today held a mini-summit in Rome with the Italian prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, which was dominated by recent bombing attacks in Iraq.</p>
<p>Although the ostensible purpose of the meeting was to discuss further privatisation within the EU - most notably in the fields of energy and telecommunications - the two coalition partners in Iraq met in Rome under the shadow of this week's massive bombing attacks.</p>
<p>Following their meeting, Mr Blair told reporters after his talks with Mr Berlusconi: "We are trying to work with the Iraqi people to put the country on its feet.</p>
<p>"The purpose of the terrorism is to stop that happening, is to try and cause religious division, hatred, so that Iraq cannot make that journey of progress.</p>
<p>"The terrorists know that if we manage to put Iraq on its feet that is a blow to the whole of their extremism, to that fundamental case against not just the western world but moderate Arab countries too.</p>
<p>"The struggle that's happening is a struggle that literally will be of fundamental importance to the future of the Middle East and to the future of the world.</p>
<p>And he dismissed the notion that Iraq was plunging into civil war, saying: "A civil war is two parts of a country in hostility to one another. This isn't what's happening in Iraq. The vast majority of people there want to work together.</p>
<p>"There's no reason why they can't make this political progress."</p>
<p>Mr Blair and Mr Berlusconi also agreed to write a joint letter to Ireland's taoiseach, Bertie Ahern, who currently holds the EU's rotating presidency, stressing the need for continuing economic reform.</p>
<p>The prime minister also stressed Britain's relations with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> were as strong as they have ever been, with an Anglo-Italian summit to be held this summer.</p>
<p>Mr Blair was flying back to London tonight.</p>
<p>The meeting was also, at least in part, a bridge-building exercise by the British prime minister, after Mr Berlusconi felt aggrieved at being left out of the informal "trilateral" summit of Britain, France and Germany last month.</p>
<p>The Italian leader, freshly recovered from an alleged facelift over the Christmas break, has said he would reject any moves from the so-called Big Three that Italy did not approve of.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>