<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Owen Bowcott" categories="Law" date="2011-05-23" description="Owen Bowcott: Industrial action by the country's advocates' union has tarnished the reputation of lawyers further in the eyes of the general public" fingerprint="7834910c7a508314" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Law,Solicitors,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news" title="Compulsory mediation angers lawyers working in Italy's unwieldy legal system | Owen Bowcott" url="http://www.theguardian.com/law/butterworth-and-bowcott-on-law/2011/may/23/italian-lawyers-strike-mandatory-mediation">
<main>
<p>Prime ministers rarely welcome strikes. The decision by Italy's lawyers to avoid court hearings in protest at the introduction of mandatory mediation must, nonetheless, have been gratifying for a national leader who enjoys berating his country's legal system.</p>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi is facing multiple trials over his convoluted personal and financial life – including allegedly paying an underage prostitute.</p>
<p>He has repeatedly expressed his disdain for "leftwing" prosecutors and courtroom entanglements.</p>
<p>The industrial action launched by the Italian advocates union, <ref target="http://www.oua.it/NotizieOUA/Notizie.asp">Organismo Unitario dell'Avvocatura Italiana</ref>, closed courts across the country for two days in March.</p>
<p>Further boycotts are under consideration; Berlusconi's future court appearances could even be disrupted.</p>
<p>The idea that mediation – dictionary definition being "an attempt to effect a peaceful settlement" – could provoke such wrath might seem as counterintuitive as the notion that mediation can be made compulsory.</p>
<p>But the reform is seen as a severe threat to the income and integrity of those who operate Italy's slow-moving legal system.</p>
<p>Riccardo Buizza, a Milan-based lawyer for Withers LLP, who attended the Civil Mediation Conference in Manchester this month, supports the change.</p>
<p>He explained: "Bearing in mind that mediation was almost unknown in Italy until recently, it has been a kind of shockwave.</p>
<p>"There has been lots of criticism from Italian lawyers, particularly over the fact that mediation will now be compulsory. But the strike was an own goal because the perception of the general public in Italy is that the civil justice system does not work perfectly.</p>
<p>"Most people thought introducing mediation was a positive way of avoiding waiting two years and paying lawyers' fees.</p>
<p>"When it was seen that lawyers were opposing the reform, their reputation took a further downturn.</p>
<p>"There's a call now for another day of action. Last time most of the lawyers sat in their offices but refused to go to court. I'm not sure it had much effect."</p>
<p>Critics pointed out that the protest extended a long weekend during the height of the skiing season.</p>
<p>The new Italian law requires those involved in most civil cases to attempt resolution through mediation initially.</p>
<p>It incorporates – but goes far beyond – EU directive in 2008 that required all EU countries, apart from Denmark, to provide mediation for cross-border civil disputes by this spring.</p>
<p>"Sometimes in Italy we go from the Middle Ages to the future without stopping," said Buizza, who specialises in complex insurance claims and has been interested in mediation for many years.</p>
<p>"The Berlusconi government is in favour of mediation, the opposition is against.</p>
<p>"Many lawyers fear they will be losing business, thinking that you are paid for litigation if you go to court. But that's shortsighted. Lawyers also get paid for mediation work. Personally, I think it's worth a try.</p>
<p>"From my point of view, any dispute – even the bloodiest – has a point of compromise."</p>
<p>In the UK, the Ministry of Justice has already announced that financial and child custody disputes must initially go through mediation before moving on, if unresolved, to court.</p>
<p>The justice minister, Jonathan Djanogly, a former City solicitor, gave a resounding endorsement to the principle of mediation at the same Manchester conference.</p>
<p>"Why get involved in an expensive, long-winded and often stressful litigious process and have your dispute decided by someone else when you could remain in control and shape the outcome through mediation," he said. "For far too long, access to justice has been equated with 'having one's day in court'."</p>
<p>In Italy, Berlusconi has been accused of launching his legal reforms as a personal vendetta to get his own back on the judiciary. However, it's difficult to imagine him gleefully entering into mediation with his many accusers.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>