<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2009-01-21" description="Roberto Mancini: Berlusconi's shameless bending of political convention on appointments needs a strong referee. But who is there to do the job?" fingerprint="f6a74a8ae621ef5f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Media,Europe" title="Roberto Mancini: Berlusconi's shameless bending of political convention on appointments needs a strong referee. But who is there to do the job?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jan/21/italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>As if it was playing a rigged game of rugby, and certainly in a manner contrary to the spirit of the game, Silvio Berlusconi's Centro Destra (centre right coalition) government has yet again been bending political convention. For the past two months, a row has simmered over its unilateral appointment of its own candidate as president of the watchdog <ref target="http://www.parlamento.it/parlam/bicam/14/RAI/">Vigilanza sulla Rai</ref>, which monitors the three public television channels.</p>
<p>Italy's President <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Napolitano">Giorgio Napolitano</ref> often protests that civil and political morality is in decline. (Protesting is all he can do, since the role of president of the Republic has few powers in Italian politics beyond the role of "<ref target="http://www.answers.com/topic/moral-suasion">moral suasion</ref>".) The facts behind the appointment of the Commissione Parlamentare di Vigilanza della Rai is a good example of what he means.</p>
<p>It is a peculiarity of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>, that rather than the media monitoring the politicians, parliament, through the Commissione di Vigilanza, controls the media. But for the past decade a "gentlemen's agreement" has been in place designed to maintain the balance of power typical of liberal democracies.</p>
<p>This agreement between the government and the opposition ensures that appointment of the presidency of the Commissione di Vigilanza (which also monitors the secret service) should be in the hands of the opposition. It is a recognition that both public television and the secret service are powerful instruments and need careful monitoring by the opposition in order to avoid the kind of abuse by governments which is endemic in Italian political history.</p>
<p>The opposition Centro Sinistra (the centre left coalition of the Democractic Party and the IdV) therefore nominated the former mayor of Palermo, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leoluca_Orlando">Leoluca Orlando</ref>. Throwing convention out of the window, the Centro Destra announced he was unacceptable because he was too hostile to Berlusconi. Instead, they elected their own, more acceptable opposition candidate <ref target="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riccardo_Villari">Riccardo Villari </ref>to be the president of the Vigilanza. Not surprisingly, the Centro Sinistra walked out.</p>
<p>Villari has been asked to resign by the Democratic Party and Idv on the grounds that he is not the candidate the opposition actually chose. To date, in spite of mounting pressure, he has refused - at the cost of his expulsion from the party he helped found. But the mass resignation two days ago of the entire board of the Commissione di Vigilanza has left him isolated. He may not last much longer.</p>
<p>In the meantime, the balance of power is nonexistent.</p>
<p>What Italy needs is a rugby referee, with the power to send off any player for acting in a manner contrary to the spirit of the game. If only rugby was more widely played in Italy....</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">This has been translated from Italian.</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>