<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lucy Mangan" categories="From the Guardian" date="2011-02-12" description="Lucy Mangan on the people in the media spotlight in the past seven days" fingerprint="72352137df28c241" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Arianna Huffington" title="This Week: Silvio Berlusconi, Arianna Huffington, Michael Kennedy" url="http://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2011/feb/12/this-week-silvio-berlusconi-arianna-huffington">
<main>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">President evil</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>
</p>
<p>Another week, another attempt by the Italian criminal justice system to curb the president's fun. This time, prosecutors claim Berlusconi paid a prostitute but forgot the rule that no matter how <hi rend="#i">bella </hi>the <hi rend="#i">figura </hi>is, it must be over 18 before you are allowed to pay to have sex with it, and then abused his official position to cover up the crime.</p>
<p>Berlusconi's defence has been robust. He has warned that he will sue the state, and points out that it is the taxpayer who will therefore suffer in the end. "I'm not worried about myself. I'm a rich gentleman who can go on to setting up hospitals for children around the world, as I have always wanted to."</p>
<p>It's kinda hilarious, really. Or would be if, y'know, it didn't, at bottom, involve trafficking in underage flesh. Crazy guy.</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">The cheque's in the Post</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Arianna Huffington</hi>
</p>
<p>The media world reeled in shock this week when news broke that someone had made money out of the internet. Entrepreneur Arianna Huffington sold the US online news website she founded for around $1.76 six years ago for $315m – all but $15m of that cash being real money, fold-it-and-put-it-in-your-pocket-old-fashioned-tangible-moolah – to AOL. Truly it is amazing what you can do when you don't pay your contributors.</p>
<p>Huffington herself will become president and editor in chief of a new entity called Huffington Post Media Group and will, amongst other things, be in charge of AOL's entire news operation.</p>
<p>Of course, last time AOL merged with anything, it was with Time Warner in 2000, which resulted in a corporate bloodbath leaving the reseparated companies worth about a seventh of what they had been worth. But still – with $300m in cash (CASH! Cash money!), who really cares?</p>
<head rend="h2">
<hi rend="#b">Bring on the wall</hi>
</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Michael Kennedy</hi>
</p>
<p>And finally, one of those tiny, cocklewarming stories without whose rare infusions of joy most of us would find it even harder to drag ourselves out of bed in the morning and onward towards another grey and pointless day.</p>
<p>Kennedy is a 73-year-old retired engineer from Hunstanton who has spent two hours a day (except Saturdays) for the past 14 years moving rocks along his local beach to build sea walls at the base of the cliffs, to retard the effects of the coastal erosion that is endemic in that part of Norfolk. Then he goes home to watch Countdown.</p>
<p>That's an estimated 9,000 hours of work and 200 tonnes of the heavy stuff shifted. And the walls are working. Now, say thank you to Mr K (you rock!) and then off you go and have a slightly brighter, happier day.</p>
<head rend="h2">What we've learned</head>
<p>The Catholic church has OK'd a confessional app for the iPhone</p>
<p>Sales of herbal tea rose by 60% last year</p>
<p>The Jaguar E-type turned 50 this week</p>
<p>Penelope Keith is opening a tea shop in Avoch in the Scottish Highlands</p>
<p>The cost of childcare increased by twice as much as the average pay rise last yearWhat We Haven't</p>
<head rend="h2">And what we haven't</head>
<p>What lovely, thoughtful, beautifully wrapped presents we are going to receive on Monday from our beloveds. Valentine's Day, people. You've got about 15 shopping hours to find something.</p>
<head rend="h2">What they said</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">"Obtain a suitable set of defined cycle underwear with a padded crotch area to prevent discomfort during riding."</hi> Part of a 21-page document issued by West Midlands police to its bicycle patrol.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">"It's hyperstimulated, vivid, lurid … terrifying, confusing, ridiculously slick, shockingly clumsy, unmistakably monomaniacal and clinically bipolar."</hi> The New York Magazine on Broadway show Spider-Man. I think it's a rave.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">"Pointlessly tall … there's a long center stretch of his body that he doesn't know what to do with." </hi>The New Yorker's David Denby on Ashton Kutcher.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>