<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2011-03-11" description="Film lot loved by Federico Fellini – which gave the world La Dolce Vita, Roman Holiday and Ben-Hur – fights for its future" fingerprint="79ced4be3dce7517" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Benito Mussolini,Silvio Berlusconi,Hungary,Europe,World news,Film,Culture,Film industry,Business" title="Cinecitta studios in Rome in danger as film producers look to eastern Europe" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/mar/11/cinecitta-rome-film-studio-threat">
<main>
<p>Summing up its effect on his creative juices, the Italian film director Federico Fellini described Rome's Cinecitta studios as "my ideal world, the cosmic space before the big bang".</p>
<p>But the legendary 40-hectare (100-acre) lot built by Mussolini, which became a home from home for Hollywood stars in the 1950s and 60s, is now fighting for its future.</p>
<p>With productions heading east to cheaper locations such as <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/hungary">Hungary</ref>, the studio where the classics Ben-Hur and Roman Holiday – and more recently Gangs of New York – were shot has seen its earnings shrink.</p>
<p>It is now pinning its hopes for income on an amusement park, hotel and spa being built on the site where Richard Burton and Elizabeth Taylor smooched while shooting Cleopatra in 1963.</p>
<p>Times have also changed in the centre of Rome. Tourists attempting a tour of real locations today discover that the garret where Gregory Peck and Audrey Hepburn fell in love in Roman Holiday is in a state of disrepair.</p>
<p>The final straw this week for Italy's cinema establishment was the slashing of funding to the national archive of 100,000 prewar and postwar cinema newsreels, including Mussolini's 1940 declaration of war, housed at Cinecitta and now risking closure.</p>
<p>"That's our memory, our history. How can you close down history?" said Roberto Benigni, who won an Oscar for his film Life is Beautiful.</p>
<p>The state-run archive, known as Cinecitta Luce, has had its funding cut from €29m (£25m) in 2004 to €7.5m this year thanks to an austerity drive ordered by finance minister Giulio Tremonti which has slashed overall performing arts funding by a third.</p>
<p>"These old films are disintegrating – careful maintenance is essential and any damage would be irreversible," said Luciano Sovena, head of the archive.</p>
<p>Even Sandro Bondi, Italy's culture minister and a once fanatical backer of Italian prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, was aghast.</p>
<p>Sounding more like the opposition than the opposition, his ministry this week called the cuts "a bitter surprise that leaves us dismayed and dumbfounded".</p>
<p>Next door to Cinecitta Luce at the film studio, prospects are less dire. The lot has been rented out since 1997 to private backers including the Della Valle brothers – the Tod's Shoes tycoons – and is just about in the black.</p>
<p>But if Cinecitta could attract Hollywood productions with its skilled and cheap staff in the 1950s, the low-cost lots are further east today. Cinecitta's last big outdoor set, for the HBO series Rome, wrapped up in 2007, and even Italian filmmakers are now spending 71% of their budgets abroad.</p>
<p>"We cannot guarantee big profits with film, meaning we need parallel projects based on the brand," said Maurizio Sperandini, deputy general manager.</p>
<p>Hence the Cinecitta World amusement park, built on a separate lot once owned by the producer Dino De Laurentiis. It will soon host attractions – based on films such as Ben-Hur and Gangs of New York – designed by the Oscar-winning set designer Dante Ferretti.</p>
<p>Sperandini said the studio was still keeping faith in film by investing in new sets and production suites.</p>
<p>"What has hit hard are the incentives offered by countries like Hungary, which made them around 25% cheaper," he said.</p>
<p>"But now Italy has confirmed tax incentives for the next three years which should level the playing field. And we've got the weather. Woody Allen will be shooting in Rome in June and we really hope he will use us."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>