<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2011-11-08" description="Editorial: One way to grasp the difference between the Italian and Greek situations is to imagine that by some miracle Italy and Greece could exchange their prime ministers" fingerprint="2784812fd120df05" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Eurozone crisis,World news,Italy,Europe,European banks,Business" title="Italy: Berlusconi at bay | Editorial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/08/silvio-berlusconi-at-bay-editorial">
<main>
<p>One way to grasp the difference between the Italian and Greek situations is to imagine that by some miracle <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and Greece could exchange their prime ministers. The essence of the Greek crisis has been that a patently trustworthy, able and serious man found himself suddenly in charge of a deeply compromised economy but could not muster the resources or the support to deal with it. The essence of the Italian crisis is that a man whom nobody has fully trusted for years was in charge of an economy with both manifest strengths and some obvious but not crippling faults.</p>
<p>George Papandreou's departure from office will weaken Greece, but Silvio Berlusconi's fall, assuming it now occurs, will strengthen Italy. The rates on Italian debt, after all, went down on rumours of Berlusconi's resignation, and then up again when he initially rebutted them. When he confirmed that he would quit once his budget has been approved later this month, the euro quickly rallied against the dollar.</p>
<p>There can be no clearer indication that in Italy it is the man who is the immediate problem and not the country, whereas in Greece it has been the other way round. Italy's difficulties ultimately stem from one of the great lost opportunities of recent European history. When Italy's political system collapsed in the early 90s after investigative magistrates revealed the corrupt practices – including accommodations with the mafia – which had kept it going during the cold war years, there was a moment when there could have been a genuine new beginning.</p>
<p>A cleaner politics and a more responsible politics seemed to beckon. Europe expected it. Italians expected it. Instead, the gifted populist Berlusconi moved into the vacuum at the head of a party which he had conjured up overnight on the model of a football fan club. He has not always been in office since then, but he has nevertheless dominated the Italian scene for longer than many younger Italians can remember.</p>
<p>Leaving Berlusconi's personal faults aside, his most significant failure was that instead of countering the economic bad habits of the Italian past, he tended to accommodate himself to them. Projecting himself initially as a Thatcherite clean sweeper, he was nothing of the kind. The Italian economy, with its thousands of tax-evading little firms and its inefficient welfare state structures, and also with its considerable virtues, bumped along much as it had before.</p>
<p>Most, although not all, of what reforms there were came during the periods when Berlusconi was not in power. He did little to shore up Italy's declining competitiveness, nor did he reduce the large debt which Italy had begun to accumulate in the 70s. He did not create this debt and he did not greatly add to it.</p>
<p>Unlike Greece, Italy has not been borrowing to cover current spending. But he did not cut it, precisely because he did not reform revenue collection or reduce government spending to give himself the extra income to pay it down. It is this omission that has now come back to haunt him. Italians as individuals have low levels of debt, as do Italian businesses. Britain would be happy to have a middle band of family companies as varied as that which Italy still possesses, or some of the major corporations which Italy still boasts. The Italian economy is not a shipwreck. But the Italian ship of state needs a credible new captain. Unfortunately, there is no obvious charismatic choice. Throughout the Berlusconi years, an inadequate opposition has played into his hands. A figure from his own party, with Berlusconi still behind the scenes, would almost certainly fail to convince the markets An interim government of experts might briefly calm things down, but a new election would almost certainly do the opposite. Whether a better government can solve Italy's problems if it stays in the eurozone is the biggest question of all.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>