<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2009-11-24" description="Patrizia D'Addario explicitly claims for first time in book that she had sex with Italian PM Silvio Berlusconi" fingerprint="3bbac22c976fd7cd" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi is sexual record-breaker, says prostitute" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/nov/24/berlusconi-sex-record-breaker-prostitute">
<main>
<p>The Italian prostitute at the centre of a sex scandal involving <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has explicitly claimed for the first time that she had sex with the Italian prime minister.</p>
<p>Since first alleging she spent a night last November at Berlusconi's Rome residence, Patrizia D'Addario has limited herself to saying she shared a bed with the 73-year-old prime minister. But in Gradisca, Presidente ‑ Take Your Pleasure, Prime Minister ‑ D'Addario writes: "He told me he wanted contact with my skin, he held me tight, he took my breath away. I took him inside me, he suffocated me with kisses."</p>
<p>"This is the first time she has really made it clear that they had sex," said Maddalena Tulanti, an Italian journalist who co-wrote the book with D'Addario.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied paying for sex or knowing that Giampaolo Tarantini, the businessman who says he introduced Berlusconi to D'Addario, had offered her and other women money to spend the night at Berlusconi's residence. Tarantini is being investigated for aiding and abetting prostitution. Berlusconi is not under investigation.</p>
<p>D'Addario writes: "We kissed an infinite number of times, with him above all kissing my intimate parts," a performance for which "he could get into the Guinness Book of Records". When D'Addario admitted she was struggling to enjoy the moment, Berlusconi "took it like a challenge", keeping her up until 8am, when he left to speak to journalists.</p>
<p>"I am much younger than him, and quite an expert, I must say," she writes. "But there were moments when I feared I would not stand up to his assaults. Does he take something? I have asked myself many times." The only substance she claims Berlusconi had on hand was "disgustingly sweet" herbal tea.</p>
<p>D'Addario claims she secretly tape- recorded the occasion and went public after Berlusconi failed to make good on promises to help her obtain permits for a building project near Bari in southern <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. In the book, D'Addario describes her early life and drift into prostitution, stating: "The clients increased, I became more than an escort, a real whore."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>