<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2008-01-27" description="Controversial tycoon demands snap elections after the squabbles that brought down Prodi - and proposes a 'very British' 10-point plan" fingerprint="277b92c59687874d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi models his comeback on Blair" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jan/27/italy.tomkington">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi has put a very British stamp on his comeback campaign, promising to govern for three years, if elected, with a pragmatic rather than ideological approach modelled on Tony Blair - before handing over to an 'Italian Gordon Brown'.</p>
<p>'Berlusconi will propose a very simple, very pragmatic and very British eight-to-ten-point plan, similar in style to Tony Blair, whose achievements Berlusconi really admires and with whom he always had an excellent relationship,' his spokesman, Paolo Bonaiuti, told The Observer yesterday.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, 71, made his first election speech in Naples on Friday, following the collapse of Romano Prodi's fractious centre-left administration after 20 months following a walkout by key allies in the Senate.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has found a second wind since having minor heart surgery, and polls tip the media tycoon to form his third government. By demanding snap elections in April, he is defying President Giorgio Napolitano, who will hold meetings with political leaders until Tuesday to seek consensus for a caretaker government able to reform Italy's unwieldy electoral system.</p>
<p>An electoral law passed by Berlusconi's government in 2005 handed more influence to smaller parties in parliament, where 39 factions were crammed on to the benches of the lower house and senate by last week. Prodi's likely successor as centre-left leader, Rome mayor Walter Veltroni, is calling for an overhaul of the system, as is Luca Cordero di Montezemolo, the influential head of Italy's employers' confederation.</p>
<p>While Prodi was hamstrung by the squabbles of his smaller allies, Berlusconi benefited. He was joined in Naples by Senator Sergio de Gregorio, who was elected on the Prodi ticket in 2006, then formed a tiny party, Italians in the World, and jumped to the centre-right.</p>
<p>Following the popping of champagne corks in the Senate on Thursday as Prodi lost his final confidence vote, Bonaiuti said Berlusconi's triumphalism would now be toned down in tune with his 'Blairite' approach. 'We will go ahead in the British way, calmly, with possible requests for co-operation with the opposition on some difficult issues,' he said. One issue is likely to be the resolution of the Naples rubbish crisis, which has left streets piled with garbage.</p>
<p>Berlusconi said his priorities were to ban property tax and introduce a five-year jail term for prosecutors using wiretaps in cases not related to Mafia or terrorist crimes. Newspaper editors publishing leaked transcripts of wiretaps would be fined €2m, he added. This month a Naples prosecutor requested Berlusconi stand trial after he was recorded on the phone to a senior figure at state broadcaster RAI, allegedly promising to back a business venture if five actresses he listed were given roles.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has been the target of numerous corruption probes that have ended in acquittal or reached the statute of limitations. He has always denied wrongdoing.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>