<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-12-14" description="Prime minister scrapes through vote in Italian lower house by three votes as thousands protest on the streets of Rome" fingerprint="b7a995ba91038f15" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi survives second no-confidence vote" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/dec/14/silvio-berlusconi-survives-confidence-vote1">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's rightwing government has survived a second of two votes of confidence in the Italian parliament, beating off a censure motion in the lower house by three votes. The chamber of deputies voted against the resolution amid tumultuous scenes inside and outside the house.</p>
<p>As Berlusconi loyalists and rebels brawled in parliament, tens of thousands of anti-government demonstrators poured through the centre of Rome, some brandishing flares and setting off huge firecrackers that rocked the city as they exploded.</p>
<p>The vote – 314 to 311 – was greeted with scenes of wild jubilation by the prime minister's followers who waved Italian flags and shouted in chorus for his former ally Gianfranco Fini to resign his position as speaker of the house. Fini led the rebellion against the governing majority that brought it to the brink of collapse.</p>
<p>The opposition, joined by Fini's mutineers, failed in their bid to unseat the prime minister despite the efforts of three women deputies in the last stages of pregnancy who turned up to cast their votes against the government. One, Giulia Cosenza, arrived in an ambulance. Another, Giulia Bongiorno, was helped into the chamber in a wheelchair.</p>
<p>The third deputy, Federica Mogherini of the Democratic party, Italy's biggest opposition group, who is nine months pregnant, won a round of applause from her colleagues after fulfilling a promise to get to parliament "unless my water breaks".</p>
<p>Adding to the tension on a day of high drama, riot police were out in force as the demonstrators headed for the centre of Rome to register their own protests against the economic crisis and Berlusconi's government.</p>
<p>Police vans ringed the prime minister's official residence and blocked the street in front of his private home. Surveillance helicopters clattered overhead.</p>
<p>During the ballot in the lower house there was a scuffle between members of Fini's faction and deputies belonging to the Northern League after a member of Fini's faction switched her vote to the government. Four members of the lower chamber had to be separated after one of them apparently called the defecting politician a "whore".</p>
<p>The prime minister and most of his followers had earlier walked out of the lower house in the final stages of the debate in protest at the heated rhetoric of Berlusconi's most implacable enemy, the leader of the Italy of Principles party, Antonio Di Pietro.</p>
<p>"We have a prime minister derided and ridiculed abroad," said Di Pietro who went on to allege that Berlusconi had "bought opposition deputies to assure himself of a majority". Two politicians from the Italy of Principles party switched their votes in the runup to the ballot, prompting opposition claims of foul play.</p>
<p>Earlier, Berlusconi survived a confidence vote in the senate, the upper house of the Italian parliament. His coalition won comfortably, by 162 votes to 135. But its path was smoothed by the rebel group loyal to Fini, which opted for tactical abstention, and by four opposition members who unexpectedly switched their votes at the last minute.</p>
<p>A senator who did so was promptly expelled by his party, the Sicilian-based Movement for Autonomies. His whip accused him of "one of the most squalid examples of this buying and selling [of votes] that has turned parliament into a sort of cattle market".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>