<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2004-07-13" description="Italy's billionaire prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, was battling to stay in power yesterday as he faced the threat of mutiny within his coalition over his conflict of interests, his attempt to take personal control of the nation's finances and his plans for government reform." fingerprint="5fc0cfeff727ce2f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi losing grip on coalition" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jul/13/italy.sophiearie">
<main>
<p>Italy's billionaire prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, was battling to stay in power yesterday as he faced the threat of mutiny within his coalition over his conflict of interests, his attempt to take personal control of the nation's finances and his plans for government reform.</p>
<p>As members of his House of Liberties coalition went into a second night of survival talks last night, reports said Gianfranco Fini, leader of the second largest coalition party, the Alleanza Nazionale (National Alliance), could be appointed economy minister.</p>
<p>The move would be a victory for Mr Fini, currently vice-prime minister, who has jostled for more power for his party since its success in recent European and local elections. For Mr Berlusconi it would be a peace-making compromise that could yet cause problems as Mr Fini's views on tax cutting conflict with other coalition parties.</p>
<p>In talks late on Sunday night, Mr Berlusconi, struggling to rein in his fractious coalition allies, reportedly threatened to turn his Mediaset television channels against the leader of the Democratic Union of the Centre, Marco Follini, the latest ally to speak of abandoning the coalition.</p>
<p>"You want to weaken my leadership in the country without understanding that without me you won't be here either," Mr Berlusconi told Mr Follini, his most junior ally, according to La Repubblica.</p>
<p>"The truth is that on Mediaset no one ever attacks you," he said. "But if you carry on like this, you'll see."</p>
<p>"We've reached the limit," said the opposition Democrats of the Left in a statement, outraged by the threat. "Berlusconi has not resolved the conflict of interests, the country is going through a serious crisis, the economy is standing still. And now he threatens to use his television against his allies. We need a change of government."</p>
<p>Mr Follini has said his party would leave the coalition unless a new economy minister was named by tomorrow. Mr Berlusconi has been filling the job himself since Giulio Tremonti resigned on July 3 and has indicated he intends to carry on until Christmas.</p>
<p>But Mr Follini says it is unacceptable for Mr Berlusconi to control the economy ministry, which owns Rai, the state broadcaster. As prime minister, Mr Berlusconi influences appointments and programming at the Rai.</p>
<p>If the UDC withdraws its support another coalition partner, the Northern League, has threatened to follow suit. This would trigger the collapse of Mr Berlusconi's government and early elections would be called.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi has appeared increasingly cornered by his allies over the past fortnight. His centre-right Forza Italia party lost support in recent European and local elections while his coalition partners all gained. He is supposed to stay in office for almost two more years, but analysts say his chances of holding his coalition together for that long are slim.</p>
<p>While fighting to appease his allies, Mr Berlusconi is also under pressure to get Italy's economy back on track after it escaped an "early warning" last week from the EU for overspending.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who promised an economic miracle to Italians three years ago, has acknowledged that if elections were called now his party would lose.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>