<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-05-17" description="Italian prime minister offers world leaders accommodation in city devastated by earthquake in keeping with frugal times" fingerprint="7e62991ce61bf0a9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="G8,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Barack Obama,World news,Global economy,Business,Europe,Earthquakes" title="It's a barracks for Obama, and the rest of G8, says Silvio Berlusconi" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/17/g8-silvio-berlusconi-italy">
<main>
<p>As they jet from summit to summit, the leaders of the world's richest countries are used to having their stressful lives made that bit more tolerable by five-star accommodation and all that goes with it: braided lackeys and gourmet cuisine, not to mention downy pillows and complimentary bath salts.</p>
<p>But for the G8 meeting in July their host, Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, has lined up something bracingly different. A source close to the summit's organisers confirmed to the Guardian today that the plan was to house Presidents Obama, Sarkozy and Medvedev, and Gordon Brown, Angela Merkel and other government chiefs in the two buildings pictured above.</p>
<p>"Everything is ongoing. But that is the idea", said the source. If the buildings look rather more like police officers' married quarters than a luxury hotel, it is because that is what they are.</p>
<p>Berlusconi astonished his guests last month by switching the venue of the summit from the picturesque Mediterranean island of La Maddalena to the city of L'Aquila, which was hit by a devastating earthquake last month which left 295 people dead. The idea was to attract funds to the area's reconstruction, and at the same time stage an event more in keeping with the frugal spirit of the times.</p>
<p>When Berlusconi does something, he rarely does it by halves. The delegates, who were to have stayed on luxury cruise liners in the azure waters off Sardinia, are now being offered two nights in a barracks instead.</p>
<p>With the area still suffering aftershocks, the historic centre of L'Aquila is unsafe. One of its hotels is more horizontal than vertical.</p>
<p>But a large complex outside the city belonging to Italy's militarised revenue guard was undamaged in the earthquake, and it is there the Italian government is to hold the summit. It had been expected the delegation leaders would stay in Rome and fly up by helicopter. Some may do so.</p>
<p>But, with their economies in recession, none will be blind to the political risks of lavishing taxpayers' cash on a Via Veneto five-star, when they could be staying for free outside L'Aquila.</p>
<p>"There will be everything the leaders need," said a senior official. "But whereas the accommodation at La Maddalena would have been beautiful, at L'Aquila it will be totally sober and — do you have the word in English? — <hi rend="#i">spartano</hi>."</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>