<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Barbara McMahon" categories="World news" date="2006-03-27" description="Italians are being wooed by their flamboyant prime minister Silvio Berlusconi, who is mailing a glossy magazine detailing his government's achievements to millions of households." fingerprint="7288d3649b63f79f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi posts 11m free magazines to gloss over flaws" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/mar/28/italy.mainsection">
<main>
<p>Italians are being wooed by their flamboyant prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who is mailing a glossy magazine detailing his government's achievements to millions of households this week.</p>
<p>The 160-page publication, called The Real Italian Story, is crammed with flattering facts and photographs of the 69-year-old billionaire, proclaiming his five-year term of office a success story.</p>
<p>Throwing modesty to the wind, it portrays the permatanned premier as an important world leader, standing alongside the likes of US president George Bush, Russian president Vladimir Putin, and Tony Blair.</p>
<p>He is also shown hugging famous acquaintances such as rock star Bono and the motorcycling champion Valentino Rossi, as well as paying respectful homage to the late Pope John Paul II.</p>
<p>The media magnate has spared no expense in producing the magazine, which he hopes will win over undecided voters ahead of a general election on April 9-10. It is being sent to 11m households.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi took a similar initiative in 2001, sending a 125-page biography of himself to voters, after which he conquered the polls and swept to power. This time he is trailing behind the centre-left challenger Romano Prodi, according to most opinion polls.</p>
<p>"The ego has landed - again," remarked one political commentator in the daily newspaper La Stampa.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi courted further controversy yesterday when he declared: "We don't want <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to become a multiethnic, multicultural country. We are proud of our traditions."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>