<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Opinion" date="2008-01-25" description="John Hooper: The former prime minister of Italy wants fresh elections ... because they would probably bring him back to power" fingerprint="a3fddb61d005de4a" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Is Berlusconi right?" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/jan/25/isberlusconiright">
<main>
<p>Now that Romano Prodi's centre-left government <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/italy/story/0,,2246606,00.html">has fallen</ref>, political debate in Italy is moving on swiftly to new terrain. The issue at the centre of the <ref target="http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id=1&amp;click_id=3&amp;art_id=nw20080125134922718C246931">talks</ref> begun by President Giorgio Napolitano is this: should he appoint an interim "technical" government or call fresh elections?</p>
<p>The right, led by <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silvio_Berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, wants to go back to the country. The first reason could not be simpler: it is way ahead in the polls. The second is subtler.</p>
<p>The job of a stop-gap administration would be to change <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Italy#New_electoral_system_.282005-.29">an electoral law</ref> passed by the last Berlusconi government just before it was voted out of office in 2006. This law is close to proportional representation in its purest form and critics argue it makes the country ungovernable by ensuring space in parliament for even the tiniest of parties (known in Italian by the delightful term "partitini"). Any reform would aim to put the country back on the road towards a two-party system, or perhaps a four-party one like Germany's.</p>
<p>Assuming that reform was inevitable, the centre-left took a giant stride towards creating an all-embracing movement, the <ref target="http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5iJgxTPLO8A4ALrle9SUxqf_vDDLQ">Democratic Party</ref>, which came into existence last autumn. Berlusconi's efforts to achieve the same result have failed. None of the three groups in the alliance with which he won the last election was willing to merge in a party led by him, or rather his protégée, a flame-haired former beauty queen, <ref target="http://www.michelavittoriabrambilla.it/">Michela Vittoria Brambilla</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/7f9d5746-c925-11dc-9807-000077b07658.html">The argument</ref> for an interim government was set out recently in the Financial Times. The logic is formidable. Even the man who drew up the existing electoral law for Berlusconi later called it a "load of rubbish". It should be changed. A grey cabinet of non-party technocrats and/or mutually acceptable politicians from across the ideological spectrum would doubtless do other sensible things that would be good for Italy. And - a matter of no small concern to the FT - it would reassure markets.</p>
<p>There is one snag: parliamentary democracy. As of Thursday night, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> has a hung parliament. Prodi won a confidence vote in the Chamber of Deputies and lost a confidence vote in the Senate. It is hard to think of a better reason for going back to the country and asking the electorate to give a new verdict.</p>
<p>Part of the difficulty for the FT, and no doubt for most Guardian Unlimited readers, is that to do so would probably mean letting back into a power a man whose concept of democracy is, at best, debatable. He saw nothing wrong with effectively monopolising Italian television when he was prime minister and has never formally conceded his defeat in the last election. His opponents argue that Berlusconi, rather like the Islamists in places like Algeria, only uses democracy when it suits him. But, on this occasion, they are laying themselves open to precisely the same objection.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>