<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2004-01-30" description="Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, who reappeared last week after uncharacteristically dodging the limelight for almost a month, said his wife had talked him into having cosmetic surgery during his absence." fingerprint="ffa8d238b3e3a50d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Life and style,Europe,Cosmetic surgery" title="Wife talked Berlusconi into surgery" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jan/30/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, who reappeared last week after uncharacteristically dodging the limelight for almost a month, said his wife, the former actress Veronica Lario, had talked him into having cosmetic surgery during his absence.</p>
<p>"It was she who urged me to do it," Mr Berlusconi told journalists accompanying a group of fashion designers who visited him at his official residence in Rome on Wednesday.</p>
<p>His account cast doubt on reports that the two are estranged. Equally surprisingly, Italy's image-conscious prime minister said he had "only had his eyelids redone".</p>
<p>How Mr Berlusconi, 67, lost most of his wrinkles, regained discernibly more prominent cheekbones and strikingly taut facial skin must, for the moment, remain a mystery. But he said that, at the start of December, he had gone on a strict diet and shed 11kg.</p>
<p>"For 15 days I ate no bread, pasta, rice, puddings or alcohol. Then I halved [the normal intake]," Mr Berlusconi said. "I've gone back to wearing clothes from 1992."</p>
<p>According to a report last week in the news magazine L'Espresso, Mr Berlusconi underwent extensive plastic surgery at the end of December in the Ars Medica clinic at Gravesano in the Italian-speaking part of Switzerland. The magazine said the operation was carried out by a surgeon from San Francisco.</p>
<p>Asked if he was vain, Mr Berlusconi replied: "I merely strive to be agreeable."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>