<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Business" date="2011-08-12" description="Silvio Berlusconi faces anger from all sides over cuts to meetultimatum from the European Central Bank" fingerprint="5ec788b498b3f9a9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Italy,Europe,European Central Bank,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Italy's government meets to approve new austerity package" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/aug/12/berlusconi-italy-austerity-cuts-protest">
<main>
<p>Amid howls of protest from supporters and opponents alike, Silvio Berlusconi's cabinet was meeting tonight to approve a new austerity package – the second his conservative government has imposed on Italy in less than a month.</p>
<p>The measures – aimed at meeting an ultimatum from the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/european-central-bank">European Central Bank</ref> – appeared to rip away two central planks of his government programme, leaving the eternally resilient prime minister vulnerable. After details of the package leaked out, the rightwing newspaper Libero headlined its front page: "Betrayal! Dammit, they're raising taxes."</p>
<p>Berlusconi said that, to meet the ECB's target of eliminating the budget deficit by 2013, his government would make additional fiscal adjustments worth €20bn (£17.5bn) in 2012 and €25bn in 2013. The tax increases and spending cuts will be enacted immediately by decree, but subject to approval by parliament later.</p>
<p>Among the measures were an increase to 20% in capital gains tax on investments other than government bonds and an income tax surcharge of 5%-10% on incomes of more than €90,000 a year. That alone appalled many supporters of a leader who has long promised that he would "never put their hands in the pockets of the Italian people".</p>
<p>But there was also criticism from local authority leaders, hit by yet more cuts. They included previously loyal members of Berlusconi's party like the mayor of Rome, Gianni Alemanno, and the governor of Lombardy, Roberto Formigoni.</p>
<p>Alemanno said the additional cuts were "not acceptable". And Formigoni hit a nerve when he told reporters: "It seems clear [fiscal] federalism has vanished."</p>
<p>Fiscal federalism, or giving the regions more control over their finances, is the pet policy of the Northern League, and, for some members, the only reason it stays in Berlusconi's scandal-beset coalition. Its leader, Umberto Bossi, hastily contradicted Formigoni, but he himself is also unhappy about parts of the package that would erode pensions.</p>
<p>Among measures reportedly under discussion was one that would bring forward to 2012 a mechanism to tie the level of old age pensions to life expectancy. Tighter budgets and structural reforms were demanded by the ECB last week as the price of intervening on the markets to contain Italy's soaring borrowing costs.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>