<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Oliver Burkeman" categories="World news" date="2006-02-14" description="Oliver Burkeman: Silvio Berlusconi, the avuncular megalomaniac who personally owns every physical object in Italy, is in trouble again, this time for comparing himself to the son of God." fingerprint="7d6b404b83a7030d" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Religion,World news,UK news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Oliver Burkeman: Silvio Berlusconi is not Jesus Christ" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/feb/14/italy.religion">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi, the avuncular megalomaniac who personally owns every physical object in Italy, is in trouble again, this time for comparing himself to the son of God. "I am the Jesus Christ of politics," he told supporters at an election campaign dinner in Rome. "I am a patient victim. I put up with everyone. I sacrifice myself for everyone."</p>
<p>Pernickety theologians will notice some immediate problems with the analogy. Are we talking sacrifice as in "enduring agonising crucifixion", for example, or sacrifice as in "owning three television stations, a leading football team, and an amount of money so large that you can't express it in lira"? But there's another, more pressing question: when are people in public life going to learn that comparing yourself to Jesus is never, ever, a good idea?</p>
<p>Last month it was former Verve frontman Richard Ashcroft; a few months before that it was former Iraq frontman Saddam Hussein. This month it's the Italian prime minister, and also the hip-hop artist Kanye West, which means that it has happened four times recently, that it therefore constitutes a Worrying Trend, and that it's time to call for an immediate halt.</p>
<p>This isn't about being respectful to the Christian faith. On the contrary, it's the secular democrat's duty to expose religious ideas to mockery, and I for one can think of few more fulfilling ways to spend a spare afternoon than laughing at a church or teasing a vicar. But whatever your views on organised religion, it's impossible to deny that Jesus was really quite good, and so it follows that the comparison is almost never going to flatter the other person involved.</p>
<p>John Lennon's 1966 claim that the Beatles were "more popular than Jesus" is clearly the main historical antecedent here. Really, though, that was just an overblown claim about relative fan-base size; present-day Christ-comparing reaches much further and deeper. "I love the man, I feel like him," was how Ashcroft put it. "There's only Richard Ashcroft and Liam Gallagher who know what it feels like. We're the only ones who know how many people we've touched, and how powerful that is."</p>
<p>(This, incidentally, is a doubly ridiculous example of the genre. Note not only Ashcroft's monumental self-belief, but also his apparent conviction that the only other person worthy of admission to the blessed circle is the man responsible for singing Roll With It.)</p>
<p>At the very least, we ought to insist on a bit more diversity when it comes to self-aggrandising comparisons. What about the figureheads of other world religions? Or even good old God, who bizarrely doesn't seem to get much of a look-in? But no: it's Jesus every time - the same way that people who believe in reincarnation were always Mary Queen of Scots in a former life, and the way that stereotypically mad people in sitcoms and novels always believe they're Napoleon.</p>
<p>In fact, Berlusconi had compared himself to Napoleon, the day before he compared himself to Christ. Opposition politicians heaped voluminous abuse on him for that, too, but he bore it good-humouredly, reflecting, no doubt, that we all have our cross to bear.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>