<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Lizzy Davies" categories="World news" date="2013-02-08" description="Silvio Berlusconi's brother condemns media outrage over racial slur and claims he has made peace with AC Milan striker" fingerprint="f5a8822d92a78fd3" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Race,Mario Balotelli,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Football,Europe" title="Paolo Berlusconi: I was being affectionate towards Mario Balotelli" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/08/paolo-berlusconi-affectionate-mario-balotelli">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's brother has insisted he was being "affectionate" towards Mario Balotelli when he used a racial slur to describe the Italian footballer, condemning instead "stupid" media coverage for suggesting he had done something wrong.</p>
<p>Paolo Berlusconi, the younger brother of the former prime minister, who is running again in the country's election this month, sparked anger around the world this week when a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/feb/06/berlusconi-brother-fury-balotelli-remark">film</ref> of him referring to Balotelli as a "<hi rend="#i">negretto</hi>" – "little black boy" or "little Negro" – went viral.</p>
<p>"And now let's go and watch the little Negro of the family, the hothead," said Berlusconi, who, as well as being a businessman and owner of daily newspaper Il Giornale, is vice-president of AC Milan, his brother's football club.</p>
<p>He was speaking on Sunday before the former Manchester City star played his first match for the club since returning to <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. The comment provoked considerably more outrage and media coverage internationally than in Italy.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Paolo Berlusconi, 63, said he had since discussed the matter with the footballer and would be saying no more about it. "I have spoken with Balotelli but in truth there was no need seeing as he's an intelligent boy," he told Milan Channel, AC Milan's official club channel.</p>
<p>"He had already understood that what I said was an affectionate expression that led to a stupid media circus. Let's be done with this affair; Mario told me there was no need to say anything else."</p>
<p>As if to reinforce the statement, the club, which has not commented<hi rend="#b"/>on the controversy, released a <ref target="http://www.acmilan.com/en/news/show_gallery/815">photograph</ref> of the two men smiling together at the Milanello sports centre.</p>
<p>Balotelli, 22, who has been in the country for little more than a week, has been at the centre of several controversies. First of all, opponents of Silvio Berlusconi questioned his motives for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jan/30/balotelli-berlusconi-ac-milan-signing">bringing back the striker</ref> in the midst of an election campaign in which the three-times prime minister is attempting to make a comeback.</p>
<p>Then came the row over the other Berlusconi's remark. And on Thursday AC Milan was forced to deny the player had been involved in an argument with traffic police when picking up his girlfriend from the airport. The club confirmed, however, that Balotelli, who while in the UK earned a reputation for picking up parking fines, was given his first Italian ticket.</p>
<p>"Mario Balotelli was given a parking ticket today at Linate airport in Milan," the club's statement said. "Contrary to what has been reported by some sources, there was no argument between the parties and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/mario-balotelli">Mario Balotelli</ref> showed up as usual for training at the Milanello sports centre."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>