<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Associated Press; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2011-01-25" description="Italian PM phones live TV show to criticise its 'despicable, vile and repugnant' conduct and is branded a 'lout' by host" fingerprint="5cfa8a6514c7e209" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi trades insults with talkshow host" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/25/silvio-berlusconi-insults-tv-talkshow">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi phoned in to a TV talkshow about the prostitution investigation against him, trading insults with the host and calling the programme a "brothel".</p>
<p>It is not the first time the Italian PM has called a live TV show to complain, but his comments last night were harsher than usual. "I've been watching a disgusting show, conducted in a despicable, vile and repugnant way," Berlusconi said.</p>
<p>The host, Gad Lerner, a left-leaning journalist, invited him to tone down his comments and at one point called him a "lout" when Berlusconi made a swipe against the show's female guests.</p>
<p>"Why don't you go before the magistrates instead of insulting people?" Lerner asked.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has refused to heed a summons by Milan prosecutors who have placed him is under investigation on suspicion he paid for sex with a 17-year-old girl and used his office to cover it up.</p>
<p>The 74-year-old has denied wrongdoing, saying he never paid for sex. He insists he is the victim of politically driven magistrates who want to oust him from power.</p>
<p>"The reality that has been represented here is the opposite of the truth and I feel insulted," Berlusconi said on the show. "I know what I'm saying, you don't," he told Lerner. He urged a political ally in the studio to leave this "incredible TV brothel".</p>
<p>The show was broadcast on La7, a private station that is one of the few national channels over which Berlusconi has no control. He owns Mediaset, the country's largest private broadcaster, and as prime minister indirectly controls the state-run RAI.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>