<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Sophie Arie" categories="World news" date="2004-09-22" description="Silvio Berlusconi suggested yesterday that he might retire from politics in the future because of his age, and indicated the head of Fiat as his possible successor." fingerprint="8f9ad11bb4b2d705" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi tips wink to Fiat chief" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/sep/22/italy.sophiearie">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi suggested yesterday that he might retire from politics in the future because of his age, and indicated the head of Fiat as his possible successor.</p>
<p>With a jovial grin he said that his job would at some point be available to Luca Cordero de Montezemolo, a former head of Ferrari, who became chairman of Fiat and president of the employers' body Confindustria earlier this year.</p>
<p>"Little old men should have the grace to retire at the right moment," the Italian prime minister joked at a shipping industry meeting in Genoa, Corriere della Sera reported.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi, who turns 68 at the end of this month, has aged visibly during his three years in government, despite having had plastic surgery and, it is reported, a hair transplant earlier this year.</p>
<p>He said he would not hesitate to stand down when he knew he was no longer up to the job.</p>
<p>It is the first time that he has suggested anyone could take over his job. Elected in 2001, his government became Italy's longest-serving post-war administration earlier this year, and he has repeatedly said he intends to serve a second term after elections in 2006.</p>
<p>Without criticising him, Mr Montezemolo has hinted recently that Italy's struggling economy ought to be made a higher government priority.</p>
<p>Mr Montezemolo rose in industry as a protege of the Fiat Agnelli family, running Ferrari and Maserati before being nominated president of Confindustria, Italy's most influential business lobby, in May. A few days later he was named head of Fiat after the unexpected death of its chairman, Umberto Agnelli.</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi tried to bring him into his government as industry minister in 2001 but was turned down.</p>
<p>The prime minister, who has stood firmly by the US and Britain in Iraq, was greeted by raucous anti-war protests on his arrival in Genoa.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>