<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="David Hills" categories="Football" date="2013-01-12" description="The week in football – Chelsea's big impact, masseur of the week, plus what makes the Guardian satanic" fingerprint="9c05d10b29c98783" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Chelsea,Birmingham City,Fifa,Silvio Berlusconi,Football,Sport,Football politics" title="Said &amp; Done: Chelsea, Berlusconi, plus what makes the Guardian satanic" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2013/jan/12/said-and-done-chelsea-berlusconi">
<main>
<head rend="h2">Healing power: club of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Chelsea </hi>– making a social difference this winter by: <hi rend="#b">a) </hi>Auctioning two tickets and a shirt for charity, helping to use "the power of football … to raise money for vulnerable communities". <ref target="http://www.chelseafc.com/foundation-article/article/3009983/title/chelsea-foundation-teams-up-with-viagogo">John Terry</ref>: "It really will make a massive difference." <hi rend="#b">b) </hi>Paying 0% tax on their £1.4m profit. Club accounts show offsetting profits against historic £600m losses will keep the club corporation tax-free for decades.</p>
<p> Also from the accounts, released last week: <hi rend="#b">£481,468 </hi>– Chelsea's spending on wages, per day.</p>
<head rend="h2">Campaigner of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Silvio Berlusconi</hi>: renewing his attack on the "uncivilised, heinous" racists who targeted his Milan players at Pro Patria on 3 January, and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/feedarticle/10600302">renewing his political ties</ref> with the hard-right Northern League, days after their councillor Riccardo Grittini resigned over his alleged part in the chanting. Grittini denies wrongdoing.</p>
<p> Also from the ongoing Pro Patria fallout: local mayor and Northern League politician <hi rend="#b">Antonio Balzarotti </hi>giving a telephone interview on the subject, in which he condemned the racist chanting. After the interview, Balzarotti forgot to hang up and <ref target="http://www.blitzquotidiano.it/blitztv/antonio-balzarotti-boateng-dire-buu-a-un-negher-un-reato-video-1441615/">was recorded asking a colleague incredulously</ref>: "So now it's a crime to boo a black?"</p>
<head rend="h2">Football family: man of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">2012: </hi>Fifa executive <hi rend="#b">Ricardo Teixeira</hi> resigns after 23 years of denying "pathetic" press corruption allegations, two months before it emerged in court that he had taken "at least" £8.4m in bribes.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">2013: </hi>Starts receiving his Fifa pension – a reported £20,000 a year. Brazilian paper <hi rend="#i">O Estado de S. Paulo</hi><hi rend="#i"/>says the sum will "top up" his £35,000-a-month "consultancy fee" from Brazil's FA.</p>
<head rend="h2">Financial fair play news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">4: </hi>Months between Uefa confirming all top clubs have signed up to the spirit of the new financial fair play rules, and the Qatar-owned <hi rend="#b">PSG </hi>signing a £570m sponsorship deal with Qatar's tourist board. PSG's Nasser al-Khelaifi says they need the money for transfers to stay competitive. "Why must we stop pouring in money? It would be unfair."</p>
<head rend="h2">Hard times</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">December: </hi>Birmingham director Peter Pannu reveals the club has to cut nonessential costs to avoid administration, with player sales likely to "maintain the cash flow".</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">January: </hi><ref target="http://www.birminghammail.co.uk/news/local-news/birmingham-city-peter-pannu-paid-779356">Pannu tells the Birmingham Mail</ref><hi rend="#i"/>that the £687,611 shown as his salary in the club's new accounts was misleading – with only £250,000 for him, and the rest "pocket expenses" for his Hong-Kong based staff.</p>
<head rend="h2">Moving on</head>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Among January's exits so far:</hi>
</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Russia, 5 Jan: </hi>Kuban Krasnodar director Suren Mkrtchyan dismisses press talk about coach Yuri Krasnozhan – "I don't comment on rumours, only on facts, so I don't need to comment on this" – and says claims of an internal rift with Krasnozhan are "deserving of a psychiatrist". <hi rend="#b">8 Jan:</hi> Sacks him.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Portugal: 18 Dec: </hi>Sporting president Godinho Lopes attacks claims that his decision to hire Jesualdo Ferreira as a general manager means the end for coach Franky Vercauteren. "Of course not. They will blend together." Vercauteren: "I'm staying 200%. I spoke to the president and the message is clear: we're true to each other, and that's all that matters." <hi rend="#b">8 Jan: </hi>Vercauteren sacked; Ferreira takes over.</p>
<head rend="h2">One to watch</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Croatia: </hi>Dinamo Zagreb owner <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2007/oct/03/europeanfootball.sport">Zdravko Mamic</ref>: pledging a cooler 2013, with no more of his trademark threats to critics, including "I'll maul you, you donkeys" and "I'll beat you like cats": "So far I've been good, calm, backed off agitating situations. I'm serious. You'll see how mature I am."</p>
<head rend="h2">Ruse of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Brazil: </hi>Palmeiras officials, attending a ceremony with league sponsors General Motors, but "gracefully declining" their offer of a free Chevrolet Cruze out of respect to the club's own sponsors, rival car firm Kia. Local media: "However, when everyone had left, the officials returned discreetly to claim their gift – only to be discovered when they then crashed it into a Ford Fiesta in the car park." President Arnaldo Tirone: "We barely hit it, but everyone saw. It's distressing."</p>
<head rend="h2">Masseur of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Brazil: </hi>Santos youth-team masseur Biro-Biro says his <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EK951G_wCKs">solo pitch invasion</ref> after being sent to the stands for abusing a referee was a "cause of regret". Reports say Biro-Biro "raised eyebrows among the boys" by running on to the pitch carrying two balls, kicking one into his own team's net, then "glaring". Biro-Biro: "We were all unbalanced that day."</p>
<head rend="h2">Plus: endorsement of the week</head>
<p>Steaua owner, MP and ex-MEP <hi rend="#b">Gigi Becali</hi>, <ref target="http://www.rtv.net/becali-a-ajuns-din-nou-de-rasul-englezilor-de-la-the-guardian-video_60623.html">asked by Romania TV </ref>about his appearances in Said &amp; Done: "God inspires me to say what I say, the British have no idea. It's just some crazy Brits from the Guardian [who quote you] if you talk about sex, prostitutes, tits … They're a satanic newspaper. They ridicule all that's pure and holy."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>