<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2009-05-03" description="For Europe's longest suffering first lady a golden necklace was the last straw" fingerprint="2daf420f9982c5a3" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,World news,Europe" title="Silvio Berlusconi's wife announces divorce plans" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/03/silvio-veronica-berlusconi-divorce">
<main>
<p>For Europe's longest suffering first lady, it seems as if the golden necklace was the last straw.</p>
<p>"I am convinced that at this point it would be more dignified to stop here," said Veronica Lario todayas she announced she would divorce Silvio Berlusconi, the Italian prime minister. "I cannot stay with a man who frequents minors," she told La Repubblica.</p>
<p>The minor in question, aspiring TV presenter Noemi Letizia, was celebrating her 18th birthday last month in Naples when Berlusconi, who described himself as an old friend of her family, dropped by with the necklace for Letizia, who revealed she calls him "daddy".</p>
<p>Lario's first reaction to the incident was an angry letter to an Italian news agency pointing out her husband had forgotten to attend the 18th birthdays of his own children by her. For good measure, she also criticised his reported attempt to send a number of other young women to the European parliament, calling it "shameless rubbish" and entertainment fit for "an emperor".</p>
<p>Today she confirmed was talking to a lawyer about winding up her marriage to the man who has made flirtatiousness his trademark and injected the sexual politics of a Carry On film into Italian public life.</p>
<p>It has been a tormented few years for the former actor, real name Miriam Bartolini, who was first courted by Berlusconi after he saw her perform topless in a Milan theatre production in 1980.</p>
<p>At the time Berlusconi was married to his first wife, Carla Dall'Oglio, with whom he had two children, Pier Silvio and Marina, now managers in his financial and media empire. By the time Veronica married him in 1990 she had given him three children.</p>
<p>Why she has decided to call it quits now has had <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> guessing. At 52, it is not too late for her to carve out a new life, perhaps hitting the road again after her recent trips abroad including a memorable voyage through Syria. Her youngest child Luigi is now 20, suggesting she may have waited for the nest to empty before clearing out herself.</p>
<p>Her surprise interviews about the divorce with two Italian newspapers also suggest she may have wanted to get the news out before Berlusconi, "a man capable of calling a press conference to say he had the idea first," wrote La Repubblica.</p>
<p>The announcement appeared to take Berlusconi by surprise. "It's a personal issue that pains me, that is in the private sphere, and which seems necessary not to speak about," he said.</p>
<p>But if he is concerned about the prospect of a scrap over his £6.3bn billion fortune, he may not need to worry. "I want to avoid a battle," Lario said yesterday.</p>
<p>Divorce would mark the culmination of a long bid for independence by Lario, who has rarely accompanied Berlusconi in public and has been putting political distance between them for years, starting with her opposition to the invasion of Iraq and her challenge to a Berlusconi-backed law limiting fertility treatments in Italy.</p>
<p>In 2003, Berlusconi famously acknowledged rumours linking her to the leftwing philosophy professor and mayor of Venice, Massimo Cacciari, telling reporters he wanted to introduce her to the Danish prime minister "because he's much more handsome than Cacciari".</p>
<p>No sooner had Berlusconi been re-elected last year, than Lario was dismissing his pet infrastructure project, a bridge linking Sicily to the mainland, as a bad idea. Berlusconi publicly asked Lario for forgiveness in 2007 after she wrote to an Italian newspaper complaining about his flirting with a TV presenter at an awards ceremony.</p>
<p>But following her outburst last week, Berlusconi did not back down, claiming Lario had been swayed by misleading press reports. Her comments also earned the wrath of rightwing newspaper Libero, which pointed out in an editorial she had no right to object to showgirls taking seats in the European parliament when she was once herself cavorting about topless on stage in Milan.</p>
<p>What is unclear is whether divorce will damage Berlusconi politically, as his popularity rises following his hands-on tackling of last month's Abruzzo earthquake. "In Italy people will tend to avoid such a subject, claiming it is the couples' business, but this question is a political one," said broadcaster Mario Adinolfi.</p>
<p>Walter Veltroni, a former opposition politician, once suggested Lario would make a fine opposition politician, but her biographer Maria Latella has suggested that her disgust at the 18th birthday incident in Naples shows she has lost patience with Italy.</p>
<p>"Reading between the lines, she seems to be saying that if this is a country where parents will do anything to get their daughter on TV, it is a country she wants little to do with," she said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>