<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2008-10-09" description="Comic claims former model's scantily-clad appearance in calendars makes her unsuitable for political role" fingerprint="5c18822d910acffe" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Comedy,Stage,Culture,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Showgirl-turned-minister sues comedian over Berlusconi joke" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/oct/10/italy-comedy">
<main>
<p>The war of words between Italy's most controversial female comedian and a topless model-turned minister for equal opportunities in Silvio Berlusconi's government looked set to become a courtroom battle yesterday, with €1m in damages at stake.</p>
<p>Sabina Guzzanti revealed that she is being sued by Mara Carfagna, the former model and TV showgirl, after joking that Carfagna, 32, got her job as minister by indulging in an explicit sexual act with Berlusconi.</p>
<p>Rumour has been rife in the Italian press about Carfagna's relationship with Berlusconi after the prime minister quipped in 2007: "If I was not already married I would have married her immediately."</p>
<p>The quip prompted Berlusconi's wife, Veronica, to demand an apology in a letter to an Italian newspaper, an apology her husband duly gave.</p>
<p>Rumours have suggested that wire-taps allegedly conducted in a separate inquiry by an Italian magistrate pointed to a relationship between Berlusconi and Carfagna. The Italian prime minister has denied the claims.</p>
<p>Guzzanti, 45, has long been a thorn in the prime minister's side, earning an unofficial boycott by Italian state television for her pains. She took aim at Carfagna during a leftwing rally in July, as well as criticising Pope Benedict, claiming: "In 20 years [the former Cardinal Joseph] Ratzinger will be dead and will end up in hell, tormented by queer demons - not passive ones, but very active ones."</p>
<p>Plans by magistrates to prosecute her for attacking the Pope were dropped, but Carfagna has been less forgiving, the comedian revealed on her blog yesterday.</p>
<p>However, the comic remained defiant, writing that Carfagna's scantily clad appearance in photographic calenders was enough to make her unsuitable for her new ministerial role.</p>
<p>"By putting Carfagna at the ministry for equal opportunities, Berlusconi has offended every Italian woman yet again, and in conclusive fashion."</p>
<p>Appearing on Italian television on Wednesday, the minister said the rumour-mongering about her and Berlusconi proved she was the victim of a sexist campaign. "If a woman builds a career she is suspected of having sought shortcuts and received favours while people believe that men who go far deserve it," she said.</p>
<p>She then hit back at Guzzanti, accusing her of being "mentally fragile".</p>
<p>Guzzanti said yesterday she would now consider counter-suing Carfagna for the statement.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>