<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2009-09-28" description="Public broadcaster RAI censured for airing interview with escort while prime minister once again causes controversy over remarks about Obamas" fingerprint="3f0cd38191059705" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Media,Television industry,Censorship,Europe" title="Berlusconi family newspaper urges Italians to boycott TV licence fee" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/sep/28/berlusconi-family-newspaper-television-licence">
<main>
<p>A Berlusconi family newspaper has advised Italians to stop paying their television licence fee to punish Italy's public television service for broadcasting an interview with an escort who allegedly spent the night with the prime minister.</p>
<p>Patrizia D'Addario's first appearance on Italian television, broadcast last Thursday by the current events show Annozero, drew 5.6 million viewers, but triggered the ire of the economic development minister, Claudio Scajola, who threatened sanctions against the RAI network for broadcasting "trash, shame, infamy and dirt".</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied paying for sex.</p>
<p>The Italian opposition leader Dario Franceschini called the threats against the state broadcaster an act of "censorship" and "intimidation".</p>
<p>On Sunday Il Giornale, a newspaper owned by Berlusconi's brother, Paolo, launched a front-page campaign against the licence fee, as did Libero, a pro-Berlusconi newspaper.</p>
<p>"If RAI is a public service it should be at the service of the public that pays the licence fee and not at the service of haughty preachers whose toxic stump speeches twist information for political ends," wrote Il Giornale's editor, Vittorio Feltri, today.</p>
<p>The newspaper printed a sample letter to send to the tax office to request removal from the register of licence payers. The consequence, the paper stated, could be a visit from tax inspectors to see if a television was on.</p>
<p>"Reading between the lines, it appears Il Giornale does not think anyone will actually show up to check," said Gianluca Di Ascenzo, vice-president of the consumer group Codacons. Licence fee evasion already runs at 30% in Italy.</p>
<p>Feltri was singled out by Berlusconi for applause at a political rally on Sunday, during which Berlusconi again found time to produce another joke about Barack Obama's "tan". He told supporters he was bringing greetings from the G20 meeting in the US from "What's his name? Some tanned guy. Ah, Barack Obama!" He added: "You won't believe it, but two of them went to the beach, because the wife is also tanned."</p>
<p>His previous remarks about the US president's skin colour appear not to have gone down well with Michelle Obama. In photographs taken at last week's G20 summit in Pittsburgh, she was seen greeting many leaders with a kiss, but holding out a formal hand when the time came to say hello to Berlusconi.</p>
<p>However, Berlusconi insisted at yesterday's rally that the relationship between Rome and Washington remained intact.</p>
<p>He delivered a backhanded compliment to the US president when referring to Obama's use of a teleprompter in speeches: "He's not reckless, like those of us who say what comes to mind. We all asked ourselves: 'Does he know what he's doing, or is he just someone who knows how to read well?'"</p>
<p>He added: "But he's all there, in a big way, and that should make us all happy and satisfied because we need the greatest democracy, the greatest country, to be in trustworthy hands."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>