<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2011-04-04" description="Italian prime minister denies claims his company Mediaset duped shareholders and evaded millions of euros in tax" fingerprint="7fa8c20edbe7479c" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,Tax avoidance,Corporate governance,Business,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi accused of tax fraud while in office" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/apr/04/silvio-berlusconi-accused-tax-fraud">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi dodged taxes while serving as head of the government to which they were owed, according to fresh charges laid against him.</p>
<p>Most of the allegations levelled at Italy's billionaire prime minister over the years have concerned his activities before entering politics or while in opposition. But a prosecutor told a court in Milan he was involved in a conspiracy to defraud the Italian treasury "even when he was prime minister".</p>
<p>Fabio de Pasquale called for Berlusconi to be put on trial for tax fraud and embezzlement.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has denied any wrongdoing.</p>
<p>De Pasquale said he had evidence to show the media tycoon-turned-conservative politician conspired with 11 others, including his son Pier Silvio, to evade millions of euros in tax between the end of the 1980s and 2008. He claimed shareholders in Berlusconi's Mediaset television empire were embezzled until at least 2006. But he told the judge: "As far as I know it could still be going on."</p>
<p>The case is one of four involving Italy's embattled prime minister, and the only one that has not yet come to trial. Berlusconi and his alleged accomplices were investigated on suspicion of using a subsidiary of Mediaset to buy TV film rights at inflated prices through an intermediary.</p>
<p>Prosecutors concluded that one effect was to cut Mediaset's profits, thereby artificially reducing its tax bill. They also claimed another was to deplete Mediaset's assets, and thus the wealth of its owners who include not only Berlusconi but other holders of his group's publicly quoted shares. The difference between the fair and actual cost of the rights was allegedly diverted to offshore companies under Berlusconi's control.</p>
<p>At the opening hearing on 28 March, he denied any direct involvement in the purchase of film rights and declared himself "the most accused person in history and in the universe". The judge is expected to hold at least two more hearings before deciding whether the accused should stand trial.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who was in Tunisia attempting to negotiate a deal on migration, did not attend the hearing. A senior government official announced the prime minister would also miss the opening on Wednesday of the most sensational of the three other cases in which he denies paying an underage prostitute and abusing his official position in an attempt to cover up his alleged offence.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>