<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Roberto Mancini" categories="Opinion" date="2009-06-10" description="Roberto Mancini: As Silvio Berlusconi sorts out his love life, the xenophobic, federalist Northern League is effectively running the country" fingerprint="33ca4079d1a0df55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe,The League" title="Hate at the heart of Italy's government | Roberto Mancini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/jun/10/italy-northern-league">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi is busy sorting out <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/04/silvio-berlusconi-divorce">his divorce</ref> – an ironic twist of fate for a man who long ago overturned the barriers between private and public life, using the family as a weapon of political propaganda and reducing parliamentary debate to the level of a bedroom farce in a celebrity news magazine.</p>
<p>Following the elections of 7 June, the real leadership of the Italian government is now in the hands of the Northern League. In Italy, as elsewhere, these were not only <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/jun/07/silvio-berlusconi-european-election">European elections</ref> but also council and provincial ones. And it is in the council elections that the League has really hit the jackpot.</p>
<p>The League (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lega_Nord">Lega Nord per l'indipendenza della Padania</ref>) is the oldest party in Italy (it was founded in 1989). It is a federal movement inspired by xenophobia, the expression of the wealthiest and most productive parts of Italy, such as the Veneto and northern Lombardy.</p>
<p>The party's founder, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umberto_Bossi">Umberto Bossi</ref>, uses unsophisticated and colourful language, peppered with popular movie metaphors and bar-room cliches.</p>
<p>On one hand the party presents itself as the guardian of Catholic tradition. On the other it has invented a symbolism of Celtic rites, copied from the Asterix and Obelix comic strips: referring to the river god <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Po_river">the Po</ref>, with its annual summer pilgrimage to the river's source, the Celtic <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padania">Padania</ref> (all of northern Italy) and resistance against Rome, considered the cesspit of all Italy's vices and weaknesses.</p>
<p>The party's symbol, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carroccio">il Carroccio</ref>, represents a cart drawn by oxen, around which foot soldiers would gather to fight in medieval city-states. The warrior depicted on its logo is <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberto_da_Giussano">Alberto da Giussano</ref>, who defeated the emperor <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Barbarossa">Frederick Barbarossa</ref> in 1176.</p>
<p>It is not so much an image as a political programme: the warlike virtue of small city-states fighting against every invasion that comes from the outside.</p>
<p>"We," hints Bossi, "are the heirs of small local authorities who have always fought against foreigners."</p>
<p>The Carroccio is also a mental horizon: only those who live in the city-states, your fellow citizens, are worthy of trust and respect, and are recognised as belonging to the community because they speak the same dialect as you do. In the League's opinion international organisations, such as the United Nations and the European Union, are deemed to be meddling opponents.</p>
<p>Apart from the fascist values of "blood and soil" (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_and_soil">blut und boden</ref>), language has become the League's touchstone for how to distinguish friends from enemies: in towns governed by the League they are already experimenting with school courses to teach the children the Veneto or Lombard dialects.</p>
<p>It's not surprising that with a cultural background like this, worthy of the Ku Klux Klan, the government has just passed a <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/may/13/italy-illegal-migration-bill-berlusconi">new law</ref> making it a crime to enter or stay in Italy illegally. The current interior minister, the League's <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto_Maroni">Roberto Maroni</ref>, has entrusted the Libyan government with the task of identifying which of those immigrants refused entry to our shores should be granted the right to seek political asylum in Italy. It is a bit like asking Count Dracula to run the blood bank.</p>
<p>A second feature of the League's ideology, <ref target="http://www.forumfed.org/en/products/magazine/vol8_num1/italy.php">federalism</ref>, has now been passed as a state law. It grants the regions disproportionate powers and is an irresponsible attempt to break the country's already weak and precarious unity into pieces.</p>
<p>Each governor of a northern region will now, presumably, see himself as a little Alberto da Giussano – standing up to the supposed tyranny of the central government in Rome.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#i">Translated from Italian.</hi>
</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>