<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-10-24" description="Italian government suspends plans for new facility after month of violent protests" fingerprint="1c4dcc98ddbb766f" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Landfill,Incineration,Waste,Environment,Protest" title="Rubbish piles up in Naples as waste dump is put on hold" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/oct/24/naples-rubbish-waste-dump-riots">
<main>
<p>The Italian government today offered to suspend the opening of a new waste dump near Naples in an attempt to halt violent protests that have lit up the night sky over Mount Vesuvius for a month.</p>
<p>Demonstrators have set fire to vehicles trying to bring rubbish into an existing dump, blocked the road leading to it with tree trunks and fought police with rocks, firecrackers and Molotov cocktails.</p>
<p>Police today said they had found a small quantity of explosives in the town of Terzigno, close to the scene of the nightly clashes.</p>
<p>Rubbish has meanwhile been piling up in the streets of Naples and the surrounding region of Campania, creating a situation reminiscent of a crisis two years ago that helped dispose of Italy's last, centre-left government.</p>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's administration has often pointed to its resolution of the last Naples waste emergency as evidence of its ability to get things done.</p>
<p>But the situation has been gradually deteriorating for months, and on Friday the prime minister promised to release €14m (£12.4m) to improve the existing dump, a key element in his strategy for dealing with the waste from Italy's third largest city.</p>
<p>Local residents complain that the facility gives off a foul smell and claim it has been used for the clandestine dumping of toxic waste.</p>
<p>One reason why Naples has been the scene of intermittent garbage crises since the early 1990s is the infiltration of the waste disposal business by the local mafia, the Camorra, subject of the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2008/oct/10/crime">2008 film Gomorrah</ref>.</p>
<p>Residents are wary of agreeing to incinerators or landfill sites because they fear these will be used to dump toxic waste trucked in by mobsters from other parts of Italy.</p>
<p>Plans for a second dump at Terzigno, which is in a national park, had been announced, scrapped and then reinstated. In the latest plan, offered by the head of Italy's civil protection agency, the new dump would be put on hold, but the existing one would be cleaned up and used until full.</p>
<p>The deal was conditional on an end to the violence. The mayors of the surrounding towns, who have backed the protests, initially refused to agree to the terms on offer and demanded more stringent guarantees.</p>
<p>Gennaro Langella, mayor of nearby Boscoreale, said he had detected on the government side an "interest in maintaining [their] commitments".</p>
<p>He and the mayors of three other towns went ahead with a peaceful march today that ended at the entrance to the existing dump, where they laid a wreath "in remembrance of the way the Vesuvius [National] Park died".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>