<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2008-04-11" description="Leader: Perhaps Berlusconi appeals more to Italians than any number of competent economists. He is the devil they know" fingerprint="6d88d82bd113cf5b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Leader: Third time unlucky for Italy" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2008/apr/12/italy">
<main>
<p>To have one term of <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> as prime minister may be regarded as a misfortune. Two terms looks like carelessness. But what would Lady Bracknell have said about the very real prospect of a third term for the 71-year-old media mogul, when Italy goes to the polls tomorrow? He has remodelled himself with a facelift and a hair transplant, and he wears a pacemaker on the campaign trail, but these, of themselves, do not explain his rejuvenation.</p>
<p>Nor does his change of political image from populist to elder statesman provide any clues. And it is not as if his previous terms of office covered him in glory. His two stints as premier were barren times in which Italy accumulated a large public debt and gently began its descent down the slipway of European economies. It has fallen behind Spain and threatens to be overtaken by Greece in economic performance. Mr Berlusconi reformed the pension system, but otherwise spent most of his time staving off the prosecutors, by hook or by crook (usually the latter).</p>
<p>Perhaps the flamboyant billionaire who stays one step ahead of the law, the cheeky chappie who makes outrageous gaffes at gatherings of heads of state, appeals more to Italians than any number of competent economists. He is the devil they know. His younger opponent - the 52-year-old centre-left candidate Walter Veltroni, the outgoing mayor of Rome - is more experienced than Mr Berlusconi, having entered politics earlier. However much Mr Veltroni tries to present himself as younger and fresher, he is no newcomer to national politics, having served as a deputy prime minister in the 1990s. An ex-communist who denies ever having been one, Mr Veltroni is Italy's answer to Tony Blair. Elected head of the Democratic party last year, he brings together the Left Democrats, the heirs of the old Communist party, and the ex-Christian Democrats of the Democracy is Freedom or "Daisy" party. He is unabashed at joining rightwing causes such as the eviction of Roma, many of them immigrants, to camps outside the city of Rome. Hours after the latest in a series of violent crimes blamed on Romanian immigrants, Mr Veltroni pressed the government of Romano Prodi to approve a decree allowing <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> to expel the citizens of member states of the European Union.</p>
<p>It may not go Mr Berlusconi's way. Having achieved a five- to nine-point advantage in the polls two weeks ago, he only managed a paltry turnout at the Roman Colosseum, and he may have made one gaffe too many. He accused the AS Roma midfielder Francesco Totti of being "off his head" for saying he would vote centre-left in local elections held at the same time. Politics is politics, but football is another matter.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>