<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Dominic Rushe" categories="Business" date="2011-11-09" description="The European debt crisis is getting ever more serious, and attention is moving away from Greece to one of the biggest – and potentially most explosive – economies in the world: Italy" fingerprint="39ff007939f33f41" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Business" title="Italy's debt crisis: 10 reasons to be fearful" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/nov/09/italys-debt-crisis-ten-reasons-to-be-fearful">
<main>
<p>Greece and Italy were the cradles of European culture: now they are threatening to drag the European Union to the grave. While Greece's fiscal woes were worrying, Italy's are monumental. Even <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, one of the great political survivors of our age, hasn't escaped this one. The Italian premier is out as the country's debts threaten to take down stock markets around the world. Here are the top 10 reasons to be concerned:</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">1. Italy is the eighth largest economy in the world</hi> and the fourth largest in Europe. Its gross domestic product (GDP) was over $2tn in 2010. Greece, Europe's other basket case, has a GDP of $305bn – an economy about the same size as Dallas, Fort Worth and Arlington in Texas.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">2.</hi> The country is label-queen heaven – Ferrari, Prada, Armani etc – and a major player in utilities, telecoms and banking. But the recession has put a strain on its economy and a succession of pop-up governments have failed to tackle fundamental problems, including the massive pension debts owed its ageing population. <hi rend="#b">Italy's debts now top $2.2tn, or 120% of gross domestic product</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">3.</hi> The debt matters because Italy is one of the world's largest markets for government bonds<hi rend="#b">.</hi><hi rend="#b">Fears that Italy cannot pay what it owes on government debt have driven rates on Italian bonds to over 7%.</hi> The levels are higher than bond prices reached in Ireland and Portugal before they had to be bailed out.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">4.</hi> Higher bond rates should, in theory, make Italy more attractive to investors. But what it really indicates is that the country has lost the faith of the markets. It probably doesn't help that Berlusconi pretended to fall asleep during key meetings with European leaders.<hi rend="#b"> Credit rating agencies have already cut Italy's credit scores.</hi> Moody's said last month it had cut Italy's rating because of a "sustained and non-cyclical erosion of confidence in the wholesale finance environment for euro sovereigns," and said it had the country on watch for more cuts to come.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">5.</hi><hi rend="#b">The speed at which government bond crises can escalate is startling:</hi> in April 2010, 10-year bond yields in Greece hit 7%; within a month they had reached 12%, prompting Greece's first bailout package. In Ireland, 10-year bond yield hit 7% in November 2010; a month later it had risen above 9%, triggering a bailout. In Portugal, yields hit 7% in November 2010; the bailout came in May.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">6.</hi> Last month, at the crisis meeting of European leaders, Berlusconi promised wholesale reforms in Italy. His 14-page "letter of intent" included a commitment to raise the pension age to 67 by 2026; steps to make it easier for companies to fire workers; and asset sales and other measures to improve conditions for business. But <hi rend="#b">Berlusconi's sketchy reforms failed to please anyone</hi> and met with both a political backlash and business scepticism.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">7. </hi>"At this point, Italy may be beyond the point of no return," Barclays Capital said in a gloomy report this week. "While reform may be necessary, <hi rend="#b">we doubt that Italian economic reforms alone will be sufficient to rehabilitate the Italian credit</hi> and eliminate the possibility of a debilitating confidence crisis that could overwhelm the positive effects of a reform agenda, however well conceived and implemented."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">8.</hi> Analysts Capital Economics calculate that if Italy's cost of borrowing continues to soar, it will have to raise around €650bn ($880bn) for the next three years or so. If the government also received loans to provide its troubled banking sector with additional capital buffers, <hi rend="#b">the bill could end up being closer to €700bn</hi>. Clearly it doesn't have that cash, so it will have to turn to the European financial stability facility (EFSF), the bailout fund that is backed by Euro big boys including Germany, France and – you've guessed it – Italy.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">9.</hi><hi rend="#b">The EFSF doesn't have unlimited cash</hi> and a multi-year financing programme for Italy would seriously deplete funds. If it can't save Italy, who is next? The European Central Bank (ECB), possibly, but it has been unwilling to step in for fear of "moral hazard" – the risk that euro countries will not make any move to put their accounts in order if they believe a bailout is coming. Economists fear that matters will have to get even worse before the ECB steps in. If Italy has to leave the euro and go back to the lira, the whole eurozone is in jeopardy.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">10.</hi> US officials keep saying that US banks have little "direct" exposure to Italy.<hi rend="#b"/>But <hi rend="#b">US institutions have been snapping up credit default swaps</hi> (CDSs), insurance against credit losses. The value of guarantees provided by US lenders on government, bank and corporate debt in troubled eurozone countries rose by $80.7bn to $518bn in the first half of this year, according to the Bank of International Settlements. One, admittedly small, firm – MF Global – <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/oct/31/mf-global-bankruptcy-eurozone-crisis">has already gone belly-up in the US</ref> thanks to indirect bets on Europe. If Italy goes down in a disorderly default, it will make the Lehman Brothers collapse feel like a Roman holiday.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>