<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-02-09" description="Government announces intention to speed through legislation which will stop feeding tubes being removed" fingerprint="afae8acabea1e677" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Vatican backs fight to save coma woman" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/feb/09/eluana-englaro-italy-assisted-suicide-vatican">
<main>
<p>The Vatican yesterday expressed "deep appreciation" for Silvio Berlusconi's efforts to rush through the Italian parliament legislation that would keep alive a woman who has been in a coma for the past 17 years.</p>
<p>The case of 34-year-old Eluana Englaro, which has been compared to that of the American Terri Schiavo, has divided <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> and prompted a constitutional showdown between the prime minister's rightwing government and the president and judiciary. In the latest move, the health minister said yesterday that a clinic in Udine where Englaro had been taken to die was not legally entitled to look after her.</p>
<p>The minister, Maurizio Sacconi, said a court ruling that Englaro's feeding tubes could be removed by her father had spoken of "a hospice or health facility, whereas here all we have are rooms on loan". The head of the clinic replied that the only anomaly was that volunteers were looking after Englaro.</p>
<p>On Friday, Italy's president, Giorgio Napolitano, refused to sign a government decree to overturn the court ruling. He said the judges' decision was final and had to be respected. But on Saturday the government announced that it was converting the decree into a bill, and intended to speed it through parliament this week.</p>
<p>One of Berlusconi's leading critics, Antonio Di Pietro, leader of the Italy of Principles party, accused the prime minister of trying to "split the country further, make it unstable and ungovernable, so as to then say he'll take care of things, just like [Benito] Mussolini did".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>