<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Matteo Mandarini" categories="Opinion" date="2011-09-25" description="Matteo Mandarini: The S&amp;P downgrade is an illustration of how markets have degraded human life, in Italy and across the developed world" fingerprint="1e4c9075da882e1b" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Market turmoil,Financial crisis,Global recession,Silvio Berlusconi,Euro,European Union,Economics,Euro,Business,Europe,World news" title="Italy invented politics beyond left and right and ended up with dancing girls | Matteo Mandarini" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/sep/25/italy-politics-left-right-dancing-girls">
<main>
<p>As markets race to catch up with the general downgrading of societies across the globe – chasing the collapse in living standards, educational and health conditions, and working and social life, and the degradation of political representation – they are finally catching up with <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
<p>This is a society that in many ways has been ahead of the game in the transformations of modern society and politics. We Italians like to think of ourselves as the inventors of modern politics, as the <hi rend="#i">laboratorio Italia</hi>. Nowhere was this more successful than in developing a politics "beyond left and right". But in this race to evacuate the political scene of ideology (or perhaps simply of ideas) we found nothing to replace it with but dancing girls and fiscal amnesties for tax evaders. Bread and circuses would already reveal a much more advanced social compromise.</p>
<p>What can be said of a society whose population endlessly returns to power the losers of previous elections? For no one ever leaves parliament once elected (even when convicted of links to organised crime, and sometimes precisely because of that conviction). But even those free of that particular stain (see <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massimo_D%27Alema">Massimo D'Alema</ref>, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Veltroni">Walter Veltroni</ref>, <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Rutelli">Francesco Rutelli</ref>, or <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romano_Prodi">Romano Prodi</ref>) are politicians who seem completely unaware that persistent, public, mediatised political failure is a sign that they should not try again. Thus it is a parliament of losers, without an idea to share between them, only parliamentary seats and the immunity they provide.</p>
<p>The degradation, sorry, downgrading, of public and private life is by the bye, since it merely reflects what is the case for so many Italian institutions, from the church to parliament, local government, trade unions and football clubs. Even Fiat is in the hands of <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergio_Marchionne">Sergio Marchionne</ref>, a man who thinks that Italian industrial innovation comes from cutting workers' rights down to Chinese levels. It might be against the Italian constitution and without a hope in hell in a court of law, but none of this matters as long as another little strong man can strut across the Italian media, the only public space. (The thought of Marchionne strutting is only a little less ludicrous than a prime minister in a bandana).</p>
<p>But let us get back to the case in point: the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/sep/20/italy-downgrade-eurozone-contagion-fear">downgrading of Italy by Standard and Poor's</ref>. What makes this downgrade so important is not the impact on the Italian costs of borrowing, the risk of contagion to other European countries, or the pressure this puts on the euro, European and North American banks – on the whole of the biggest economic zone in the world and the consequent risk of global contagion. All this is important. I wouldn't want to discount it as I know who will be made to pay for this – again.</p>
<p>But what I think is important is what this tells us, once again, about markets. Markets have a certain power over us; but they are not pushing anything. They are finding, illustrating and leading to its conclusion the degradation of human life we have already set in train. We have been downgraded because we have allowed ourselves to be degraded. Any number of us will rush forward to defend the inevitability of having to work longer, harder; to defend the claim that a decent life is unaffordable.</p>
<p>In such a situation perhaps it's not so wrong that the self-flagellators are being asked to pay, having placed the flagellator there and done so little to remove him. (It almost invariably is a he, despite Angela Merkel.) So markets are always playing catch-up; always behind the times. To downgrade Italy, one didn't need to analyse its debt-to-GDP ratio. (It has fluctuated around this line for decades.) It was enough to switch on our TVs, run by and populated with the Italian prime minister. Quite reasonably he recognised – even before this downgrade – that Italy is <hi rend="#i">"un paese di merda</hi>": a shitty country. Even Berlusconi was ahead of the markets.</p>
<p>And yet, markets are merely responding – not only in Italy, but across the developed world – to the austerity of social, political and working life. So it is at this level that the rebuilding must restart. The process of reconstituting public life, and reclaiming and reorganising the institutions of the world of work and political autonomy might be a long one, but Italy has a history of reinventing and rebuilding itself. Initial signs are there. In June the referendums on the defence of public services and against the privatisation of water were won by huge majorities. General strikes against austerity have brought the country to a standstill, despite the best efforts of some of the most compromised trade unions to prevent them.</p>
<p>These are the first signs of a challenge to Berlusconi's vulgarities and the rapacious capitalism he embodies. The task is to rebuild the <hi rend="#i">laboratorio</hi><hi rend="#i">Italia</hi> and tread the path for an international fightback against the austerity policies of the past three decades.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>