<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="Opinion" date="2011-11-10" description="Editorial: There are three possible solutions to the debt crisis: hope for improvement, stump up cash, or break up the eurozone" fingerprint="29dd509718b1a6e9" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Eurozone crisis,Silvio Berlusconi,Euro,Italy,Greece,France,Germany,European Union,Economics,Europe,World news" title="The euro crisis: slouching towards Bethlehem | Editorial" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/10/eurozone-debt-breakup">
<main>
<p>A last wake-up call. The moment of truth. A crucial crossroads. These descriptions of the eurozone meltdown <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/blog/2011/nov/10/eurozone-crisis-italy-greece">came yesterday</ref> from, respectively, the EU's top economic policymaker Olli Rehn, David Cameron, and Greece's new prime minister, Lucas Papademos. But it's fair to say that the air in Europe has been thick with such warnings for months now. Indeed, the European approach to this crisis has been to talk in terms of great drama while acting with self-defeating slowness, or what one might call the fierce urgency of tomorrow.</p>
<p>Yet the European crisis has built this week to a point where even the continent's leaders now acknowledge that unless a big and convincing solution is found within days, the 17-member eurozone will break up. The evidence of that escalation does not lie primarily in the resignations of Greece's George Papandreou or Italy's <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, proof though they are that this is a maelstrom that can topple governments. No, it can be traced instead to something seemingly less dramatic: the amount Rome is charged on its loans.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">The bailout zone</hi>
</p>
<p>One rule of thumb has endured over the past couple of years: when a European state pays more to borrow than an ordinary taxpayer would be charged on a bank loan, the government is only days away from calling in the international reinforcements. This week, it has been Italy's turn to head into the bailout zone. Yesterday it auctioned off €5bn of one-year bills <ref target="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/g/a/2011/11/10/bloomberg_articlesLUG1271A74E9.DTL">at an interest rate of 6.09%</ref>, the highest it has paid since September 1997. And this counts as an improvement over Wednesday, when a 10-year bond was yielding 7.45%.</p>
<p>What this effectively means is that the market trusts the Italian state – with its own treasury and tax-raising powers – less than it does a couple in Warrington who fancy a new conservatory. This is unbearably expensive for Rome: as Mr Rehn pointed out yesterday, merely a 1% increase in Italian bond yields would wipe 1% off the country's GDP after three years. It was reported yesterday that the European Central Bank was snapping up Italian bonds – but on its own that measure is unlikely to help for long. When a government is in the bailout zone, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2011/nov/07/bonds-markets-q-and-a">there is no ready way back</ref>, as politicians in Athens, Lisbon and Dublin can tell you.</p>
<p>Yet Greece, Portugal and Ireland are small economies; Italy is the third largest in the eurozone, and it has outstanding borrowing worth 120% of national income. Next year alone it needs to borrow €356bn. At these interest rates, this debt becomes unsustainable for Italy – and unaffordable for the European bailout fund. Default on these loans would send far greater shock waves around the world financial system than the collapse of Lehman. All this is without mentioning Spain and France, where rates are also climbing as investors shun anything that does not look 100% secure. To put it bluntly, a continuation of this panic would be disastrous for Rome and the rest of the eurozone.</p>
<p>In the short term, eurozone policymakers have three main options. One is to wait and hope that the likely installation of economist and technocrat <ref target="http://www.governo.it/Presidenza/storia_chigi/index.html">Mario Monti in Rome's Palazzo Chigi</ref> will calm nerves. But that would be to miss the point: financiers are not worried about personnel at the top, nor about a particular country's policies, but whether a 17-nation single currency will be around for much longer.</p>
<p>The reports this week about <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/germany">Germany</ref> and France plotting to form a breakaway currency both echo and amplify the current hysteria. What to do? Up till now, the eurozone has had one prescription for the sovereign debt crisis: punishing austerity to drive down debt in the short term, supply-side reforms to restore fiscal balance over the long term. The IMF has done this in many countries in the past – the current chaos in Greece bears out that this medicine does not work economically, is unjust socially, and can lead to ungovernability.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="#b">Commit or quit</hi>
</p>
<p>The other option, then, would be for the eurozone to stand behind the sovereign debts of its members. That motivation underlies the bailout fund: the problem being that Germany and its few flush friends cannot stump up the cash now required without unleashing a backlash from voters and ratings agencies. That leaves the ECB to step in. For some time it has been doing so on an ad hoc basis – buying bonds to smooth the markets and propping up troubled banks. Now it must act systematically, or risk the euro breaking up.</p>
<p>Because that is the final option, of course, however unimaginable it once seemed. The markets are now treating it as a serious possibility, and politicians have yet to do anything that proves otherwise. The ECB standing decisively behind distressed bonds is only the first of a long list of changes and U-turns which the currency zone would in the end have to make if it is to thrive. But it would at least be a show of real commitment to the first challenge: survival. Eurozone leaders now have a very short period to prove their club is here to stay.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>