<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="David Hills" categories="Football" date="2013-10-19" description="The week in football: Qatar, Ronaldo and Sven; beating referees; plus why marrying footballers makes no sense" fingerprint="3f05df5f9032f7b7" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Fifa,Football politics,Finances,World Cup 2022,Silvio Berlusconi,Milan,Uefa,Cristiano Ronaldo,Football,Sport" title="Said and Done – the week in football: Qatar, Ronaldo and Harry" url="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2013/oct/19/said-and-done-karl-heinz-rummenigge">
<main>
<head rend="h2">Qatar: the final word</head>
<p><ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-2436952/Karl-Heinz-Rummenigge-receives-Rolex-watches-worth-84-000-trip-Qatar.html">Karl-Heinz Rummenigge</ref> – telling the press how to handle the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2013/sep/26/qatar-world-cup-migrant-workers-dead">Qatar slave state story</ref> about workers denied the right to unionise or strike: "Move on. The media must be more careful: German industry has contracts there worth billions. Qatar was chosen, so just respect it, and accept it."</p>
<head rend="h2">Meanwhile</head>
<p>Taking a lead on union rights last week: Qatar's state-owned <hi rend="#b">Paris Saint-Germain </hi>– joining a "unanimous" clubs' union protest against the French 75% wealth tax, <ref target="http://uk.eurosport.yahoo.com/news/football-french-sports-minister-hits-clubs-strike-threat-132151604--sow.html">backed by a threat of strike action</ref>. The new tax would cost <ref target="http://www.swfinstitute.org/swfs/qatar-investment-authority/">Qatar Sports Investments</ref> €20m.</p>
<head rend="h2">Salesman of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Italy: </hi>Silvio Berlusconi<hi rend="#b">, </hi>linked with a plan to <ref target="http://forzaitalianfootball.com/2013/10/ac-milan-president-interested-in-new-investment/">sell part of his Milan stake</ref> to Arab investors by promoting Milan in the Middle East – two years after he warned voters to back his candidate for Milan's mayor or face living in an "overrun Islamic city … besieged by foreigners".</p>
<head rend="h2">Football family news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Last week's big winner: </hi>Worawi Makudi, <ref target="http://www.insideworldfootball.com/world-football/asia/13460-makudi-wins-another-4-years-as-thai-fa-chief-after-bitter-election-fight">re-elected for another four years</ref> as Thailand's FA head. The delayed vote went ahead after Makudi forced through a cut to the number of eligible voters from 180 to 72. "I'm confident this election was transparent. I start work tomorrow."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Quote of the week: </hi>Fifa installing officials to <ref target="http://www.insideworldfootball.com/world-football/oceania/13454-fifa-takes-control-of-solomon-islands-football-after-budget-bungle">take charge of the Solomon Islands FA</ref>, due to what Oceania's general secretary, Tai Nicholas, called "lapses in financial management in terms of the accountability of where the money went".</p>
<p><hi rend="#b"> Best solidarity: </hi>Uefa fining Basel €30,000 for failing to prevent an <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/video/2013/oct/02/greenpeace-protest-basel-fc-schalke-video">in-match Greenpeace protest</ref> against <ref target="http://www.uefa.org/events/marketing/news/newsid=1839761.html">Uefa sponsors Gazprom</ref>.</p>
<head rend="h2">Other news</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">8: </hi>The number of days between the <ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-2446792/HARRY-REDKNAPP-BOOK-EXCLUSIVE-The-FA-appoint-decent-England-manager-lives-depended-it.html">launch of Harry Redknapp's book</ref> – "I wouldn't trust the FA to show me a good manager if their lives depended on it" – and his verdict on England's week: "They made a good choice. Roy's an excellent manager. Nobody disputes that."</p>
<head rend="h2">More managers</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">April: </hi>Gillingham chairman <hi rend="#b">Paul Scally </hi>on why it takes vision to <ref target="http://www.kentnews.co.uk/sport/martin_allen_can_lead_gillingham_back_to_championship_says_scally_1_2007159">employ a manager like Martin Allen</ref>: "I don't know why he's got that [Mad Dog] nickname … He gets the results. There are a lot of chairmen that are fearful of him … if chairmen aren't bold enough to think outside the box then they aren't going to get anywhere." <hi rend="#b">Oct: </hi>Sacks him.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Mozambique: </hi>Costa do Sol's Portuguese manager <hi rend="#b">Diamantino Miranda </hi><ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-24492431">expelled by the government</ref> for "letting loose" on journalists: "All here are thieves. You are all a bunch of thieves, you journalists can be bought off with a bowl of soup. This country isn't serious."</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Chile, 27 Sept: </hi>Colo Colo president Arturo Salah on coach Gustavo Benítez: "He will be here to the end of the year, whatever happens next. He's key to our project, to our stabilisation, he's totally aligned with our vision. His role cannot be questioned." <hi rend="#b">14 Oct: </hi>It can.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">1: </hi>The number of months between a Saudi prince buying Sheffield United and <hi rend="#b">Sven-Goran Eriksson</hi> being <ref target="http://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/news/sven-goran-eriksson-backed-sheffield-2460585">linked with the job</ref>.</p>
<head rend="h2">Protest of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Serbia: Red Star Belgrade </hi>fans reacting to players blaming bad performances on poor club facilities – including "a lack of necessities, such as shampoo" – by <ref target="http://www.whoateallthepies.tv/videos/177896/irate-red-star-belgrade-ultras-throw-shampoo-into-players-cars-in-protest-over-slump.html">throwing shampoo bottles</ref> through their car windows. Police say inquiries are "ongoing".</p>
<head rend="h2">Saddest exit</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Romania: </hi>Cluj releasing ex-West Brom defender <hi rend="#b">Gabriel Tamas </hi>a week after they signed him, following a "series of incidents, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/football/2013/oct/12/said-and-done-football-family">some published in the press</ref>, some not". President Iuliu Muresan: "He came, he drank, he left. We had little option."</p>
<head rend="h2">Mother of the week</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Portugal: </hi>Cristiano Ronaldo's<hi rend="#b"/>mother Dolores Aveiro, telling a new book how much he has changed: "As a boy he would get angry and cry easily if other boys didn't pass him the ball, or because they did not play as he wanted. They called him cry baby."</p>
<head rend="h2">Most regretful</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Romania: </hi>Former manager <hi rend="#b">Ionut Popa</hi>, looking back at the regrets from his career: "I would like to have beaten a referee during a match," and: "I would like to have been a politician. Politicians are thieves with huge fortunes, having lovely lives, doing what they like. They can run people over on pedestrian crossings and no one does anything. Politics, man. That's the future!"</p>
<head rend="h2">Plus: best principles</head>
<p><hi rend="#b">Spain: </hi>Model <hi rend="#b">Michele Zuanne</hi>, posing in Atlético Madrid underwear to tell <hi rend="#i">Interviu</hi> about her ex, Diego Costa. "I do like footballers physically, though not mentally. I'd never marry one: their lives are shallow and they become unfaithful. Diego was nice, but he made a play for my sister. There's too much competition."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>