<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="UK news" date="2010-02-25" description="Judges rule on technicality, but prosecutor says no grounds for Tessa Jowell's estranged husband to be acquitted on facts of case" fingerprint="aa2001f55b916d7" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="David Mills,Silvio Berlusconi,Tessa Jowell,Italy,World news,UK news,Politics,Europe" title="David Mills bribery sentence quashed" url="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2010/feb/25/david-mills-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>Italy's highest appeals court tonight quashed the four-and-a-half year prison sentence handed to Tessa Jowell's estranged husband, David Mills, for accepting a bribe on the grounds that the charges against him had been "timed out" by a statute of limitations.</p>
<p>But the judges made no comment on the merits of the case and upheld an order that the British lawyer should pay €250,000 (£222,000) to the Italian state as compensation for giving evasive evidence.</p>
<p>Mills said he was "very relieved" by the outcome. In a statement, he said he would now be able to "get back to a normal life". He was found guilty last year of taking a $600,000 bribe from Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, in return for perjuring himself in two trials in the 1990s in which Berlusconi was a defendant. The conviction was upheld on a first appeal.</p>
<p>It is not clear when the prime minister's own trial for allegedly corrupting Mills will be timed out, but it looks highly likely to collapse before the final appeal stage.</p>
<p>Both men are defendants in another trial involving the allegedly fraudulent trading of TV film rights.</p>
<p>The case which ended tonight was politically charged from the outset and never more so than in its final stages, with Britain and <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> facing elections. Gordon Brown gave Jowell, his Olympics minister, a ringing endorsement after Mills's conviction last year.</p>
<p>Labour could still be vulnerable to opposition attack since the acquittal was not on the merits of the case, and the cash at the heart of the trial was brought into Britain by a remortgaging operation to which Jowell put her signature. Jowell has repeatedly denied any wrongdoing and was cleared by a parliamentary inquiry.</p>
<p>The ruling was also a bittersweet one for Berlusconi's rightwing administration, which faces regional ballots next month. They will be the first big test of Italian public opinion since the prime minister was swamped by sex scandals last year. Tonight's outcome certainly removed a cloud from Berlusconi's sky. But the court did not comment on whether he was the source of the payment to Mills and the judge in the original trial decided that if Mills were found to have taken a bribe then the Italian prime minister could not be innocent of having given it.</p>
<p>The turning point in the hearing came when Gianfranco Ciani, assistant chief prosecutor of the court of cassation, told the judges that he believed the charges against Mills were already subject to a statute of limitations. But he added: "There are not the grounds for <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/david-mills">David Mills</ref> to be acquitted on the facts of the case."</p>
<p>Arguing for the €250,000 compensation payment, Ciani said Mills had done "harm to the image of the state in respect of its exercise of the judicial function". Neither Mills nor Berlusconi was there to hear the ruling.</p>
<p>A key issue in the final appeal was the exact moment at which the alleged crime had been committed. The prosecutors argued successfully in two lower courts that it was when Mills entered into possession of the money.</p>
<p>But there was disagreement between the two sides over when that was – in February 2000 or November 1999. The difference was crucial because under Italian law the offence is subject to a 10-year statute of limitations. The prosecutor in the court of cassation, unlike his counterparts at earlier hearings, said he believed the offence had been committed before 11 November 1999.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>