<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="Politics" date="2009-02-17" description="The clever British lawyer whose dealings with Italy's Silvio Berlusconi put him in the dock" fingerprint="bf8d008d54a4a4db" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Tessa Jowell,Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,UK news,Law,World news,Politics,David Mills,Europe" title="David Mills: a career punctuated by several lapses in judgment" url="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-berlusconi-trial">
<main>
<p/>
<p>On the afternoon of 2 February 2004, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/david-mills">David Mills</ref> phoned his accountant. He needed to see him. Urgently.</p>
<p>When Mills arrived at the Jermyn Street offices of Rawlinson &amp; Hunter, in London, he was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2009/feb/17/david-mills-berlusconi-trial-letter">carrying a letter</ref> that set out everything he was about to recount. During the meeting, he handed over the letter to his accountant and friend, Bob Drennan.</p>
<p>Anyone who has met Mills, 63, will tell you that he is a clever, indeed brilliant, man. He speaks four languages, can talk knowledgeably on art history, plays the clarinet, and is said by friends to be an expert cook.</p>
<p>Yet his career has been punctuated by several lapses of judgment. In 2003 it emerged he was involved in a project to sell jets to Iran. In 2006, the authorities in Dubai rejected his application to practise law on the grounds that he did not state he had been the subject of an official investigation.</p>
<p>The letter to Drennan, however, was to prove the worst mistake of all.</p>
<p>After 10 years at the bar, Mills had retrained as a solicitor and linked up with the Italian law firm of Carnelutti. He soon became highly adept at setting up offshore trusts and companies, which his rich Italian clients used to minimise their tax liabilities.</p>
<p>Though some might regard it as an odd choice of specialisation for a former Labour councillor and husband of a rising MP in the party, there was nothing illegal about it. Starting in the mid-1990s, however, Mills's activities came under increasingly close scrutiny by Italian prosecutors investigating one of his clients, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>.</p>
<p>Mills had set up a web of offshore companies and trusts for the Italian prime minister's business empire, which prosecutors were trying to show had been used to dodge tax and convey under-the-counter payments to politicians.</p>
<p>Although Mills was still formally a prosecution witness in some of the cases brought against Berlusconi, the prosecutors had decided to stop treating the lawyer as no more than an independent professional adviser. Indeed, as he himself noted in his letter to Drennan, they were about to lay charges against him.</p>
<p>In addition, HM Revenue &amp; Customs was investigating his affairs, and Mills was concerned they might home in on a payment of $600,000 (£400,000) he had received four years earlier.</p>
<p>Explaining why it had not been declared, he told Drennan it was a "a long-term loan or a gift" from "the B people": they "knew quite how much the way in which I had been able to give my evidence (I told no lies, but I turned some very tricky corners, to put it mildly) had kept Mr B out of a great deal of trouble that I would have landed him in if I had said all I knew".</p>
<p>Mills seems to have been unaware that his accountant had a duty to hand over the letter to the British authorities. He only learned that he had made it available to the Italian prosecutors four months later on a suffocating Milan summer's day.</p>
<p>Fabio De Pasquale – a Sicilian with a ready, impish smile – and Alfredo Robledo were already investigating the involvement of Berlusconi and Mills, in an alleged scheme for tax evasion on television film rights. Several hours into Mills's interrogation, they showed him the letter that began "Dear Bob". He crumbled.</p>
<p>Mills signed a statement confirming the contents of the letter which, he said, needed "little clarification". But whereas Mills regarded the $600,000 as a gift or loan, the prosecutors saw it as a retrospective bribe – payment for perverting the course of justice.</p>
<p>What they did not expect was that Mills would then withdraw his statement and give an entirely different version – that the money came from a Neapolitan ship owner. The trial that ended today led the judges into some of the most remote paths and tangled thickets of offshore finance. Mills's accounts and those of his clients were almost unimaginably complex.</p>
<p>But, ultimately, it came down to whether the prosecution could disprove his revised version.</p>
<p>It was found that the money trail behind the $600,000 did indeed lead back to a trust in the Bahamas of which the ship owner, Diego Attanasio, was the beneficiary.</p>
<p>But a big question mark hung over whether Attanasio, or his lawyer, Mills, was really in control of the trust at the time the original transfer was made. Attanasio denied having authorised it and said he had given Mills a free hand to manage some of his affairs.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>