<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian Staff; Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2006-02-10" description="Letters: I found some of Tristram Hunt's remarks on Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi (Comment, February 6) to be totally out of place." fingerprint="7aa201ce1a33fb04" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,World news,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Letter: Berlusconi puts the record straight" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/feb/10/italy.mainsection">
<main>
<p>I found some of Tristram Hunt's remarks on Prime Minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> (Comment, February 6) to be totally out of place. First, the statement about the superiority of western civilisation attributed to Prime Minister Berlusconi was denied several times and in actual fact he takes pride in his friendship with many heads of state and government in the Muslim world, from President Mubarak of Egypt to Prime Minister Tayip Erdogan of Turkey.</p>
<p>The "neo-fascists" Mr Hunt talks about are a fully fledged democratic party of the ruling coalition, which has always shown full respect for the constitution. Gianfranco Fini's track record has been demonstrated both in his capacity as leader of Alleanza Nazionale, and as foreign affairs minister and deputy prime minister. Mr Fini is indeed appreciated and esteemed in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/europe-news">Europe</ref> and in the whole world.</p>
<p>The alleged systematic misuse of legislative power would, according to Mr Hunt, place <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> on an equal footing to some of the unfortunate South American countries during the years of military dictatorship. This is a view that only your commentator seems to hold.</p>
<p>The electoral law passed in 2005 is more or less similar to the one the left failed to have approved because of its inner divisions. And the alleged "environmental damage" inflicted on the Sardinian coastline is an allegation which can be made only by people who are not familiar with the place. In fact all the fuss concerns a narrow cave invisible from the sea and the coast.</p>
<p>All of which shows, once more, that the cliches spread by the opposition do not always tally with the facts.<hi rend="#b">Paolo Bonaiuti </hi><lb/> Spokesman for Silvio Berlusconi</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>