<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2009-02-10" description="Italy's prime minister partly blames president for not signing decree forcing doctors to restore Eluana Englaro's feeding tubes" fingerprint="f3afd94b1a938b75" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Human rights,Assisted dying,World news,Law,Europe" title="Berlusconi says woman in right-to-die row was 'killed'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/feb/10/berlusconi-says-coma-woman-killed">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi, has further stoked the flames over a right-to-die case that has divided Italy by suggesting that Eluana Englaro, the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/feb/09/italy-silvio-berlusconi">woman who died yesterday</ref> after 17 years in coma, had been "killed".</p>
<p>The Italian prime minister's remarks are sure to cause outrage as he added that he felt the Italy's president was at least partly to blame for her death.</p>
<p>"Eluana did not die a natural death," Berlusconi was quoted as telling the Libero newspaper. "She was killed. She died while they were arguing over the constitutionality of a government bill."</p>
<p>Englaro, who was in vegetative state, died apparently of a heart attack three days after doctors at a clinic in Udine, in north-est Italy, cut off her supplies of food and water. The chief prosecutor in nearby Trieste, Beniamino Deidda, said he had no "news of the carrying out of any offence".</p>
<p>The 38-year-old woman died as the Senate, the upper house of the Italian parliament, was debating an emergency bill tabled by the cabinet that would have ordered her doctors to restore the supply of nutrients. The government had earlier been forced to withdraw a decree that would have taken immediate effect because the president, Giorgio Napolitano, refused to sign on the grounds that it was unconstitutional.</p>
<p>"Napolitano made a serious mistake," the newspaper Corriere della Sera quoted Berlusconi as saying.</p>
<p>The objection to the decree was that it would have overturned a final decision by Italy's highest appeals court. Last November, the court of cassation ruled that Englaro's father could ask doctors to withdraw her life support systems.</p>
<p>The ruling prompted a vigorous campaign by the Vatican, which saw it as an attempt to legalise euthanasia in Italy, and Pope Benedict XVI has repeated referred to the case, if only indirectly, in his public statements, saying that "the sanctity of life must be safeguarded from conception to its natural end."</p>
<p>The Vatican's efforts were backed by Catholic ministers in Berlusconi's rightwing government, who tried by every bureaucratic means at their disposal to ensure that no hospital or clinic took her in to allow her to die before a private facility in Udine did so last week and her feeding tubes are removed.</p>
<p>Opposition politicians claimed that Berlusconi was exploiting the case to extend his powers and humiliate the judiciary.</p>
<p>An autopsy is to be carried out, probably later today.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>