<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Paola Buonadonna" categories="Opinion" date="2014-08-11" description="Paola Buonadonna: Many of my compatriots blame Italy’s recession on Europe, but the problems – complacency, corruption, sexism – go far deeper" fingerprint="b6a819bc307cdf49" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Europe,World news,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Italy’s malaise goes to its very heart | Paola Buonadonna" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/aug/11/italy-malaise-recession-complacency-corruption-sexism">
<main>
<p>Italy, it was revealed in recent days, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2014/aug/06/rising-ukraine-tension-european-markets">is sliding back into recession</ref>. According to the latest GDP figures released by the country’s statistical institute, Istat, the economy shrunk by <ref target="http://www.istat.it/en/archive/130067">0.2% in the second quarter</ref>. Unless there are drastic cuts, the government’s budget deficit may now breach the EU’s 3% of GDP threshold for 2014 – the third slide into recession since 2008.</p>
<p>Many of my compatriots blame Europe or at least the strictures of the single currency and the recent eurozone crisis for this malaise, which has brought about, among other things, a disastrous <ref target="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_MEMO-14-466_en.htm">43% youth unemployment rate</ref>. But Italy’s problems go far deeper and are far more complex than this. The chief one, it seems to me, is a propensity for magical thinking, the flipside of the dreamy delights of la dolce vita.</p>
<p>When as a university student I left my homeland in 1989, Italy was a mafia-ridden, traditionalist place, run by a corruptly efficient political class. But hope, the possibility of change, was in the air. The <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani_pulite">Clean Hands judicial investigation</ref> into corruption at the highest levels would sweep away the old parties, bringing the First Republic to an end, a mere three years later.</p>
<p>I moved to the UK because I wanted to be a journalist, a dream that I could never achieve in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref>. I was not the daughter of journalists and had no political patrons – back home I had as much chance of entering the profession as I had of becoming pope.</p>
<p>The Italians I tended to meet in London were middle-class kids set on improving their English, or eager to live an openly gay or alternative lifestyle in a tolerant, big city, away from disapproving relatives. I didn’t think of myself – or them – as immigrants.</p>
<p>But the anti-corruption fervour didn’t last. The Second Republic turned out to be a lot worse than the first, with a corrupt but inefficient political class and a subservient media, respectively focused on and mesmerised by Silvio Berlusconi’s epic efforts to stay out of jail by way of ingenious and imaginative law-making.</p>
<p>While other countries reformed and modernised their economies in answer to the looming challenge of globalisation, Italy clutched the euro chip to its chest and carried on gambling. In the decade that preceded the financial crisis, other eurozone countries grew by an average of 9.5% while Italy managed a measly 1.2%.</p>
<p>Women didn’t count for much when I left, but the direction of travel was a hopeful one. Parents wanted us to do well at school, we were at least encouraged to be ambitious. The media portrayed us mostly in the kitchen but with our clothes on at least. But Berlusconi, through his media and advertising empire, had as big an impact on the culture as on the political sphere. Now the women are mostly naked objects in the billboard ads, and mute and lipsticked on TV.</p>
<p>Middle-aged me recoils at reading accounts of how the parents of the young women who took part in the former premier’s “parties” egged their daughters on. For those who did not find fame and fortune that way, work is a brief, sexually harassed interlude between school and motherhood, after which they can officially forget about any career advancement. This systematic failure to harness the talents and energy of half the population has made it even harder for the country’s productivity to rise.</p>
<p>Italy sleepwalked into disaster. Yes our leaders were corrupt, more taxes needed to be collected, the mafia needed to be fought, but I fear that deep down we felt that it was not our destiny to be a normal country – to pay taxes, to fill jobs without subterfuge, to demand a free and accountable media to question those in power, and to have public services delivered without preference and backhanders. We, the heirs of the Renaissance, in our gorgeous land of great wine, food and fashion, which everyone loved and wanted to visit, were special somehow, and a special way would be found, some accommodation which meant that the normal rules – of public administration, of journalism, of economics – did not have to apply.</p>
<p>The current generation of young Italians flocking to London now are from the middle classes with masters and second degrees, embracing the minimum wage barista lifestyle as a more stimulating alternative to nothingness. Back home, despite the new prime minister Matteo Renzi’s bullish optimism, most professional fields of activity are still run like medieval guilds, and labour reforms have made permanent work contracts a rarity for everybody else.</p>
<p>It’s hard not to think of these young Italians as immigrants – and, in the daily barrage of anti-EU, anti-immigration front pages, it’s harder not to think of myself as one.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>