<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="David Gow" categories="Business" date="2003-08-08" description="Tony Blair and his Italian counterpart, Silvio Berlusconi, are intensely lobbying George Bush to buy AgustaWestland EH-101 helicopters for his new presidential fleet, it emerged yesterday." fingerprint="7cc2839194ad6f24" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Business,Politics,Economic policy,Silvio Berlusconi" title="Blair and Berlusconi lobby Bush for helicopter deal" url="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2003/aug/08/politics.economicpolicy">
<main>
<p>Tony Blair and his Italian counterpart, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, are intensely lobbying George Bush to buy AgustaWestland EH-101 helicopters for his new presidential fleet, it emerged yesterday.</p>
<p>Kevin Smith, chief executive of GKN, joint owners with Finmeccanica of AgustaWestland, said the two prime ministers were repeatedly marketing the helicopter in their face-to-face talks with the US president.</p>
<p>Industry sources said that the British government was "putting an enormous, unprecedented amount of effort" into getting a substantial order from the US, where the helicopter market is worth $7bn (£4.3bn) over the next few years, according to Mr Smith.</p>
<p>The green and white Marine One fleet of Sikorski helicopters ferrying Mr Bush from Washington to Camp David is due to be replaced with 24 new craft, with a decision due early next year.</p>
<p>AgustaWestland has teamed up with US rival Bell under the leadership of defence company Lockheed Martin to compete against Sikorski and Boeing for the order.</p>
<p>Eurocopter, the world's biggest manufacturer, broke ground yesterday on a new plant in Columbus, Mississippi, to build para-public helicopters for agencies such as the coast guard and county sherriffs.</p>
<p>It has kept out of the bidding for the fleet, convinced that only a US team will win. But Mr Smith said: "This is our best shot for a long, long time to get a product into the US - and we've proved them wrong by breaking into the Japanese market, which had been closed for 50 years.</p>
<p>"You never know, you might just see the president climbing into a foreign helicopter. If he takes another route that's not the end of the world for us. If we win it would be a major, major credibility reinforcement for us."</p>
<p>GKN is aiming for orders worth $7bn for 360 craft, including 196 search and rescue helicopters for the US air force worth up to $5bn. The entire programme is worth more than $20bn over its lifetime.</p>
<p>The group, buoyed up by growing defence sales, delighted investors by limiting the decline in first-half operating profits to 1% at £160m, despite weaker automotive and civil aerospace markets. Mr Smith said civil aviation would not recover before 2006. GKN, which is now paying £40m a year extra towards eliminating a net £486m pension deficit, said the worst of the problem was now over, with a stock market recovery and rising long-term interest rates in the US.</p>
<p>According to the group, every 100 point gain in the FTSE index is worth £20m and every 1% interest rise £300m. It said the increased contribution would help clear the deficit "in a reasonable period of time".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>