<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Anna Masera" categories="Opinion" date="2009-04-07" description="Anna Masera: Threats to curb the media for daring to criticise his performance at the G20 and Nato summits are popular with the Italian public" fingerprint="7fbb93a3992a4249" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,G20,Media,Europe" title="Anna Masera: Berlusconi's threats to curb the media go down well with the Italian public" url="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2009/apr/06/italy-silvio-berlusconi">
<main>
<p>It's not Silvio Berlusconi, stupid, it's the press. Italy's premier has not appreciated the <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/apr/06/berlusconi-gaffes-queen-g20-press">press coverage</ref> of his performance at the G20. So what's new? He never appreciates the press; indeed he is famous for denigrating the whole pack as "communists". But he also uses the press quite craftily for his own purposes, mainly to make sure that everybody – in bars, coffee shops, corridors, on the streets – talks about him. He is the ultimate self-publicist.</p>
<p>And it would be wrong for political analysts to judge Berlusconi as a buffoon, with his silly jokes at official international diplomatic meetings: as the Italian journalist Francesco Verderami <ref target="http://www.corriere.it/politica/09_aprile_04/berlusconi_calunnie_azioni_dure_contro_media_00d2867e-214a-11de-94b6-00144f02aabc.shtml?fr=box_primopiano">wrote</ref> in Il Corriere della Sera, the Cavaliere is briliant at using man-of-the street mateyness as a political strategy to win over his electorate, his "people". How does he shake Barack Obama's hand without losing the attention of the ordinary Italian housewife? How does he discuss global politics with Sarkozy while still talking to the elderly in Palermo? This is Berlusconi's obsession – how to mix with the powerful of the world without losing contact with his base. He uses popular gestures and expressions to appear like a friend among friends. And he achieves his goal. According to the polls he remains far more popular than the opposition. As Nando Pagnoncelli, head of the Ipsos research center, says: "What seem like gaffes actually convey quite well public opinion and public feelings." And Gianpaolo Pansa, an old guard veteran journalist of newsmagazine L'Espresso and newspaper La Repubblica, comments: "The left doesn't understand him because the Left is snobbish. But Berlusconi is a craftsman of politics. His only enemy is the economic crisis." Giuliano Ferrara, journalist editor in chief of Il Foglio, echoes this: "Berlusconi won, over stuffy establishment protocols."</p>
<p>Andrea Bonanni <ref target="http://www.repubblica.it/ultimora/politica/BERLUSCONI-TENTATO-DA-AZIONI-CONTRO-STAMPA-E-TV/news-dettaglio/3628836">in La Repubblica</ref>, one of those most critical of Italy's premier, said in his editorial "L'ossessione del cavaliere", that Berlusoni's behaviour can be explained by by his desire to appear in the national media, since he didn't do anything worth mentioning at the international policy level (underscoring that Berlusconi is the only G8 member not to have been able to meet with Obama).</p>
<p>What is more worrying is Berlusconi's continuing threats to control Italy's media. He promised revenge when the editors of Corriere della Sera, La Stampa and La Repubblica criticized him and did not back him during the electoral campaign, asking (symbolically) for their heads. Last week he got what he wanted. Changes in editors in chief in the main television news network, Rai's Tg1, and the main newspaper Corriere della Sera, were announced. The others may follow. And their successors are advised: criticise Berlusconi, and you might find yourself out of a job.</p>
<p>So far, Italy's premier hasn't won over all the media, because in the internet era, where bloggers and social networks organise opposition, not even a television monopoly is enough to guarantee him protection. That's why his coalition is pushing laws in parliament against anonymity and for censorship of the internet. Certainly, the Italian press is the most vulnerable to pressure from Berlusconi. Already in deep crisis due to shrinking advertising revenues and competition from the net, newspapers depend on subsidies from the state. And Italy's media proprietors are not independent: Il Corriere della Sera is owned by industrialists and financiers who side politically with the premier, La Stampa is owned by Fiat, which by definition is considered by the public "pro-government", since it depends on government subsidies for the car industry's unemployed.</p>
<p>Whether this is true or not doesn't matter, as media guru <ref target="http://www.lessig.org">Lawrence Lessig</ref> points out, it's a question of public opinion and of trust. Politics, finance and companies in Italy are interconnected in such inextricable ways that public opinion doesn't trust them. Ironically, it's the perfect turf for Berlusconi to win over public opinion with his "man-of-the-street" type jokes. So when he calls the press evil, the public sympathises. It's not Berlusconi, stupid: it's the press.</p>
</main>
<comments><head>Comments (…)</head>Sign in or create your Guardian account to join the discussion</comments>
</text>