<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Guardian staff reporter" categories="World news" date="2017-04-10" description="Film featuring Italian ex-PM circulated on social media as meat lobby calls on advertisers to boycott his TV channels" fingerprint="ffbad22f10efe125" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Vegetarianism,Easter,World news,Meat,Meat industry,Farming,Italy,Europe" title="Berlusconi cuddles lambs in vegetarian Easter campaign" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/apr/10/silvio-berlusconi-vegetarian-easter-lambs-italian">
<main>
<p>Former prime minister <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> has infuriated Italy’s meat industry by joining a vegetarian campaign and “adopting” five lambs that would have been butchered for Easter.</p>
<p>A video by the Italian League in Defence of Animals and the Environment, showing Berlusconi cuddling, kissing and feeding the lambs with a baby’s bottle, was circulated widely on social media over the weekend.</p>
<p>The 80-year-old former prime minister was filmed in his parkland estate in front of a sign saying “Defend life, choose a vegetarian <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/easter">Easter</ref>,” while a scrolling message urged viewers to “Be like him. He saved five lambs from the Easter slaughter.”</p>
<p>Berlusconi was <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/nov/27/silvio-berlusconi-ousted-italian-parliament-tax-fraud-conviction">expelled from the senate in 2013</ref> following a conviction for tax fraud, but his Forza Italia party is still the third or fourth most popular in Italy with about 12% of the vote, according to opinion polls.</p>
<p>Italians traditionally eat lamb or goat on Easter Sunday but consumption has declined sharply over the last five years due to an economic slump and the growing success of vegetarian campaigns.</p>
<p>Ital ian butchers’ lobby Assocarni attacked the billionaire media tycoon and called on advertisers to boycott his television channels and publications.</p>
<p>“It’s incredible that even though he is a business person he is contributing to damaging the meat industry to try to get the votes of animal lovers,” it said in a statement.</p>
<p>Several newspapers reported last year that Berlusconi had become a vegetarian. He responded in a statement that he had “never made any declaration on this, either in public or in private,” neither confirming nor denying the reports.</p>
<p>Berlusconi has worn a pacemaker for a decade and underwent <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/14/silvio-berlusconi-undergoes-heart-surgery">open-heart surgery</ref> in June last year to replace a defective aortic valve.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>