<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2012-12-28" description="Former Italian prime minister had reportedly offered Veronica Lario €300,000 a month" fingerprint="e2e923f9a02ef75" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Silvio Berlusconi,Italy,Europe,World news" title="Silvio Berlusconi 'told to pay ex-wife €3m a month in divorce settlement'" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/dec/28/silvio-berlusconi-wife-divorce-settlement">
<main>
<p>Three years after Silvio Berlusconi's wife walked out on him over his alleged frolicking with teenage girls, the former Italian prime minister has reportedly been ordered to pay her €3m a month in a divorce settlement.</p>
<p>The climax of the long-simmering divorce battle – reported by Italy's Corriere della Sera – follows Berlusconi's offer of just €300,000 a month to the former actress Veronica Lario, whom he married in 1990 after divorcing his first wife.</p>
<p>Although Lario had demanded €43m a year, higher than the €36m awarded, the judge's ruling is heavily in her favour.</p>
<p>Lario denounced her husband in 2009, saying: "I cannot stay with a man who frequents minors," after he was snapped attending the birthday party of the aspiring TV showgirl Noemi Letizia, then 18.</p>
<p>Lario, who has had three children with Berlusconi, also described his attempt to send female TV starlets to the European parliament as "shameless rubbish" and entertainment fit for "an emperor".</p>
<p>Since their separation, Berlusconi has been engulfed by allegations of sex with prostitutes and his so-called Bunga Bunga parties in Milan. Female guests at the parties have revealed in court that Berlusconi still sends them regular cheques for thousands of euros.</p>
<p>As he hits the campaign trail, Berlusconi has claimed he is in a steady relationship with Francesca Pasquale, a former TV showgirl and member of his political party who is 27, almost 50 years his junior and younger than his oldest daughter.</p>
<p>That claim was challenged this month by Katarina Knezevic, a former Miss Montenegro, who reportedly attended Berlusconi's parties and said Pasquale had been given a contract to appear at Berlusconi's side.</p>
<p>Knezevic, 22, told the Italian daily Il Fatto Quotidiano that she was Berlusconi's true love and would marry him, adding: "I will kill for him and die for him."</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>