<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2010-11-30" description="Night of heavy rain brings down 7m of Roman wall around House of the Moralist" fingerprint="bb85de91cd9db475" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Archaeology,Silvio Berlusconi,World news" title="Pompeii wall collapses to pile woes on Berlusconi ally" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/nov/30/italy-archaeology">
<main>
<p>A further collapse in the ruins at Pompeii today stepped up the pressure on Silvio Berlusconi's beleaguered heritage minister and prompted calls for emergency measures to safeguard the Roman site.</p>
<p>A custodian making the first inspection of the day found a 7m stretch of wall surrounding the so-called House of the Moralist had given way during a night of heavy rain. The wall stood yards from the 2,000-year-old House of the Gladiators, part of which fell down on 6 November.</p>
<p>An Italian government statement said the wall was not "of importance or historical, artistic or archaeological value". The heritage minister, Sandro Bondi, warned against pointless alarmism.</p>
<p>The statement blamed the disintegration of the wall, rebuilt after a US bombing raid in 1943, on incessant rain in recent days. In a later statement officials raised questions about the efficacy of conservation at Pompeii, revealing that earlier this year the wall had been the "object of a consolidation operation".</p>
<p>The mayor of Pompeii, Claudio D'Alessio, said: "Till now, little or nothing has been done to safeguard this immense patrimony."</p>
<p>A member of the opposition Democratic party, D'Alessio said the damage at the House of the Gladiators should have triggered an emergency intervention by the government which, "as demonstrated by today's collapse, has not taken place".</p>
<p>Bondi is already facing a no-confidence motion in parliament. Today he came under more pressure as opposition politicians demanded to know why his department had provided generous backing for a film by a Bulgarian actor-director, Michelle Bonev, who is reputedly a friend of Berlusconi.</p>
<p>What makes the crisis in Pompeii so dangerous for the government is that it has been taken up by opposition politicians and media commentators as a metaphor. On 14 December Berlusconi's weakened administration faces confidence votes in parliament which, if lost, could force his resignation. Paolo Ferrero, a minister in the last, centre-left government, called the latest collapse an "allegory".</p>
<p>Antonio Irlando, president of a heritage group, the Osservatorio Patrimonio Culturale, said: "This latest collapse confirms there is no longer a moment to lose in activating conservation initiatives for the highly fragile archaeological site of Pompeii."</p>
<p>The House of the Moralist is named after its hectoring wall inscriptions. One urges visitors to "postpone your tiresome quarrels if you can, or leave and take them home with you".</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>