<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Tom Kington" categories="World news" date="2009-10-04" description="Group owned by Carlo De Benedetti awarded sum for lost revenue following legal battle defeat in 1991" fingerprint="3ff4992f917fde45" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,World news,Europe" title="Berlusconi firm ordered to pay €750m to rival in bribery case" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/04/silvio-berlusconi-fininvest-cir-damages">
<main>
<p>Silvio Berlusconi's family holding company, Fininvest, has been ordered to pay €750m (£686m) in damages in a bribery case to the company of a rival media mogul, which is pressuring Italy's prime minister over his alleged dalliances with escorts and a teenage model.</p>
<p>The Italian energy and media group CIR, which owns the left-leaning newspaper La Repubblica, was awarded the sum for lost revenue following its defeat by Fininvest in a legal battle to take control of the publishing group Mondadori in 1991.</p>
<p>The award follows the conviction in 2007 of Berlusconi's former lawyer, Cesare Previti, for bribing a judge to ensure victory for Fininvest.</p>
<p>Carlo De Benedetti, CIR's honorary chairman and a longtime rival of Berlusconi, said the ruling brought "justice to the company and its shareholders", although Marina Berlusconi, the prime minister's daughter and chairman of Fininvest, said she would appeal against the decision, which she called "incredible and disconcerting".</p>
<p>A Berlusconi family newspaper, Il Giornale, described the award as an "atomic bomb", which "risks putting Fininvest on its knees". The holding company, which controls the Mediaset network of television channels, reported cash holdings of €729m in 2008.</p>
<p>The 1991 decision by a Rome court to award control of Mondadori to Fininvest laid the groundwork for today's Italian media landscape. Berlusconi added the publishing firm's magazines to his TV network to strengthen his media empire, but he also split off two publications from the group, La Repubblica and L'Espresso, selling them to De Benedetti.</p>
<p>Since Berlusconi's wife demanded a divorce in April, accusing him of "frequenting minors", La Repubblica has regularly printed a list of 10 questions it says the prime minister must answer about his private life. On Saturday tens of thousands of Italians gathered in Rome to protest against defamation lawsuits Berlusconi has launched against newspapers reporting the case, including La Repubblica, and to contest his control over Mediaset, combined with his indirect control over the state TV network, RAI.</p>
<p>In a prime time statement read out to TV viewers, Augusto Minzolini, the head of RAI's flagship news programme, called the protest "incomprehensible" and "absurd".</p>
<p>"You cannot believe the newspapers are always right," he said, recalling that, "in 2004, Tony Blair, after a long struggle that almost went to court, forced the resignation of BBC managers who had accused him of falsifying documents related to Iraq."</p>
<p>Beppe Giulietti, a spokesman for the freedom of speech group Articolo 21, said Minzolini's editorial "confirmed that freedom of information really is at risk".</p>
<p>Berlusconi has often claimed the Italian courts are hostile to him and on Saturday described the €750m award as "a well timed assault", Il Giornale reported. The court's decision, the paper said, was nothing short of "an attempted coup".</p>
<p>Italy's constitutional court is expected to rule next week on a law Berlusconi created to give himself immunity from criminal prosecution. Should the court rule against the law, he may call an early general election, Il Giornale said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>