<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="John Hooper" categories="World news" date="2004-07-08" description="The two oldest children of Italy's prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, are being investigated for suspected money-laundering, it was reported last night." fingerprint="fe88811992738779" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="World news,Italy,Silvio Berlusconi,Europe" title="Berlusconi's children in 'dirty money' inquiry" url="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/jul/08/italy.johnhooper">
<main>
<p>The two oldest children of Italy's prime minister, <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/silvio-berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref>, are being investigated for suspected money-laundering, it was reported last night.</p>
<p>Italian media, quoting court sources, reported that Piersilvio and Marina Berlusconi, the prime minister's son and daughter by his first wife, had been made suspects in an inquiry that began three years ago.</p>
<p>But one of Mr Berlusconi's lawyers denied late last night that this was the case.</p>
<p>The confusion arose in the midst of a tumultuous week for the media tycoon-turned-government leader, and just hours after a move that will increase the cost of Italy's huge debt.</p>
<p>The credit rating agency Standard &amp; Poor's earlier downgraded Italy's long-term rating, apparently in reaction to Mr Berlusconi's decision to take personal control of his country's finances.</p>
<p>The Ansa news agency reported that Mr Berlusconi's children were under investigation for money-laundering and handling stolen goods. But Niccolo Ghedini, the prime minister's lawyer, said: "I know nothing of this, nor has there been any formal document in this respect [to show that] any prosecutor's office is investigating them."</p>
<p>Mr Berlusconi himself is already under investigation in the inquiry, which is being carried out by Milan-based prosecutors. The prime minister is suspected of embezzlement, false bookkeeping and tax fraud.</p>
<p>The inquiry focuses on the purchase by Mr Berlusconi's TV empire, Fininvest and Mediaset, of rights to US films in 1994 and 1995. Prosecutors believe the deals were channelled offshore to inflate the cost to Mediaset and cut its tax bill. The operation is alleged to have boosted the group's costs by almost £100m.</p>
<p>Later, in a statement sent by Mediaset, Mr Ghedini denounced what he said was the "absolute baselessness" of the news.</p>
<p>He said that when the alleged transactions were said to have taken place in the early 1990s the two children were finishing their university studies "and had no role, either directly or indirectly."</p>
<p>In a statement the two companies declared the "absolute correctness and total transparency" of their deal ings and called the accusations "absurd".</p>
<p>Piersilvio Berlusconi is now deputy chairman of Mediaset. Marina Berlusconi is deputy chairwoman of Fininvest, the family holding company that controls the TV group and a raft of other firms.</p>
<p>News that they are under investigation is bound to prompt renewed claims from the right that the Milan prosecutors are acting in a politically motivated fashion.</p>
<p>The timing of last night's leak could scarcely have been more embarrassing for Mr Berlusconi, coming on the same day that Standard &amp; Poor's announced their humiliating decision.</p>
<p>The agency had not been expected to reach a decision until after the government had seen a reform of the pension system through parliament. But last weekend Mr Berlusconi electrified the political and financial environments in Italy by appointing himself interim economic overlord.</p>
<p>Soon afterwards he signalled that he was ready to defy determined opposition from within his own coalition to supervise personally the introduction of a round of tax cuts on which he has staked his political future.</p>
<p>Standard &amp; Poor's analysts reached the conclusion that Italy, labouring under a debt burden greater than its gross domestic product, and with an economy that is barely growing, could not afford the proposed measures.</p>
<p>Though committed under the pact underpinning the euro to keep Italy's budget deficit to 3% of GDP, the government is having difficulty containing spending. Yet Mr Berlusconi's coalition partners continue to press for programmes that can only boost spending further.</p>
<p>The latest to issue an ultimatum was the Union of Centre Democrats, which earlier this week threatened to leave the government, even though it would continue to back the prime minister in parliamentary votes.</p>
<p>Faced with an outcry over his decision to make himself economy minister, Mr Berlusconi yesterday indicated he might remain for only a few days. It had earlier been reported he hoped to stay on in the job until the end of the year.</p>
<p>He also moved to deflect criticism his tax cuts would benefit only the rich. "We will put a special emphasis on the tax brackets of the middle classes," he said.</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>