<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text author="Geoffrey Macnab" categories="Film" date="2008-09-02" description="Geoffrey Macnab meets Director Nanni Moretti the man mocked for claiming Silvio Berlusconi has caused a cultural crisis in Italy" fingerprint="1a0e012f51028d55" hostname="theguardian.com" sitename="The Guardian" tags="Film,Italy,World news,Culture,Silvio Berlusconi,Nanni Moretti,Europe" title="Geoffrey Macnab interviews director Nanni Moretti" url="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2008/sep/03/italy">
<main>
<p>'Berlusconi, Berlusconi, Berlusconi." The Italian writer-actor-director <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/film/nanni-moretti">Nanni Moretti</ref> repeats the name of the Italian prime minister again and again, as if reciting a desperate mantra. He is sitting on a sofa in a hotel room, eating a pastry (he has a famously sweet tooth). Last month, he was the subject of a career retrospective at the Locarno film festival in Switzerland, and while he was there he watched his 1990 film, La Cosa (The Thing). Seeing the film again, a documentary about the Italian Communist party's attempts to redefine itself after the fall of the Berlin Wall, plunged him into a deep gloom. "It seems like a millennium has gone by since then," he says. "The whole country, everybody followed that debate. If something like that happened now, people outside the party wouldn't care."</p>
<p>Moretti blames Berlusconi for this political apathy, and reminisces about a time when the word "communist" wasn't an insult, and when rival political parties engaged in debate rather than abuse. In particular, he detests the cult of personality that surrounds the prime minister.</p>
<p>"You may think I am obsessed with Berlusconi," he says, "but I am not. The problem in <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/italy">Italy</ref> is that there is no longer a public opinion. In other countries, newspapers represent and form public opinion. In Italy, vis-à-vis Berlusconi, there is a passivity. There are no more antibodies. It's as if the immune system has been sent to sleep. Five times - in 1994, 1996, 2001, 2006 and 2008 - a guy who has a monopoly over the TV channels has run for prime minister, something which is not acceptable in a democracy. Now, not only for the rightwing voters but for the whole of Italian society, it is considered normal that a guy who has a media empire, and the origins of whose wealth is not really clear, may run for election." Meanwhile, critics of Berlusconi are, according to Moretti, considered "boring, trivial - saying things which are taken for granted". He points out that there is now a generation of young Italians who have grown up watching Berlusconi's TV, and who have lost the will or power to question the status quo. "I refuse to make the ritual statement that there is hope among our youth, because there is not," he says.</p>
<p>The irony is that, in Italy, Moretti is himself the subject of a cult of personality. An instantly recognisable figure, the man often styled as the Italian Woody Allen makes news there with everything he says - something which clearly annoys him. "Italian journalism is getting worse and worse. It is looking for sensationalism. I don't identify with the descriptions many journalists give of me, but never mind. For sure, I can't and don't want to be on TV every day to show that I am different from the character the journalists depict."</p>
<p>When Moretti's new film Quiet Chaos, in which he acts but does not direct, was released in Italy earlier this year, the critics honed in on one scene. Moretti plays a bereaved husband who quits his job as a businessman to sit in the square outside his daughter's school. It's a gentle and perceptive study of a broken man trying to re-assemble his life. However, rather than acknowledge the subtlety of Moretti's performance, the press have concentrated on a rough and graphic sex scene, clearly startled at the sight of the lovable star of Dear Diary working up a formidable sweat. "If any other actor or director acts in a sex scene, nobody cares that much. But if I do it, there is a scandal," Moretti complains. "The movie is based on a book and that scene is in the book. In the book, the scene is much cruder and even more raw."</p>
<p>Moretti orders a second pastry, and as he chews away I'm reminded of the scene in his 1984 film Bianca, where he eats his way through a giant jar of Nutella. When he is not holding forth on the decline of Italian public life under Berlusconi, Moretti is actually a brilliant comedian. The Italian critic Carlo Chatrian, who curated last month's retrospective at Locarno, sees in Moretti a link to the nouvelle vague cinema of the 1950s and 1960s: "He is an auteur, a filmmaker. But he is also someone who is very linked with the popular tradition of Italian cinema, one of the few Italian directors who has maintained a relationship with the audience. In his films, there is always this main character, played by himself. But this main character is a mirror through which we can see the world."</p>
<p>Born in 1953, Moretti started going to the cinema as a teenager, where he warmed to films by Karel Reisz, Pier Paolo Pasolini, the young Bernardo Bertolucci, as well as the nouvelle vague. "The reason I feel so related to these movies is that there were two aspects to them," he says now. "There was the search for a new cinema, but also a search for a new society." Moretti believes few young filmmakers today pay enough attention to the work of these old auteurs. In 1991, he opened his own cinema, the Nuovo Sacher in Rome, where he shows films he feels passionate about (Ken Loach's Riff Raff was the first to screen). Now, he says, his audiences are getting older and older. "It is rare to see a young audience. I don't say they [young people] don't go to films. They may go to other cinemas. It took me 15 years to train the audience, and in a short while they will all be dead," he says, ruefully.</p>
<p>Are there any young Italian directors he is excited about now? Surprisingly, Moretti responds with enthusiasm. "Until recently," he says, "Italian audiences were so biased that, out of principle, they wouldn't go and watch movies by Italian directors." Now he thinks things are changing: he points to the emergence of a new generation of dynamic young producers and directors making serious, politically engaged films such as Matteo Garrone's Gomorra and Paolo Sorrentino's Il Divo, both of which won major prizes at this year's Cannes film festival. "These film-makers have given up playing the victim. It was a widespread Italian habit to say you were the victim of someone else. It was always the fault of the state, the industry or the audience. Now, they're getting rid of that attitude and taking some risks."</p>
<p>Just for a moment, as he reflects on this mini-renaissance, Moretti seems to cheer up. There are, it seems, some corners of Italian culture that might flourish again, in spite of Berlusconi.</p>
<p><hi rend="#b">Quiet Chaos </hi>is released in the UK on 24 October</p>
</main>
<comments/>
</text>